A. Thanks for coming back.
So we're going to be
continuing talking
about how we could
deploy things,
and we have to be
very comfortable at
atic Shell environment
to do that.
Last time I posted
a worksheet that is basically
a bunch of things that
you have to learn.
It's kind of a simple
worksheet just
with different things that
you can take notes on.
And we've done maybe about
half of these things so far.
Today, we're going
to be learning
some other things like these
special operators down here.
And so if you have your
worksheet from last time,
now it'd be a great time
to just like pull that
out again and you can
take more notes on there.
And eventually, when
we're all done,
you should have notes on all
these different commands and
basically describe what
they do in your own words.
And if you don't have
your worksheet, well,
you can just take notes
in some other form.
Same thing with the flash cards.
Some of those flash cards
from Friday also cover today,
so there's no new flash
card deck down here.
You might notice that there
is actually a reading today.
All the readings for this
course are optional.
Any reading will be redundant
or kind of supplementary
to what is in lecture.
Right? So if you kind of come
to a lecture and you
absorb everything,
then that would be you
kind of do all the
projects and all that,
that would be preparing you
to do the exams, right?
But I think it's sometimes nice
to have some readings as well.
And so this one is from letman,
which is the book, designing
data intensive applications.
We look at different system,
we're actually to
be sampling from
a few different books
and we do have readings,
and I don't want people to
have to buy a bunch of books.
And so what I'm going to do is
actually select everything
from theRiley collection.
TheRiley collection
is actually free
online if you have access
to a Madison library card.
How many of you
have a library card
currently? So just a few of you.
That would be a
great thing to get.
There's some details here
about how to go get it.
It's not that hard, actually,
you know, I just went
to a library near me,
and I brought a piece of mail
showing I'm in the Madison area,
and then I filled out a form,
and then, like, 5 minutes later,
I walked out with a
free library card
that will have a
number on there.
And if you have that number,
then you can sign into this
ORiley collection here.
They'll just like,
paste that in,
and then you can get
access to all these books.
So that would be
a great thing to
go ahead and do this week.
And it's a nice excuse to
visit your local
library as well.
Maybe get off campus. All right,
so that was trying just a
little bit of background.
Today, we're going to be
talking about Linux pipelines.
And I have a few
goals for you today.
I want to be able to take a
few different Linux programs
and chain them together
to create a pipeline.
That's useful in and of itself.
It's also useful to
get kind of exposure
to how you can create
little pipelines
like this because
those ideas will show up again
later when we're learning Spark.
Spark, we're also going to
have these data pipelines
to get data from one
point to another.
And so a lot of these ideas
are going to show
up again and again.
Another thing that we have
to learn how to do today is
redirect output from
a program to a file.
Often, you're going to be
running many programs at
the same time that are
basically interacting
with each other.
And so it won't be kind
of like this traditional
environment where you
have one program,
and you just see its output.
You'll have the output of
these different files,
and then you'll be
reading up on those
files to see what's happening.
And then finally, briefly at
the end, time permitting,
we'll try to see
how we can measure
resource consumption
in terms of compute,
memory, storage, and networking.
So, Unix, Unix is
actually what is Unix?
Unix is really a family
of operating systems.
Linux is the most
famous one, probably.
MacOS is also a Unix
operating system.
There's other ones
like free BSD.
Some of these like
Linux actually
have many different
flavors for them.
So Unix has actually been
very successful in general.
And it was built on
a philosophy that was
enumerated in a few points.
Those points are kind
of summarized nicely
in this book that I assigned
for the reading today.
And I have a couple points in
here kind of formulated
the same way they did.
One is that every program
you make should just
do one thing well.
If you want to do
something else, well,
then don't just keep adding on
features and making things
more and more complicated.
Go and write a new program
that does that new thing, right?
Don't have a large
number of features.
Now, if we have a bunch
of programs that each
do one thing well,
how can we do something
more complicated?
Well, what we want to
do is we want to use
these programs in
conjunction with each other.
And so what we can do that
brings us to the second point,
we should expect
that the output of
every program might be the
input to another program,
maybe a program that's
not even written yet.
And so that means that when
we're producing our output,
we don't want to produce
kind of extra output,
right, that might mess that up.
We want to focus on outputting
stuff that could be
intermediate data
that we could feed
into another program, right?
So we don't want
to be too strict,
maybe just having
general text output.
We'll let us combine
a lot of these things
together in various ways.
So the reading actually has
a nice example of this.
The example was that
we have some kind of
web server and people are
visiting the website,
and whenever they
visit the website,
we can see in the web logs,
what page they're visiting.
And we might want to answer
questions about those web logs,
like, you know, what are
the ten most popular web
pages or something like that?
The kind of thing
you might go and
write a little Python code for,
maybe you use Pandas
or something like
that to answer that,
maybe you write
some sequel for it.
But this example in
the pocket shows that you
can actually do this with
some simple Linux
command line tools
if you know how to
chain things together.
In a pipe. So here's
an example that I grabbed
right out of the book,
and you can see they have
this vertical character,
which is a pipe character.
It's the same character as
key as like the backslash,
but you'd hit shift to
type that pipe character,
and it's piping a bunch
of commands together.
So the first one is CAP,
which we've seen, that's
cating this axis log.
And then there's a bunch
that I won't talk here
like x sort, unique,
another sort.
And we have seen what Had does.
And if you know how to use each
of these things and
how to combine them,
then you can answer
some questions
without writing a single
line of actual code.
You can just run
these in combinations
if you're good at piping things.
So what actually
happens when we run
a command like
that on the shell.
Whenever I type a program
name in the shell,
it creates a process.
A process is just what we
call a running program.
I could have the same
program, and I could run
many processes from
it if I wanted to.
So here I have an example
of running process,
and every process has
these two things,
standard input and
standard output,
often abbreviated
standard N, standard out.
Standard N is often taking
input from things I'm typing on
the keyboard or maybe
feeding in from
some strip file or
something like that.
And then standard
output is often
drawing to the streen
where I can see it.
So I have a process there.
Now, if I type something like
this on the shelf, I type A,
Pipe B, the shell
will actually start
two processes for me,
an A process and a B process.
And the shell will also perform
this connection for me.
I'll connect the
standard output of
the first process to
the standard input of
the second process.
So there's kind of a
simple elegant syntax
to be chaining these
things together,
and you could, of course,
make longer chains,
however you want to to
accomplish what you're
trying to accomplish.
Now, you remember
that philosophy earlier
that you shouldn't have
all this extra output
because it makes
it harder to chain
these things together?
Sometimes you might have errors
or warnings or things like that,
where should that stuff go?
So processes on Linux
actually have a third thing,
which is called a
standard error.
And each of these processes
has a standard error.
And even if I pipe all
these things together,
they're each sending
their standard error
separately to the output strain.
If you are writing
say a Python program,
and you just do a print,
that will go to standard
output by default,
but you could google out of
there's like ways to tweak that,
so it would go to
standard error instead.
So you can start
thinking about that.
If you write Python programs
that might be part
of this shade,
And there's maybe some extra
warnings or other information
that wouldn't make sense to feed
his input into another program,
then maybe you can print that
to standard error instead.
Sometimes that might happen
automatically for you.
So, for example, I
have a little program,
and then it's producing
a much of output.
And then there's, you
know, an exception.
I did that stack
trace that would
go to standard error
by default, right?
So if there's any of
these programs in
the pipeline that have errors,
I can see that directly
on the streen.
Any questions about pipe so far?
Oh, right. A related
concept that's different.
Some people make them up
is called redirection.
Here, I'm just running
a single command A,
single process A, in
both standard out
and standard error
by defoler going to the stream.
But I might want to capture
the output of A in
a separate file.
If I do that, then I
would write Brader then.
I kind of think of
that as like an arrow,
almost, and I could put
a file name after it.
And that would redirect
standard output.
I could go to that file.
Standard error would
still go to the
screen as normal.
If I have some kind of
long running server
or something and I'm
watch it continuously,
it would make sense to
collect some logs in
a file somewhere in that way.
If I want to redirect
both of them,
I'd have to write two
redirections down here.
You know, internally,
these three things are
actually numbered.
These streams are numbered.
Standard is zero,
standard out is one,
and standard error is two.
And so if we want to
redirect standard error,
the syntax as we say
two arrow because two
is standard error.
So I could send standard
output to output dot text,
and I could send
standard error to
error dot text if I
wanted to to do so.
So all these things so far
should be in your nose, right?
Like the pipe character
the redirection,
the standard error redirection.
Make sure you remember
those things.
So maybe I want to combine
standard output of
standard error.
Here I can do Ampersand,
and that will send both of them.
Ambers stand arrow, would
send both of them to
output dot text. All right.
Any questions about
redirection? All right.
Oftentimes we will be
running things that take
a long time, right?
If we have big data that makes
sense that that
would be happening,
and that can be a
problem if we're trying
to do some other things in
the shell at the same time.
By default and the shell things
run synchronously,
what does that mean?
I start some slow program.
It runs for a while.
I do not get another prompt
again until that thing
is done running.
If I want to run
things asynchronously,
meaning it's kind of
in the background
and I can do other work
while it's running.
One way to do that is I can
put an ampersand at the end.
That's unrelated to
Ampersand arrow,
which was the redirection.
Here I have an
ampersand by itself.
In that case, that slow program
starts running and I
immediately get a prompt,
and I can do some other
things while that's running.
So we've seen features,
pipes, redirect, and Async.
So let's look at something
slightly more complicated.
And maybe I'll get a volunteer
to help me help explain
what exactly this command
is doing in the shell.
You think you understand it?
Pop up a hand, and
then I'll call on you.
Yeah, go ahead over
here. Runs command.
Excellent. Runs command A,
and it sends output
from A to command
B. I'll just key echo
what you're saying.
Yeah, Cary on. Great. So both
the standard out
and standard error
of B are sent to out dot text.
Okay? And then the Ac Yeah,
the Ampers keeps the
shell kind of active.
It's try to run at
A sin, so I can do
other things while
that is running.
And so the picture might
look like this, right?
Le Process A could still send
it standard error to the streen.
But otherwise, all this stuff
is happening in the background,
and when I'm all done,
I can look at output do te
see what happened there.
Any questions about
how these things
work in conjunction
with each other?
Yeah, question over here.
Oh, each of the steps back here?
Yeah, Yeah, maybe I'll
repeat it right here.
Yeah. Okay, A pipes to B.
And so you can see right there,
the standard out is
feeding into standard
N. And then out of B,
we're actually redirecting both
standard out and
standard error, right?
So I see down here,
standard out and
standard error are
both going to a file.
Right? So first I have a pipe
is it's process to process,
then I have a redirect
because it's process to file.
And then the last
thing that aprecen at
the end is completely different
than the one over here.
The one at the end
means all of this just
runs asynchronously
in the background.
That makes sense.
Yeah, people have
other questions or
clarifications on that? Yeah.
Question right here. Yes.
Excellent, right? Thanks
for clarifying that.
So when I put that
ampers in there,
it's only really doing
that for process B.
So anything from Process A
is still showing
up on the streen.
I might actually be a
little bit annoying
because it's like supposed
to run the background,
I might be like typing
all other stuff,
and then all of a sudden
like, whatever something to
standard I'll just pop up on
top of whatever I'm doing.
Maybe if I was trying
to be careful,
I might redirect
that as well, right?
Thank you for calling that
out. Yeah, right over here.
I wanted. What if
I wanted the standard error from
A to go to outt dot text?
I don't know if there's
a way to do that.
I mean, we could
certainly redirect
it to a separate file, right?
I don't know if there's
a way to kind of have
it reconverge up here.
Maybe if somebody finds
a way, let me know.
That'd be kind of
interesting. I on
other hand over here
somewhere. Yeah. Go ahead.
You were asked the same
question Excellent.
Yeah. Yeah, go s right here.
Oh, that's a really
good question.
So when we have this arrow here,
what if there was already
an output dot TXT?
Like, do we wipe it out or
do we make something new?
And the behavior right here
is that we're going to
wipe it out if
it's already there
it's gonna be a brand new file.
And I'll actually
show a demo later,
so you're going a
little bit ahead of me.
But if we wanted it to add
kind of new things to the
end of an existing file,
then we would do two arrows
instead of a single one. Yeah.
Thank you for calling
out that difference.
Yeah, lots of great questions
and kind of observations.
Any other questions?
Yeah, right here.
You want to the standard error.
Oh, yeah, if you want to
do the standard error
from A into a file.
So before the pipe,
what we would do is we
would say two arrow,
that would capture
the standard error,
and then we could
send that to a file.
Yeah, thank you. Yeah, there are
questions or comments
on this example.
Anybody up upstairs have
any questions or comments?
Yeah, right down here. Yeah, if
I had one arrow or two arrows.
So if there's no file there
already, it doesn't matter.
If there is a file, then
it raises the question,
Do we wipe it out and start
fresh or do we keep
adding to what is there?
If there's one arrow, it's
going to wipe it out.
If we have two arrows, then
it will just add at the end.
It's like an overwrite
versus a pen would be
the technical word names
for those two things.
Yeah. Thank you for
calling that out.
Yeah, other things people have.
Oh, right. Yeah, right
here. If you just wanted.
If I wanted the standard error
to go on the file,
but not an output?
Yeah, it's a good
question. Do Abody
have any ought? How
would I change this?
If I just wanted the
standard error and
not the output? Was that? Yeah.
I would put two instead
of the ampersand,
and I would get standard
error in the file,
and then standard output would
still come to the stream.
Yeah, thank you. There's quite
a bit of flexibility here,
how we stitch together
these pipelines.
All right. Let's go
ahead and we're going to
jump in and do some demos.
And so I'm going
to come over here.
And I'm already S S S Chen.
And a common program
that's used as part of
these more complicated
pipelines is WC,
which stands for
word count, right?
I'm going to do a word
count, and I'm going to say,
Hello, world. And I can type.
I can keep typing stuff.
If I want to get out of this,
somebody remind me in
a Linux environment,
how do I say I'm done
typing? Let's control.
I hear a mix of C and D,
I would do control D to
indicate that I'm done typing.
I'm not trying to kill it.
I'm just saying I'm done.
And so this is telling
me a few things.
It's telling me that there were
two words. Okay,
that makes sense.
There was one line,
and there were 12
characters, right?
So I can use that to count
various kinds of output.
In this case, when I was typing,
I'm typing standard n myself.
But if I use a pipeline,
then standard n would be
coming from a separate file.
All right, so last time
you remember that we
created this stations
dot TXT inside of data.
And so I could look
at that again.
There's all these weather
stations around the world.
Let me just make that
a little bit wider.
And if I wanted to
count them, right?
I could take that right
there, when I cat it, right?
What is it doing? It's
reading that file
and it's sending everything
to standard out?
I could connect that standard
out to the standard
end of word count,
and then I could
basically summarize that.
And so this was the number
of characters, the
number of words.
In this case, I think the most
interesting thing
for us is, well,
how many lines
were there because
each line has its own
own weather stations.
So I could say, well,
there's 123,000 weather
stations in that file.
What else might I do?
If I kind of come back to this,
I might be interested in
ones that are in Madison,
there's tools that I can
use to filter it out
and the main tool that we
use is something called rap.
Again, this is just like you put
the stuff in your notes
I just you memorize it.
I don't have any clever way
of remembering that
p means filter.
It just does, and I could
try to filter to things
that were in Madison.
There are none because
it's case sensitive.
I could say make it taste
insensitive like that,
or maybe I would just type
it capitalized, right?
I kind of depending on
whether I care about case.
I'll have to do that a
little bit differently.
I might see here that
I'm getting a lot
of Madison things.
There's some weird ones like
Madisonville somewhere.
And so maybe I would
want to exclude that.
So what I could do
in this case is
I could do another graph,
and I could say, Madison, ill.
I guess that I would do the
few that are Madisonville.
If I wanted to, I could do
basically an inverse search.
I'd say V, that would
mean everything
except Madisonville.
So I it the things that are
Madison but not Madisonville.
And then you can imagine
I could build on that.
Maybe I could even figure
out how many there are.
I might also want to feed
these two head, right?
Head can take standard input,
and it can figure out
what are the first ten.
I could doit the first ten lines
that contain Madison, right?
So you can t see if
you have a bunch of
log or TXT files around,
you can quickly jump in and
kind of understand what's
inside of them. All right.
Um, So a lot of
these things that I do if I'm
starting with some kind of file.
So CAT is kind of a
natural starting point
for your pipeline.
Other times, instead of
looking at the
contents of the file,
we want to kind of search
through files themselves.
And so in that case, find is
a common tool I'll use to
start off my pipeline.
Find will recursively go
through and basically find,
you know, every path to
every file anywhere,
starting in the
directory I'm at.
So for example, I
might use Find and I
could graph for dot TXT,
and then I could find all the
TXT files that are under here.
Maybe that I might dig
into those more by using
grap and CAT and try to
find out what's inside
of those, right?
So you can kind of get
a little bit agile in
this environment and kind of
poke around and find things.
And it's a nice once
you get used to it.
It's actually pretty
efficient. All right.
Any questions about
those examples so far?
C. So we're showing
you a top pat.
And this is like an open form
like type something in top hat.
So it's just going to
be pure participation.
I don't have a great
way of grading it.
But I just want to
see if you can write
a simple pipeline that counts
how many lines of stations at
TXT contain the text Wisconsin.
I'll give this a
little bit longer
since you have to
do a little typing.
I'll give you a minute
and a half toll.
Yeah. Question back here.
Yeah, I don't know.
I mean, I guess you
can show me offline,
but if you kind of go to the
top hat link from Canvas,
hopefully that will
get it in sync.
And this is extra, if
folks have issues,
then hopefully it
feels low stakes.
Right. So I'll just look at
some of these answers, right?
Some people maybe found ways
to do it without a pipeline.
So that whole idea of
having a bunch of small
programs we chained together.
It's a bit aspirational.
Not every tool does it.
I think sometimes these tools
creep in more functionality,
like maybe grap added
a way to count things.
Right? Practice is always
more complicated in theory.
I like ones like this, right?
So this is a pipeline,
so we're getting
everything in stations.
We're grapping for Wisconsin,
and then we're counting how
many lines there are there.
I might nit pick
it a little bit,
like it's case sensitive.
So and we probably
trying to get a space
around Wisconsin,
so we might do
something like that.
There's probably
other options here.
This is kind of nice down here.
Word count by default shows
the number of characters,
words, and lines.
In this case, we're just
interested in the
number of lines.
There's different ways to do it.
Some graph by itself
is not going to work
unless it's part of,
you have to tell
where the data is.
There's different
approach. Some of these
are maybe correct
and some are not,
I'm not sure which
other ones might
also work because these
tools are a bit flexible.
Do people have any
questions about I guess
the technical aspects
of the question.
Cool. So I will
close out of this.
And we're head over
here and we're going
to do some demos.
So kind of coming back
to the stations TXT.
What I want to do is
I want to see if I
can build a data set of this.
That's just the
weather stations in
the Midwest. I'm just
trying to do two states.
I'm going to do
Wisconsin and Illinois,
and you can extrapolate how
you would add more
states to that.
And the way I'm
going to do this is
I'm going to grab for Wisconsin,
and then just to kind of make
sure it's like a whole word.
I'm going to put some
space around it.
And I'm going to get
all these things that
are from Wisconsin.
And then I am going to
redirect that to Midwest TXT.
And then maybe I'll
just peek inside that
Midwest TXT and see there's
a bunch that are
related to Wisconsin.
I might want to add
Illinois to this.
I'm going to say Illinois.
And at this point,
if I do that, it's actually
going to wipe it out,
and there's going to
be no more Wisconsin
just be Illinois.
I'm going to modify
this slightly,
and I'm going to
change it to two,
and that makes it a pen mode.
And so what that means
is it's going to add
Illinois after all
the Wisconsin ones.
So now I could look at the head.
Of Midwest, I have
some Wisconsin,
or I could look at
the tail of Midwest,
and I could have some
Illinois, right?
So I can kind of combine
my pipe and my
redirection to build
the data set and I might
have a few commands.
Now, you might imagine that
the original data set
changes on occasion, right?
Maybe new stations are
built or whatever.
And I wouldn't want
to have to manually
redo those things every time.
So I might want to turn
into some kind of stript.
Last time we saw how we could
take a Python program and
basically make it
something that I
can easily run as a program.
We're going to do
the same thing now,
but now it's going to be a
bash strip instead, right?
And so what we'll do, is
I'll go back to this right
here and I'm going to
copy this. All right.
And what I'll do is
I'll make something
called make Midwest SH,
and I'm going to
paste this in here.
And then I'll actually append.
I'll add the other
one where I was
appending Illinois. All right.
And then at the top,
I can have a habang line,
and I can say
something like I mean,
is this a Python program?
No, is it a bash program?
Yes. I have to specify
what it is that should
run this thing.
In this case, it'll
be bash. All right.
Let's try running
this thing, so I'm
may say make Midwest.
And I get a permission denied.
What do I have to do so
I can actually run
it like a program.
Yeah, go ahead. I have to
make it executed, right?
Pudo won't help me, right?
Because if I'm the root user,
right the root user can change
permissions on anything,
but doesn't mean
they already have
permissions on anything, right?
So CH Mod with the
answer given is correct.
So if I do an LSL here,
I can see that my make
Midwest program,
let me look at it.
So this part is a directory
or file, that looks like a file.
The user doesn't have execute,
the group doesn't have execute,
others don't have execute.
I could say CH
mod, and I'll say,
my user should dig execute
permissions make
Midwest. Run this again.
Now I see that we've
added for the user,
execute permissions,
and now I can run that.
Let me just try it.
I'm going to remove Midwest TXT.
Then I'm going to
see it's not there.
And then I'm going
to do make Midwest.
And then all of a sudden,
I do have Midwest I TXT again,
and I could, you know,
run that whenever my original
dataset changes in some way.
All right. Any questions
about that example?
Maybe I'll just cat it out in
case people have questions.
All right. Yeah, right here.
You Yeah, this line up here?
Yeah, that's a
haban line, right?
So I made this executable,
but a lot of programs that might
execute need some
environment with them.
They need like a Python runtime,
Java, runtime, a
bash strip, right.
So when I just look
at the file itself,
how do I know what it is?
Like, We as humans
look at the extension,
but Linux doesn't care
what the extension is.
That's just almost like a
comment or documentation.
The hab line is what tells it.
Here's the kind
of program it is,
and here's how you run
it. Yeah, thank you.
Thank you for clarifying that.
Yeah, other questions people
have. Yeah, question
right over here.
To modify the first
line language.
Yeah, sure. So last time
we saw the switch command,
so I could see
where Python lives.
And so if I if I if
this was like Python T,
then I would say that, right?
And then I would get a weird
rab because like Python will
say this is not valid
Python syntax, right?
But I could basically
use any kind
of run time that I
wanted to there. Yeah.
Question back here. What
the arguments for CH mod.
Yeah. F CH mod.
The format is we'll
say who and then what,
and then we'll say some file.
For example, I could
say that I want
other users to be
able to read it.
Right? And actually, let's
make it so they can write it.
So I'll say other users can
write to Midwest
TXT. I'll do ASL.
And now I see that
these Leslie group,
it's rewrite, execute, and I
just turned on the W, right?
So other people can overwrite
that file now. Do
that makes sense?
Yeah, thank you. Yeah, other
questions people have.
I can do minus to
takeaway permission,
plus to add it. All right.
Cool. So I'm going to
shift gears a little bit.
And what I'd like to talk about
is processes and how we can
kind of work with processes,
maybe processes that are
running for long time.
And so you might
remember last time we
had this count dot Pi.
I think I installed
it. I just moved
it back to my home
directory here.
And what was count
Pi doing, right?
It was opening up the data
stations at TXT. Python file.
It was looping over
all the lines,
adding up a count and
then printing that out.
And so how might I run
that otherwise, right?
So it's kind of fast right now,
but if it was taking
a long time to run,
I might want to run
it in the background.
One of the ways that I'll
kind of play around with
things that run slow is I'll
just artificially
make my program
slow by sleeping
occasionally, right?
So this would be
sleeping for 1 second.
And if I want to do
that, then up here I
could import import time, right?
So I can import
time, and then this
will be a very slow
running program now,
so I could do count to Pi.
That's to take very long
over 100,000 seconds.
If I wanted to kill it
in some I mean how I
kill things. Yeah, right here.
Control C. So I'll just
kill that for now.
When I kill it, I actually
see that this was the line.
I get a Python exception
showing me this was
the line that was on.
It's actually kind of
a quick and dirty way
to debug some
performance issues.
I mean, if you think about
some part of your program
being kind of slow,
if I just interrupt
at a random time,
kind of probabilistically,
it's more
likely going to be
on that slow part.
So if I kind of just kill
a slow running thing,
I might see Oh, this part
was slow. Yeah,
question right here.
Yeah, I guess maybe,
do I need that?
Maybe not, because
I guess we added
the hava line and we added
executeable excellent
point, right?
I forgot that Yeah,
in the context of last lecture,
that makes more sense
to run it that way.
Then result will
be the same, but
that's kind of a more
elegant way to run it.
Excellent point.
Yeah, thank you.
Yeah, there are points or
questions people have.
Alright. So I have this
slow running thing.
And so what I'd probably want to
do is run in the background,
and so I'll add an
ampersand there,
and now it's just running
there in the background,
and eventually, it'll finish.
I'll just get that output
straight to the screen.
So I might want to have
some way of kind of
poking around and seeing
what's running in
the background.
I use LS to list files,
and I'm going to use PS
to list running programs.
And so I do PS, and
I can see there's
three things running.
There's Bash, the
count then PS itself.
PS has different arguments
that we can pass to it
or different flags.
I think most tools would do
things like this,
I'd say, like A.
For whatever reason,
they kind of went with
a different thing,
and they'll just
have the letters by
themselves with no dash.
And so one of the
things you might
do is you might do PSA.
And what that means
is that I don't want
just processes for my user.
I want them for all the
users on the system.
And, you know, there's
not many more because
most of the processes
running were started by me,
the TRH user, so I can do that.
If I really want a lot, though,
then I can add X.
So a lot of these
processes that are running
are associated with a shell
a shell session, right?
So I kind of SSH in,
and I have these
processes running.
But there was a bunch
of processes that maybe
started during Buda before
I even did anything.
And so if I do this,
I can actually
see while there are there's,
like, over 100 processes
on this system, right?
So A and X are
often what I'll add
in conjunction with PS,
right? So I can do that.
I might go through and I grap
for count Pi, and then
I can try to find it.
It's kind of funny because
when I grap for it,
I find the actual
count D Pi there.
And then I will also
Grep sees itself, right?
As Grep is running, it
sees itself running.
All right. So I can do that.
I can kind of identify
what's happening.
If it's a long running
thing, I might want
need to kill it and
and restart it.
And so there's a few
ways I can do that.
At the very beginning
of this line,
I have a process ID, right?
So every process that's
running has a process ID.
And so what I can do
is I can say kill,
and then I have a
process ID here.
And so I'm going to do
that. I'm going to kill it.
I'm going to do PS again,
and I see that basically
it's terminated,
now it's just drawn entirely,
right? So I could do that.
When I do that, it sends
a special signal to
it asking it to stop.
That's the same
signal I get if I
hit Control C, actually, right?
So a kill sends a
signal to a process.
Control C sends a
I'm curious if
anybody here has ever
been running like Jupiter
lab or Juper or notebook,
and you hit Control
C to kill it.
What what happens
when you do that?
When you hit Control C in
Jupiter Lab or
Jupiter or Noe book?
Yeah, right here. Does
it reset the kernel,
maybe, it actually prompts you
with something. Dest even
you know what it does.
So it'll usually pop
something up that says,
Are you sure you
want to exit, right?
So I send it a kill signal
and it kept running.
It says, Are you
sure? Why is that?
Oftentimes, we'll just like send
a friendly kill signal
if there can be
such a thing to a process
because maybe you wants
to give me the chance
to change my mind.
Maybe, for some reason,
it shouldn't stop,
so it can actually
refuse and ignore that,
or maybe it needs to
save some files or
something before it exits.
So processes can receive
this kill signal and they can
decide what to do with it.
Sometimes in a process is
buggy and it's
trying to do that,
then it's actually really
hard to get it to stop.
And so, in that case,
what I need to do is
I need to send it
a stronger signal.
These signals are numbered,
and the number that you
should remember is nine,
because nine is the
most aggressive one,
and it's trying to kill
the process whether
or not it wants to die, right?
So let me just do that
Python three again.
Oh, and I'm going to run
that in the background.
I'm going to do the PS.
I'm going to grip for it.
And so if I really want to
aggressively make sure it stops,
I could do a kill nine,
and then it'll stop even if
it doesn't want to, right?
And I can see it's s. Let
me start it one more time.
So I'm going to have
it running here
and I'm going to
do the PS thing.
And so one option right is I
can do a kill with
or without nine,
and I can have a process ID.
Related option is P Kill,
and then I would
have the name of the
program that's running.
There's trade offs between that.
The name of this right
here Python three, right?
Python three is a
program that's running.
And Count a Pi, even
though I think of
that as my program,
that's an argument to it.
Right? So if I do P
Kill of count Pi,
nothing will happen.
It's still there.
It's still running. But if I
do a P kill of Python three,
that would be kind
of a convenient way
to terminate it, right?
So Are you going to
do kill or P Kill?
I think PK is usually a little
easier to remember. You'll
probably normally do that.
But if I had a bunch of
Python processes running,
I don't want to
kill all of them,
so I might use the other
kill to more selectively
figure out which PIDs I want
to target in that case.
All right. Cool.
Any questions about
killing processes? Yeah, here.
Yeah, so Pk always has to be
followed by an argument,
which is the name.
Do that make sense
or were you asking?
There's something have
to come after it?
I guess where did I You mean,
like when I did a P KL here?
Oh, yeah, uh huh. Oh, Oh,
you're saying, no, after I've
run the Pa KL, it's gone.
I guess it's a good I mean,
I can see why you might
think you might have to
do something after that.
It kind of seems
like the first time
I run it says terminated,
and after that, it
doesn't say anything.
I don't know if that's
just because now
I'm kind of curious, actually.
So I'm running it, and then
I'm going to do a P K.
I don't know if like after
a certain amount of time,
it just doesn't say terminated,
or if it's like the
first time it's
somehow detecting that
it was the first time.
Let me just kind of
run it for a while.
I'll do the P Kill.
There we go. Yeah, I'm not sure.
Maybe it's just time
of notes that it's
terminated the first time
I run something else,
but it'll be terminated either
way as soon as I run it.
But it does seem like as
soon as I do something else,
it's kind of letting me
know that it happened,
but you don't have to
do something else.
It will die if you do
the p Ki. Yeah, uh.
And I'm not quite
sure, why it tells
you at that point in time
instead of telling
you immediately,
but it will kill it
when you run the P i.
You don't have to do
anything else beyond that.
Yeah. Thank you for
clarifying that.
Yeah, are questions people have.
Alright. Cool. So we
talked about processes.
What I want to talk about now is
different resources and how
we can measure their usage.
And so the resources are CPU,
memory, storage, and network.
And if I want to look
at CPU and memory,
one of the things I can use is
Top and topo the
old way to do it.
I kind of has not
very nice output.
So instead, there's H top,
you probably have to, like,
an apt install H top the
H is for human readable.
And so I run H top and it's
basically the same thing,
but a nicer view of it.
One of the first
things I can see from
H top is how many
CPU cores I have.
So up here, I can see that
I have two CPU cores,
both of which are
idle right now.
That's actually going
to be very informative.
Like if I have a program that's
taking a long time to
run, and I come here.
Sometimes I'll see that there's
like one CPU that's 100%,
and all the other ones are idle.
That probably means I need to
figure out how to break up
my program in a
way that it's kind
of running across
multiple cores.
We're going to learn how to do
that with threads later on.
But that'd be kind of a good,
kind of thing to troubleshoot.
Down here, I have memory.
And there's a few things here.
One is that I see that I have
almost 2 gigabytes of ram,
and I'm using a little more
than 200 gigabytes of memory.
That's a little
bit more than 10%.
It's also representing
that as a bar.
The bar looks like
more than 10% of that.
And the reason why is
that it's just measuring
this first part,
which is green by apologies
to anybody color blind.
They kind of chose horrible
colors for that here.
But I have this green portion,
which corresponds, to
that number there.
Why do we have more of that?
Well, It's because of
caching. What is caching?
Well, I have some
of those files,
like stations at TXT,
or things like that,
that they live
on a hard drive or on an SSD.
They're on disk somewhere.
But when I'm accessing
them frequently,
it wants to put it
somewhere faster,
so it has a copy
in memory, right?
And so that's what this
is telling me over here.
I have a kind of all this memory
that's used to cache files.
If I'm tight on memory, that's
not going to be a problem.
I'll just stop caching that.
Whereas, the stuff over here
is kind of more critical, right?
There's not how much
memory I really need,
and that reflects
this number here.
And then there's kind of
like the memory that's used
for optional stuff that
gives me better performance,
but I could stop using
that memory if I had to.
Down here, you can see all
these different process
IDs that we've already talked
about, what users using them.
We see the CPU and
memory percentage.
You can see if you press F six,
you could actually
sort by CPU or memory.
So you could use this
as a way to first,
like jump in and see if
I'm really low on memory,
then I can try to figure out,
well, who is using the memory?
Then I could go do a P kill
or something like that.
I could reclaim some
of these resources.
I'm going to do Q to it that.
That's H top. All right.
Any questions about
H top? All right.
Col. Let's talk
about storage space.
And storage space,
there's two tools.
I want you to know, DF and DU.
We'll do DF first.
There's a bunch of
different file systems
we talk more about file systems,
and this is showing
me how much space
is used by all of them.
If I want to look at
the current directory,
and this is not the
current directory,
but it's time of
the file system with
the current directory.
And so it's going
to be a sub files,
maybe files above
me. I might do that.
And I'm just trying to get down
to that one that's
really interesting.
And so I can see how
much space is available.
That's 20% of this total.
Little hard to read. So one
of the things I might do
is I might say for
human readable.
And now I see what I have
is a 24 gigabyte disc,
and I'm using 4.5
gigabytes of that.
I think it'll be very
common that all of you will
get low on disk
space this semester.
And so you'll kind of like run
that to diagnose the problem.
Then you'll have to dig around,
find some big files,
delete them, free up some space.
Right? How might you
find large files?
That's this other
tool called DU.
DU is basically going
recursively and looking
at different directories.
And so one of the things I
could do is a DU summary.
And that's I'm
trying to summarize
how much I have in
a particular place.
And I can also
use a human readable
format of that, right?
So that's saying
that this directory,
at least from the stuff I
can see has 35 megabytes.
There's some practice stuff I
created that's not
readable by me,
and so that would not be there.
Maybe I'll just delete that.
So that we don't have
a cluttered output.
This is 35 megabytes.
Oftentimes, I'll
say dot slash Star,
and then I can see each
directory how much it is, right?
So I can see, for example,
that I have 21 megabytes
for the data directory.
Sometimes I might do things
like RP for G for gigabytes,
and I can use that to kind
of quickly figure out
which directories are kind
of consuming multiple gigabytes.
That might be where
I might start to
go clean some stuff up.
All right, so that's DF and D U.
The next one I want to talk
about is related to networking,
and there's a concept with
networking called the socket.
I'm not trying to
really define what
a socket is right now
or a port number.
I just want to show
you the tool to kind
of show you something for
each of the resources,
and we'll explain this.
We'll revisit this tool when
we have a whole
lecture on networking.
But the tool is SS,
and that stands for
socket statistics.
And that shows me about
all these different network
connections that are
kind of going on.
Some of these might
actually be local,
and some do to get TCP.
We're going to talk about
more what TCP is later.
But these are kind of
like actual connections
between different computers.
Sometimes my computer is
acting like a server that's
responding to messages.
Other times it's like a
client that's reaching
out and sending
message messages.
I may do dash out to see
cases where it's
acting like a server,
it's listening, and so I can do
some things here that
are kind of interesting.
We see different IP addresses.
These are common names
for various ports.
I want to actually have
just numbers for there,
so like 53 or things like that.
And then finally, last
thing I might do is
I might want to have some
process information.
When I say P,
it actually doesn't give
me an err or anything,
but can't show me any
process information
because I'm not the root user.
So I'm sharing to a pseudo.
And now I actually get
some pretty useful
information here,
let me just try
running this again.
Still kind of a
little bit too large.
I wonder if people
can still see it
though if I do it like that.
So kind of wraps
around a little bit.
But what I can start to do here
is I can see what port numbers,
different processes
are using, right?
So if I grap for, SSH,
I might learn, for example,
that SSHD D stands for Demon.
Demon is a background process.
The SSH Demon is running
on this virtual machine,
and it's using Port 22, right?
And so we're going to
learn more about how
we can kind of connect
to Ports later.
That's going to be crucial I
spend a lot of time on it.
So I know it's kind of all
fuzzy a little bit right now.
But I can connect that port.
One of the issues that
you're all going to have
this semester is that you're
going to start a process,
it's going to be using
a port, say 5,000,
and you'll get an error
message saying that Port
5,000 is already and use.
And so you're going to
have to figure out, well,
what other process is
using that already,
you're going to have
to kill that process,
and then you're going to be
able to start your software.
Or maybe I have a server
running somewhere,
and I'm trying to
like connect to it,
and it's just like,
Oh, I can't find it.
The port number is
probably wrong.
So I'll probably have to go onto
that server, run this tool,
figure out what port number
is actually being used,
and I can figure out how to make
my client code actually
connect that server, right?
So port numbers are
very important.
This is a tool for understanding
port numbers as a resource.
And we're going to be talking
more about port numbers and
sockets in an upcoming lecture.
All right. So all
of these things.
Well, any questions
about any of these,
like the storage and
networking CPU memory,
any of these tools
for inspecting them?
Yeah, right here. Ecell, what's
the difference between
DF and DU, right?
So So when I have
this file system,
it's all backed by
a disc somewhere.
Maybe it's like an
SSD or a hard drive,
and DF is telling me
for like that disk,
how much space am
I using, right?
So DFS trying like
the global picture.
That's where I would
start to just see,
like, do I have a problem?
DU is looking at a
specific directory
and space used by the
files in that directory.
Right? So after I've
identified a problem with DF,
I'll use DU to
actually try to find
a large file somewhere that
I'm not using that I can delete.
That makes sense? Yeah, thank
you for clarifying that.
Yeah, other questions
people have.
All of these things
that we're looking at
might have an influence
on how fast things run.
And so it's important
to be able to
measure how fast
things are running.
And so if I have a command
like find or
something like that,
and I want to know
how long that takes,
what I can do is
in front of that,
I can say, time.
I can put time in front of
any other shell command I might
have. I'll run the command.
And then in addition to
that, time will print
off some details
about it, right?
There's a few numbers here.
The first one is real time.
Real time is what we're used to.
If I have a watch
and I start the time
and I stop and I subtract,
that's real time.
What are these two down here?
This is user time
and system time.
User time is time that is
spent in my actual program.
And system time is that
means it's inside of
the operating system.
So here I actually see
there's mostly system time
because we're asking
the operating system,
what is in a directory
or things like that.
In this case, user time
and system time are
equaling the real time,
but that's not always the case.
You can imagine
these things down
here are measuring
like actual CPU usage.
You can imagine that
maybe a program is
sleeping or it's waiting to
download a file from the
Internet or any of those things.
In those cases,
then those numbers
might be a lot less
than the real time.
Then I can see, Oh, CPU
is not the bottleneck.
For this program.
I might also see that user plus
system together might be
bigger than real time.
Can anybody guess why, say,
the user CPU time might be
bigger than the real time?
Yeah, right here.
Use two CPU at once.
Excellent, right? What if
I'm using two CPUs at once?
If I have a program
that runs for 1 second,
and both of these are
utilized at 100%,
then I would have
two CPU seconds,
but only 1 second of real time
would have passed, right?
So, kind of looking at
this, I can see lots of
things I can see
is that CPU bound.
Is it able to use multiple CPUs?
Just how long did
it take in general?
Right? So again in the habit
of measuring these things so
that will help you
make things faster.
Alright. So thanks, everybody
Next time we come back and learn
about one of my favorite
systems, which is Docker.
So, have a great day.