So we've been talking about
networking for a week now.
You might notice that I
split up this lecture.
It was going to be
GRPC at Campos.
It was just too much. I put
them on separate days now.
Today, we're actually be
learning about Docker Campos,
where we spend up multiple
containers that are
working together.
We're also learned
about a little bit
about Docker
networking in general.
Gib and I split it,
the Anki flashcards
from last time are going to
be covering both
of these lectures.
Another thing is that when
I kind of pushed it back,
I accidentally moved
the project deadline.
So rather than cause confusion,
I just left it, I think
it's sill reasonable
enough schedule.
So, I guess P one is
due on Monday now,
how many of you
have already pushed
some code that's passing at
least some tests to it Lab?
That's fantastic
because if you get sick
over the weekend or you get
unusually busy or whatever,
you might need to
ask for somebody
to waive the late
penalty for you.
And so the threshold
in this case is
that if you've
submitted by Friday,
that's three days ahead, so
Saturday, Sunday, Monday,
If you've submitted
something by Friday,
you've pushed it to the Git lab.
It's passing at
least some tests.
Anything that's not zero,
then that sounds a
significant start.
You could ask a TA to review it.
And then they could waive
that penalty so that
you could submit on,
let me see, what is it?
And sea of Monday,
it could be Tuesday,
Wednesday, Thursday, right?
I always recommend you know,
people get sick and suf,
but I want to see that there
was a good faith effort
to get an early start.
Yeah, question over here.
What's that? P two I think I
would like to still
release it, but I guess,
the deadline I put for myself is
that I always have something
in front of students to
work on, so I don't know,
maybe I'll do it on Monday
if we're doing actually a
completely two new P two,
so I might use
extra time myself,
but it would also be
nice to get it out on
Friday and people who are
done with P one could do it.
So we'll see. I'm not
trying to promise anything,
but I do think I would prefer to
get it out sooner
rather than later.
Yeah, there are
questions people have.
Cool. O thing is that there's
a Quiz night who has
taken the quiz already.
Fantastic. So just make
sure you don't miss that.
Alright, so we're
ahead over here
to some slides and learn about
Docker Networking
and Docer Compose.
And I have a few
goals for you today.
We want to be able to
figure out how we can
connect like a browser on
our laptop to some server
that's running in a
container somewhere.
We have to chain things along
where you have to know last
time we talked about a
lot about how we can
did a packet from
point A to point B.
Sometimes you're going
to have a point B
forwarding onto another
point C, right?
So we're going to have a chain.
We have to figure out how
to set up those chains
to really make that
scenario work.
I have something in my
browser that's talking to
a server and a container
and a VM somewhere.
Second, for Door Compose,
we need to learn how to deploy
applications that consist
of multiple containers.
And then finally, I may briefly
introduce this idea of
partitioning and replication.
Those are B ideas that show
up many times throughout
the semester.
So this is just a
first look at it.
But that will really be talking
about how we can take a
dataset and split it up
across it from
machines or maybe have
multiple copies of data for
the sake of reliability.
Okay, let's start with some
Dock report forwarding.
And I'm going to start
with this picture,
and it's already complex,
and it's going to get
more and more complex.
I'm going to kind of go
slowly and talk bit by bit.
First off, I have a laptop
on the left hand side.
That laptop has two
network interfaces.
I'm using IF for interface.
Can anybody remind me what
this one is for the LO Nick?
Just pop up a hand,
if you want to tell
me what the LO interface is.
Yeah, right over here.
It's basically like
a local network.
It's as if that that neck
is the only device
on that network,
and so you might use that if
you want to try and
just do things,
you want to kind of program
in a networking style,
but you still want
to just keep it
local and not have it
available to anybody else.
Excellent, right? So my
laptop has a loopback device.
It also has a real
physical neck that
can be used to communicate
over the Internet.
For example, with
this virtual machine.
This virtual machine
has a similar setup,
has a loopback device,
the public facing neck
that is actually connected
to the Internet,
might have a different
name in this case,
ENS zero or NS four,
not an important detail.
On this virtual machine,
I ran two Docker
commands down here.
I have this image
called my Image.
Maybe that was built
from a Docker file
that starts up Jupiter lab,
for example, Jupiter
lab is a server.
We're going to be using
this this semester.
And so I ran that twice.
I'm creating two containers,
and I can see my two containers,
container A, and container B.
And when Docker creates those,
it gives them virtual
network interface
cards as well, right?
So these in this case,
it is called ETH zero,
and they both have
one of those. And
And these are virtual, and
we can use ports on them.
Now, normally, I would
not have the same port
on the same Nick used by
multiple different applications.
But since I have two different
nicks here, and they're virtual,
it's fine for
Jupiter lab up here
to use port 80 and Jupiter lab
down here to use Port
80 because those are
separate virtual network
interface cards.
Yeah, question right here.
They're not associated Right.
Yeah, they're not
associated with
any hardware neck, usually.
They're just there and
ultimately right if I'm
sending something over them.
They can have address assigned
them and stuff like that.
But if I'm sending
traffic over them,
ultimately that they're
going to have to go
off of a real neck
somewhere, right?
It's going to have to
get forwarded off.
Yep. Yeah, thank you
for clarifying that.
Yeah, right here. Yeah, exactly.
So anything on this machine
is going to have to
go through ENS four, right?
And so Doctor are going to
take care of forwarding
outgrowing traffic
over ENS for us,
and that could be a whole
thing we could look into.
We're going to look at
the other case this
time where we're
trying to communicate.
I guess, and we want to
kind of have like
in D dress traffic.
How can we talk from
this browser over here
to Jupiter lab, right?
But everything is going
to have to go through
NS four, definitely.
Yeah, thank you for
making that point. Mm hm.
Alright, so this is a setup.
I these two containers,
they each have a virtual neck.
And because of that
they can both have
a port 80. All right.
So What I might want
to do is I might
want to be able
to have a program
running on my virtual machine,
not in any container, just on
my virtual machine itself.
And I might want that
program to be able to talk
to these Jupiter labs
inside of the containers.
Okay? So I have to have some way
of sending traffic to these.
And the way we do that,
it is with something
called Docker port forwarding.
Okay. And so when
I do Docker run,
I can add this DP option.
I don't have to, but I
could optionally do it.
I could have multiple
dashP options.
And each of these represents
a docker port forwarding.
Okay, when I do that, I can
have three things after there.
I either have two
or three things.
In this case, I have three.
When I have three,
then the first two
are an IP address
and a port number.
And that IP address, of course,
corresponds to a
network interface card.
In this case, 127001,
that's one of those IP addresses
you just need to memorize.
That corresponds to
loopback device.
And so what this whole statement
here is saying is that I want
port 300 on that looppc device.
If I get any packets there,
I want Docker to
forward those along
to port 80 inside of
my container, right?
And so if I have one
of each of these,
they would have ports 300400
on that looppa device,
and depending on
which where packets
are coming to on that loop
act device on the BM,
the traffic might get forward to
one Jupiter lab or the
other Jupiter lab.
Okay? Some caveats,
sometimes people say,
like, local hosts.
A lot of tools will allow
you to use local host.
Doctor, for whatever reason
makes you use an IP address,
which is one of the
reasons that you
shouldn't remember this one.
And it's okay that
80 shows up in both of these
because they're different,
but I could not forward from
the same source on
the virtual machines loop back
to different ones, right?
So if I had said, 300300,
then that would have
been a port collision.
But this is totally fine.
Yeah, question right here.
Dash D. Yeah, excellent.
So Dash D just means I want
to run in detach modes.
So normally when I
run a container,
like I see the output,
and then kind of I don't get
a shell prompt until I
kill it or it's done.
Dash D means, like,
basically run
it in a detached
in the background,
and then I can do
other things, right?
Yeah, thank you for
reminding everybody of that.
All right. So at this point,
right, if I was on
this virtual machine,
I could use a curl command
or something like that,
and I could send traffic
to these two web servers,
and I could get
responses from them.
If I did like a docker exec,
I could also jump inside of
one of these containers,
and I could use a curl command
to visit these these servers.
So one of the things
you have to get
comfortable with is
you have to know,
like, what the docker port
forwarding configuration is.
You have to know
where you're running
a curl or other kind of command
and then know which port
to use based on where you are to
communicate with the server
you want to communicate with.
Alright, let's add some more
complexity to the picture.
We might if I want to run
a kernel command on
the virtual machine,
I have to SSH to
it first, right?
And so how does
SSH actually work?
Well, there's two programs
or processes
associated with SSH.
The SSH client.
And then SSHD is the SSH demon.
It's running in the
background, that's a server.
And the SSH demon
is a server that's
listening on port 22 of
that public facing neck.
And so what happens
when somebody runs
an SSH command in their
terminal on their laptop?
Well, it's going to
communicate out over
that public facing ENS or
that public facing neck,
and it will send traffic there.
And basically, any
command you type
here is going to get
forwarded over there,
and SSHD will run
that command on the VM
instead of my laptop, right?
So I can do that. Alright.
My goal that I'm working
towards is that I eventually
want this browser
to open up Jupiter lab
for one of these over here
on the right hand side.
Okay. So there's an idea
very similar to Docker
port forwarding,
which is called an SSH tunnel.
Basically accomplishes the
same thing. Different name.
You use it slightly differently,
but if it's very
related concept.
So with an SSH tunnel,
what we can do is we can say L,
after SSH command, I
could do like one dash
or I could have multiple tunnels
if I had multiple
things like that.
And in this case,
we're always going
to have four parts.
The first two parts are
corresponding to a neck,
local host corresponds to
my loopback device
neck and a port.
And so the first two are for
the machine where I'm
running that command.
And then the other
two are the same,
but those are for the machine
that I'm connecting to.
And what this tunnel means is
that if there's any traffic
coming to the loopback device
on port 5,000 on my laptop,
SSH is normally a client,
it's going to be
a server and it's
going to capture those packets,
and it will forward
them along to SSD,
the server or on the
virtual machine,
and SSHD is responsible
for sending them
to Local Host 300, right?
So whenever I send something to
Local Host 5,000 on my laptop,
it pops out on the other
side at Local Host
300 on the virtual
machine, right?
So SSH tunnel gets us
from the laptop to
the virtual machine.
The Docker report
forward and gets us from
the virtual machine
inside of a container.
And so maybe you can
see how we could
start to combine these things,
actually set up a
communication channel, right?
So if I open Chrome
and I type in Local
Host 5,000 slash lab,
that will get here, it'll
get forwarded along.
It'll then get forwarded
through Docker port forwarding,
and then ultimately, it
will end up at Jupiter lab,
and I can interact with
Jupiter lab from my browser.
Okay? All right.
Any questions people have about
that? Yeah, right over here.
So the two Docker commands
right now they're both image.
Does it have to be two different
images, right? Oh, yeah.
You're saying both docker
commands are going to my image.
So does it have to be different?
It doesn't have to be.
It could be the same.
Always one container.
So whenever I do Docker
on and I say an image,
then it creates a container
from that, right?
I can have a bunch of
containers that are
from different images,
or I can have a bunch
of containers that are
from the same image.
Either would be fine.
Yeah, thank you for
clarifying that.
What else do people want
to know about this?
What other things are
confusing right here?
Slide point of device.
Yeah, what is the point
of the loopback device?
Sometimes I want to have
some kind of server that
I'm maybe doing development
with or interacting with,
but I don't want other people
to have visibility to it.
I don't want them
to be able to visit
my server, for example.
And so, one of the things I
could have done is when I did
the doc report forwarding,
I could have instead of being
on the loopback device,
I could have forwarded
from ENS directly, right?
That would have some
different security.
I have a slides I'll show
how that would be different,
but it would be less secure.
Is a short answer, right?
It's more secure to listen
on something local than to
listen on something
where you might get
traffic from malicious
parties, right?
And so this is something
that, everybody's
going to do a bunch of
times this semester
because we have whole projects
where it's like you're doing
stuff in Jupiter lab
inside of a container.
And one of the things I
want you to get
really good at is,
um is you'll set all this up,
and you can see there's
lots of parts to it,
and it just won't work.
You open up your web
browser and it's not there.
And so one of the
reasons that we spent
a lot of time looking at
this picture is that
when it doesn't work,
you have to think
about, well, like,
am I starting Jupiter lab wrong?
Did I do Doc report
forwarding wrong?
Did I do my SSH tunnel wrong?
And one of the things we're
going to practice with is,
how can we run coral commands
in different places to
try to diagnose where
this chain broke down.
But I want everybody
to kind of, like
internalize what this
chain looks like.
Any other questions
about this picture?
Right. Cool. So let's try
changing this a little bit.
So I said that we could opt
have with doctor Por Horner,
we could octually
have two things,
or we could have three.
I did three, but now
let's say I do two.
If I do two, then it
actually gives me
a default IP address,
which is 0000.
That means actually listen
to everything, right?
So in this case,
you can see before,
we were Oh, did I
go the wrong way?
Before we were forwarding
through that loopback device,
when I do that,
now somebody could
directly connect to
that port there.
Is that good or bad?
Well? It means that
somebody could try to
guess my password on
Jupiter or if you're running
Jupiter without a password,
which is what we'll
usually do this semester,
then they just have access.
Once you have access to Jupiter,
you can run arbitrary code.
Maybe one of the more
benign things you could do.
So somebody could
start crypto mining
and then Google
will just span you.
They could start
actually like mounting
attacks against other
other machines.
You don't want people to get
access to your Jupiter lab.
That happens
occasionally, right?
It's not the end of the world,
but we want to avoid
that situation, right?
So there's some other
security measures.
Like, one of the things
you could do is you can
imagine a firewall
that blocks 300,
maybe from certain
sources or all sources.
You could imagine having a
password in Jupiter lab.
You know what I usually do is
that I will have the
other security measure.
We're back here, and we're
going through 127001.
And I also leave the
default firewall
intact that the Google
Cloud gives me,
so if I can mess one
of those things up,
people still cannot own
my Jupiter notebook
and start running
malicious code code there.
Another thing that's kind of a
functionality related thing.
You might have noticed
that with the SSH tunnel,
there's like the
four parts, because
I have the ports on both sides,
but I also have the
necks on both sides.
Was the Docker report forwarding
is the most three parts.
And it's just
because they haven't
implemented as many features,
for whatever reason, I
don't know why and not.
They could.
But with the Docker
report forwarding,
it always forwards to the
public facing Nick, right?
It will never for forward
to the loopback device.
I don't know why they
haven't done that
maybe they will
someday But one of
the implications of
that is that if I start
a server here and I listen
on the loopback device,
then there's no way to get
port forwarding to get
the traffic to me, right?
So, my advice when
you're starting Jupiter
lab inside is always zero,
zero, zero, zero or
any other server
inside of a container for that
matter that we can forward in.
But outside of it, we want to
forward from the
loopback device so
that people cannot send this
traffic from just anywhere.
Alright, do people have
questions about the in
security aspects of that or
how to set it up in this way?
All right. Cool. So we'll
do the demo first, right?
And then people can ask
questions during the demo.
Then right after that, I'm
going to do a top hat.
Send going head over here
to my virtual machine.
And I'm going to go under
this forward directory.
And let's take a look
at this Docker file.
Okay? So I'm starting from
a Ubuntu Docker image.
I'm doing my apt update
and install stuff.
Before I was showing this tool,
I was like, IP address.
That's usually installed by
default and not entertainers,
so I have to install this
IP route two thing to get
that I'm topping in this
requirements dot TXT file.
Down here, I'm doing a
PEP install R and that
means it wants to read from this
requirement, dot TXT file.
I'm go to show it
soon, but basically
what that has is a list of
all the packages one per line
that I want PEP to install.
So if I have a bunch of
them, that's often more
efficient than putting
them on one big line.
And then finally, down here,
we're starting Python.
So run Python module
is a program.
The Python module
that we're talking
about is called Jupiter lab.
When I'm in a container,
everything is root.
Jupiter lab doesn't normally
like to run his root,
but we'll do it anyway.
If I set the token to
be empty like this,
that means that my Jupiter lab
has no password
associated with it.
So I need to make sure
I have those other
security measure
measures in place.
All right. So then down here,
I have to put an IP address.
D remind me what
I must put here.
What is the only
reasonable option.
The right here. Excellent.
Excellent, right?
0000. Because we're running
inside of a container
and any docker port forwarding
only goes to the
public facing neck,
it won't troll to
the loopback device.
I don't know what IP address
the public facing Neck has yet.
And so this will make
sure I cover it.
The port number
could be anything.
Does anybody wanted to shout out
their favorite
number? What's that?
300. Okay, let's do 300.
So I will do 300 over here.
All right. Fantastic. And
then I'm going to build it.
So let's build this thing.
Actually, I'm may to say build
the docker file that's in
the current directory
and then tag
it as something called demo.
I did that before. I would
have been kind of slow,
but I've done it
before, so it's fast.
Let me show you
this requirement,
dot TXT file that
was used, right?
There's actually quite a lot of
packages in here, you know, 90.
And let me take a
look at Jupiter Lab.
You can see I'm installing
version 4.25. Of Jupiter Lab.
That was really the
only thing I wanted,
but Jupiter Lab
had dependencies,
and those dependencies
had other dependencies,
and ultimately had
like all this stuff.
And one of the implications
of that is if I'm
trying to get somebody
else to reproduce my environment
exactly to be exactly
the same as mine,
it's not enough for me to tell
them use Jupiter Lab 425.
Because when I did that,
maybe Jupiter Lab grabbed
the latest version
of markup safe,
which was 2.1 0.5.
Maybe when somebody else uses
that same version
of Jupiter lab,
it might grab the
latest markup safe,
it might be like
2.1 0.6, right? So
When you want to tell somebody,
run your environment exactly the
same way like I ran mine,
you have to tell them
the exact versions
for all these
different packages.
That sounds like a pain, but
it's actually easier than
you might expect because
there's with PIP,
you have this freeze tool,
and that will basically
tell you the versions
of all the packages you
currently have installed.
And so, for example, the
way I built this file is
I just redirected
that to request ITXT.
So people often do that.
They have the environment.
They do a PIP freeze, dumpit
to requirement, I TST file,
and they tell
everybody else like
PIP install that same
thing that we have.
Alright, so that's
all fine and well.
So I think what we can do now
is we can do a doc or run,
and I want to run
that demo image.
And you know, I could
put a command here,
but that would override
the default that I
already showed you,
and the default was
basically Jupiter lab.
So I can do that.
That will take a moment,
but it's going to
start up Jupiter.
I can see their Jupiter is
running. That's pretty cool.
I can see it's
listening on port 300
inside as suggested, so
I'm going to kill this.
And what I want to do now is I
want to run it with a
specific port, right?
So I can say P,
and then I'm going to have a
port forwarding to a port.
And before this, for
this first port,
I have to say which neck
on my virtual machine
is it forwarding from.
And I'm going to
say one, 27, 001.
And then there's these
two numbers here.
One of them, there's
only one choice
that I can use andother
one that could be free.
So I want to survey
people one or two.
If I only have one choice here,
hold up one finger, if
the second one is the
one where I have to get it
exactly right, hold
up two fingers.
I see people saying
two, which is correct.
To shout out, what do I
have to put on this side?
300, because that is what is
inside my notebook.
Then I don't know.
Somebody else have
some favorite number.
Three oh one. Three
oh one. Okay.
Fantastic. So we're going to
forward three oh one to 300,
and I may run this in
Demon mode or detached
mode. So I'm may run that.
It's running in the background.
I'm going to do Docker PS.
I guess I have quite
a few things up,
but this is the one that
started in the last 2 seconds.
And I can see that it's
forwarding three oh
one on my loop back
device to 300, right?
And so maybe what I might do
is I might try to
communicate with it.
And I May 1 do that from
inside of the container.
So I'm going to
do a docker exec.
IT. And this one is
called Wizard Agnesi,
and I'm going to get a bash
session inside of there.
And then I can do
a curl if I want,
I can do a curl to Local host,
and then let's do 300 was
the number that was chosen.
And I have a typo there,
so let's try that.
And there's no output.
You know, if I tried
something else,
right, like, it'll
actually give me an error.
So it's not a complete
failure, right?
Because I'm not getting an
error. Why is it empty?
Well, it was a successful
request and response,
but that response is sending me
back success and an empty body.
So it's showing me the
empty body right here.
So sometimes instead
of just seeing
the request or response
body coming back to you,
you might want to say,
V, V means verbos.
Verbos means, like,
tell me everything.
I could do a verbose on that.
And now I see, sure,
what I told you, right?
There was a zero content length.
There's some other debug stuff.
But more interesting is
I can see in plaintext,
what the HTP request look like.
And then down here,
I can see what
the HGP response looks like.
So I got a three oh two status,
which was found like four
oh four would be not found.
Here it is finding something
But what it's telling me is
that instead of having a body,
it's giving me a location.
And what this is basically
is an HTP redirect.
I'm sure you all have seen that.
You type in a URL and
redirects you elsewhere,
and a web browser would
fall out automatically,
Carl is not doing that.
But it gives me a good
hint about what to do,
and that I can type
in lab afterwards.
Now, what is all this?
This is like a bunch of
HTML and Java strip
for that page.
It would be nice to
see in a browser,
but at least what
I verified is that
the networking aspect
of this works.
So when you're
troubleshooting these things,
like if you're trying to
get Jupiter lab working,
the first thing I asked a
student is can you go into
your container and can you
talk to the server? We can.
Great. That's fantastic.
So I'm gonna jump out of there.
Let me just grab that command
again that I just used, right?
I think it was somewhere.
It was right here, actually.
So I'm gonna grab
this command again.
I'm also going to just like to
refresh our memory
to a doctor PS.
And then if I run
that thing, now
I'm getting an error, right?
So I wonder what do I need
to change about this?
He.
One. It should be
three oh one, right?
So when I'm inside, I use 300.
When I'm outside, I
use three oh one, right
now, I'm outside.
And so you have to think
about where you are to
properly formulate your
request. Fantastic, right?
So now I verified that Docker
report forwarding is working.
If I was trying to troubleshoot,
I would try to rule that
out as an issue. Alright.
Cool. So that's all
fine and well so far.
What I want to do
now is I want to see
if I can actually do this in
my web browser on
my laptop, right?
Let me just Let me just
do this by the way,
to make it a little bit
shorter, by the way.
Alright. So what I'm going to do
is I'm going to come over here,
and I may get a new
SSH session drawing.
And then I can say L,
and then I have to have
the four parts, right?
I have on my laptop
where I want to
forward from session,
going be local host.
Some number. And
then I need to go
to my virtual machine, right?
I may have to have
something over there.
Maybe be helpful to look back.
What did I do over here? I did
local host three oh one, right?
I know that if I can
forward somebody to
local host three oh
one, I'm good, right?
So I have local host here
and a local host here.
Does somebody else have some
favorite number they would
like to use 302.
Okay, right? The earlier
crowd was like, malicious.
They were like trying to
choose, like, Port 22 or like,
ports that were going
to cause problems for,
maybe SSH choses Port 22.
So thank you all for choosing
nice friendly ports. So
I'm going to do that.
It actually says
permission denied,
so I didn't actually
establish that.
Maybe it was a malicious port.
Why is that? Well, there's
certain well known ports
like 22 or 80 or 43.
And to use those,
you have to be the root
user, right Because they
kind of normally have this
other well defined purpose.
So I could do like a pseudo.
That should work, or
probably better is that I
choose a port number that's
bigger than three oh two.
Notice that, like it end
be an obvious error.
You have to kind of read
carefully and notice,
though it was a problem
because it kind of
just carries on. So
I'm going to do that.
And so now, If I
come back to here,
it's forwarding everything
on my laptop that's coming
here to this place on
the virtual machine.
And so since I'm on my laptop,
this is the local host
that I need to put here.
My browser on L url is
smart enough to forward.
You see I put a lab in there
for me automatically.
That's cool.
I can open a Juper notebook,
I can run whatever
computation I want to run.
This is what your
development environment
is going to look like for,
like, a fair number of the
projects this semester. Oh.
All right. Cool.
So maybe I'll just
be over here showing this.
And I'll just pause and see.
Do people have any
questions about either like
the port forwarding stuff
or the SSH tunnels?
Oh, right. Yeah, right here.
Explain to me why we
don't have to use
the 300 part why we don't
have to use the 300 part?
Well, we're trying to
chain things along.
So the first live link of the
chain is from laptop to VM.
The second link of the
chain is VM to container.
And so you said,
why don't we have to use
You said why don't we have
to use 300 or three oh one?
300 Yeah.
So 300 was what Jupiter
was running inside
of the containers?
That's the second
link of the chain.
The second link of the chain
was three oh one to 300.
And so I set that up when I
did the docker port forwarding.
And so once I have set that up,
to connect that chain all
I have to do is I have
to get to 301, right?
That 301 to 300 is
already set up.
Now I just have to get to 301.
And that's what this
is doing right here.
So I do SSH tunnel
to get to the VM.
Then I use Docker port
forwarding to get
inside of a container on the
VM. Does that make sense?
Fantastic. Yeah, what else
do people want to know?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So the question is,
if I exit out of
this SSH session,
that would break the chain.
And then I would refresh this,
and it's. The chain is broken.
And so maybe if you're like
working on something stop,
you have to like figure
out, did you close
a terminal or figure out
where it broke, right?
Yeah. Yeah. Excellent point.
Yeah, what else do people
have points or questions?
Yeah, right here. Yeah.
Sent So you're saying,
what is the risk of somebody
running something malicious
inside of our docker container?
Well, if they could
run on my laptop,
then they could do
something malicious, right?
Because they could take
advantage of that SSH tunnel.
If they had my private SSH key,
they could establish
a tunnel from
a different machine and they
could do something bad.
But if they don't have anything
related to SSH, right?
If they can't have
access to that tunnel,
then it's relatively
secure, right?
Because they don't
have a way to talk to
local host on that machine.
And local host is the
only thing that is
forwarding to the
docker container.
So this is a safe set
up. That makes sense?
Yeah. Mm hm. They couldn't
even establish a
connection, right?
Like the default, if you create
a new virtual machine on GCP
and you don't mess with
the firewall settings.
By default, the only
thing they have
open is Port 22 for SSH,
because, well, that's
like the first thing
you do with a new
virtual machine.
So if you don't go in and
mess around with your
firewall settings,
then all the security kind
of falls on SSH alone,
and then of course, SSH
is very secure, right?
Yeah, doing questions. Yeah
other questions people have.
All right. Fantastic.
So now let's go ahead
and we're going to go to
top at and make sure that
all kind of sunk in.
30 seconds left.
Alright. So most people
are saying 7,000,
which is correct.
We're running in a
browser on our laptop.
And our laptop is
forwarding from
Local Host 7,000 to
the virtual machines.
So Local Host 7,000 is
the correct answer.
You can imagine trickier
variance I could have of this.
I could say, like if I
was running a curl command
on the virtual machine,
then it would be
kind of irrelevant,
what I did with the SSH tunnel.
I mean, I could say,
if I was running a curl command
inside of the container,
then there's a lot of kind
of misleading information here.
That's not relevant. So,
you have to think
about the chain,
and then I might ask you
about at various
points in the chain,
how would I connect to
that server? All right.
Cool. So I think that's good.
So that is networking
port forwarding stuff.
Let's learn about
doctor Compose.
And doctor Compose is
an example of an
orchestration tool.
Orchestration is
something that will let
you deploy a bunch
of containers at
the same time that are working
together in some way. Right?
And so the most by far,
the most famous
container orchestrator
is called Kubernetes.
It's often abbreviated k8s
because there's
like eight letters
between the K and S.
It's quite complicated.
We're not going to spend
time learning this semester,
but it's something that
I bet a lot of you will
end up using in your careers.
And so we're going to
use doctor Compose.
Some people don't even really
consider doctor Compose like
a real orchestrator
because it cannot
spin up containers on different
machines in a cluster.
It's spinning up
all the containers
on the same virtual machine.
But as advantage of that,
it's kind of a
simple, easy to use.
It's great for
pedagogical purposes
to get exposed to what we need.
And so like often you're going
to be doing the semesters,
you're going to be
writing something called
a Doctor composed file,
and then I can run
some command on it,
and then I can bring
up your cluster,
similar to what you were
running on your machine.
So, we've seen that
with the Docer
There's a bunch of subcommands.
Like I can say, like
Docker PS or Docker run
or Docker build or Docker pull.
And the same way, it's
going to be like Docer
compose and a lot of
different things.
Docer compose up,
Docker compose down,
Docker compose PS, right?
And so what we'll do is we
can run Der compose off,
and then we'll spin up a bunch
of containers that
work together.
Maybe there's like
a web server that
is kind of displaying
information from a database.
Maybe there's a separate
thing that's doing
some machine
learning on the data
in that database.
Who knows, right?
You could have some
application with a
few parts that are
working together,
and they can all
come up together.
Let's add over and do
some examples with this.
And so let me just
close this over here.
And so Here I am.
I guess I have an SSH
teller right now.
I don't think so. All
right, that's fine.
So I'm going to go out
here and I am going
to start with an
existing application,
and it's in the
starter directory,
which is already pushed.
I'm just going to recursively
copy starter to lecture two.
And then I'm going to
go on side Lecture two.
And there's already
some stuff here.
And I have an application.
What we're going to do
is we're going to have
three instances of
this application
running alongside each other.
So the application
Is a GRPC application.
And so we have a
protocol buffer file,
and the service that we're
going to be building, right?
When I build this,
that service is
going to get traverted
into a class,
and the class will have one
method I have to override.
That method is called count.
It takes a request and
returns a response.
The request is empty,
and the response is just
giving me some number.
And the idea of the applications
is like the first time I call
it is going to return one,
the next time it's
going to return two,
and it's going to keep
ticking off, right?
So this is an server Pi.
You can see that there's
that counter servicer,
and if I want to basically
build an application,
use that interface,
I have to create
a subclass from it and I
can override that method.
So here I have a
global total variable,
counting up, returning it,
and all this other
stuff is trying to like
generic GRPC stuff that we
talked about on Monday.
All right, so that's
my application,
and I would like to deploy
it in a docker container.
So I may take a look at this
docker file right here.
I can see that I'm installing
some stuff that we need,
and then ultimately down here,
I am going to run it. And
I thought I did this.
Maybe I updated somewhere else.
When I run that
server, I want to run
it in an on buffered mode.
Let me just take a look at
that server quick again.
Alright. This is all good print
started when it starts running,
and it's on buffered,
so we should actually
see that. Alright.
Let me build this thing. So I'm
going to do a docker build,
and I want to build
the Docker file on
the current directory and I'm
going to call it counter,
and so I'm going to
get a docker image.
Cralld docker images,
I'm going to get
one called counter,
which is right here, fantastic.
All right. So that's
so far so good.
So what I'm going to
do now is I want to
run do a docker run on it,
and I'm just going to
start with one before
we do the Docker composed stuff.
And I'm going to run
it in the background,
and I'm going to have some port
here and it's staring to
forward to some port inside.
Let me just take a moment
and look at my server dot
P. My server dot P is
listed on port 5440.
And what that means is
that when I run this,
I have to put 545440 here,
it's not going to work.
Over here, I could
put whatever I want.
So I'm going to put 54321.
And then anything
going to 54321 on,
my virtual machine is going
to forward to the 5440.
So I'm going to do that.
I think it already
has a reasonable
start up command.
And so hopefully, well,
what is the name of it?
It's called counter, right?
So I can run that thing.
I could look at like
the docker logs
for this container
idea, if I wanted to.
It says it started fantastic.
And then I could try
communicating with it, right?
So there's a client over here.
And the client creates
a counter stub.
Remember that with GRPC,
the stub lets you call
methods on it like you're
calling a regular method,
but it doesn't execute like
a regular method. It
doesn't execute here.
It executes somewhere else.
So when I create this stub,
I can call that
count method on it,
and then, you know, I'll
get the count back
from the server.
Up here, what I'm
going to do. I thought
I made all these changes,
and then I think I made them
in the wrong directory.
What we're going to
do is we're say up
here for that stub,
that sub needs a channel,
and I say in the command line,
like, where is the server
that we're talking
to here, right?
That's the goal. And so
I can say over here,
I can say Python three,
client dot Pi, and I
can say local host.
In this case, I need to say
the port on the outside
because even though
the server is inside of
that virtual machine,
I'm running the client outside.
It needs to forward the GRPC.
There's some modules
I have to install.
I've actually done that.
It's in this virtual
environment.
Again, like last time, I could
say, source virtual environment,
been activate, and then I should
be able to run that client
and I can talk to it,
and that count keeps going up.
L et me just take a look at
that container I have running.
So I think it is
this one up here.
And so I am going to
jump inside of it.
I'm going to say Docker Each
IT and I'm going to get
a bash session here.
If I'm inside and
I try to run this,
It's not going to work in
that in that case, right?
I have to figure out
what is it inside?
I could look back
at my code or I
could run an SS
command like before.
I guess maybe I forgot
to install something.
I think there's a
bunch of suff I
fixed on an older version.
Anyway, inside it was 5440 440.
And if I want to fix
that, I would have
to install that IP route.
So why is that not working now?
Well, I'm going to try
installing that thing after all,
I'm going to do an app
to install IP route
because now I want to
actually troubleshoot this.
So I guess it's nice to
teach troubleshooting,
even if that wasn't my
intention at the moment.
So I'm going to
install this thing,
and then I can see IP address.
And I can also do S STLPN.
And so I can see sure
enough it's on Port 5440.
And so you know what
my problem is is that when
I'm doing this client over here,
It's the old version. I just
literally changed that,
but I have to rebuild it, right?
So I'm going to
rebuild that thing.
I'm going to run it again.
Actually, I'm just going to
kill everything honestly.
Let's kill all the containers.
Run it again. My apologies
for all the confusion.
I just have one thing now,
and I'm going to
jump inside of it.
Docker Exact IT, I'm going
to jump inside of it,
and now I g to be able to
say Python three client Pi,
and now I should be able
to say local host, 5440.
It's counting inside.
Let me go outside again.
When I'm outside, then I have to
use the outside p, right?
When I do like Docker PS,
I can see there's the outside
port and the inside port.
In this case, I'm outside,
so I would use the outside port,
and it's the same same count.
Okay. My apologies.
That was a big
diversion. I want to get
back to Docker Compose.
What may do is I may spin up
three counters like this,
and I can communicate
with different ones.
The way I do that is
I create something
called a Docer Compose file,
and it's a dot YML,
and that stands for yet
another markup language.
So I guess it's a
joke that people keep
coming up with markup languages,
and they have yet another one.
This one is often used
for configuration stuff,
and it's equivalent to JSN.
So in JSN, you have,
like lists and
dictionaries, all that stuff.
But it's going to
be a format that's
actually nicer to look
at for a human, right?
So it's kind of
equivalent to JN,
but they have a different
syntax for all this stuff.
And so what I will do
down here is I have to
define some services
that I want to start up,
and I can give them some names.
I'm going to have a counter
service that I want to do.
And then inside of
that, I have to
say what docker image do
I want to start from?
And I had created a Docker
image called Counter, right?
So I could grow and I could
run this if I wanted to,
and that would start
up that container for
me automatically.
The other thing I can
do, is I can say,
I want to have some
deploy options.
And I can say, how many
of these do I want?
And in this case, I want to say,
I want to spin up three
of these things, right?
Let me come out here. I have
one thing running right now.
What I may do is I'm may
say, Docker compose,
up, is starting to
find that Yamel file.
It's starting to create
a virtual network for
me for this little
cluster of containers.
Is starting to start
those three containers.
I can see by
default, is actually
showing me the log
output of each of them.
Like one I guess each of
them printed started,
and it's showing me that
altogether, so I could use that.
The other thing I could do
is I could start them all on
a detached mode, right?
So I could do that.
And then if I do Docker PS,
I can see there's
four containers here.
There's the three for my
Compose and one other one.
Another thing I
could do is I could
say Docker Compose PS,
and would just show me
the ones related to
this specific cluster that
I have up and running.
So I was able to
start these three.
None of them have
port forwarding,
so I cannot communicate with
any of them from outside.
I'd like to
communicate with them
all from the outside world.
So I may come back here to
my Docer composed dot aml.
And what I'm going to do is I am
going to say that I want to
have some port forwarding.
I want to make sure I get
the syntax right on this.
So you can see this is
kind of like a dictionary.
This was a dictionary, and then
counter service was a
key inside of that,
which brings us to
another dictionary.
We have these keys.
That's all equivalent to
like a JSN dictionary.
This is going to be
equivalent to a JSN list.
I can kind of mark things
off like bullet points.
And so the port
configuration is going
to be a string, and I
could say something like,
I want port 5,000 to go
to 5440. I could do that.
By default, that's
going to be the 0000.
By default. I don't
really want that.
I want to keep everything
private for security reasons.
So I'm going to say, Okay,
I only want to forward
from that local
host to the 5440.
I could do that. When I do this,
I actually have a
little problem.
Let's try a Docker compose up.
I'm going to say,
Docker compose up.
Ist recreating these things.
And it seems like that's
going to take a moment.
And sometimes Docer
composes just
randomly slow, and frankly,
I'm not sure why that
is. There we go.
And right now when I did this,
it turns out that only
one of the three is
running the other two died
because when I
look back at this,
I'm starting three of them.
And so one of them
will grab port 5001st,
and the other ones cannot do it.
And the way we solve
this problem is we can have
a range of port numbers.
So I'm going to say 5,002,
and I'll have 5,000,
5,001, 5,002.
Those three will be ports
on my virtual machine,
and each of them will forward
to a different container.
Inside of each container,
I have this port,
but these are the three
containers outside.
Let's try bringing
that up again and
see if that works a
little bit better for us.
And I want to do it
with detached mode.
So I'm going to say
Docker Compose PS,
and I can see they
each have it, right?
So this one has 5,000
forward to this.
This one has 5,001.
This one has 5,002.
And so when I'm
running my client now,
I can say local hosts,
and I can say any
of these, right?
So the first one, I'm going
to get a count there.
And then I'm ready
to go to this.
And can people hold up
some number of fingers?
What would I see when
I run this command?
I'm seeing some ones,
which is correct.
I'm going to do that, and
that's a different server,
so it has its own account
associated with it.
If I go to the next one that has
a fresh count as well, right?
So I have different
servers that are
each kind of doing
something similar.
Of course, you do something
a lot more complicated.
Maybe they're each responsible
for different data.
That's where you're
going to do on one of
these upcoming projects.
That's communicating
from outside.
I can also communicate
from inside if I want.
And so let me jump
inside one of these.
I'm going to do a doc exac
and they were each given a name.
And so this is the name
that it was given.
Start based on what
directory I'm in,
and I want to get a bash
session inside of there.
And so when I'm inside,
I could say Python three client,
and I could say local host.
5440, so I could do that,
and I can keep going
with this count,
or I could try to
communicate with some of
these other ones, right?
So what I could do is,
I could try to communicate
with let me see. I
jumped into this one.
Let me communicate with
the other one, right?
And that one has a
different count, right?
So when you're inside of that,
they can communicate
each other using
these names that were
automatically generated for them.
So on the next project that
we're going to release soon,
you're going to have a little
doctor composed cluster,
and they're going
to figure out based
on their name what their job is.
They're each going
to be responsible.
We're going to have
a giant data set and
there's going to be two parts,
and then they're
each going to be
responsible for half
of the data set.
What questions people have
about doctor Compose?
Yeah, I right here. Yeah, so
why can't you have one port that
forwards to multiple
docker containers.
You know, it really
depends on the operating
system in the old days,
like Linux could never
have multiple applications
on the same port.
They actually lifted
that constraint,
but a lot of applications
still don't allow it.
So, I mean, you
could imagine that
like somebody could
have built Docker
differently so that
stuff coming in on
one port randomly goes to
a different container.
They don't support
it that I know of.
Maybe there's some
weird flag somewhere.
And I think I'm out of time,
but I will be happy to
take questions if
people just want
to come up and happy to chat.
So I hope you'll have
a great evening. I