Day. So we're going to continue
talking about the Cloud,
and we'll probably
wrap that up and start
talking a little bit about
big query today as well.
Looking ahead at the schedule,
I'm sure you're all
aware that we have
a Thanksgiving break
coming up as well.
I am, at least for
now planning to still
do a lecture on Wednesday.
But I know a lot of
people will be traveling.
So if I do do a top hat
or anything like that,
I'll just leave it
up for a while,
or maybe I'll just
skip a top hat.
So I won't be offended if
people are traveling that day.
The other thing is
that a lot of TAs,
matters are also traveling,
and so rather than trying to
mess up our whole schedule
and revert it back,
we just have a
separate schedule,
really, actually starting
today for Thanksgiving week.
So make sure you're
looking at the right
schedule during this week.
I think that we you know,
a lot of these people
are traveling as well,
so they change,
like, whether it's
on Zoom or in person as well.
There's probably more zoom, so
hopefully that will
help all of you,
you know, if you're needing
some help from home.
And and then like Wednesday
through or I'm sorry,
Thursday through Sunday,
there are no office hours.
Cool. So You know,
that's time me up.
Hopefully everybody
has a good break.
I want to do some
quick top hats before
we just to review where what
we've been lucky at so far.
This one has asked you about
what kind of hosts we deployed
our virtual machines
this semester.
Alright, so most
people are saying
multi tenet, which is tractory,
remember that multi tenant
means that you have
one physical machine that's
shared across
different customers.
Those customers
are called tenets.
And that's the usual case.
If you're willing to pay a lot,
and you're very
concerned about privacy,
that maybe you could pay
like thousands of dollar
a month to have a
sole tenet host.
Cool. Let me bring
up the next one.
This next one is
about the Spark stuff
that we're looking at
the spark streaming stuff
with the water mark.
Let me pop this one up.
Alright.
Alright, so most people
are saying 5:00 P.M.
Which is correct. So the
time window starts at 2:00
P.M. We're grouping
by two hour windows.
So the end of this
time window is at 4:00
P.M. And so I'm
here to imagine at the
very end of this, right?
We have a row for
3:59 P.M. And so
what is the latest
possible that at
3:59 row could come in?
Well, based on the
water mark we have,
we're assuming it can be
delayed by most 1 hour.
So instead of 359, be 459.
That's the most
going to be delayed.
At 5:00, well,
there's going to be
no more data coming
in for this window.
Do people have any questions
about the water marks?
This is a strategy that
was very useful for
grouped aggregates
with streaming
and also the stream
stream joint.
Alright, cool. So we're
going to head back here.
And we were talking about
different resources
last time that you can
read of the Cloud.
We already talked about
compute memory and storage.
Now we're talking
about networking.
So what we're really interested
in with thinking about
what you can pay
for networking is is the
topology of the Cloud.
So most cloud providers
will generally
break up the world into Cdiates,
those cadates t to roughly
resemble the geographic
candidates we're familiar with.
But of course, from the network,
you're really interested in
is network connectivity.
So sometimes they fudge it a
little bit, but that's fine.
They have kind of
big regions, penits.
They'll have more localized
areas called regions.
The region might be
a single building or
maybe like a few buildings
of data centers, right?
Within one of these regions,
they'll have what they
call availability zones.
I actually went on a tour
of a data center once.
So I got to see some
availability zones.
We were kind of,
like in the big,
like warehouse room, and
they had different
shipping containors,
each of which had quite
a few servers of them,
but each shipping container had
its own power
supply and network.
And so it's like you
could look at it, Oh,
that shipping container,
is this availability
zone if that one.
So you can already imagine,
like if there was a tornado,
like, probably all those
availability zones
will get destroyed together.
But things like localized power
outage or network issues,
odds are that only
one availability zone
will go down at a time.
If you're to play
the stuff we learned
about this semester,
this is very relevant.
So, for example, when we
learned about Sandra,
we talked about how
there's a token rig.
And you walk the token
rig to figure out
which vetoes you want to assign
to a given piece of data.
We talked about how
sometimes you skep, right?
If you have two
vetoes on the same
physical machine,
you skip, right?
Be that machine dies,
you lose both your Vendes.
And so you could configure it,
so it will skip in more
complicated situations.
Maybe you want to skip
so that you don't
have two Vendes in the
same availability zone,
or maybe you want to
make skipping rules,
so such that you
get your data at
at least two different
AWS regions, right?
So you want to kind
of think about
the plow topology when you're
deploying these all your systems
and try to make
them fall tolerant.
So when we're talking
about network,
we can talk about either data
coming to a node or coming out.
And the words for
those are going to be
dress and grass respectively.
And Cloud providers
will generally
bill you for how many
bytes you're moving,
and they'll bill it differently
depending on which
direction it's going in.
For res, again,
different cloud providers
do whatever they want.
But for NDS, what
I've seen is that
they often will
do that for free.
And that makes sense because
they want you to
loan your data in
the system because once
your data is in the system,
then you start paying them
for different services.
They'll usually make that free.
And then Egress is
more complicated.
They'll usually
charge you for that.
They don't want you to
leave. And in general,
they don't want to
subsidize it, right?
There's a cost to them,
and they're passing
that on to you.
And so the rate is actually
quite complicated, right?
If you like go look
it up, you know,
there's like tables and
tables of information.
And I'm just trying
to give you some,
very coarse overview of what
Egress fees might look like.
They'll often break it down
into a few different levels.
They might, for example, say,
what does it cost if it's in
the same availability
zone, right?
That whole availability zone
shares some networking,
so it's usually pretty
cheap for them.
And so, I looked up some prices
for the Google Cloud last year,
this was the Asian continent,
the same availability zone
there was free, right?
So that's cool. The
same region, right?
So again, this might
be the same building,
but different areas
of the building,
in this case, was one
sets per gigabyte.
The same continent, so anywhere
in Asia was five sets.
And then finally, if
you're exiting the Cloud,
that could either be
to other data centers
in Asia or it could just be,
you know, to different
candidates, right?
That was 8.5 gigabytes.
You kind of get a
sense like, Well,
how far are you
moving your data?
What does it cost?
And of course,
we're looking at something
like Casandra, right?
We're trying to
spread out our data
because we don't want to,
you know, fail if
availability zone
grows out or
something like that.
On the other hand, that's
really costs so more when
we're talking about
the network communication
between our nodes.
So you can imagine if I had like
different data nodes for
HDFS in different places,
right out it was
pipelining by data,
well, I would have
an egress fee there.
Was if it was localized,
I might not All right.
We'll just strip that for now.
Great. Any questions about
the main resources you
can rent in the Cloud?
Alright, let's talk
about billing models.
Again, like the billing
models are very complicated.
There's lots of
different services they
build differently.
But I see some common
patterns of them,
and I'm going to
show you a pattern
that applies for one of my
favorite Cloud services,
which is AW SaMD.
In this case, what
they're doing is they're
charging you for when
your functions run.
And they're basing it on
how long your functions
are running and how much
memory you allocate for them.
And the first thing they're
going to talk about
is a free air.
So this case, the
free tear, you get
1 million free function
invocations per month,
and then you get 400,000
gigabytes seconds, right?
There usually sub
kind of free tear.
And then after that,
the pricing depends
on your volume.
Lots of things in
life, if you buy
more, you get a cheaper rate.
And so the plot looks
something like this, right?
If I have x axis, a total usage,
the Y axis would
be a unit price.
It's what it starts at zero,
and then it drops
up to the peak,
and then it kind of
drops down as you go.
And my recommendation is
that whenever you're doing
something new, like,
do a back envelope
calculation, say, Well,
if we have so many users
and we're kind of, like,
just beyond the free
tier, what will we pay?
Sometimes I just people
be a little bit
careless about that.
They'll just try build
their application and
run it a bit and like,
Hey, our cloud bills are cheap,
and we have 500 users.
We have 5,000 users,
it'll still be cheap. That
might not be true, right?
You might be mostly
in that free tier.
Now, if you think
about all of this
from the cloud
provider's perspective,
they bought a bunch
of machines, right?
There these data seers, and they
can't quickly add
add more machines.
They can't do it like within
the next hour if they wanted to.
So they have at any
given point in time,
this fixed physical capacity,
and they're trying to sell
as much of that as they can.
Now, from the customer side,
it's kind of natural that
there might be times of
day when there's more
demand than others, right?
I if you're running
some kind of website,
Maybe it's busier during
times when people are
awake locally, right?
And so I don't know, I'm
pre this a simplification,
but maybe by the time of day,
there's some kind of day's peak,
and maybe at night and evening,
people are running as many
virtual machines, right?
And so any kind of gap
between that physical
capacity they have
and what they're
actually able to
sell people is
waste and capacity.
That represents lost
potential revenue, right?
So cloud providers
want to create
incentives for A for you to
run less at the peak times and
then B to actually run some
stuff at the low times.
And so sometimes
what they'll do for
virtual machines is they'll have
different kind of
complimentary billing models.
They have the odd demand model,
which basically,
if you say, Hey,
I want to start a VM, they
just start it for you,
and they keep it
running indefinitely,
assuming they have capacity.
And usually there will
be a higher price for
that because you just say
you get it when you want it.
In contrast, you can also rent
the same VMs as what
are called spot cans.
And with spot sizes,
you can specify well, what
you're willing to pay for it.
And it's almost like a market
price it'll vary
throughout the day.
If there's a bad, it's a
higher price, load of bad,
it'll be a lower
price, and then that
will kind of incentivize
you to run when
you don't have to.
For a lot of stuff,
we have these batch
computing jobs that
run in the background,
maybe it is like some
kind of big computation
that runs what's the day
to generate some report,
and maybe you're not
picky about when it runs,
there's an opportunity
there for you to pay pay
less if you're a
little bit flexible.
Now, it's possible they could
also start running you,
and then all of a sudden
there's more to bad,
and so they could do what I'm
call prep Preet means
that they take away
those resources.
So maybe they kill your VM
in the middle of its job,
and then you have to
start again later
and try to pick up
where you left off.
So if you're re to be
a little flexible,
you're willing to
be interrupted,
then you could potentially
save somebody there.
I kind of want to talk a
little bit more broadly
about different ways in
which they'll charge you,
right if they're
charging you for
reserved resources or
what you actually use.
The VMs that we rented
the semester was
really a fixed rate.
Like when you created,
it'll tell you, well,
you're going to pay
$25 a month flat.
And it doesn't matter
whether you're
using it or not, right?
I control my VM.
And if I say H top, you know,
I'm not quite using
all my memory,
and here I'm using
almost no CPU.
And that's probably
most of the case.
I'm just trying to
paying this flat rate
for something I'm
not using that much.
So that's not it's a little
wasteful. The flip side.
I'm making very predictable
bills if I just
have some kind of
flax flat billing system
like I get for virtual
machine instances.
There's also different
cloud services out
there that are what
we call auto scaling.
In that case, they will
try to look and see,
like, Well, how busy
is your service,
and maybe if you
have, for example,
think about elastic beads stock.
They have these little
containers running.
If I have, three running,
and it's under heavy load,
maybe they'll
automatically start
up a fourth one for you.
If load drops, they won't shut
it down right away because
there's kind of a fixed
cost to start it again.
But over time if load
is light load is light,
they might shut some down again.
That would be an
auto scaled service.
There's a bunch of auto
scaled services out there.
It doesn't perfectly
match your usage,
but it's a little
bit better than,
you know, some kind of
fixed billing approach.
A lot of these things
cannot scale down to
zero because it takes some
time to start up again,
and they don't want to
be kind of caught flat
footed when it's time
to I don't know,
serve some web
requests or whatever.
So there's usually kind of
a low fixed rate you pay,
and then you pay more when
load is higher, right?
Lots of services like that.
And then finally, of
the state of the art
is that they have
different pay as you
go, billing models now.
In that case, you're
just paying for
what you're actually using.
So, for example, with AWS abd,
when you call a function,
you start paying with
the function returns,
then you stop paying, right?
And I try to be the
trend overtime, right.
Bill models tend to be
fighter grade and kind of
more closely tailored to
what you're actually using.
And in big query, try to
have an option like that,
where it's just like paying
for what we're actually
using instead of just
some kind of fixed rate.
Alright, people have
any questions about
Bill models? All right.
C. Let's talk about platforms.
What I want to do is I want to
look at the different
things we've learned
this semester and then see what
is the state of the
art in the cloud.
So let's just review
this history and that
we've seen before.
Google wrote these
three famous papers
that have inspired
a lot of work,
actually, they were
Google File System Map
reduce and Big Table, right?
And core idea of these is
that you could just run on
cheap commodity hardware
that's not very reliable because
reliability should be built
into the software
out of the hardware.
If you have thousands
of machines,
even the most reliable hardware,
was going to have
some failures, right?
So they built a distributed
file system GFS.
Google File system
across lots of machines.
They had Map reduced for doing
analytics on top of that.
And then they had
this database called
Big Table built on
top of GFS as well.
And we've talked about
the open source of
equivalents, right?
Instead of the Google File
system, we have HDFS.
We have an implementation
of Map reduce.
And then instead of Big
Table, we have H base.
And so we've seen
that there's already
some different systems on
the open source side, like,
you know, after this, like,
Spark came on the sed,
for example, these systems
have been evolving.
And things have actually been
evolving like on the
commercial side too.
So we're going to go back
and kind of look at,
well, what is Google
doing now, right?
They don't publish
everything that
they're doing, but they
have published sub.
And so we can see, well,
how are things
evolving and what are
the current cloud services,
and how do they kind of fit
into these three systems
that we've seen earlier on.
So the way I do this outline
is maybe a little bit different.
But what I'm to
do is I'm to show
the four major systems we
learned this semester,
show you one
possible way you can
imagine using them
together at the same time.
And I'll go through
and see, like, Well,
how might we use a
Cloud service to
fit in this picture instead of
having these particular systems.
So here I have a
Hadoop file system,
running out a bunch
of data nodes.
I imagine have some
park files in it,
and so Spark is running
on top of that.
Where do those Spark files or
those park files come from?
Maybe there's a consumer
reading from Akoka Stream,
and it's taking
those messages and
putting them in Park files.
Where are those messages
coming from to Kafka?
Well, maybe we have some type of
Cassandra cluster
that we actually
use for transaction processing
for our front end application,
and maybe as there are
changes open there,
maybe it gets
published to Kafka,
so we eventually get it
downstream for analytics, right?
So all these systems we've
learned kind of fit together,
any of these things you could
swap out for Cloud systems.
So I'm just trying to treat this
as an outline at the top.
Instead of HDFS, we're
going to look at something
called the Closss file system.
And so let's look at this
history again, right?
So Google created the
Google file system,
and that inspired HDFS And
the Google File system,
unfortunately had a
bottle deck, right?
That was the name node,
I think they call it
something different in GFS.
But it had that kind
of single point
of failure, and
even if you have,
one secondary node to fail
over to, I wasn't great, right?
There was a performance
issue there.
And so they built
a new file system
that avoids a central
point of bottle deck
called the Colossus
file system or CFS,
they use that widely
within Google.
And you cannot directly,
if somebody outside of
Google just start using it,
but it underlies different
services that they have.
And so one of the
big ones is GCS.
Google Cloud Storage.
If anybody is
familiar with Amazon,
it would be similar to S three.
And in this system,
in some ways, it
resembles a file system,
they call it a bucket,
and it has files in it,
but we call them objects
because I don't know.
There's some minor differences
that are not too important.
But anyway, we could create
a bucket and put
some files at it,
and underneath it,
we would basically
be using the colossus
file system, right?
So it's something
that you could use
if you're willing to pay, right?
If you have one
of these buckets,
you could make it private,
maybe for your analytics data,
or you can make it public and
use it to back a website.
I would be a very cheap
way to generally back,
a public facing website.
Now, what's kind
of interesting is
that all this open source
stuff has happened,
and CT providers are
always trying to
bring people back in and
make them customers again.
And that's often
possible, right?
Because you find out that, okay,
you to play HTFS, and
it's a giant paid,
and you end up paying a
person to maintain it,
maybe more than you would pay
Drool to run something for you.
And so what they've
actually done is they
have taken the HDF interface,
and they've layered
that on top of GCS,
and that any kind of
application using HDFS,
can work in this
environment as well.
So, for example, maybe
SMART normally runs
on stuff at HDS,
but you could start
using Spark on top of
the Closss file system if
you have these buckets,
and you could set up
some kind of data
la where they're going
to manage that for you.
Alright, let's look at Spark.
Spark might be doing
analytics on HHS data,
and the equivalent here
would be big query.
And big query is a system where
they spend the most
time on this semester.
And so Big Query has a
little bit of history.
So, originally,
there was a team at
Google that was supposed to
go build something
called the Marketplace.
So the marketplace was a place
to sell software and data sets.
And for the data set stuff,
they didn't want to
just make some kind
of stupid website where people
download these big data sets
because they might be huge.
What they realized is
that if they are kind of
Hosting these datasets,
they need a way to
like query the data where it
is instead of pulling it out.
And so the people building
marketplace are like, Oh,
we should build some
query engine for it,
and that thing was
called Big query.
And they didn't have to build it
all from stretch
because within Google,
it turns out if you're a
giant company like that,
a big tech company, they
actually had lots of
different implementations of
the SQL engine internal
to the company?
I just something that
people keep building
different SQL engines
for different purposes.
And there was one that
was really gaining
traction called a
Dribble, right?
We talked about Map reduce and
kind of analytic
stuff that would do.
But it turns out that
Dribble was really
eating into that.
A lot of people are
switching from Map reduce to
dribble and kind of doing that.
So they kind of took Dribble,
and they wrapped it up
and they sell it as
a public facing service
called Big Query, right?
So we can actually go
and we can read like
the dribble paper if we want to
kind of understand a little bit
about how Big query probably
works internally, right?
They have this dribble engine.
And they did a couple of
different things with it.
What is they built it as
an ad hoc system like
Spark that could query
for data in different
places, right?
The big query engine
or rebel internally,
could query from HDFS files,
or it could query
from GCS buckets,
which are in Closss, or it
could query from various
integrations, right?
They could have a Google Street,
and they could allow big
query to query from it.
The other thing they
did is that they built
a special storage
engine that's very
tightly integrated
with big query.
Whatever you co design query
engine a storage engine,
there are ways that
you can optimize
them to get better performance.
So the big query storage engine
is also based on colossus,
but it'll be more opinionated
about what format
the data is a and then
Big Query can take
advantage of that.
We've talked about
different architectures,
how you could have like
this data warehouse
where the engine
and the storage is tightly
integrated in one system,
that's a data warehouse.
We've talked about
Data lake where
it's a little bit
more decoupled.
And Big Query doesn't
really nicely
fit into one category
or the other.
There's different
ways you could use
different components of it to
either have it kind of resemble
a data warehouse or a data lake.
So, for example, on
the left here, right,
I can imagine using
the query engine
just with some data
and GCS bucket.
That would be kind of like
a data lake architecture.
Other systems could use
the data of those
buckets as well.
If I'm using the Big
Query query engine
with the storage
engine they have,
then it would more
resemble a data warehouse.
I could use a query engine
with somebody else.
Yes. That would look like
a data lake as well,
or I could even do
something very weird.
I could use Spark on top of
Big query storage because they
expose that to external systems.
That would be another
example of a data lake.
So kind of a very
flexible system.
You'd have to pick,
well, what makes
the most sense for
your organization?
Probably based on what other
tools you're trying to use.
Right? If you're using
Spark for lots of
different things,
and you spot data,
big query storage,
maybe it makes sense
to use it like this.
Now, given the Colossus is doing
the actual work of saving
these files for us,
the big query storage ig,
what it's really thinking
about most is, well,
what is the format
for these files?
It's for analytics.
Of course it's to
be a column oriented format.
I want to talk about
three formats here.
Park, which we know extensively
from this semester,
Columbo and capacitor,
all three of which are
our column oriented.
So, again, there's a little
bit of history there,
which they talk about in
this book by some roglers.
And they talk about how people
used to use protocol
buffers for everything.
You all know protocol buffers.
We use that for GRPC.
We use it for Kafka messages.
And it's kind of crazy.
I'm not even sure how this
would happen, but apparently,
what they say is
that some of these
protocol buffers they'd have
would have like
hundreds of thousands
of fields of them, right?
They just grow enormous.
And Soe people would use
that for logging, right?
Some kind of event
happens, and they'd
write a protocol
buffer to a file.
And you can imagine,
if you want to do some
analysis on that,
you could read over all the
protocol buffers in a file,
and then maybe sub over a
column or something like that.
And that's terrible, right?
That's a row oriented format.
You'd read a little
bit of data here.
Instead of reading kind of like,
big blocks of data at the time.
It's bad for Discio,
it's bad for the CPU catch.
Anyway, that was terrible.
And so they ended up building
this thing called
the Columbo format,
which was a column
oriented oriented format.
And when people built dribble,
those are also the people
building Columbo, right?
So they built dribble
which underlies
big query to use this
Colby O format, right?
Okay, that's a history there.
And it turns out
that's relevant to us,
is that Colbo
format was actually
inspiration for
Park files, right?
They published a
paper about Dribble.
And you know, other
people have read that.
And then Park files.
A lot of that was spearheaded
by Twitter and Cloud era,
and they cited that
tended the script of
Columbo format as
inspiration for, Hey,
let's build an open
source format Parke that
has a lot of the save
strategies that Colby O has.
Now, even though they
start with Cal bio,
eventually, they have
a successor to that,
and that's called capacitor.
So a big query, at least
last we've heard, right?
Who knows what's happening
internally at ogle?
Last we heard, they're
using capacitor
underneath big
query and dribble.
And they have a couple of
key optimizations there for
different kinds of data.
These refer to toting.
And totings say, well,
we have this data, but how do I
actually represent a disk?
There's a couple of scenarios
they wanted to optimize for.
One is that they said,
Let's use run leg toting, right?
So here I have Apple Apple
apple, banana, banana.
Why not just say three
apple, tata, four apple?
And that's what they do. This
is a run length encoding.
That's a general strategy.
You're find other formats that
have run lengthen coding.
If somebody says, Hey,
this format uses run
length and coding,
you should know what they're
talking about, right?
And why do you
need to know that?
Well, depending on how
your data is ordered,
run length and coding might be
great or it might
be useless, right?
If all my data is shuffled up,
run length coding won't
work well, right?
So if you're using
some new format,
you should understand what
these terms read for the
format and then figure out,
well, is this going to
help me with my data?
Or not, right? Okay, so they
get some rid of some
redundancy that way.
We see there's sill redundancy
because there's
apple there twice.
Not a big deal, but if
there's a longer word,
kind of duplicated log strings
are a source of waste.
And so the second thing
they would do is what is
called dictionary toting, right?
Each unique big value
like that would row it
in a dictionary, right?
So we have apples
wood, banana is two.
And then up above, we
could say three wds,
so that would be three
apples, two twos,
so two bananas, four
wads, four apples.
That's called
dictionary tooting.
There are lots of formats out
there that use
dictionary toting.
You should know what
that means as well.
If I have some data, I'm
trying to figure out,
is dictionary coding
going to help me?
Well, it depends, right?
If I have big strings
of their duplicates.
Yes, if all the strings are
different from each other,
then no, that would actually
make it worse, right?
Things like pier, you
can actually choose.
You could say, I want dictionary
encoding or not, right?
You need to know what
these things mean.
You need to know
kind of the characteristics
of your data.
You go to figure out if you want
these entrodings or or not.
Alright. Cool. So I do a
tophat about the entrodings.
Alright. Let me head over here.
15 seconds left.
Alright, people are saying
only run length and
toting of which is
tracked, right?
So how would I read
this down here?
There are sevens, I'm sorry,
17, three eights, two
sevens and 19, right?
So we can definitely see
that there is lingere.
What about dictionary
and? There's not.
And the reason why is that
the original values like
seven appear down here.
AD appears down here?
The original values
appear out there.
Would I want to use
dictionary Trode
here? Not really, right?
Because the whole idea of
dictionary Trode is that we take
these log strings and we
replace them with these
short editor values.
My original data is short
editor values, right?
So if I replace that editor,
the different editor, that
doesn't really by me anything.
In fact, would make it
worse because I'd
have to do a look
up each time to actually
figure out what that data is.
Do you have any questions
about the trots? Oh, right.
Let's talk about Cassandra
and some related systems, right?
And so we learned that
Cassandra and H base,
were both inspired by Big Table.
In terms of that Big
Table is still used.
That's a Google Cloud service.
You can use if you
want to, right?
So I want to sort look at the
inspirations here, right?
So Cassandra, one
inspiration was Damo.
Damo inspired it in
terms of the partitioning
and replication.
Dabo also now backs Dao DB,
which is current AWS
Cloud service, right?
So the stuff is still relevant.
Casado was also inspired by
Big Table for the data
model and storage layout.
Big Table also more directly
inspired H base, right?
And so even though Big Table
and HBase are ire similar,
some people would be running
HBase apps on top of H base.
Others would be
running Big Table apps
on top of Big Table.
One of the things
that's changed is that
Big Table now runs
on top of Closs,
instead of the
Google File system.
And they're not quite
sure, like the details
about how they pulled off
this circular dependency, right?
Be there's t limits how much
has been published. But
It's kind of cool.
Colossus, instead
of having that
centralized name node,
it stores its data
about block locations
in Big Table, right?
So somehow they figure
out how to have
a circular dependency
where, you know,
all these big table
regions, right,
are stored colossus, but
then Coss sores data
about the locations of
those in Big Table.
And the consequence
of that is they
got rid of that bottleneck,
which was the name node,
and they were able
to scale it up to,
clusters that are 100 times
bigger any used to be.
Right. That was a real
pain point they solved it.
Now, again, right, and
all these things, right?
People went off and are using
these open source systems,
which can be kind
of hard to use.
And these cloud providers
are always trying to
pull them back and
make them customers.
So HBase has its own API.
And so what they've
done is they've layered
the Has API on top of Big Table.
And now if you have
HBase application,
you can actually run it
on top of Big Taylor,
try to make it as
easy as possible
for people to move back into
the cloud and become customers.
All right. Any questions about
Cassandra or Big Table or
how that all fits in. All right.
Let's talk about Kaka.
FA is kind of interesting
because for all these
other things, right?
We see that they're
different cloud equivalents.
But Kaka is built
and maintained by this
company Ced and Fluid,
and they've managed to actually
partner with all the
cloud providers.
In a lot of cases, if
you're y a smaller company,
the cloud providers will build
their own thing to compete with
you, but somehow, I don't know.
They must have had
some business savvy,
or I don't know how
they pulled it off.
Be curious. And they
partnered with each of these.
So if you're on AWS, you can,
you know, Kafka from Tfluid,
and then tfluit will
get a cut of that.
Same thing at Doogle
or Azure, right?
So what that does
mean is that there's
two different kafkas out there.
There's the open source Kafka,
which is under the
apache license.
And then there's the tlit Kafka,
which is the closed source
one that, you know,
you could either pay
confluit for through one of
these cloud providers
or pay them directly
if you're deploying it yourself.
I think it's interesting
that there's
all these open source
companies that can
manage to have the paid service,
and then they're giving
away for something
for free as well.
I just want to talk
briefly about that of
open source licenses
and maybe how
they can build businesses
around some of these, right?
And you know, of
course, this has
very much a legal aspect to
it, and I'm not a lawyer.
But, I've read these licenses
and have read about them.
And so I'll just try to share
the limited what I know about
these different licenses that
you're likely to see out there.
Maybe that'll help you, right?
If you're doing some
open source thing,
maybe choose a license
and that'll be especially
important if you're
looking to open source
something and also build
a company around it.
It'll be cool if
some of you do that.
So one license out there
is called the GPL.
And the idea there is that
if I build this
open source thing,
and that other people are using
my source code, and
they're changing it,
and then they're selling
that software e ploy
it in some way,
they have to share the changes
they made as well, right?
So often, if you have that, it's
hard to build a
company around it
because you have to give away
all your stuff that's free,
well, then what are you really
selling in the d, right?
A lot of companies will use
either the MIT or BSD license.
Those are very short.
Delightfully. So there
will be a few paragraphs.
You can t to read it and
understand it as a non lawyer.
In the most part,
the requirements are
usually things related
to attributing like,
Oh, I got this code from so
and so, or liability, right?
I the code creates
some big problem,
it's my problem, not the
person who wrote the code.
And so those are out there.
One of the things that
these do not make you
do is open source
changes, right?
So you can d find
MIT or BST project.
You could make
improvements to it,
and then you would have
a closed source product
that you could sell, right?
So you can kind of
imagine having 1 ft on
the open source side
and 1 ft in the, Hey,
I have this proprietary product
based on the open source
thing. That's better, right?
The apache license is
kind of similar to
the MIT and BSD license
that you can still take
an Apache project,
like, make it better,
then it's like, Well,
this is my proprietary
thing, that has,
like, secret improvements,
then you could like
sell it, right?
But it's much longer, much
more difficult to read.
And that's because
it relates to Patts,
not just a copy right, right?
The MTSD, they just talk about
copy right, but of course,
pats are another big area
of intellectual property.
And so it's actually interesting
with the MIT and BSD,
if you have some new
idea, you could pat it.
You could write
some code for it,
and you can open source it.
And then people could use
that open source license.
They would have a right
to your copy, right?
They could use that.
But then you could sue
somebody using your
open source thing
based on the paddets you have.
And so Apache license
has a bunch of
kind of complicated clauses
in there that try
to deal with that,
and it says things like just
kind of this is my Layman's
understanding of it.
Like, Hey, if I'm a
company and I have
some patts and I contribute
open source to the stuff,
I won't sue people
with my paddets,
if they're using the software,
I contributed to
the project, right?
Anyway, so apache
license is very popular,
right because it lets people
build business around it,
and it considers intellectual
property more broadly.
And so what you'll often see is
that a lot of
these open source things
where you looked at,
there'll be like the open
source apache version,
and then there will
be some kind of paid,
like, better proprietary
version of it.
So, for example,
data bricks, right?
They'll help maintain
apache spark,
but they also have
data brick spark,
which is like better,
more reliable, and then you
pay data breaks for it.
Cassada you could deploy the
apache version of yourself,
or you could pay data
stacks to do it for you.
Aca, you could either
run a past Kaka yourself
or you could be paid
to run fluent aca.
Anyway, just a
little bit of a side
that might help folks
if they're kind
of working in this space
at some point. Ah, right.
So I have a few conclusions.
Clouds just keep growing
in ports and revenue,
and the services they provide,
and you know, there's
more cloud providers.
I think lots of you already have
jobs that involve working
on stuff of the Cloud.
So if you're getting
good at that,
that's, you know, a
very marketable skill.
All the resources we care
about like compute
memory, whatever?
You can rent that
in various forms in
the cloud instead of
owning your own hardware.
And then finally, right,
these cloud providers
are definitely charging
you a markup to use
their services over owning
the hardware yourself.
But that doesn't mean
that it's going to
be more expensive, right?
Because if your needs
for compute resources
fluctuates over time,
and you buy hardwareelf,
you're kinda have to buy
for the peak, right?
Whereas if you're renting, then
maybe you pay less overall,
because you aren't renting
everything all the time.
Anyway, so those are my
thugts on Cloud stuff.
Do we have any last questions
about Cloud stuff
before we talk about
big query? All right.
Col. Let's do a deep dive
on one particular cloud service,
which is Big query.
Let me head over here.
I have a few goals for you.
What is that we have to figure
out how to authenticate, right?
So if I buy by Vb, and
I want by Vb to do
queries to big query,
it needs to have some of
the permissions
that I have, right?
Like, I as a Google user,
have access to a bunch of stuff,
and I have to choose a
subset of that and say by
VM has access to a subset
of the stuff that I do.
Right? Maybe they have
access to my big query,
but I don't want my VM to
have access to my email.
To figure how we can
limit that scope.
So if somebody gains
access to my VM,
the damage will be limited.
There's a bunch of
different places
you could run big query.
We could do it like
in the Cloud Console.
We could do it with like
regular Python code.
There's a special Jupiter
extension for it.
I'm going to demonstrate
all that stuff.
And then finally, we
want to see how we
can query over
complicated types,
like, um arrays and structures.
And we're going to
have to learn a
new kind of join for that called
a correlated cross join to
kind of dig into the nested
structure and get
information out.
Alright. So just s to do some
demos first and jump in.
And remember that big query,
I either has its
own storage engine.
We can I see that, or
it could be pulling
data from a bucket,
a GCS bucket.
Is to show how we can
trade a GCS pocket first,
and then we'll be using that
in subsequent lectures.
So I'm going to head over here.
And almost everything we've
been doing so far has been
under the compute edged,
but now we're going
to be exploring
some more of the Google Cloud.
And so I reed to go
to Cloud Storage.
And as you can see, they have
these buckets over here.
And touch how to go ahead and
try to walk you through
what would happen if
we want to create a new bucket
and some of the options
that would have.
So first of, I have to
give my bucket a name.
And if I choose somebody
test, it says it's taken.
And because it's a little
bit like a domain name.
It has to be globally unique.
And of course, somebody has
grabbed test before I have.
So I'll do something a
little bit more, unique,
like November 2025, section two.
Nobody has taken that one yet.
Alright, for our
brokes, we have to
choose where the data lives.
We could say US multi region.
In that case, they're going
to try to keep it reliable.
They'll trying to keep copies
of data in different regions,
and they're going to
try to move it around
dynamically based
on where the data
is actually needed, right?
They don't want to like
send data over the network
every time there's a query.
So they just automatically
try to do their best for me.
I think that's usually
like a good option.
There are kind of like broader
regions you could choose.
I could choose a single region
more narrowly if I wanted to.
I might do that
if I want to if I
know where my customers are and
I know I want to
have it near them,
I might choose it based on that.
I might choose it based
on the cost of it.
on CO two emissions.
I could also have a
pair of them if I want.
Let me just show you some
of these things over here.
They actually have For each
of these different regions,
you can actually
just drove through,
and you can see how much is
categorized in what they call
carbon free energy
for the data center.
And so some of them
are like 98%, right?
You know, maybe there's a
dam or whatever, right?
Maybe it's thermal power, right?
So you could choose based on
that or maybe you
choose choose on price
or maybe some combination
of factors, right? Alright.
Well, so we will we'll
let them decide, right?
They have different
storage classes
based on how often
I'm acing your data.
Sometimes, we're constantly
reading and writing to the data,
so we need better performance.
Other times we might choose,
for long term archive.
I just write to it.
And since it's a backup,
I almost never need it unless
something really bad happens,
right? And so we
can choose that.
And that will
determine the pricing.
Right? We can see
up here, I'm billed
for both how much
data I write, right?
In terms of gigabytes written,
and I also pay for gigabytes
of data that are just
sitting there, right.
If a gigabyte is sitting
there for one month,
I will pay 2.6 cents,
right? Relatively
cheap, actually.
If I did something like archive,
right, then it would
be a tenth of that,
it would be 0.2 $0.04
per gigabyte per month.
Right? I can choose that.
I'm going to do standard and
and continue. All right.
We've talked about different
Linux file permissions.
We've seen that we can have
different permissions
on each file.
That would be an example
of find drain permissions.
We could do if we want.
Or we could just say, like, Hey,
the whole bucket has the same
visibility for
given user, right?
It's uniform. Either they can
see it or they can't, right?
We'll just keep it
uniform for simple.
We've talked about
data retention.
There's some
retention stuff here.
I'm ready to get past, and
I could go ahead and create it.
And at the very end,
they can ask me,
do I want to prevent the
public from seeing it?
Like it's a private bucklet,
or I want to make it public?
I'll keep it private
in this case.
Alright, so I have my bucket,
and it really just feels
like a place to
store files, right?
I can upload files
if I want here.
And sorry for that.
Let me just go over
to my downloads,
and I will upload this
Park file right here.
I'm going to upload
that. And there
we go. I can store files.
Cheap place to store
files, honestly,
compared to like
kind of a more user
facing Cloud service.
Alright, cool.
That's GCS. Any question
about GCS before I switched
to big query? All right.
So I'm going to head over here,
and I am going to go to
the marketplace,
which I mentioned,
remember that the people
building the marketplace,
that was their job,
and they realized, well, we
need a query engine, two,
so they ended up building
two Cloud services.
We can see over here
that I can filter
the data in various ways, right?
I think, for example,
maybe I want
data and I want it to be free.
And I think somewhere in
here, they have like maps.
Here are maps. Okay, great.
So I can drove through
here, and I can see
all these different data sources
that are free that I could use.
I'm going to go to the
US Census Bureau data.
They have some US
boundaries there.
And I'm going to say view that.
And when I do that, you see that
it's slightly integrated
with Big Query.
I'm going to up over and now
I'm inside of Big Query.
And I can see there's a
hierarchy up here, right?
At the top of the hierarchy,
we have different projects,
which are owned by
different people.
Like, I have my
own project here.
And then one project is
called Big Query public data.
Each project has a lot of
different datasets with it,
and each dataset with it has
a bunch of different
tables, right?
So coming down here, I can
see that I have these
GO US boundaries,
and there's different
tables underneath it.
So, for example, we have a
dataset of counties, right?
I can see the
different fields that
I have for my counties
here. All right?
So if I want to, I can
go over here and I can
query from this data, right?
So maybe I want to just
select everything first.
This is an example of
partition data set.
We'll eventually talk about
what that means, right?
There's some information related
to partitioning down here.
For now, I'm just going to say,
let's limit to one row,
or we'll say let's limit
to like three rows.
All right. So I may
I run that thing?
Well, one of the things
that sin quals, up here,
they're already showing
me how much data
will be touched when I run it.
Because they're going
to charge me in
proportion how much data is
actually touched, right?
It's a pay as you go service.
So I'm may run that, and
I will get some results.
A few counties down here.
They have these FIPS codes that
the US Census Bureau uses to
categorize different places.
I have the county names.
All of that is there as well.
And then under the
job information,
I can see how many bytes were
processed, 182 megabytes.
It's a column oriented format.
And so any kind of, like,
row oriented access
I'm doing is not very efficient.
I end up touching
a lot of stuff.
I also see they're
rounding me up in
terms of the billing
that I have, right?
Alright, Well, I have all that.
Let me do a couple
more examples here.
I want to see if I can find
Dane County here, right?
And so we will come
through and we will say,
where county name equals Dane.
And in this case,
I'm going to try to
do some fewer things.
I might say county name,
and I might say, let's
figure out what the
FIPS code is for it.
So I will say, I
think it's GO ID,
we'll tell me what that FIPS
code is. Let's try that.
In this case, I can
figure out, Okay,
this is our number
for our county there.
And if I look at
how many bytes or process
is actually much smaller.
It's like 50 kilobytes.
It's still rounding me up to
10 megabytes for billing,
but it's much cheaper than the
previous one. Why is that?
Well, if I go back over,
I wonder if I can
see it over here.
If I look at these counties,
and maybe a preview of it,
What I'm going to
see is that they
have geographic
data here, right?
They have the boundary
of each county.
That's a polygon that takes up
quite a lot of space, right?
So the main strategy
here, right,
if I want to have cheaper
queries is I try to
avoid these really heavy
weight columns, right?
Most of the billing
is drawing there.
If I don't need that, then
avoiding it's going
to make things
a lot cheaper for
me. Okay, cool.
So we have all of these
different projects,
which have different datasets,
which have different tables.
And one of the things
that's cool is we can
do joins across
different tables,
even if they're in completely
different projects
owned by different users.
Very powerful, actually, right?
If I had some private dataset
with latitude and
longitude points in it,
I could join that across
the public dataset here
where there are counties.
I can figure out, well this
latitude and latitude point
is inside of that county, right?
I wouldn't have to get
all that data myself.
I may do a simpler join.
I just want to see how I can
get all of the counties
in Wisconsin, right?
So I want to do that, so I may
select from the
counties up here,
and I am going to
join to the states.
I'm going to say
interjoin states.
Then I have to say what
what I'm joining on.
I'll say counties so
check my notes here.
It's State PIPs
code equals state,
State PIPs Code, can do that.
And then I'm going to say where
state name equals Wisconsin.
We just like to
figure out what are
all the counties here?
I already say I'm
getting an error here
and it's say unrecognized name.
And the reason counties
is unrecognized
is because I have the fully
qualified name up here.
The fully qualified name
goes project dataset table.
And so even though it's
already named counties,
I need to say counties here,
and I have to say states here.
I try that. I think I'm
still have a little problem.
That's saying GID is ambiguous.
That means that
both counties and
states has a GOID, right?
So in this case, I'm may say
this is the counties GID.
And what else would
I need? I might need
to have a state name. All right.
So let's try running this.
And this looks
correct to me, right?
These are like Door
County, Bayfield County.
There's probably Dane
County in here somewhere.
I can go through and I
can run these queries.
You know, I would work just
as well if these were in
completely different
projects. All right.
Any questions about any of
this stuff in the council?
Right. Cool. So I have
1 minute left. So I I
have a break there.
And next time we're going
to come back and see how
we can authenticate
for certain scope,
so we can do the same stuff
in a Jupiter notebook.
Have a fantastic day,
and if I don't see you
Wednesday, have a great break.