Being here today. We're going
to keep talking about big query.
We started doing some examples
last time in the Cloud Totsle.
Now, when I'm in
the Cloud Totsle,
I'm sided and Google Nos F
and I have access to everything.
What I'm may be doing now is
some examples in
Jupiter Noe book.
Jupiter Noebook
is running by VM,
and I have to give my VM some
of my credentials,
but not all of them.
And so in the lecture stip,
there's a little command,
which I've already run for that,
where I say, Well, they
are the specific scope.
It has access to
all my Cloud stuff.
It has access read
only to my drive
because I see how we can quarry
from a Google spreadsheet there.
So there's some Stuff
I could access.
That limits the damage if
somebody gets access
to my Va, right?
I they hijacked in
some way, well,
they could actually do a
lot of damage but they
couldn't access my e mail,
for example, or they couldn't
delete my Google Drive files.
Alright, o. Some
a head over here.
I've already done
that. You'll probably
use something similar
on your project.
And what I want to do is I
want to see how we can connect
with the client and then
just poke around and
see what datasets there,
what tables are there.
And so I've already
installed everything.
That's in the lecture
snippets as well.
I'm going to say from Doogle do
Cloud do Let me just
check my notes here.
Oh, Import. Big query.
And then from that
I'm going to create
a client called Big Query,
and it will be big
query dot client.
And that's automatically
going to pick up
these credentials from my VM
since they've already signed in.
And then I can do things
like big query dot
list datasets.
And here I can put some
kind of project name.
And so if I go over
to my console,
maybe your project
name is different,
but I can see up here
at the top minus CS
544 fall 24, right?
So let me see what datasets
I have. All right.
And it's going to give
me this thing that
I can list over,
so I'll say for data
set and those datasets,
I print the dataset
ID of each of those.
And I can see I've created
a couple of these so far.
Remember the hierarchy here
is that we have projects
and then that contains
different datasets
and each data set can
have a bunch of
different tables in it.
And so what I'm going to
do now is I'm going
to go ahead and
create a new dataset
programmatically.
And so I will say a
big query data set.
And I'll give it a name.
Soma have to say
project data set,
and somebody have the same
project that I own, right?
I'm going to do that.
And maybe I'll just call
this Section two, right?
Because we're section
two. That's going
to return a new
dataset for me, right?
So I'm to get that dataset,
take a look at it.
And that hasn't actually
created anything yet.
So if I want to go
ahead and create it,
then what I will do is say
big query create data set,
I'm going to pass
on that data set,
and then it will
create it for me.
Now, if I wanted to, I could
say some things up here,
I could say, data
set location equals.
I don't know, I could
pick a region, right?
Like maybe US Central
one or something
like that. I'm not
trying to do that.
I'm may let BigQuery actually
decide where to do that.
There's actually kind of a lot
of smarts that go into that
because I can query from
anything from anywhere, right?
And so if I'm running a
query in a specific place,
they want to have that data
near where I'm
running the query.
Sometimes that's hard
because any two tables
that are visible to me, I
can do a query to them.
And so if I'm joining two tables
and they're different places,
well, something has to go
over the network, right?
And so what they're
going to try to do is
they're constantly looking
at what queries I'm doing,
what tables they're touching,
and moving the data around,
if I give them the flexibility.
If for some reason,
I really want
a specific location because I
know where my customers are
or something like that,
maybe I might do that,
but in this case,
I'll let it have
the flexibility.
So we'll go ahead and
create the dataset.
And if I were to run it again,
then I would end Arab
as it already exists,
but I can tell it to
ignore that if it's already
there. That'd be totally fine.
So once that's been created,
I can come and see it over under
Big Query and under
the Big Query Studio,
I will see all of
the projects I have.
I just have one
project. And then
under here I can
see my data set.
And I just created this
one called section two,
which is empty because I haven't
put any thing there yet.
If I come back, I
can list those data sets
and now I see I was able
to create that there.
Now, even though I don't
own some projects,
there are projects out there
that are publicly visible.
And so the important one
that we're going to use for
a few things is the
Big Query public data.
And so I just want to
list what is inside
of that project.
I may come over here
and I'm may to say,
what do we have in Big
Query public data, right?
I'm maya print that
out. And there's
a bunch of stuff here
right that we can access.
And the one I'm going
to be using is called
Jit Hub repos for some
of our examples, right?
And so it turns out that
they straighted or is
that J Hub repos or just it Hub?
Why is it not finding that?
There we go. So
there's GitHub repos.
They sped scraped
Kit hub for us,
and so we can look at that.
We can analyze
different projects
and see what languages
are popular,
what licenses people are
using that sort of thing,
if we would like to.
So I'm going to come over
here and I'm going to
say a big query
that list tables.
And now I have to say
project data set, right?
And so the data set,
in this case is
that it Hub repos,
and the project is that
big query public data.
I'm I do that for
a table in that,
let me just print off the
table that table ID, right?
I can see there's maybe a
few different things there.
If I wanted to, I could actually
see the contents of
all these files.
Otherwise, I could see some,
metadata about it like
what languages are used
or what licenses applied
to the repositories.
If I want to, I could
tum peek over here,
and I could try to
find this stuff.
If I come back and I'm
looking for Jitub repos,
I might go ahead and
search that here.
And this is a little
bit confusing,
because by default, it's only
searching projects that I own.
I don't own that one. If I
say search all projects,
then I'm actually
going to find it.
And from there I can see,
for example, what
languages are being used.
I'll take a look at that.
There's two things there,
there are repository names,
and then this array or
repeated type called
language, right?
Because a single
repository might have
multiple languages
associated with it.
When I preview that,
it's kind of spreading it out,
but I may have to do a little
extra work to get that format
where I have different
lines for each language.
All right, well,
tell me back here.
Um, let's see how
we can query it.
There's a few different ways
we can query it from here.
Maybe the easiest one is by
using this get Hub extension,
which I will load from
Google Cloud dot Big Query,
a load that thing in.
They say that thing is
deprecated, deprecated,
means that they aren't
going to be supporting
it in the future,
right, so they want
you to stop using it.
Eventually, this might
not work anymore.
So they're trying to
giving you a warning
in the meantime.
I guess I just have to install
some other stuff and do it
a little bit differently.
Maybe I'll worry about
that another semester.
Still going to work
fine for today.
Once I've done
that, then I can do
big query queries like this.
Maybe I want to do a select star
from let's do one of
these tables up here.
I'm going to do a select star
from this table, I'm sorry,
that data set, and
then the table
will be the one about languages.
Let's see what languages
people are using.
And I'm going to limit to
let's say, like three,
so I don't get too many,
right? So I may do that.
If you do too many, right,
then I'll run out of memory,
and I'll have to reboot my VM.
And so what I can see here is
that they're giving
me a ras back,
and these arrays
contain structures.
So one of the goals
today is to understand,
how can we go ahead and
extract information
out of both arrays
and structures using
just just SQL.
Alright. So I have that.
You know, another thing
you could do, right,
is that I could say,
I want this to land in some
kind of Python data frame,
which is going to be Pandas,
if I look at the
type of DF, right?
That's a pandasata frame,
and then I could look at
the data there as well.
All right, that's one
way we can do it.
That's probably the
easiest way to do it.
There's also just a pure
Python API that will let us
prog programmatically
interact with and do queries.
And sometimes that's
useful because
we can see additional
information, like,
for example, how much
are we going to be
charged for this query.
So let's do that.
I'm going to say a
big query query.
It return query object.
And then I can put my
query inside of here.
Let's do that same thing
that we did before, right?
And at this point in time,
it doesn't actually do any work.
It hasn't done the query yet.
It will only do the work
if I say to data frame.
If I do that, then I
can go ahead and I can
see I have a data frame
as I normally have.
Now this is why, even
though it's more work,
it's interesting because I
can come along and I can
see how many bytes did it
have to touch to do that.
So whereas the great.
Total bytes processed.
Let's get that and that would
be kilobytes, megabytes.
Let's see how many
megabytes that is, 194.
And then I could also come
down here and I could see well,
how many are actually
build to me.
Right? So I can get
a sense of like,
how much does this
query actually cost?
Now that's in bytes.
It's not in dollars.
So I think a
valuable skill is to
be able to do some
back low calculations.
Say, Well, how far
will my free tier go?
How much will I pay after
I'm out of my free tier?
And as I'm sure I have a
couple examples of that.
I may say. For example,
how many times can I do a
query like that for free.
And a month. And
that's one question.
You know, the other question,
sorry, it keeps jumping.
The other question is, how
much does that query cost
after we've exhausted
the free tier.
That's just kind of
a good back envelope
calculation that you
should be able to do,
so you don't get surprises.
And when we do that, we have to
say well a specific
region, right?
And so let's do Tokyo.
And that's one of the more
expensive ones and
see how much it
costs to run that
query in Tokyo.
Okay, so if I want to do that,
I have to dig in and read
some documentation.
I could google it.
I also put this on
the lecture snippets.
We're using something
called on demand pricing.
And so I could come
over here and I
could read, and I
could see, well,
Okay, the first terabyte
every month, is free, right?
So I figure, well,
how many queries
like that can I do
with 1 terabyte.
Okay? So a terabyte is
L's kilobytes, megabytes,
gigabytes, terabytes.
I want how many times I go
to do a query like that?
I guess it would be
terabytes divided by.
You know, they do this round up,
so I'm not interested
in the process.
I'm care how much they're
actually billing me for.
And I could do a
query like that,
you know, 5,000
sometimes, right?
So it's a relatively
generous free tier, right?
I can do some serious
work with that.
Now, eventually,
if I exhaust it,
I want to know how
much I'm actually
going to end up paying, right?
And so in that case, what
am I going to have to do?
I'm going to have to figure out,
you know, I have
to have some kind
of price that I'm paying.
And then I need to
multiply that by
how many terabytes we're
actually using, right?
So let me just check
this here quick.
So I'm going to say,
Well, how many I
build by, right?
This is how many
bytes I'm paying for.
But since it's going to
be in units of terabytes,
I'm going to divide
by terabytes.
This is how many terabytes
I'm using to do that query,
and then I should come
over here and check well,
how much does it cost
to do to one of those?
I can see it on the
US, it's like 625.
Let me find Tokyo.
There's Tokyo. There it's
7.5. Let me copy that.
And paste that there.
This query costs 0.1 $0.03.
So still a relatively
cheap query
even after we've
exhausted the free tier,
assuming I'm not doing
it a bunch of times.
Now there are some
other factors that you
should keep in mind.
There's other billing factors.
One is that we pay for
storage if the tables
are in big query.
This is not data
we own, this case,
we're not paying for that
at all, which is straight.
Another factor is
that we round up to
the nearest megabyte
as we saw, right?
That's why there were two
different numbers here.
Then finally, what else?
We have a minimum
charge of 10 megabytes.
So you always want
to identify, hey,
am I doing a bunch
of small queries,
they're always
getting rounded up?
If so is there a way I
can group them together,
so I'm not paying
that extra overhead.
Makes sense that it's
there, right because
they have to have some start up
costs for their services.
All right, so I can do all that.
Now, in this case, I actually
ran the query because I
wanted to find out about how
much it's going to cost.
If I come back here and try
to do it again like this,
let me I'm be just trying to
come down here and run this,
and then I'll say my data
frame equals Q two data frame.
Let me run that. And when I
take a look at it again and
I look at the total by its
build, it's actually zero.
And that's because
they're doing cashing for
me on my behalf,
which is fantastic.
Thanks school for
some free results.
If I'm actually trying
to understand pricing,
I don't want them
to cash it, so I
can actually explore that.
And one of the things that
we'll sometimes do is we'll
pass in a job configure,
which will say that we
don't want cashing on.
And let me just trade
a configure here.
I may call my config no cash.
It's going to be
a big query job?
What is it called?
It's a query job.
A query job can fig.
And up here, I can say,
use query cash, and I can say,
no, I don't want
to do that, right?
And I can pass on that can fig.
Well, I'll take longer now
because it's actually
redoing the work.
And then I could see well,
what my actual pricing is.
So do people have any
questions about this, like,
basic strategy of just
like how we run queries,
how we inspect the
pricing of it,
how we do these pack of
the envelope calculations?
Oh, right. Cool. So for fun,
they've straighted all
the stuff on DET Hub,
and I have an open
source project
on DETub, called Open Lambda.
So I'm may use Open
Lambda for some examples.
We're kind of inspect what
code Open Lambda uses,
what licenses are on it.
And I'm to do a big
query down here.
And when I'm selecting it here,
what I will say is
that I want to get it,
maybe do a bigger limit.
I want to get it where the
repo name is like something.
The structure on Jet Hub is
that we have organization,
and then it has repos.
And so what I want to see is,
what are all the repos
under Open Lamb, right?
So I'm just to put
a wild card there,
and I should be able to
get a few of them, right?
So I'll get those out, and
then we're going to be
working with these a bit.
And what I can see is
that there's different
languages on Open Lamb.
I have this array of structs,
and we go to figure
out how we can that.
For example, I want to see
how often is C used, right?
I might want to do
that, or maybe I care
about This is like
how many bytes of code are
actually in that language.
Maybe I want to see
what percentage
of projects are usually and see.
I can do that kind
of stuff, too,
but we have to learn
a little bit more
about how to extract
that information.
So I'm going to pop
back here to the slides
and look at some
general concepts,
and then we'll come
back and do more demos.
Alright. So first, we're
just trying to talk
about this idea of
arrays in structures.
And then we're
introduced a new kind
of join called cross joining,
which are actually
use a lot both for
geographic data and for
working with these arrays.
There's a specific kind
of cross join that
is trying to help us pull out
the information
from those arrays,
called a correlated cross join.
That's used in conjunction
with something called nesting.
On nesting means we're
taking that array,
and we're stacking it
vertically like a table.
And finally I'm just trying
to talk very briefly about
geographic data and the
support Big Grey has for it.
We're going to spend like,
you know, a whole lecture
looking at that in more detail.
All right. So here I have
an example straight off
the documentation
for a big query.
It's a data set of books.
They have arrays of authors,
and authors have IDs,
names, and I don't know, date.
Maybe it's their birth date.
Who knows? Right?
So we have that.
And we have feel extract
information from that.
When I have an array, I
extract information a lot
the way I would from a list,
except instead of just
putting that index in there.
We put the word offset before
we say offset and then
parentheses around the
index. Little bit strange.
The structures, I think are more
kind of common sense, right?
We just use that dot syn text
to pull out a field from it.
So we could do that,
we could, you know,
pull out specific
structures and then
pull out fields from those
structures if we wanted to.
All right, let's talk
about a cross join.
And previously, we've seen
a few different joins.
We've seen inner join,
left join, right join.
One thing that all those
joins have in common
is that we have a
predicate filter.
We have an statement that
has some kind of condition.
Our predicate filter, and
it'll either be
true if we want to
pair up those rows or it'll
be false if we wouldn't.
Maybe that condition
says something like
this feign key equals
that primary key, right?
With cross join, it's different.
It doesn't have any
kind of on statement.
kind of filter.
It matches every row in
the first table with every
row in the second table.
Maybe I have like five
rows in the first table,
ten rows in the second table.
I would get 50 rows
of output, right?
And as you can imagine,
some cases that's going to
be too expensive, right?
You don't always want
that, but there are
cases where it does
exactly what you need.
So there's a couple of
different syntaxes for it.
One is, I say, select
star from table one,
cross table two, and that
we'll get every combination.
And so what does that look like?
In table one, I have the 12 row,
and the 12 row will
get paired with x,
get paired with y.
Okay, I have a 34 row.
The 34 row will
get paired with x,
and the 34 row will
get paired with.
I just doing every
single combination.
There's a more concise
syntax from it for it.
That means exactly
the same thing,
and that is that you just
put a comma in between
the table names instead of
putting the word cross toy.
So you'll sometimes
see both of these,
just know that they mean
exactly the same thing.
All right. So with all
these traditional joins,
it made a lot of sense
that we'd use that
on statement and kind
of filter it down.
Cross joins, by definition,
don't have any kind
of filtering, right?
But people found that there
were lots of use cases
where it just kind of made
sense to them to
do a cross join.
And then after the
fact, they would
filter with a were statement.
And so when you look at that,
it looks inefficient,
and in most cases,
it is very inefficient, right?
Because you're computing
every single possible
acmboation, and filtering down.
Later. Now, that's not
the end of the story.
When a lot of people like to
do something that's
very inefficient,
then the people
building systems come
along later and they create
optimizations, right?
And so this is a
very common pattern.
We have a crosstoin
followed by aware.
Honestly, it's just ugly, right?
When I see that, I
wish that the syntax
supported an on statement,
but it doesn't.
But when that was often show
up is with geographic data sets.
Forever reason, right?
What people would do
is they maybe have
a bunch of latitude
and longitude points,
and they maybe have a bunch of
polygons for different
states or things like that,
and they want to say, Oh,
this point is in this region.
And kind of pair them up, right?
And so they would just do
let's consider everything
with everything and then
have a complicated filter.
And so Big Query and other
tools have come along,
and they will recognize
certain queries like that
and make them fast, right?
So if you look at the BigQuery
documentation, you'll see that,
if I have a were statement
and I have any of
these kinds of filters
with my cross join,
It's going to be fast
even though it looks like
something that is like
naively, very slow.
Whenever you're seeing a
cross drain like that,
read the documentation,
see what the database has.
There's some filters
that they're
going to do very well
for and some are not.
All of these are for
spatial types, ST,
and they relate to saying, Oh,
do these shapes
touch each other?
Do they overlap? Is there one
inside of the other, right?
We're looking at
those in more detail.
Oh. Cool. So I
want to talk about un nesting
now and correlated cross.
I guess first I just pause.
Yeah. Any questions right here?
Yeah. Oh, how do
they optimize it?
Yeah, that's a good
question, right?
So, I mean, it's not
not my area, right?
But I can speculate, right?
You know, let's say
I have a bunch of
coordinates all
around the world.
And then I have a
bunch of polygons
representing
geographic boundaries.
I want to pair up the
points with the polygons.
You can imagine kind of, like,
roughly bucketing the world
into different shapes.
And, you know, pretty clearly,
if I look at a latitude, point.
I don't necessarily
have to look at
every single shape and say,
is it in there or not?
Right? I could t to break
the world in regions, right?
Regions that are much
larger than any shape,
and then try to pair them
up region by region, right?
So, you know, I'm sure,
it's an area of research
where people are
publishing and doing even
more clever things than that.
But you could imagine
optimizations you could do.
Yes, you're asking
does it only work
when you use these
functions and yes,
it only works when you
use these functions.
And so, they've just
documented, right?
If you're using
those, then, okay,
it's not a reasonable
thing to do.
If you're not, then you
should be kind of
looking at like, Hey,
this is an n squared
kind of operation where
I have to compare
everything with
everything. Maybe it's okay.
Maybe it's very slow,
but they're going to document
the things that
they're fast at and
things they're slow
at so that you
can make informed choices.
Yeah, even though the query
looks like something that's bad,
it looks like you're going to
cross and filtering afterwards,
they're going to realize, hey,
that's the end and they're
going to find a
different way to get
to that same end
goal that's faster.
So they will never
actually materialize
every combination.
What's that? Yeah, it is like
a lazy evaluation, right?
Because when I give a
SQL query to a system,
they know You know,
it's not like when I'm using
a SQL, I say, here's
the whole query.
I don't say, do a cross join.
Now filter down,
now do this, right?
I tell it like the whole
thing. Here's the whole query.
And if if the database engine
can find a different way
to get the same results,
that's faster, maybe
a non intuitive way,
than they do that, right?
So y, in looks like something
that's can be slow.
In some case, they document
that they're doing
something clever to
make it not be slow.
Yeah yeah, great
questions. Other questions
people have about cross join.
Right. Cool. Let's talk about
this idea of un nesting and
correlated cross strain.
So here I have a query, right?
And it's over a
couple of things.
I have this x field here, right?
And then for coordinates,
I really have an
array of structures,
and those things are these
y z coordinates. Okay.
And so if I want to
query over these things,
what I'd really like to do
instead of having this like,
you know, horizontal array of
all these things is I'd like
to stack it up vertically.
So I actually have columnames
that I can query over.
And that's what on
nesting is, right?
So you see there's an on
nest statement on table.
And basically every row of
data is going to get split
out, so it's its own table.
So here I had two rows.
I had two arrays, and
each of these arrays
become a little table.
Like that, right?
I have one table
of Y Zs for the first row.
I have another table of Y
Z's for the second row.
Okay, that's on
nesting. Now, what
about the cross join part?
In this case, because
we're doing nesting,
what we're going
to do is something
called a correlated cross join.
And the idea is that
we're going to pair
up one with two, three.
We're gonna cross join
one with two, three,
and we're gonna cross
join one with four, five.
And I realize this
is intuitive, right?
Because when we are talking
about cross joins, right?
We're like, Oh, every
combination of these two things.
And on this side,
when I look at x,
there's only one x value there.
So sometimes we do correlated
cross joins where I only
have one value on one side,
but that's still what it's
called and what
it's doing, right?
So I pair up one with
23 and put it out,
I pair up one with
45, put it out.
And then I do the other
one independently, right?
So I'm going cross
join six with 78,
spit it out, six with
910, and spit it out.
And I would have four rows
outputted total, right?
So I'm doing a cross join,
but it's more localized.
I'm not literally considering
everything with everything.
I don't pair up one
with 910, right?
That's why it's
correlated, right?
Correlated, means
that we're looking
narrower in scope, right?
So sometimes when I do
the crush, it's like
one thing to many things,
or in other cases,
if I have multiple
columns that have a rays,
then it would be kind
of within that one row,
I would do everything
with everything.
I'll be showing an example
of a query like that
when we go back to the NoePok.
Yeah, crush right here.
Oh, how do we get the nested
coordinates to start with?
So I guess when we
inserted the data,
right? They have
different da types.
I mean, they have
all the simple stuff
like edgers and strings,
and then they have array
and structure types,
and those are kind of complex
types where they can you know,
an array, could have another
array or things like that.
So when we inserted it, there's
a syntax for it and I can
insert an array
of struts, right?
So that's how the data is there.
Was that the
question? Yeah, well,
our y and z separate tables.
These struts, I'm not
really showing it,
but when I put a struck there,
they actually have names
on those fields, right?
So two is a y value and
three is a z value.
And so what logically
happens when I run
this query up here when
I do this on nesting,
the way to think about
the correlated cross
joint happening is
you should imagine
each of those
single cells become
a separate table, right?
I have a bunch of
different tables, right?
If I have 100 rows,
well, then I have 100
little tables like that.
That makes sense? Is that?
Was there or was that?
Yeah, they were nested, right?
So the nesting refers to I mean,
when I look at an
array of structs,
that looks like a table, right?
But it's like I have a table
inside of a table, right?
So that refers to
the nesting, right?
I for all practical purpose,
have all these little tables
inside of a bigger table.
And on nesting means that
I want to go back to
just one big table
where everything is
stacked on top of
each other because,
you know, that's what SQL
is good at querying, right?
So I can have to get the data
in that form before I can
actually do any kind
of query on it. Does
that make sense?
Yeah, great questions. Yeah.
Do all people have questions
on that? All right.
Cool. I'm I skip the top hat.
So I just want to briefly
talk about geographic data.
Again, I spent a bunch
more time on that.
But whenever you're working
with geographic data,
you have some kind of
coordinate reference system.
A coordinate reference system is
a way to pick some
point in space,
maybe on the surface
of the earth or not
and assign some
numbers to it, right?
And so the most famous
one by far is latitude
and longitude.
I'm sure you all have used
that in some way at some point,
like if you use any
kind of GPS system,
you can imagine an extension
of that would be like
latitude longitude and altitude.
Latitude and longitude
look like this.
At the equator, we have degree
zero, and then as you go up,
it would go to 90 degrees
north or 90 degrees south,
and then the longitude would
be a horizontal measure.
So more complicated systems
like geopands, or
stuff like that.
They can work with lots of
different coordinate systems.
Maybe they can have altitude.
Big car is a little bit simple.
It's just like they just work
with latitude and longitude.
That's all they
really do, right?
But they support a bunch of
common operations with
latitude and longitude,
like you can do a geographic
join, for example.
They also have a bunch of
built in types based on these.
You could have a single point,
you could have lines, you
could have poly guns.
And we say we can do different
operations with these.
All right. Fantastic.
I'm me head back
and do some demos now with
that correlated cross join.
I have a couple of questions
I want to ask here,
for the first question, ops,
I didn't want to do
that. That's code.
All right. Let me great.
For the first question is
I want to know how often
is C used with a Docker file?
In the same repo.
This is something that would
be expensive because I
have all these rows for
etub, these Detub repos.
And I don't really have to
compare different
repos with each other,
but for a single
individual repo,
I have this long
list of language,
and I have to
consider every pair
of languages and say, Oh,
is this pair, Is it
C in a Docker file?
I'm not trying to do the whole
thing over all the stuff.
I'm just trying to go
to the simpler example
that I had before
because here we
only had two repositories,
each of which has a
bunch of languages,
and I'm just going to
answer this question
over these two repositories.
I'm going to grab this here,
And so what am I have to
do is I'm going to have
to nest this, right?
And so I'm to say
when I do that,
I'm may do a cross join.
And what am I going to
do a cross join on?
I'm may do it on an nesting.
As soon as I have on
nesting with cross join.
I know this is a
correlated cross join.
I'm going to do that on
the language field, right?
Maybe I'll just call that L one
because I eventually
have two, right?
And when I'm up here now,
what I will do is
I will say po name
and one SAR. Let's just say dot
Do name. Okay. Let's try that.
And so this we'll expand it up.
I see that for the well,
I have an open lamb.org,
and I have an open lamb
de repo inside of it.
And so for that,
there were seven rows
because there are seven
different languages
in the first repository.
There are three different rows
for the second repository.
Already, you can see that
this nesting was useful.
I could count out how often C is
used or something like
that, right? All right.
So that was just like,
kind of a simple correlated
cross because I only
have one field.
Now, what I'm going
to do that's kind of
weird is I'm going to output
every combination
of two languages
that any given repository has,
because that's a step that
gets me closer to thinking
about C being used with
a Docer file CC here,
and I see Docker file here.
And so If I had
two different columns
that both had a arrays,
I could do the correlated cross
join between those two columns.
Here, since I want to
get different combinations
of languages,
I'm going to do a cross join
with the language again.
And so what that
means is that when
I just had the one
correlated cross join,
for this repo, I had,
I had something like
seven different ones.
Now I'm going to have 49.
I'm may say, for the
pen Lambda repository,
here are 49 different
combinations of two languages.
For this one, rather
than having the three
different languages,
I may say for the load
balancer repository,
I may have these nine
different combinations
of two languages.
I may do. And so up here,
I may say two So I'm
going to do that.
Now I can see.
Well, in open lab,
there is a C with C,
there is a C with Docker.
This is what I'm
really interested in
because I want to know how
often is C used in combination
with a Docker file.
Now I'm in shape or I can
actually filter like that.
I can say where L
one dot name equals
C L two dot name
coloring of that
makes me feel like
this is going to do
something bad to me.
Let's just try Docker
file. Let's try that.
It's working. I co see
across these two repos,
there was one
instance where C was
used in combination with
Docker. Right here.
Yeah, what I'm doing is
I'm doing a cross join
of one array with itself.
And so you know, if I had, like,
two different
arrays, I could say
every combination of A with B.
Or, I mean, why can't
I also just say
every combination of an A
value with an A value, right?
There's nothing wrong with cross
joining with themselves, right?
So I'm doing the cross
join with itself here,
so I get every combination
of two, right?
And then I'm also doing
it with a field that was
not unnested, right?
So in that case, I just
have to individual values.
That po name is going
to get paired up with
every possible two different
values of language.
Do that make sense?
Yeah, great question.
How other questions people
have about that so far?
You know, I could. It might
be kind of expensive.
I could draw and do this
on the whole dataset.
I could remove this filter.
How would that scale? It would
honestly scale fine with
the number of
repositories, right?
Because all of this kind of
crazy crossoin stuff is not
happening in different rows.
It would scale poorly
with the number of
languages, right?
If I had some repository
that had, like,
a very large number of
different languages,
that would take a long
time to execute, right?
Because this is not optimized
as far as I'm aware
from the documentation.
All right. Cool. Let's
do some other examples.
Another question I have is,
what are the most
common languages?
Right? So let's find that out.
And so maybe I'll come
back here and copy that.
And in this way, this
one might be a little
bit easier because
I don't have to.
I just want to
demonstrate, like, Hey,
like, why we call this
a correlated crosstoin?
It's always strange
to me calling it
a correlated cross train
when I only have one
ray instead of two.
I just want to show
one example like that.
But this one will be
a little bit simpler
because I'm only on nesting it.
I'm only using the
correlated crosstin
for nesting purposes.
And so what I'm going to
do here is that actually.
I want to see all the
different repo names and
all different languages.
Right? If it's a repo name
that corresponds to a lot
of different languages,
I'll just do a bunch of
different rows for that.
Right? Now, if I want to,
then, well, let me think
about what I'm doing.
I don't really care about
what the repo name is.
What I want to know now
is how often different
languages appear.
Right? So this is the
name of a language,
and I'm going to say how
many times do that appear.
If I do that, I have to
do a group by down here.
I group by the language name.
Okay. And then I want
to get maybe like the
top languages, right?
I'm call this this count,
and I'm order by count
descending, right?
And I don't Let's get
something like 20,
and I'm may take all this
data and I'm going to
throw it in a data
frame after I fix my r.
So expected word by order by.
Okay, fantastic. I'm
going to do that.
Is a helpful error message
that's running, it finished.
All right, cool. And so we can
see Java script is at the top.
Python is like the
fifth most popular.
Just for the sake of completes,
let's turn this into
a nice little plot.
If I do plot bar on this,
the x axis will come from
the Pandas index, which
is not what I want.
And so what I'm going
to do is I am going to
say set index of name.
I'm going to take
that column and
slip that over to the index.
And at that point, I could
just very naturally plot it,
and that will make
this nice plot.
Let's just for the sake of
completeness, make it
a little bit nicer.
I'll say a width of
five and maybe a height of
three. How does that look?
That looks decent,
scientific notation,
even if people get it,
they really have to slow
down and think carefully about
it. I try to avoid that.
One of the ways you
could do that is,
I could just do like an
element y is divide.
I could divide it by 1 million.
That would get me these
values and millions.
I could plot that again. Now,
of course, if I do that,
I have to communicate that, I
may say x that set y label.
Maybe I'll call this language
occurrences on Jet Hub,
and then I should
specify my units.
I turned to 1 million, so
I should say, say as much.
Maybe I'll just say occurrences.
It's already obvious.
It's for languages. Now that
fits a little bit nicely.
There's something
like 1 million repos
with Java stripped,
maybe something like
550 with Python. Great.
We were able to
throw the whole way.
We do the query, we make a plot.
We learn something. All right.
A question about that example.
All right. What else?
So the next question I have,
I want to just see a join
with Big Query as well.
And again, right, like,
I'm ready to join
two tables that happen to
be in the same dataset,
but I can join any
two tables I want.
I could join a table
and a data set a project
that belongs to me with,
like this public stuff, right?
In a completely
different project.
Alright, but in this case,
it'll be in the same one.
And so my question
I want to ask is,
what is the distribution?
Of licenses over
Python projects.
There's maybe a few
pieces to this.
Maybe I'll just start back
from my old query up here.
So I think that one
thing we have to do,
I'm just trying to delete
all of this for now.
One thing we have to do,
again, is we have to figure
out which ones are
Python projects.
And to filter, I have to
unnest it, and then later on,
I can do something like
languages name equals Python,
right? I can do that, right?
I'll kind of figure
out, here are
the repos that use Python.
And then I have to have
another join, right?
I have to somehow join
here so I can figure out,
I found a repo that uses Python.
What is the license
that is used on that?
Yeah, question right here.
Do I have a small
typo, or is my typo?
Languages. Okay, great.
Thank you. That one.
Okay, great. Thanks. Good catch.
Okay, so I'm going
to peek over here.
And so I have the
languages here that has
repository name and then these
repeated language values.
And then over here, I
have actual licenses.
So here I have a
repository name,
and I can pair this up with
an individual license
in this case,
right? I'm going
to pare this up.
And that will be an
inner join, right?
B in this case,
I'm not trying to get
every combination of
license with a repository.
I just want to do it when it has
the same repository name.
And so in this case, I'm
pairing it up with licenses.
Because of that,
with the cross join,
I don't have any filter.
Maybe I filter down later.
I don't have any
filter I do that here.
But for an ener join, I
definitely do need to have
some kind of filter on it.
And so in this case,
I need to say, well,
when is a language paired
up with a license,
it's when the repo
name is the same.
Then I can pair those things up,
if it's very convenient.
Alright, great. So I
see figure out what I want
to have my select line.
But this is pretty good so far
because I can kind
of figure out, Okay,
here are all the
Python repositories,
join it to figure out
what license it has.
And in the end, I want to know
what is the distribution.
That kind of suggests I'm
counting in some way.
Right? So I may
do a group buy on
The license. I'm going to say,
well, what are those licenses?
I guess they just
the field and it is
just called license.
Somebody group by that.
Then when I'm up here,
I want to see, well,
what license was it and how
many times did it appear?
I'm going to call that count.
I want to order by
that count descending.
I'm do all that.
A more complicated thing.
We have everything.
We have a cross join join
group by order by and
a bug name is not found
inside of languages.
At some point I said
language dot name
and let me peek over here.
Maybe I actually
did that earlier.
I guess it was
languages dot name.
Down here, I should also say,
what did I do wrong there?
Invalid where The name is not
found inside of languages,
because language is
that whole table,
but I really want to
do it on nesting.
So my apologies, I
nested that thing.
That's where that name
actually shows up.
Let's see if that works.
Fingers crossed, it does.
All right, cool. Now I'm
going to do that same
deal as last time.
I have some data down here.
I'll just do the classic stuff.
I'm going to group it by What I
may make the license
be the X axis.
And this time, let's just
do it by thousands, right?
Because these numbers are
smaller, right? I'm may do that.
And I think that we're
actually good to go, right?
So we can see, you know,
most Python projects
use the MIT license.
After that, we have
the GPL and Apache.
Most of the things we did
this semester Apache,
there's different
version of the apache,
then we have the BSD.
And after that there's
kind of, like,
this long tail of less
popular licenses.
So it looks good.
L the stuff I taught you
about different licenses.
I hit all the popular ones.
Yeah, question right. Oh,
that's a really good question.
So when I do both the cross
join and the inner join,
which one happens first?
The answer is, we can't
know at the query, right?
What the queries do is
they communicate like,
I want end results
corresponding to this, right?
And so that's actually a
really interesting
question, right?
And there's people who
will write papers on that.
And so in general, right,
we kind of have a
simpler query here,
but it's very common
that you'll have a row,
and there's a bunch of
foreign keys into it,
and there are all kinds
of different tables.
And then there's filters,
and tell what you
want to do, right?
As you're joining
different things and
filtering is you want to kind of
like shrink your data down
quickly before you join
across more things.
And so it's like, Well, I'm
joining across like
these ten things.
What do I join
against first, right?
And so the database people,
they really get deep
into the theory of that.
And I don't know if
this is stll true,
but at one point what I
heard at the State of
art is that if they
have about four tables,
it's already there's not
a general theory of like,
this is the order you
should do them, right?
If it's smaller, then,
maybe there's some theory like,
This is definitely the
way you should do it.
So anyway, that's something
that people worry about a lot.
Well, I have all these joints.
What is the order? I mean, get
the same result in the end.
But there's going to be
faster and slower ways
to do that join. Is
excellent question.
Maybe if you go take like a
graduate database course,
I mean, you'll
probably read like
many papers about that topic.
But I'm not that
deep into databases.
I have a better answer for now.
Yeah, fantastic question.
Other questions people have.
Yeah, language. Oh, yeah.
So where is the language
table that's being nested?
Great. So I think that I'm
doing language right here,
which was actually when I
go back to the languages.
So I have a table
called languages,
and within that, I
have an array field
called language, right?
So what I'm on nesting
is language, right?
So that's not the
name of a table.
That's the name of
a field within a table
called languages.
And the naming, of course,
is all confusing here.
So sorry for that.
That makes sense.
Yeah, instead of instead of
having all these arrays.
I'm like, Hey, let's take out
all the structs from these
arrays and stack them up,
and then we're going to
have some nice columns.
Exactly. Yeah, thank you.
You all other questions
people have. All right.
Cool. I have 5 minutes left.
And so what I want to do
now is I want to
pit a little bit.
I want to look at I want to look
at data sources for big query,
because there are a lot of
different things we can do.
And remember that big query has
its own storage engine
that's tightly integrated
with big query.
And that's one thing we could
do is we could copy data
from somewhere else and
dump it into big query.
Big Query can also
work a lot like Spark.
Spark can work as this
ad hoc SQL engine.
You're like, Hey, look, there's
some new park files over
there in HDFS that
you never even
knew about until
you got your query,
and I'll just grow
and I'll figure
out how to query
them the best I can.
Big Query can pretty
much do that as well.
I can point it to
some park files
somewhere. I'll do its best.
I do have to do a
little bit more work in
big query to register
them and tell them,
like, Hey, they're over here
in this particular place.
And so all of this stuff
has a bit of setup that I
don't like remembering.
And so I put some
starter code in
the lecture snippets that I
am going to paste down here.
Let me just split this up.
All right so I have
my three examples.
And so the first one is,
I'm doing a load job.
I'm copying data
from somewhere else,
sticking and big query.
Then I have two cases
that are external.
One is that I may have some
Park A file setting in GCS.
And then the third
case is that we're
going to have some
data in Google Sheets,
and we're going a
query from that data,
we can just do SQL queries
on top of Google Sheets,
which is honestly kind of cool.
Let's do this first one first,
the load job can fig,
and where I'm going to
load the data from is
a PK file that's already in GCS.
If we come over here and
Cons if I look at If I look
at Google Cloud Storge.
Remember, we made a bucket
last time together.
And we're Section two.
I'm going to look at our bucket,
there was a Park file that
we had created, right?
And so just copy the
path to that Park file.
And coming back to my
notebook over here,
there's a few things
we have to do.
One is when I load
a table from a URI,
I have to pass in what
those URIs are, right?
I'm to pass that in,
and I will paste this.
Like so. And then I have some
more things I have to do.
Now, I'm sure you all have seen
this protocol many
times, right the HTDP.
It's not the only
protocol out there.
There's other ones like, S
three for Amazon's thing,
GS for Google's Google Storage.
So I have to specify, Okay,
I have this Park file,
and it's inside a
bucket with this name,
and that's on Google Storage.
I can tell it. That's where
it is. That's where it lives.
And it doesn't infer
the type by the name,
so I have to be very
explicit up here.
This is a Park file.
And then down here,
I have to say,
well, where is it
trying to end up?
In big query, right?
Down here, I have
to do kind of like
the whole project
dot data set table.
And so I may call
my table loans.
And I created a dataset
way at the beginning,
so let's throw back and
take a peek at that.
I created a dataset called
section two in my project.
Let's put it there.
So comming along.
I will paste that here.
All right. Great. And then
we go ahead and run that, right?
So I'm going to load that in.
And if that works successfully,
then a couple of
things will happen.
One is that if I look at
my project over here,
and then I look at the Section
two data that I created,
there's going to be a
loans table, right?
And I can preview
it if I want to.
I can see all this data
loans and incomes.
This is real data from
Wisconsin, by the way.
I can see the schema.
And then for details,
I can actually see how
large that whole thing is.
And then the very last
thing I'm going to do
before I wrap up is
that I'm going to show,
I can actually go
ahead and query,
now that I've copied
it in there, right?
So I'm going to do big query,
and I'm going to
select star from
that thing and I'm going
to limit it to ten.
Let's go ahead and
do that. The job
is running, and
there we go, right?
So we can get some part
K files relatively
easily into big query,
and then we're in business,
we can start doing queries.
We can combine this
with the public data
set two if we want. All right.
I'm going to end there.
I hope you all have
a fantastic break,
and feel free to come
up and chat if you
have any questions.