Great to see you all here today.
Sorry continue talking
about big query.
Last time we talked
about geographic data.
We talked about how we could
pull data from spreadsheets.
All that stuff is to
be in the project
that we're releasing
later tonight.
We're also going to talk
today about machine learning.
We did some
introductory concepts,
we're actually get some
hands on practice.
And then we'll start looking at
the billing models for
big query as well.
Before we jump into that,
I just want to do
a little bit of
review for the machine
learning stuff from last time.
So I'm just bring up a
top hat and go ahead.
I'm sorry.
About 30 seconds left.
All right. So most
people are saying
features in columns,
which is not quite right.
It's actually it's just B.
And so, of course, when
we're trading a model,
it needs to know both what the
labels and the features are.
But think about how we
actually set this up.
We write a query
first that gets all
of that information about
the features and the label.
And then we're passing
that into this,
create a replace
model statement.
And when we do
that, we just say,
Okay, this is what the label is,
and it automatically infers that
everything else is a feature.
All right. If you aren't
careful, it might be
picking up columns
that you don't
actually want as your features.
You only specify the label,
and to figure out which
features you have,
you will adjust
the query prior to
feeding it into that
statement. Alright, ol.
So I'm going a head over
here to a notebook,
and I just started
a fresh one so that
it's not too cluttered
with stuff from last time.
And we I get some
hands on practice,
training models, evaluating
them, predicting with them.
I'm just going to do a
load extension here quick
of Google dot cloud
dot Big query.
So we can run queries later.
Whenever I'm doing some kind
of new machine learning thing,
I like to just have
very simple data,
that has an obvious pattern.
Then I can figure
out, well, does
that model identify
that pattern?
So I just put this
in the starter code.
And what is this doing?
Well, it has randomly generated
X one and X two features,
and then the y value
is just the sum of
those plus some
random noise, right?
And I can see that
here, right like
four plus one is eight plus
some pise eight plus two is
ten plus some noise. So
a very simple pattern.
And it turns out that this is
a pandastta frame and
Pandastta frames have
a function built in called
two Google big query.
And when we do that, then we
can put in the project or we
can say like the
data set table name,
and then it will upload that.
So it's very easy
to move between
Pandas and these datasets.
And in here, we've been
doing section two,
for the name, I'm
just going to call
it sample one. Alright, cool.
So let me go ahead and do that.
And now I have
that in Big query,
right, as soon as this
finishes running.
And remember that when you're
doing machine learning,
often, you will do
a train test split.
And what we saw last time is
that the train test split
that Big Query does
automatically is kind of
broken in a couple of ways.
I does kind of some
strange things.
And so now that we have
this data set there,
we should figure out how to do
the train test split
ourselves, right?
So I'm just trying to say
a big query down here.
And maybe I'll do a select star
from section two sample one.
And in addition to that,
what I want to do
is I want to assign
a random number for
each row, right?
So say, let's get this
rand, that'll be 0-1.
I actually, I loaded
the extension ops.
I didn't load it
properly up here.
So now that should be loaded,
and then I should be able to get
a random number for each
of these in the sample.
And because it's 0-1,
if I want to have say roughly
25% of test data, I can.
I'm say if that's less than 25,
I'm may call that a test, right?
So I'll say up here that
approximately 25% should be
test data. Alright,
I'm to do that.
And this is non deterministic.
And so what we want to do is
we want to save this somewhere,
and then we're just
trying to keep using it
wherever it has
been saved, right?
So I can create a table,
and or I may call this section
two train train test, right?
I'm may have my train test
data together in the same table,
but I'll have that
Boolean column
indicate which rows
are for training,
which are for testing.
A I'm to do that,
and I'll create
or replace table train
test. Let's run that.
And then we'll just do a quick
check and make sure that
I got my ratios kind of
approximately what we wanted.
It's not going to be exactly
75 25, but let's just check.
I say test and then
count of star from
section two train
test group by test.
Alright, great. So
we have 31 rows for
testing data and then 69 for
training data. Alright, cool.
So now what I want to do is
I want to train a model,
and the very first step
to training a model,
is to select the training
data with a query, right?
I'm going to do that first.
I'm going to write a query,
which will be select
X one, X two,
and y from this new thing
that I just created,
and I only want it where it
where it is not test data,
right because I only want
to get the training data.
Okay, I like to specify
all these hears I'm using
the star because
then if it changes,
I'm very explicit
about what columns
I'm actually using
for model training.
I'm going to get that
training data, as so.
And then what I want
to do is I want
to feed it into a model.
And so we saw the
syntax up here where we
can create or
replace a table as,
and the syntax for creating
a model is very similar, right?
We can either take that
data dump in a table or we
can take that data and
feed it into a model.
So instead of table,
I'm going to say model.
And then for my model over here,
I may do a linear regression,
so I'll just say L R, right?
So I'll create or replace model
as while that query down there.
Okay. Sets most of it.
Now, there's some other
things that I have to do,
and primarily, I have to
have this options line.
And for this options line,
I have to say what
model type it is.
I'm going to say model type
equals linear regression.
Okay. And then from
these down here,
I have to specify which
one is my label column.
Right? I'm going to say,
input label columns equals y.
That's the only thing I want
to really predict, right?
And what is the linear
regression trying to do?
Maybe some of you are more
or less familiar with that.
But what it wants to
find is some formula,
where y is trying to equal
some number times X one and
some other number times X two.
Those numbers that
are multiplying
x1x2 are called co
efficients or weights,
we multiply it by both of them,
add them together, maybe
add in some constant
factor, and that will be y.
We have to figure, what is
a good constant factor?
What co efficients
do we do we want?
That's what a linear
regression model does, right?
So I'm going to run this,
and this should create
that model for me here.
So this is running for a while.
And then after that runs,
It should show up over
on the Cloud Console.
Over here, I'm going to come
to big query, which
is somewhere.
Did I hide it somewhere?
Okay. Let me search for it.
Can I search for it here?
All right, fine. I
don't know if maybe
I forgot to pen it or something.
I bet that's what I did. I'm
pin that. Okay, fantastic.
And so under here,
right if I go to Section two,
where we are, we see we
have all these tables
that we've created,
and now we also have
a model here, right?
So I could come and inspect
this model, and, you know,
seen it when it's trained,
depending on what model it is,
I might get various
stats from it, right?
They even compute
some evaluation
metrics for me up front.
Okay, great. So I
have this right now.
And one of the things that
we have to remember is
that is that by default,
unless I say
something else here,
it might try to do a
train test split for me.
The default is that if you
of less than 500 rows.
I will not everything
is training data.
So I don't need to
worry about that.
But for a bigger data set,
it would be really important
that I say don't split.
Otherwise, they're
going to split
my training data into
a further training
and test dataset.
Alright, trait so
I have that model.
And there's a few
different things
I could do with it.
Yeah, question.
The option. Yeah, sure.
Let me just grab
that in the slides.
Where it's this one
right here, right.
So this is the option.
You know, why not?
Let's just put it
in here, right.
Then let's make sure that
runs again just fine.
Yeah. We can just tell it to
not do any spudding for us.
Yeah, good question.
Yeah other questions
people have. What's that?
Well, they have a few
different options, I mean,
maybe you could
specify a ratio or
something I forget like what
the other options
are side no split.
No splits the one I remember
because I never use it.
The default is to
do weird things.
L they'll choose the ratio,
depending on how big it is.
I think if it's less than 500,
they train on
everything, and they
will test on the same
thing, weird decision.
And then if it's
like more than 500,
they'll have like an 80 20,
and then after, like 50,000,
then the test size, it's
just like a constant size.
So it's just like they
do weird things and
then they cash it
for like two days,
and then it's non deterministic.
So anyway, I just like
always say, no split,
if I have more than 500 rows,
and then then I avoid
all those problems.
Cool. So now I have this model,
and there's lots of things
I might want to do with it.
I might want to inspect
it and see, well,
what coefficients
are they actually
using on X one and X two.
I might want to use it to
go predict new things.
And then finally, I
probably want to evaluate
it and see how well it's
doing on this data.
It should be doing very well
because this is a
very simple pattern.
Any decent model will immediately
recognize that pattern.
I'm just adding two numbers
together. All right.
So let's do each
of those things.
And remember that
for a big query,
they have all of these,
I don't know if you
want to call them like
views or psudo tables,
but they have these
tabular functions that I
can query from to get
information about my
model or use my model.
And so they're all ML something,
and the first one is weights.
And when I do this,
I have to say model,
and then the name of
the model, right?
And so the name of my model,
Is section two
linear regression.
And so if I want to, I can
just select star from that.
I can treat it like a table,
and I'll just say a
big query up here.
All right.
So let's just take a look
at what those weights are.
And I can see that it
did a pretty good job.
Remember that for X one and X
two, I just added them together.
I don't have any coefficients
on there other than one,
I guess, one is the default.
So try to figure that out that,
you know, both of these troy
fissions are roughly one.
I was adding random noise 0-1.
So it's also good
that they found
an intercept, kind
of close to 0.5.
The model is doing
reasonable things
for me. Alright, cool.
So I can do that. Now, I might
want to use this model to
make some predictions.
And so in that case,
what am I going to do?
I'm going to have
ML dot predict.
And in that case, we say
the model like before,
but we also have to
have some query, right?
The query is going to
give us the features
that we need, right?
And so what I will
do is I'm going
to maybe actually
just split this off.
I think that's often a
little bit more elegant.
And I'm going to say
select X one and X
two from from that
table that we have,
which was called train test.
And this time, I'm going to
say where it's test data, right?
So before I specifically
selected training data,
now I'm selecting the test
data, to see how it's doing.
And so this will look
like a table for me,
and it's a table that I
can select from. I'm
going to select from it.
And it's going to
have three columns.
The three columns will
be the inputs here,
whatever I put here, will show
up on the other side as well.
And then the
additional column will
be the prediction
that it's making.
I can do that. And let me see.
I'm going to do a big query.
Star is like a table so I
have to say the word from.
And that's a a little
bit long. Tell you what?
I'm just trying
to say like Well,
the data is more
interesting at the end,
right because sort
it in some way.
Anyway, I can see it's doing
something reasonable, right?
It's nine plus one is
ten plus some noise,
if I kind of go in the middle.
Six plus two is eight
plus some noise.
It's doing something
reasonably well.
Now, if I want to, I can put
additional things here
that are not features.
So for example, I could
see the original y value,
and then I could do
all kinds of things.
Maybe I want to have a
scatter plot where I have
the real y values on
the x axis and the
predicted y values,
maybe like the y axis.
I could see what
kinds of mistakes
it's making any kind of
metric that describes how
the model is doing
is going to be comparing
these in some way,
there's a lot of metrics baked
in, but if you have
those directly,
you could you know,
compute whatever
metric you want yourself, right?
So I can do any kinds
of predictions I want.
You know, sometimes
when you have a model,
you're not doing predictions
on like a whole table at a time.
You just want to feed in
one input and then
make a prediction.
And we can absolutely
do that as well.
It looks a little bit
strange because we're so
like comfortable selecting
data from a table.
In this case, the thing we're
predicting doesn't
live in a table.
So I'm going to
delete all of this.
And I have to figure out,
well, what are these
X one and X twos?
And what I could
do is I could say
three as X one and maybe,
like, five as X two.
I can totally just, you know,
select a single row of data
with whatever values I want.
Okay? So three plus five is
eight plus some noise, right?
I can draw ahead in
and I can do that.
I could use this to start
making real predictions
for real things.
All right. Any questions
maybe I'll draw the to
this one because it's
more interesting.
But any questions about
the predict or the
weight so far here,
right here. How do we tell what?
How does it, how
does it know Oh,
you mean for these predictions,
you're saying, what is
the calculation it does?
Oh, yeah. So if I
have an X one value,
it'll multiply it by about one.
And if it has an X two value,
And then we'll add those
two results together,
add in an intercept as well,
and that will give
me my final results.
That's just like a classic
like linear regression.
Yeah. Yeah, sure.
Yeah. Yeah. You can
tell them weights.
You might call them t
efficient. Yep. Exactly.
Yeah, right here. If it
has an X one, it
doesn't ignore it.
If it has an X one.
What do you mean?
Oh, oh, yeah. Great
question, right?
You're saying, Hey, what if I
tried to make a prediction?
I don't have the features?
It's not trying to be
able to do that, right?
So, machine learning
people sometimes,
impute a value or
things like that.
But yeah,
as far as big y is concerned,
there has to be a value there.
Yeah, Yeah, good questions.
What else do people
want to know?
Maybe to pause there.
Oh, right. Cool. So,
what have we done?
We've looked at the weights.
We've looked at, different
ways to do predictions.
How can we evaluate this thing?
There's different metrics, and
they're all going to be inside
something called evaluate.
And so this case,
it's kind of similar.
We have to have a model name,
and then we have
to have a query.
This is a lot like predict,
but this query has to give us
the label or the y
values as well, right?
We can't say how good
the predictions are unless
we know what they are.
So it's kind of
similar to predicting,
but also a little bit
different, right?
And so I'm going to copy all
of this as my query up here.
And And then I will
paste this in.
All right. And now
this is required.
I'll just show
that this is true.
I mean, I select star from that,
and that should give me
an error because I'm
not giving at the label value.
Before it was optional.
Now it is actually required,
and I have to give
it a name, right?
I think I called the section
two linear regression.
Okay now, I'll complain
that it doesn't have a Y,
so I'll select my Y value.
And I may get back this table
with all these
different metrics.
So for example, the
R squared score
is a measure of
explained variance.
I mean, this y value I'm
doing has a bunch
of variance in it.
If I have these features,
I could explain a lot of
that variance, right?
So score of one
would be Perfect.
This is a fantastic score, too.
This is such an
easy pattern that
any decent model could figure
out what it is, right?
So I may just look at how
I could pull this out.
Once I have that
pulled out, I could
figure out which
metrics I want, right?
I want row zero.
There is only one row,
and then the R squared
score that gives
me a num pi float,
which I can just invert
to a Python float.
And I can see what is
the explained variance.
Yeah, sure.
What's that?
It does not train
the model again.
No, no, it does not
train the model again.
And so when you're like
around the console,
you might also see
an R square score.
So when they train on
the training data,
they will also evaluate
on the training data
at the same time.
And so you will find
R square score here.
But this is an R square score
specifically for
the data that I.
This is kind of a
more meaningful one.
The other one is kind
of a nice metric
in some ways because you might
be able to recognize that,
You know, different models,
maybe it's like overfitting.
I just remembering the patterns.
Other times, maybe your
model is too simple,
and it cannot fit the pattern
even that appears in
the training data.
So that's why it's
also useful to
know what is our
R squared score?
I you know, if I
train the model in
the training data
and evaluate it on the
training data as well.
So you'll see that
in the counsel, but
this one is just
for the test data,
or whatever other data
I might feed into it.
Yeah, great question. Yeah,
other questions people have.
Right. Cool. So lots
of good stuff there.
I'm going to head
back to the slides,
and we're going to talk
about feature transformers.
This might be familiar to
some folks, or it
might be new to you.
I think there is fine.
I'm going to show
you some examples
of tricky cases, right?
Now, on the left hand side,
I have an X feature,
and on the y,
I have a label column, right?
I want to predict the
y based on the X.
And what we can see is that
these points are not really
quite on the straight line.
They kind of slope
up steeper and
steeper as we go, right? And,
You know, some models, if I
had a deperal network,
that would be fine.
They can deal with like a non
linear pattern like that.
But if we're doing that linear
regression model
I was just doing,
what it wants to do is it
wants to say something like
y equals x times a weight.
And so whatever
weight I do there,
it doesn't quite fit
that curve pattern.
Right? So that's
one problem, right?
Can I use the linear regression
model in a reasonable way?
Yes, but I have to do
some pre processing on
my data first if I want to
use that specific model.
Okay, what about over here
on the right hand side?
Sometimes I have
categorical data, right?
Maybe maybe I have like
cat, dog, and mouse,
and then maybe I'm
trying to predict
what is the weight of
the animal, right?
Maybe that's on
the y axis, right?
So the dog is the heaviest,
the mouse is the
smallest, right?
And some models will
do great at that.
If I have a decision tree,
And a given node in the
decision tree, I mean,
I could have, is x
greater than five,
or I could also say is
x equal to dog, right?
I can ask categorical questions
very naturally in
a decision tree.
But maybe maybe for like a
linear regression model,
again, I can't do
that because what is
like dog times three?
That doesn't have
any meaning, right?
So in both of these cases,
depending on what model
I'm working with,
I may or may not have to
transform my input data.
So I don't know if
somebody who's like taken
320 or maybe seen this
in another course.
What kind of transformation
might I want to do on
the left hand side
if I want to use
a linear regression model
effectively? Yeah, right here.
Pomal features, right?
It's not a direct correlation,
but it's a squared relationship.
What about on the
right hand side?
Anybody have any
thoughts on what I
should do if I have
categorical data like that?
It's a common transformation.
Yeah, go ahead. Yeah, we need
to cort numbers some way?
There's a particular like,
answer I'm looking for.
I mean there's different
ways that we could
incorporate the numbers.
Yeah, right here.
Yeah, one hot trotter is
kind of what I'm
looking for, right?
So let's see how we would do
this in both cases, right?
So in the first case,
if I just multiply x
squared by some constant,
well, then that's fine, right?
From the perspective of the
linear regression model,
I can tip it however
many columns I want,
and it doesn't need to know
where those columns came from.
It's just trying to
see, like, can I
find a linear relationship
between this column
and the y value?
And so it's totally fine, right,
if I have a data frame
with a column of x value,
I can just add another column of
a data frame and troll
up the x squared column,
and I can compute it by
squaring the original
values, right?
And then I have a column of
data that the linear
regression model can
just slap a consonant
and troll drug, right?
So I need to have some kind
of pinbal feature transformer
to make this work on
the left hand side.
Right? Then the right hand side,
we have to assign
numbers to each
of these categories if we
want to multiply them.
And I think what people are
often tempted to do is
they're attempted to say,
a mouse cat dog is
one, two, three.
And the problem with that is
that the linear regression model
is trying to put a
coefficient on the animal,
It's baking in an
assumption that somehow
a cat is an average
of a mouse and a dog.
And that just doesn't
make sense, right?
So I can't just slap
different numbers on it,
and then multiply that a bio
cooefficient in a
reasonable way.
So what we do instead, right
is when we have categories,
we'll actually add multiple
numerical columns.
I'm going to have
like a mouse column.
And in the mouse
column, it'll be
one if it's a mouse and zero,
if it's not, same thing
for a cat column,
same thing for a
dog column, right?
And so then when I'm looking
at a specific row, right?
I see like, Oh, there's
like a mouse cat dog value.
I'll put a one in that cell,
if it is that kind of animal,
and I'll put a zero
if it is not, right?
And so then what is great
is that the coefficients,
I can put a coefficient on
the cat column or
the dog column.
And then based on
what animal it is,
I can contribute some
amount to the y value.
Any questions about
that? All right.
Cool. So those are
the two kinds of
encodings that the
transformations we want to do.
And I'm going to see how both
of those show up in big query.
What I see is that for
the left hand side,
we actually have to do a
fair bit of manual work,
and then on the right hand side,
that actually happens
automatically for us.
You need to know what's
happening automatically
so you don't duplicate
efforts, right?
Alright, I'm going my head
back here. Excuse me.
And in this case, what
am I going to do?
I'm going to generate
some new data that
has like a non linear pattern,
and I'm may copy the
same data as before.
All right. I'm going to
paste this down here.
And let's just make
it more interesting.
I'm going to say
two times this X
one thing and I'm
going to square it.
And then let's say minus
minus three times
that column, right?
So a more complicated
relationship.
I have to figure out that we
have put a co efficient
on the square of it
instead of just the
regular All right,
so I have that.
And then what I'm going
to do is I'm just
going to again put
it to Big Query.
So I'll put it to
Google Big Query,
Section two, and I'm just
trying to call this table one.
And if it exists,
I'm just trying to replace
it, right? I'm
going to run that.
And You know, if I was
doing things properly,
I would do a train test split,
but I don't want to complicate
this example with that.
And we already
talked about that.
For this one, I'm going to train
and test on the same date.
That's a bad thing to
do, but I can still
demonstrate what I want
to demonstrate right now.
Alright, cool. So I have
generated that thing.
It's there, and then
I can start training
a model with it.
And so what I think
I will do first is
I'll just fit a
linear model to it,
and the linear model
will be bad, right?
Because it's a non
linear pattern, right?
It's a polynomial pattern.
But let's try it. And so I'm
going to do a big query.
And I have select X one, X two,
and y from Section
two table one.
Let's just take a quick
look at our data.
There it is. And then we can
create or replace
model, as usual.
I'm going to call
this just Model one.
And then I'm Model two
is going to be basically
a better machine
learning model that
can handle the
polynomial aspect of it.
I'm going to say, as always,
I have to have
some options here.
And so I have to say,
like model type equals,
linear regression.
And then what else
do I need to say?
I need to say, input,
label, columns,
equals, that y value.
I'm going to do that. And
we're in Section two.
My apologies, right?
So let's train it
on the data we have,
right in that new table.
It's running and
after that's done,
then I may draw in and try
to evaluate it, right?
All right, well, what I'm
going to do now is I'm
going to say mL dot evaluate.
And the model name
is section two.m1.
And then I have to have
some query that gives
me both features
and columns, right?
So I'm just going
over here to say
select star from
section two table one.
And again, this is the bad
thing I'm doing, right?
I trained on this data, and now
I'm evaluating on the
same data, right?
But it's not going to
be feted even thugh
it's this data before because
it's a non linear pattern,
and we have a linear
model, right?
So I'm going to say, big query,
select star from that, right?
So I have that, and select star,
and I always forget it's
basically like a table, right?
What else do I
have? So Evaluate.
And if I have a
typo or something
somewhere and people
let me know, feel free.
Oh, there we go.
Parentheses. Let's try
that. All right. Excellent.
Thank you. Good Ketch.
And not a horrible
R squared score,
but it's quite a bit worse than
the 99% that we saw before.
And this is a simple
enough pattern.
We should be able to get
like a 99% out of it.
Okay. And so what I want to
do is I want to come back
to this query that we were
working with before, right?
So we have this query here.
And The strategy that I
want you to think about is,
how can we add
additional columns
on top of these raw features
that we have, right?
And we can do that by doing
another select on top of it.
So select something from
from this stuff, right?
And so, you know, I want to have
all those same features
showing up again,
and I guess the y value.
But I can add other
things here here as well.
So for example, I could raise
X one to the power of two,
and maybe I call that X two,
or maybe I raise the power of
X two to the power of two,
and I call that X I'm sorry,
I'm gonna call this X two
to the power of two and X
one to the power of two,
try a naming convention,
right that like that?
Or you know, maybe I put in like
a logarithm or any kind
of function you want.
You can put whatever you want.
Maybe I want to multiply
X one times X two,
and I'll call that X
one, X two, right?
I could put whatever
I want here, right?
So I could do that. And did
you mean X two,
probably, but where?
Next two to Oh,
great. Dred Catch. Thank you.
So as Oh, oh,
okay, great. Dred Catch.
Good Ctch. Thank you. You're
sharper than I am today.
All right. So great,
I've prepped the date.
I can have whatever
times I want.
And now I can dive this to
a linear regression model.
And the liar linear
regression model
will very happily figure out,
should I put a coefficient
on any of these?
And looking back at
the relationship,
we see that I'm hoping that
it is trying to
put a two on that
X one squared column I had.
Do we ever have X two squared
in the original thing?
No, no, we don't. And so
it's fine that I have a column
there that's like that.
But what I'm hoping is
that the model will put
a zero coefficient on top
of that column for me.
Okay? I'm gonna
come down here and
what I will do is that this is
now my new training data, right?
And so just how I
trained M one before,
which was up here, right?
I'm going to do the
same thing, but now it
gets this extra
this, what is that?
It gets that extra those
extra values for
training, right?
Alright. Fantastic. So I may
call this M two, by the way.
So that's my better model,
and so I'm going to train that,
and that will all work fine.
And then what I want to do,
After that thing
trains is I want
to evaluate it, right?
So I'm gonna come back.
I'm going to evaluate it
the way I did before.
And I'm going to
run this down here,
and you know instead of M one,
let's try M two, right?
And now I have a problem.
This is going to actually fail.
I think, should be failing.
It should have failed by now.
This is very unnerving,
that it's ce I'm
replacing a model. That's
not what I wanted to do.
Okay. What am I doing there?
Let me just I'm doing too fast,
and I need to slow down and make
sure I'm doing
something reasonable.
All right. So I train
the M one model.
I you evaluate the M one model.
I'm training the M two model,
which I think I just
overwrote, unfortunately.
And then what I
wanted to copy down
was an evaluation
of the M two model.
I copy down the wrong
cell. My apologies.
And so I'm going
to just evaluate
the M two model on that.
And now I think
I'm going to get an error
right when I do this.
And the issue is
saying, well, hey,
I don't have that X
one squared column,
and there's probably
other ones if I fix that,
there'll be other
ones that show up.
And that's because when I was
training the model up here,
it had all of these
different columns,
and table one does
not have that, right?
That's a real problem, right?
And so The solution, right?
Is that however I transform
the data for training,
I have to transform
in exactly the
same way for testing, right?
And so one thing I could do,
which is a bad thing
would be to select all of
this and add that down
here. I could do that.
When you copy and paste
big complicated stuff
like that, it's
dangerous, right?
Because maybe I update it later,
and I forget to update
it both places.
And all of a sudden, then I
trained my data with
one transformation,
that I like predicting later
with a different transformation,
may get garbage, right?
And so what I want to have
happen is I want this
transformation to
be baked directly into
the model itself,
so that, you know, whatever
transformation happens for
the training is going to
happen for the testing, too.
That's what I would like. And so
I'm just going to
comment this out.
And I'm going to copy
this line up here,
and we're going to
modify it a bit.
Okay? So what we will
do is we're going to add what
is called a transform line.
We're going to add a
transform line up here.
And I can put something here.
And the thing I put here
can basically be whatever
you would put on a select
line like that, right?
So all any of these
transformations
here, I can say,
Hey, do it there,
and it will happen
automatically for me
both when I train and
when I test, right?
And so I'm gonna just top
you all of this, right?
I'm gonna paste it up here.
And then what I'm
going to do is I'm
going to delete all actually
all of this, right?
It's more elegant
already, right?
It looks kind of nicer, right?
And I can differentiate.
I can see like, Well,
these are my raw features
that are coming in.
And then these are
ways I would transform
those features to generate
more features that I can
use for training, right?
That's what I'm going to do.
And so I'm going to run this.
And this is going to over old
M two because this is like
the proper way to do it.
And then when that works,
this thing that was
failing before,
is going to start
working for me, right?
Alright, I'll just pause and
let that run for a moment.
Any questions all
that's running?
All right. So that, R.
Let's evaluate it now.
And so one thing
that's better is
that I can see that that was
a good transformation, right?
When when I have that
X one squared column,
it was able to put a
coefficient on that and
rod prediction up to 99% again.
And then the other thing,
is that down here,
I just have x1x2 and y.
And if somebody goes
and they change
that model they can
do different
transformations, whatever,
I don't have to
change my code for
how I do predictions
or evaluation.
Yeah, question here.
What. Yeah, sure.
Let's see what
proficiens it picked.
So let's do Let's
do a big query and
select star from L dot
evaluate evaluate dot weights.
And my model this time is
called section 22, right?
Let's see what it picked, right?
And so let's take
a look at this.
And so Lots of kind of
small coefficients,
right, it has a small
coefficient on x one.
It has a small
coefficient on X two
squared has a small coefficient
on X one times X two.
Has this big coefficient
here and a big one here to
even though it's negative.
So let me check that. Do I have
two and negative three
when I generated my data?
I sure did, right?
I had two times the
squared one and then negative
three times the
other one, right?
So the model is doing exactly
what it was supposed.
It was okay that
I gave it much of
other features because
they weren't informative,
and it just ignored them, right?
But at least it had something
there to work with.
Yeah, right here.
Should still be 0.5.
The intercept should
still be 0.5.
Yeah, that's a good
question. Why is it not 0.5?
You know, I guess, is it
trying to fit all this stuff?
It penalizes, like,
large differences more,
and those might happen more when
there's a squared relationship.
And so, you know,
maybe it's trying
to shuffle it up or down to
like better fit some points.
I don't know. It's
not trying to always
be exactly 0.5, right?
I'm sorry square things,
it kind of goes over
a bigger range and
the white intercept
becomes less relevant,
right towards doing
a good score.
So it'll be noisier.
Yeah, good question.
Other questions people have.
Yeah, question right here.
Yeah. Yeah, so if
you don't know that, could
you automatically do it?
Yeah, and I think the
kind of broad category of
those things would
be like AutoML
or automatic machine learning.
There are things out
there that would do that.
You know, you could look at
a bunch of scatter
plots manually,
right, or you could just
throw a bunch of
stuff at it, right?
But, so there's different
different approaches.
Y, Yeah. Oh, oh, yeah.
Could you do at a statistical
significance test?
Yeah, I'm sure you could.
I'd have to think
a little bit, I
don't I don't do
enough stats like,
just tell you off the top
of my head to do that.
I don't think people do a lot
of statistical significance
for machine learning
models because You know,
because I guess, what does
that mean then, right?
So like predicting some y value,
and could I say that, Hey,
like, the y values I'm doing are
kind of like better
than Chance, right?
If I kind of have, like,
terrible y values that
are all over the place,
but it's like there
is a clear pattern,
and there will be a clear
pattern if I have enough data,
then kind of statistical
significance
is a low bar, right?
Maybe I can explain 5%
of the variance, right?
But I can definitely show that
I'm like beating
something random, right?
So it's like, Well,
is that good, right?
I could show, as I have
a bigger better data,
I could have any p
value I want, right?
But it doesn't mean it's
a good model, right?
It's just like, we're competent.
It's like knows something,
but that doesn't
mean it knows a lot.
So yeah, sometimes I've
seen people do
physical significance,
but I don't see them
doing it very often.
Interesting thought.
Yeah, there are other
thoughts or impressions
people have. Oh, right.
Cool. So moving along,
We've done those
transformations.
And what I want to do now
is I want to see how we
can do that with Ashley.
There was one more
thing I want to do.
I want to just try to go through
all these steps of kind
of end to end, like,
I have M one, which is
kind of not that great,
and then M two, which
is much better.
Like, how could I
create a bar plot and
show that to somebody who maybe
doesn't even know a lot
about machine learning,
but to show them, hey, like,
M two is doing better.
And so what I'm
going to do is I'm I
come back to how I
evaluate these things,
and I'm going to
grab it like this.
And let's just see if we can
compare these things, right?
I'm to do a big query.
This one will evaluate
M two for me,
and if I do it again,
then I can evaluate M one
as well. I can do both of those.
Now, I might want
to get the stats
for both of these on top of each
other and so I can do
a union all and SQL,
that means basically canate,
these rows and append
them to other rows,
and so I can get the
stats for both of these.
I'm really just interest
in that R squared score.
I'm going to get the R squared
score from both of them.
And then finally, what
I want to do is I
want to give each of these
models a name, right?
And so I may call
this one M one,
which is linear, and I can say,
well, that's the model name.
And then I can do that
down here as well, right?
So let's just try to do an
end end example where we
have an nice plot
comparing these, right?
So this is like a non linear.
U And then I'm
just trying to capture
that in a data frame
so we can work with it.
I go to get that data frame,
I'm going to peek
at it down here.
And then I want to
plot this thing.
Let me try doing a plot.
And I'm going to
just actually take
a look at it up here so I
can compare side by side.
The plot I want to do
specifically is a bar plot.
I can see that the
model numbers are just
like zero and one,
and that's because when
I plot a data frame,
it's pulling from the index.
The dex is the x axis, right?
And so what I want to do
up here is do a set dex
of the model so that these
things will go to the x axis.
Same thing down here.
I'm going to do that.
It's kind of awfully
a big plot to, right?
So I'm to say fix
size equals like
I don't know, three by 2.5.
All right. I'm to do that.
The other thing I'm
going to do is,
I'm just trying to pull
out that R square score.
So it doesn't have to have
its own own label. All right.
So this is looking a
little bit better.
Let me just slap an
access label on it.
I'm to say dot set y label,
and I can say something like
maybe the R square
score. I can do that.
Of course, I've done
with two models,
but usually when you're
doing this kind of wore,
trying to do a whole
bunch of things and
you'll create a plot like
this and you'll see, well,
these ones perform better or
worse for this
particular training da.
Yeah, right. Tu Zoom
in on the top part? Yeah,
so you could, right?
So I guess what you could
say is you could say,
like Y m equals 0.8 to one?
And now it will look like that.
Now, is that a good thing to do?
Maybe, often, when I talk to
people who are making plots,
people often say, like, I
want to see the
difference, right?
And do we want to
see the difference?
Is the conclusion that,
like, hey, they're
really definite,
is the conclusion,
actually that they both
perform pretty well.
Yeah, I don't know.
I guess, so I'm
always reluctant.
I very rarely like plots
that don't start from zero.
On the other hand, I
mean, you can make
an argument that you
might want to show,
you know, mistakes or
something like that.
Maybe you'd chose a different
metric then, right?
Because maybe each mistake
is costly for some reason.
It's hard to say, like, hey,
how we're using this model?
Is it like, like,
mistakes that are costly,
or is it that getting
things right have
most of the benefit?
Yeah, so, you could, right,
but I'm not sure you'd
want to. I don't know.
There's This is controversial.
Yeah, other questions or
comments people have.
Fantastic. Okay, so what I
want to do now is
I want to see how
we can work with some
non linear data, right?
So I'm gonna get some different
practice data over here.
Let's throw that
down. I'm sorry.
We've already been
doing nonlinear data.
I want to do categorical data.
I want to have letters or
strings or something instead
of just numbers, right?
So I'm gonna get this
data frame here.
And so now X two
is still a number,
but X one is A B or C. For
the purpose of computing,
y, I treat each letter
as a number, right?
So like A is one, B is five,
C is 15, right?
These different
letters contribute to
the y value to different
degrees, right?
And I want to C, Can I train
a model that figures that out?
You know, y that C
will contribute to
a bigger y value where
an A will probably be
like a smaller y value.
Can I figure that out just by
looking at the data, right?
And so this is
where we have to do the
one hot and toting.
And what's cool is that
Big C will do it for us.
But if I want to
trip of the results,
I need to know that
it's doing it for us.
Right? I'm to come down here.
I'm to say, big query,
and I am going to actual
I have to put all of
this in my in my table
somewhere, right?
Maybe I'll just say data framed
two big query, Google Big query.
And this is Section two,
and I'll just call
this table two.
And then if exists
equals replace.
And then all the
same stuff I said
last time the disclaimer
about how I should
do train tests,
and I'm not doing it right now.
Because I just want to
focus on the transformation
in the simplest way
possible. All right.
So I have that thing, and then
I can select X one, X two,
and Y from Section
two table two.
I can do all of that. And
that all looks great, right?
So this maybe let me
see, down here, right?
So I guess this was 15
and this was a nine,
right? That should be like a 24.
Well, that's actually
kind of strange
that's such a large value,
right? What was it?
Was it really plus
two times X two.
Okay, that makes sense, right?
So I have this, and
then two times X two.
Okay, great. So I think
that's all looking good.
And so I want to
train a model for it.
I'm going to say, create
or replace model.
And I'll call the section two M
three because I'm terrible
at naming things.
And as usual we have
to have the options.
And so let me just check my
notes here. How do I do that?
I have to say the model type is
a linear regression as usual,
and the input label columns
is just going to be Y. I'm
going to train that model.
L et's make it happen.
Fantastic. And then
then what are we
going to do with it?
So then we will,
after it's done,
I want to try to figure
out, did it find out
that relationship with AB and C?
And so from Lights,
I want to look at the
model section two M three,
let's select star from that.
I'm just going to throw
in a data frame so
we can use it for stuff, right?
And I always forget
to say from when
I'm using these functions for
whatever reason. Okay, cool.
And so I may get that data
frame, and when I look at it,
I can see that they put
the weight just directly
for H two as normal.
Whereas X one is categorical,
and say added extra
columns for us.
And so they are
actually a bunch of
weights corresponding
to that, right?
And so what I want to do is I
want to come along and see,
well, how much do each of
these contribute, right?
And so if I look
at the data frame,
I can say, you know,
I should say set index,
to the processed input,
I don't want a hard code zero
because maybe that changes.
And then I can say dot at,
and I want the X one
and the category weights.
I'm going to pull that out.
And that's going to give me
an array of dictionaries.
What I'd like to do
with this array of
dictionaries is
turn into a table.
I want a table where there's
a category column
and a weight column.
Because if I have
a table, then I'm
pretty close to being
able to plot this.
I cannot convert an array of
dictionaries to a
data frame directly,
but I can do a list
of dictionaries.
Right? I'm to say two list,
and I'll just draw this,
maybe my weights. All right.
So let's do that. And then
what I can do is I
can create a weight.
DF is going to be panest
data frame of those weights.
And now I could go
ahead and I could
set an index on it if I
want to plot it, right?
The category is going to go to
the index because I want
it to be the x axis,
and I can say plot R, right?
And did it figure
out the pattern?
Well, C contributes the most,
then B and then A. I
figured relatively.
Now, I didn't recapture
these same numbers
up here, which were.
I captured relatively speaking
what these were A B and C,
but it didn't capture 15 and 15.
I wonder if anybody knows why
it's not able to do that.
Any speculation? All right.
Let's take a look down here.
This is the catch right here.
We have a Y intercept, right?
And so when I look at where
I generated this data,
I could have added in
an intercept over here.
I could have said like plus ten,
and then this would have been,
negative nine, and
this would have been,
I guess, like, negative five.
And this one would have
just been five, right?
If I had done it that way,
The data would have
looked exactly the same.
So there's different ways
we would be on the
same thing, right?
So I'll show me
relatively speaking,
but given there's that
intercept and it doesn't have
any way to differentiate what's
an intercept or what these are.
Right?
I just want you to understand
the limitations of it.
But it also helped us
realize which of these
ABC were most important
for contributing to
the final weights
or the final y value.
Right?
So I'm wondering if I can
just leave it there
because I'm out of time.
So thanks and feel
free to come up and chat
if you have any questions.
I hope you have a great evening.