Better. By volume
go to the back.
Fantastic. Thank you
for coming today.
Today, we're going be
learning about Spark SQL.
Spark SQL actually
builds on top of
Spark Resilient
Distributed datasets.
And it's also going to
interact with data frame.
So off we have the save data,
we could either
interact with it using
the data frame API or SQL API.
If I do a SQL query,
the results that come
back to me are also
going to be a Spark data frame.
So all these layers
interact and you'll be
a better Spark user if
you understand each
of these layers.
Alright, I'm going to head
back here to the notebook.
And this is a new
notebook that's
actually pretty similar
to what we had last time.
I just thought it'd be nice
to have a clean start.
If you want, you can
find the same notebook.
I'm trying to grab my pointer.
There it is. You can find
the same notebook in
the lecture snippets.
Let me just show you
where that is briefly.
So if I come over here
and go to lecture
snippets, There's a lake here.
Some of this stuff is actually
also in the notebook itself.
But I have a starter notebook,
and I have the Docker file,
the docker depose,
all that stuff,
so you could spend that up and
start going if you wanted to.
There's a few cells
already there.
I already read them because it
takes something like 5 minutes
or so and I don't
want you to just be
study watching while I do that.
So I'll just walk
through the code
that's already been executed.
So up here as usually,
we're creating a spark session.
The things that are
new this time are that
we are going to enable
something called Hive support.
And we're also going to
specify a location HDFS,
where we have all
of this hive data.
The reason for that is that
if we want to use SQL,
we cannot just have a bunch
of Park files around.
We have to have table names.
And we're going be doing
queries on those tablenames.
So let me just head over
quick to some slides,
so I can explain a little
bit about different names we
might be queering from
in this notebook.
I also want to briefly go over
some loity objectives for Day.
We saw how I have that
hive configuration.
We want to figure out
how we can create
both tables and views and hive,
so we can then do queries.
We're going to talk broadly
about different kinds of queries
today that have to pull
together related data.
Often these distributed
systems where I
have related data
on different nodes,
and to do something
like a group by or
a joy or a eis staked operation,
or we talk about windowing
today, which might be
new to some people.
All these things are
required to bring
related data together in the
same place in the cluster.
And then finally, we
I see how we can use
SQL and data frame operations
as part of a single calculation.
Sometimes that turns
out to be more elegant
than just using one
system or the other.
Alright, so let's
talk about views
and tables that where
we have a hive.
Here I have an example
of P A file that you
can imagine living
somewhere in HDFS.
I mean it has four rows
and the x contains A,
B A C. And what I'm imagining
is I'm reading with sparse.
I've sparked out
read fourba part.
I'm loading that file,
and I'm immediately
filtering it out to x equals A,
Imbod get two of those rows.
And you could easily imagine
that I could directly
do computation on that
data frame at that point,
or I could try to save
those results in some way.
And so there's a couple
of ways I could save it.
One is I could say data
framed out right and
then Save as table,
and I could gib it a table name.
And that's be using i.
A i on my behalf, is be creating
one or more part files
that correspond to this
by table name, right?
So maybe I end up
with a part file
that looks like this down
here with these two rows.
The other thing I
could do is I could
say create temporary view.
A view is actually a
ba data based concept
that has been around forever.
And the way it works,
instead of actually
materializing these bytes of
data and writing it somewhere,
the view will just totally have
a description of how I could
get that data if I need it.
Maybe that description of
how to get the data is
the actual SQL query itself.
I could select data from
either the table or the view.
I'll feel very similar, but
the view when necessary will
actually get be that data,
when I actually do
the query, right?
In some ways, it's a little
bit like an RDD, right?
Because an RDD is giving
you a recipe to get
some data on demand.
A view is also describing
how you could get
this data even though it doesn't
immediately compute it up front.
So just want to make
sure that people are
doing the right
intuition from this.
So I have three questions
comparing these.
And for each question,
you can say one for the
table or two for the view.
So first one is, what do you
think is faster to create?
On the table or two the view.
I'm seeing some twos,
which is correct, right?
There's no real work done
when we create a view, right?
We're just try writing
that query somewhere.
Let's remembering
that. Alright, W
one should I take less space?
On the table or to the view?
Excellent. People did
saying, two, right?
I don't actually
have data there.
I just have a query, which
is not taking much space.
I Which case would it be faster
sum up all the values
in the y column?
On the table to the view.
I see some ones people seem
a little bit more
hesitant on that one.
It will be faster to select data
from the table. Why is that?
Well, if I'm looping over all
the y values in the table,
I only loop over the
one is the three.
If I want to add up all
the y values in the view,
then in addition to
selling those things up,
I also have to do the filter
on demand each time, right?
So so really selecting
over the view,
it feels like it's one query,
but it's actually two queries
that's slower, right?
So you'll have to figure
out if you have some data,
you know, how big is it,
how often are you
be accessing it?
You have to figure out
whether you want to
represent your data as a table
or view. Yeah,
question right here.
Create want data Oh,
you're actually like,
Hey, if we actually want
to read the data of the view,
do you have to do it action?
Yeah, the query that is actually
generating the data for
the view will not actually
happen until you have some
kind of action, right?
So maybe there's maybe
internal to the view, right?
There's some number of
steps that were performed
or maybe after that there's
other operations on the view,
and then ultimately sub action
at the very industry
to trigger it.
Yep. That's exactly how it
works. Yeah, great question.
Cool. So let's head over here,
back to doing those
demos that I had I'll,
try to get a little bit ahead
of myself by talking about that.
So I'm setting this up here.
And what we're doing
is able Hive support.
I've talked about Hive
briefly before how
they built this Hive
query language,
Hive QL, that basically takes
something that
looks like SQL and
translates as to
map produced jobs.
I don't think anybody's really
using that much anymore.
But one of the things that
people are still using with
Hive is they use it
as a data catalog.
If we have all these
different Park files HFS,
and I want to basically
assign table names to
some set of Park files,
then Hive can do that, right?
And so Spark
integrates with Hive.
And so they have a
special function
for enabling Hive support.
And then I have to specify
this warehouse directory
where I'm may be storing
all these Park files.
That's a path in
my HDFS cluster.
You see the vocabulary is a
little bit weird here, right?
The setup I have
here is really more
like a data lake than
a data warehouse.
There's no integrated
AP database here,
but they're using
the word warehouse
instead of a data lake.
Yeah, question right here.
Does it already exist?
No. When I first
run this in Check,
then it created it and I
already ran it earlier.
I won't re run it now, but
it created it at the moment.
I did that. Excellent
question. All right.
So I did that. We had this data
last time from the San
Francisco Fire Department.
There was a two gigabyte CSV.
And I've already run
this. I've uploaded it.
I've done schema
inference on it.
I wrote it back as a
Park file an HDFS.
When I did that, it had
the types from the Schema
inference, which was great.
And I also made sure that
all the column names
didn't have space in them.
I replaced it with underscores.
So that's all good.
Remove the CSV file.
And at this point, we can
read in that data frame,
and that's relatively fast.
It just has to check
out what the header is.
And then I can see what
all the types are there.
It doesn't have to do
with the schema inference
or any of that. Alright, great.
So I have this data, and
I'm ready to go with it.
And so what I'm ready to
do is with the data frame.
I'm going to say data frame dot
create And I see
there's actually four
different functions here,
which are all variants
on the same thing.
Each of them are replacing
a temporary view.
Why is it temporary? If I
shut down my notebook and
then restart it again,
the view is gone. I'll
have to recreate it.
Not a big deal, right? Because
no work has really done.
It's fine to recreate the view
every time I actually
want to do it.
So there's some
other things here.
There's like the
create tent view.
Or it might have the word
or replaced in there,
that will make a difference
whether or not it
already exists.
Some of them, they
add this word global.
I'm never going to use
the ones that say global.
All that means is that, even
though I create the
view in this session,
it could be visible to
other Spark sessions.
I don't have a great
use case for that,
so I'm not going to do it.
I'll just use these
two down here.
First, I'm going to
create a temp view,
and I will call it calls,
B these are calls to
the fire department.
I'm going to do
that spast because
it's not actually
doing any work.
If I were to run
it again, right?
So if I come down
here and run it,
gt error, the second time.
So I often do create or replace.
And then you can if that's
the only thing I can do,
then I can just
rerun my notebook.
No problem. It will make sure
that it's there for
me. Alright, cool.
So now, if I want to
do operations on it,
I can do spark dot squel
and I can put some
kind of query here.
So kind of a classic queries,
I could select star from calls,
and I could just look at say,
like, a few rows.
So I could do that.
Whenever I do one
of these queries,
it gives me a data frame.
The data frame is based
on top of an RDD.
So no work has actually
been done yet.
If I actually want
work to be done,
then I have to come along
and I have to say
something like,
show me the results, right,
so I could do a show.
And this has a lot
of columns and
I just the formatting
looks terrible for that.
We'll just see what
it looks like.
More often, I'll do
two Pandas, right,
because it's just too many
to really fit nicely.
So two Pandas is an action.
It's going to trigger
all the work,
both for this view and
for the other operations,
I'm doing on top of it.
And then I can come along and
I can see the data there.
The other one I could
do is I might say,
I'm going to do this
one for a show,
but I could say show the tables.
And this is a little bit
confusing because this shows,
tables and views, right?
So I'll do that.
And then what I'll see
here is that Well,
it's doing some
hive stuff, right?
We said all this
stuff is in hive.
And any moment now it
should pop up and show me,
sure enough, I have this calls
table, and it's temporary.
All views are temporary and
spark for whatever reason.
I don't know why they don't
have persistent views.
Cool. So that is
all fine and well.
I could do other queries
on here if I wanted to.
So, for example, let's say
I wanted to filter things down,
right? So I'm going to do
When it starts getting bigger,
I usually like to space it out a
little bit. I'm going
to select that.
And maybe I might want
to do a filter, right?
I'm going to do a
filter. And I'm
going to say we're call type.
They have this like
expression in SQs kind
of like regular expressions,
but more simple.
And you can just have
wild charts in it.
So I could say, sometimes
they respond to
bad odors, right?
Maybe it's like natural gas
smell or something like that.
And I could go through
and I could see, Okay,
here are all the
strange and node odors
that the Fire Department
had to deal with.
Right? So I can
filter that down.
Now, if I want to do a subset on
kind of more analysis on
this subset of the data,
I might want to save it
somewhere else, right?
Because if I use this
as my starting point,
every single query on
these stinky rows will
make me have to go over
the entire dataset, which
could be quite large.
Right? So I'm going
to come down here.
And what I'm going to do
instead is I am going to say,
I'm going to say, Well,
first off, I get a
data frame there.
Then I am going to say write
and I get this
data frame writer,
and then I can say
save as table, right?
I'm going to name this
table Stinky, right?
And I'm going to get
rid of this limit.
Right? I'm going to
run that. And they'll
have this nice
table that I could
do other queries on with
this subset of the rows.
And I can see that there are
six tasks. That are doing that.
That's because this data
here that I was working
with has six partitions, right?
And so while that's run.
I'm just try to
get that up here.
That would give me a data frame.
I can get the RDD underneath it,
and I could get the num
partitions like that.
So after this finish is
running, I'm may see, Oh, wi,
there's six partitions,
that's why there's
six tasks that are actually
writing this thing out.
All right. Any questions
while that's running?
Yeah, right here.
That. Yeah, this
is kind of like a regular
expression match,
so it means it begins with Odor,
and then this is a wild card.
So it's like SQL has this,
but just not not as good as
real regular expressions, right?
Yep. Yeah, question
right here. Yeah.
Where's it saved,
I'll show that.
Excellent. Okay, great.
So I see there are
six partitions.
That's why there were six tasks.
And so where is it saved? We can
actually come back here
to answer that question.
And so I can see that
it's supposed to
be saved somewhere
in this directory.
And somebody come back here,
and I can run an HDFS,
DFS, LS command on that one.
And there's going
directory there.
For every table I created,
and I could look
underneath that,
and that table is going
to be represented as,
you know, six different
part files, right?
You can see the part
number right here.
So parts zero through
five, that six partitions,
which cre I'm sorry,
six files, corresponding
to six partitions.
Each one had its own own writer.
I can also, if I want to, I
can come back and I can say
Spark dot SQL and I could
say show tables again.
And let me just
actually do an action.
And now I can see
the Stinky table
is not temporary. I'll be there.
Even if I restart, the
data will still be there,
the calls table would have
to be regenerated on demand.
So any tables about
Sorry, not any tables.
Any questions about
this difference
between these views or
these tables or any of
this code I'm writing?
Is that a question?
Alright. Cool. So
so far so good.
If I want to come back and I
want to run this thing again,
it's going to complain because
I've already created it.
And so I could do
a mode overwrite.
I think I showed
that one last time.
And that's good at
least I can rerun
my notebook again. It would
be kind of slow, right?
I'd have to do the whole
thing. So another one I
sometimes use with
caution is ignore.
That means if it already
exists, don't do anything.
Then I can just re run again.
It'll be really fast. I
wouldn't want to do that if
it's possible that I'm
writing different
data than last time.
But in this case, I
know it would be the
same. So I'll do this in case.
I just want to rerun my notebook
from the top. All right.
Fantastic. So let me
see where are we?
Um You know, sometimes,
even though we have these
high tables now, me,
we might want to access that as
a data frame because
we've already
learned all this stuff
about data frames.
The way you can do that is
going to say spart table,
and I could access
the Stinky table,
and that would give
me a data frame.
This is a data
frame for a table.
And I could also say,
I want to get the
calls, and this
is kind of a little
bit misnamed, right?
So this is for a view.
Right? So in Spark,
they use table,
sometimes they either
mean table or a view.
And I could have that data frame
then and I could do
whatever I wanted
with it that I normally
do with data frames.
Oh, right. Well, let's just
see on these as well as before,
I can say RDD it partitions.
I can interact with the
data with the SQL query,
data frame API or the RDD API.
All right. Cool. So
I'm going to head back
here and have some more
slides to look at.
And in SQL, right?
Sometimes we do a
group by query,
and I may talk about those.
But I also want to talk about
grouping more generally.
When do we have to group
together related data in
order to answer a
question about our data?
And there's a few
very similar queries.
And so I'm imagining that I
have this dataset here
where x has ABAC,
and that data might be spread
across many different machines.
One of the things
that I want to do is
that I want to get
distinct values.
If I do that, I may
have to bring together
my values in some
way to make sure I'm
Outputting duplicates more than.
So if I have different
partition my data
in different places
and they each do
distinct locally,
right, then I may have
duplicates in my output.
That might require us to bring
together groups of related data.
You know, the classic,
where you have to
group data is the
actual group bi.
Group bi is usually
followed by an aggregate.
And so here what I see is
that I have three categories.
There's an A of B and
a C. And if I want to,
for example, add up
all the values in
the y column for each group,
then I have to break
it down, right?
So I have one group up
here with two rows,
a group in the
middle with one row,
and a third group with one row.
And then on each of those, I
could do aggregates, right?
That group with multiple rows
is going to get crunched down
to a single row that has
some statistics with it.
That's a group and an aggregate.
Okay. And some of
you have seen SQL
before you've probably
encountered this.
Maybe some of you might be
very advanced eQL users,
and you might have
seen something related
called partitioning and window
functions, or maybe not.
I'm going to talk
about this as well.
The first thing I want
to point out is if I'm
going back and forth
between these two slides,
the first parts of these things
look very similar, right?
So here, I'm breaking
the data into groups.
SQL partitions, I'm still
breaking them into groups,
but they're just using
the word partition
instead of group. Right?
And I want to be very clear.
These are SQL partitions,
which are distinct from
Spark partitions, right?
So CQL partition is
trying to have you know,
if I'm partitioning you
say on the x value,
each partition is trying to have
just one unique
value there, right?
So I have a partition for A,
I have a partition for B,
a petition for C. The
spart partitions,
that might be different, right?
The spart partitions when doing
this work might have say,
like a B and a C
together, right?
In the same spark partition.
But here, they're all separate.
And the big difference
between this one
and the last one is
that instead of having
an aggregate that crunches
all the rows down to
a single row like before.
Now what will happen is
I will actually have
output rows for each
specific row, right?
I had four input rows
at the beginning.
Here I have four output
rows at the end.
And so if I'm outputting
some statistics for
every single row,
why did I have to bother
bringing together related data?
And the answer is that
for some of these rows,
I might want to compute
some statistics about it
that are in relation to
the group that it's in.
So for example, when I
look at the A group,
I see one and three,
that adds up to four.
And so one way I could look at
it is that the first row in
the A group represents
25% of the value,
and the second one represents
75% of the value, right?
So I might want
to get some stats
per row that are computed
relative to this group or
partition that it's in.
I might also want to,
within each group,
I want to say,
like, this is the
biggest a value.
This is the second
It's the third biggest a value.
So I might want to
get the row number
within each group for
each of these, right?
Le, 75 is the first biggest, A,
25 is the second biggest A.
I guess for the B and C,
there's just one, so then there
would be like the
one biggest, right?
So again, like,
it's very similar.
The main difference is before
each group gets one row
of summary statistics.
Here, I get each row
that's coming in,
comes as a row out,
but the statistics are
computed relative to the group
or partition that it's in.
We have any questions about
the difference between these?
Right? Yeah, right here. Yes.
Yeah, so we could have
duplicate x values, right?
So we're not aggregate
gating down,
but we still want to compute
stats relative to a group.
Instead of competing
stats for the group,
we want to compute stats for
a row relative to the group?
Do that make sense? Yeah, yeah,
great way to clarify
it. Yeah, a, follow up.
Yeah. Yeah, is there any
real world application?
I mean, I guess, if
if I was managing
a bunch of salespeople and
they were in different cities,
I might want to know
who like my top
three people are in every city,
right? Yeah, stuff like that.
I might want to do,
right? Yeah, right here.
These are spark SQ queries
Yeah, that's a good question.
Are these Spark SQL queries
or regular queries?
And so they're
actually, you know,
organizations that define, like,
this is what the
SQL language is.
And so there's
different standards.
Is evolved over time. And so
Spark SQL actually is a
fully compliant sequel.
The meet the Spec. So both.
Yeah, great thanks
for clarifying.
Yeah, questions people have.
All right. Yeah, so
what else do we have?
Sometimes when we're
doing like grouping,
we might have chains that
have multiple steps of this.
So, for example, when
I look at this first
thing over here,
maybe I want to get all
the unique rows, right?
I see that I have A one.
I have two different B
threes, and I have an A two.
So I might group together by
the combination of those,
like I have that here.
And at that point, I might
say, well, what is the ro count?
How often do each
of those appear?
I might want to further
roll up those statistics,
and I might want to say, well,
what is the row count
for both A and B?
But I might also be
interested for each A and B,
how many subcategories there
were with, Y, for example,
When I'm looking at at the As,
there's actually two
different y values.
Was I'm looking at the Bs,
there's only one
different y value, right.
There might be
different ways I want
to roll out these statistics.
I might want to have
kind of a chain
where I group things along.
Whenever I have a chain
or a pipeline like that.
Another way to represent it
would be with nested queries.
I may show that a little
bit later, right?
It feels different, but
fundamentally it's the same.
Any kind of nesting is
identical to a pipeline.
And honestly, I
think the pipeline
is the easier way
to reason about it.
But we'll see both.
Cool. So let's row ahead
and we're going to do
a quick tophat about
windowing functions.
Right. Let me bring this
up over here. Cruel.
All right. A 30 seconds left.
Alright, so most people are
saying that it was a grouping by
followed by an aggregate.
Which is correct, right?
I I had had partitioning
and some windowing
function done,
I would probably
have some statistic
outputed for each of
these hundred rows.
But I don't have that. I don't
have 100 rows of output.
I have 20 rows of output,
which corresponds to the number
of unique values, right?
There's probably some kind of
grouping for each unique value,
and I get one summary
statistic for
each of those. All right.
An follow up questions on that?
Alright. So I'm ahead over here,
and we're going to do some
more programming demos.
Let me just exit
out of this first.
Great. So now we're
do some queries.
And I'm going to
do it with the date
I've been working on.
And For the a lot
of these queries,
I'm may be breaking
down the data by
different neighborhoods in San
Francisco, and they chose,
like the longest
possible variable name,
which I don't want to
keep typing in part,
because I can never remember
how to spell neighborhoods I
guess they couldn't really spell
neighborhoods correctly, either.
L three's there. Anyway, so
I'm going to rename that thing,
so I don't have to
keep dealing with it.
So I'm may come back earlier
when I created my view, right.
So I did a great or
replaced view here.
And what I could do is I can
say, with column renamed,
and I want to rename
that areas is
nice and easy to type something.
I'll create or replace it.
Great. And then
when I'm down here,
I should be able to say
spark dot table and calls.
And hopefully, it says
somewhere near to the
end, I should say, like,
area areas somewhere,
right? Okay, great.
Maybe let's just make
it singular, so,
because that's what I have in
my notes and why I confuse
myself by drawing off
stripped. Alright,
so we'll do that.
Great. And now I have this area,
and I can do queries over it.
And so maybe, like,
the first simple question
would be something
like what are the
names of the areas?
And so I could do
that by a Spark SQL,
and I could select distinct
area from calls, right?
So instead of getting like
every entry and every row,
I just want to get
unique ones, right?
So if I do that, data frame,
nothing actually happens,
I could say something
like two Pandas,
and then I will
actually get these.
So that will run And I'll
get those unique values,
and that should finish soon.
Great. As I can see these are
all the different neighborhoods
in San Francisco,
and they get different calls
from different ones. All right.
C. So the next one I want
to do is I want to say,
how many calls are
there per area.
And for this one
I may applauded.
I don't do probably as many
plots as I should, right?
Gues maybe people learn
that other courses.
But sometimes I think
it's nice to say,
like, Okay, I have a question.
I go do some stuff in Spark.
I get my data back in Pandas
or something like that.
I do a full end to end plot
that looks kind of nice.
I think that would be
a useful exercise.
Okay, so what I'm going to
do is I'll say Spark, SQL.
And I'm going to say select.
I want to get some
kind of a count,
and I'm going to
select it from calls,
and I want to group
by area, right?
So this will give me the
count for each area.
I probably want to take
what I'm grouping by and
put that on the select
line so I can see it.
I'm going to do
that. I see that's
give me some kind
of data frame back.
And if I want to, I
can say two Pandas.
So I have something to
actually work with.
That's going to be my Pandas DF.
Great, and two Pandas,
I think I just forgot
how they did that.
And I also made the same
mistake in the morning too.
Let me just do a quick PIP
three Install of Map pot lib.
Pandas integrates
with Matplot lib.
So this example I'm going to
do needs to have that installed.
This is inside of my container.
And so there's no
virtual environment.
It complain unless I do that.
All right. So I'll just run
that briefly. All right.
Great. And so I'm going
to get this data frame,
and then I can see the
Pandas data frame.
Well, that is a
pandas data frame.
I'm just going to call
this something like count
so that I don't have to
type the star and all that.
Is have a strange name.
Alright. So if I
want to plot this,
what I can do is I can try
to extract a single
column from here,
so maybe I want to
get the count column.
And if I do that and I plot it,
the way that if I make
a bar plot from it,
what Pandas will
do by default is,
we'll have these be my Y values.
I think that makes
sense. And my X values
are going to be from
the dex, right?
So if I go ahead and
say plot do bar,
Pandas is going to make
a MT plot lib plot.
And maybe it's kind of okay,
but it's also not
great because I
don't have the actual
neighborhood names.
So coming back here momentarily,
I have this data frame.
And if I want to get the
proper labels on the x axis,
that means I need to replace
these values with
something like area.
And I can do that
just fine in Pantas.
I'm going to say, let's set
the index to be the area.
That looks pretty good.
Let's get out the count like
before. That looks good.
Now I have a series where I have
the index can be nice x values,
and these can be nice y
values, let's plot it.
All right, so that's
looking pretty good.
Let's try to make a
very nice pot though.
Let's do everything, right?
So I think one thing
that will make this
better is if I say,
like order by count
descending, right?
I can quickly see like
the neighborhoods with
the most fires or
whatever incidents
and the ones with
the fewest fires.
I'm way around that.
Some other things that I
can do is that when I
have too many zeros,
it's just a little bit
hard to read them.
And so what I can do is
when I have this count,
I could divide it
by 1,000, right?
So these numbers will be a
little bit smaller, right?
So I can do a plot dot bar.
If I'm changing that, I
better update my Y axis.
And so if I get this
Ax subplot object,
then I can change that and
I can say dot set Y label.
This can be like a call count,
and it'll be in thousands.
Right? So it's starting
to look pretty good.
The plot is too large, right?
I think it's nice to have
small plots with
large font, right?
Because it doesn't
tak a lot of room on
the page, but it
should be readable.
I won't mess with the
font size right now,
but let's at least make
this little bit smaller.
Let's say it's like 7 " wide,
and then maybe something
like 3 " tall.
And there we start to
get a pretty nice plot,
right? And I don't know.
I lived in San Francis
the Bay area for a
couple of things,
and people told me you
don't go to the Tenderne.
I don't know if they have a lot
of fires down there or what,
but this plot seems to
back up that advice I saw.
And so I guess if you
don't like fires,
you would maybe go to
Lincoln Park. I don't know.
We can start looking
at it and see
the patterns across
different neighborhoods.
So I'll just pause there
for a moment and
see if anybody has
any questions about
that kind of end
end example from Spar to a plot.
Right. Cool.
So let's carry on.
So I want to look at
a case now where we could
look at neighborhoods,
I'm going to start
looking at call types,
and they have lots of
different call types,
and call types are part of
bigger call type groups.
And so first, I want to look
at just combination of those
and then see how we can break
it down further, right?
I'm going to grab this, right?
I'm going to say, my
question now will
be how many calls are there?
Per call type call group
slash type. All right.
Great. So instead of area,
what I will do is I
will say call type,
and I will also have
a call type group.
I want to get both of these.
And that means I can have to
group down here as
well by both of them.
So I'm going to group
by both of them.
I'm not ting to worry too much
about the order of them
right now. So I can do that.
I should be able to
summarize that in
general for me, right?
So I guess, you know,
honestly, maybe it's a little
bit easier to say order by
Call type group
ascending, right?
So I can actually see
the different categories
in each of them, right?
So I can do that.
And then I can see,
for the potentially life
threatening things,
I can see while there's
medical incidents
or water rescues or
traffic collisions or
fires, all these
different things, right?
Cool. So I have that.
And I might want
to roll up these
statistics further
because some of these categories
might be dominated by
one subcategory, right?
Maybe you can see
already the potentially
life threatening things.
They're mostly
medical incidents.
And in contrast, you
think of the fire department
is dealing with fires,
but like structure fires
are relatively rare.
So I just want to get a sense,
to what extent does the biggest
category dominate, right?
I'm to say, we all phrase
this is, for each group,
what percentage of calls are
represented by the most
common type, right?
All right. And so how am I
going to do this, right?
I think that I need to have
actually a nested query would
be one way of doing it.
Let's just think about how
I'd start doing the select.
I'm I select something
from something,
and then I have to have
some kind of group by.
I think what I'm grouping
by is the call
type group, right?
So how what percentage of
calls are represented by
the most common type?
So I'm going to say for
each call type, group.
You know, is that term
here for each group?
I better have that down here.
And then I have that
up here as well.
And then I want to know, well,
how many are for the
most common type.
And the way I could do
this is I could say, well,
what is like a Max count?
Divided by the sum of
some accounts, right?
So within this call type group,
I have a bunch of
different ac counts.
I have a bunch of differ
accounts up here.
I want to get the biggest
one divided by the total.
Maybe I'll multiply
that by 100 and
then call that a percent.
Maybe I'll call it like
the top percent, right?
Because it's the percentage
represented by the top group.
And then what it's tricky is
what I actually
select from here.
What I'd like to select from
is this data up here, right?
And that data came
from a query, right?
And so what could I do? I could
actually copy all of this.
And I could put some
parentheses down here, right?
I can have some parentheses,
and I could say,
let's print this out.
And so I'm going to run that.
And I guess that's just actually
giving me a data frame.
I can say two pan to if I
want to do it for real.
And then I should be able to
go through and see what it is.
It's a little bit hard be
hard to see the
actual names on it.
I'd be actually something
easier to do if I
had was using partitioning
and windowing,
which we're going
to look at shortly.
But at least for now,
I can get some sort
of sense, right?
These potentially life
threatening and not
life threatening.
It seems like they're dominated
by a single category.
I can't quite see
what it is here,
where some of these
other things like fires,
maybe there's numerous
different kinds of fires and
even the most common
kind of fire is
only 38% of all the cases.
Now, even though I've
done nesting here,
I want you to think about
this like a pipeline, right?
It's running this query first.
And then the output of that is
feeding in to this query, right?
So nesting pipelines, that's
the same concept. All right.
Any question about
the nested query
before I do it again
with the data frame API?
Yeah, crush right here.
The indentations.
The indentation
is not necessary.
It just looks nicer
to me, I guess. Yeah.
Thanks for clarifying.
Yeah, there are
questions people have.
Cool. So let's do
the same thing,
but with a data frame API.
So same with data frame API.
Now, I've been doing all
these spark queries,
but I can go back and
use this example.
Now, I have all of these calls,
and that gives me
a data frame that I can
start working with.
And I want to have some
kind of pipeline here,
and so I'm going to
have many lines, right?
Each of which is doing
one function call.
And so I'll start
with those calls.
And the first thing I
want to do is a group by.
What do I want to
group by? I want to
group by both of these.
I want to group by call type,
group and trol type, right?
So let me get both
of those in here. And
so I can do that.
I say I get this
grouped expression,
and then I want to get a count
for each of them.
So say dot count.
And this is kind of interesting
because I'm doing count,
and is that transformation or
an action actually depends?
Whenever I've done
it before, I want to
get a single number
out to the strain,
and that is an action.
I have to see an actual number.
In this case, when
I have a group,
followed by an
aggregate like that,
that's producing data that
I might use for something else.
So in this context, it's
actually a transformation.
I want to be able to look at
count based on the context,
say, Oh, that's a transformation
or that is an action.
Alright, great. So I have this.
I have a data frame so far.
Let's do more things, right?
I think when I'm
looking up here, right,
I've already done
this part right here.
Now I want to do this next part,
which involves another
group by, right?
I first grouped by this.
Now in the outer query I'm
grouping by this. I'm
going to group it again.
I'm going to say group by,
and I want to get a call type.
Group. Okay, so I'm
going to have that.
Again, nothing has
actually been done yet.
And this is a little bit more
complicated because
for simple aggregates,
they have functions that are
just there and they're
named for you.
This is kind of a more
complicated aggregate up here.
It's not just a simple function.
And so I'm I have to
say aggregate here,
and I have to have some kind of
expression. Says
what I want to do.
Now, this expression
thing, remember this comes
from ti spark squ functions.
Remember that I have
both the column and
the EXPR there that,
you know, we'll
use all the time.
And from Okay,
great I had a typo.
I'm going to import
those things.
And then down here,
I can actually have
some kind of expression.
And so what will
my expression be?
Maybe I'll just start
with this, right?
Since it's based on
top of SQL anyway,
there's some changes
I'll have to do.
I think one change is that is
that when I did this count,
I couldn't really name
it, and so the name of
it is actually just
count in this case.
And the other thing
is that I cannot
put an as inside of
this expression,
at least as far as I'm
aware, so I can do this.
If I want to do
as, then I have to
say this alias thing over here.
And so then I'll say
this is the top percent.
All right, so I can do that.
I get this data frame,
and then if I really
want to see it,
then I have to go back and
say two Pandas and I'll run,
and I'll get exactly
the same results back.
Before you can make some
stylistic decisions here.
Do you want to use
one or the other?
I personally find like
the step by step.
Imagine when I'm doing the data
a little bit more
intuitive, right?
But some people
really like SQL and
don't aren't as troubled
maybe as I am by like
all the nesting.
Somehow, like this gets me all
confused because it doesn't
happen in a logical order.
If I think about the
series of things,
I'm kind of jumping around.
I like, you know, it group
bys, and then it aggregates,
and then it groups by again,
and then it aggregates,
and it's just not very
straightforward for me.
Alright, so great. Any questions
about either of these?
Yeah, right here.
Yeah, well, I think
the first thing I
wanted to do is I wanted
to be able to compare
the most important call type
relative to all the
different call types.
So I first had to just
come back here and did
some summary statistics.
For every combination of call
type group and call type,
I had to see how
often it was, right?
So for a potentially life
threatening medical incident,
there were this many.
But then I wanted to roll it
up further and say, well,
how big is this relative
to all of the life
threatening things.
And so each time,
I roll up the data to
another level of summary,
I might have another group bye.
And you can imagine
how that might
happen at many different levels.
You'd have a more
complicated pipeline
where I start down with
a very detailed data,
and it becomes kind of more and
more of a core strained
summary, right?
Do that make sense? Yeah,
yeah, thank you for asking.
Yeah, other questions
people have. All right.
Cool. So let's do a
windowing function.
And I just tried
to come up with a
simple windowing
function here example,
even though it's maybe
a little bit contrived.
And so for each of these
neighborhoods, right?
They have all these calls, and
each call has a call number.
And so my question is,
what are the smallest
the smallest three call numbers
for each area, right?
What are they?
Okay. And The way
we're going to do this
is rab in two steps.
The first thing
I'm going to do is
I'm ready to bring together
all the rows in the
same area, right?
It's going to be a
this single partition.
And then we're
going to rank them.
We're going to say, Well,
this is the number one,
number two, number three,
from smallest to largest.
And then after that, I could do
a separate step where
I can say, Well, a,
you put ranks in
all of them, but
I'm only interested in ranks,
one, two, and three.
So it's going to have
a two step process.
And so I will write a
Spark SQL query here,
and I'm going to be selecting
something from calls. All right.
And so one of the things I
want to know is for each area,
what's going on, right.
And then I want to
have a call number,
right because I want
to see what they are.
And here's where it just a
little bit strange, right?
Because I want to bring
together related data.
And so You know,
I don't like their syntax,
but I wish just like if I'm
doing a group I wish I could
somehow indicate down here.
Okay, I want to partition by
this. But but they
don't do that.
They actually
combine quite a bit
on the select line itself.
So the first thing I
have to do is I have to
say which window function
am I interested in,
and the one I'm interested in
is is the row number, right?
So I'm may bring
together all the data
in the same area and may
assign within each of these
partitions a row number.
Alright, so if I'm doing that,
I have to say I'm
doing the row number,
but it's relative to
these partitions,
and I have to specify that.
So I have to say
row number over.
And then inside of here,
I have to specify what
my partitions actually
look like, right?
And so You know, normally,
we're doing a group by later on,
Partition by happens right here.
For whatever reason, that's
how the syntax they designed.
So I may say partition by,
and we want to
partition by area.
Okay, Fantastic. And then
when I'm doing
that, Okay, great.
I brought everything
together in the same area,
but I need to somehow indicate
the order of the rows
within a partition, right?
If I say it's row number one,
well, one of what?
And so in addition to
doing a partition here,
I also have to have an order by.
And in this case,
I may have a call
Number, right? So to
really do this, right?
I'm still like selecting this
for every single row
of my input data.
But when I want to
get this function,
what I have to do
is I have to pull
together related data by area,
and then say, within that area,
what call number is it?
And I think I want
to do you know,
I want number one to be the
smallest rather
than the biggest.
I will say ascending,
right? So I can do that.
And that will give
me a data frame
that will answer that question.
And maybe that's a really
awful column name, isn't it?
I'm just going to call
that something like num.
Right? So so far so good.
And if I ran this right now
and actually collected it,
like if I did a two pandas
or something like that,
my whole VM would
actually freeze.
Asked me how I know, because
what it's doing is it's
taking all that spark data,
which is distributed and not
a memory at the same time,
and it would try to
bring it into memory.
So I should not do that.
What I need to do somehow
is filter it down.
So I'm I try to do aware num
is less than or equal to three.
How many rows will that return?
Well, it depends. Let
me come back here.
How many areas do I have?
There are 41 areas
in San Francisco.
And so if I have
three rows reaching,
it's like 120 rows.
That should be
fine, right? But if
I do it, it's not going to work.
Why? Well, this filtering by
num happens before any
partitioning happens, right?
It is trying to filter down
the rows before it partitions.
And so that's not good, right?
Num doesn't even exist before
I do the partitioning.
Okay, fine. If I
was doing group by,
I similarly cannot do where,
but I would do having.
So I would try to make sense
like I'm going to do having.
For whatever reason,
I think they
should support this,
but they don't.
They're like, Well, Having
only works with group B.
And so I'm like, Okay, well,
this is pretty annoying.
So now I have two
ways I could do it.
I'm going to start
doing the bad way,
and then I will abandon it.
I think what the bad way is,
I could do some kind of nested
query from all of this.
And then at the very end,
I could say where m is less
than or equal to three.
Something like that,
I could do, right?
I first, put a rank
to everything,
and then I filter it
down. That's annoying.
What I think is better
is that since this
is just like a
data frame anyway,
and the data frame
API doesn't have
all these weird
restrictions about
which transformations
happen in what order,
I can do a ware clause
wherever I want, right?
I could just say where num
is less than or equal to three.
That gives me
another data frame.
Right? When I'm
equal so particular.
You have to do the group by,
and then the order by,
and then the limit.
You can do anything in any order
when you're doing
Spark directly.
And I think it's a nice
case where like, Well,
this maybe a little
bit more readable
than the data frame API,
but kind of just tacking this on
the end is a little
bit more readable.
And so let's just go
ahead and do that, right?
So I want to see the top three
for each of these
different areas.
So that'll run for a moment.
Any questions while
that's running?
Yeah, right here. Yeah, exactly.
So this row number is
computed with respect to
some partitioning
of the data, right?
So it's over some
partitioning of the data.
And, you know, the syntax
is a little bit uglier than if I
had like a group buy down below.
I guess the advantage is
that I could have, you know,
I could have multiple
windowing functions,
each of which put the data in
different kinds of partitions,
right, I'd be kind of strange.
But I guess this
is more flexible,
even though it's much
uglier to look at.
That makes sense? Alright, cool.
And so I can see, Okay, well,
in the Bayview Hunters Point,
then these are the
smallest ones, right?
In Western edition, I guess
they have some repeats,
but these are the three
smallest numbers,
the smallest second,
smallest and
third, smallest. Alright, cool.
Any other questions about
partitioning or window functions
or the combination Excellent.
Yeah. So the order by happens
on a per partition basis, right?
So each partition will
have its own ordering.
And I need to do that because,
you know, I could have
done a sending, right?
And then number one would
be the biggest one
instead, right?
So, you know, the row number
relative to the partition,
it only makes sense
if I have a order
that's specified for the
rows within a partition.
Yeah, thank you for clarifying.
Yeah, ch right here.
41 areas. Oh. Yeah, you were
saying there are 41 areas,
and why are there.
Because there should
have been 123, right?
And there's 125 Huh.
Well, that's kind
of interesting.
Now, I'm curious. I
don't know the answer.
So let's just I won't spend
a lot of time because I'm just
trying of exploring to
try to understand myself,
and maybe that might
take me like 20 minutes.
And then so I might bring
this back to an
answer next time.
But let's just see
what it looks like if
I try to print off all
of the data, right?
So you were saying
like the area.
And let's just make this
like a list, right?
Maybe like a sordid list.
Can I see? Are there duplicates?
Where is that happening? Did I
just like to do the math
wrong or what happened?
Seems like there's
three for each of them.
Oh, oh, be the 42. Okay, great.
Yeah, I guess I
looked at the biggest
index and multiplied by three.
So hopefully that's all good.
Hopefully the math checks
out, let me know if not.
Yeah, thank you for
paying close attention.
Yeah. Is that a
question over here?
Yeah. In Yeah.
So maybe I'll raise this.
What is the difference between
an aggregate and a
window function?
Is that fair or interest.
Yeah. An aggregate will
take a bunch of rows and
crunch it down to a single row
with some summary statistics.
A window function will actually
compute a statistic for
each row individually,
but that statistic is in
relation to the bigger group
or partition that
it's in, right?
So right? Like, when
I did a row number,
I'm not trying to get just
one row number for each area.
I'm going to get
a row number for
every row within an area, right?
So aggregates will just
crunch it down to one stat?
Row numbers is going to put
a statistic on each
individual row?
Yeah, follow up here.
Yeah. Yeah, the
windowing function
will not affect the
total number of rows,
grouping by with an
aggregate will. Yes.
Yes. All right.
Great. And so great questions,
and I think we have
to call time there.
So yeah, see you all on Friday,
and we'll do some more examples
in this notebook.
Have a great day.