It well for you on Monday.
I'll try to get those results
back to you as soon as possible,
probably by the end of the
weekend if things go well.
We're moving into a new
topic which is streaming.
That's the last topic before we
start talking about
Cloud tripute,
that will end out this part
of the semester on clusters.
There's a couple of
things where we look at.
What was where we look at Kaka.
KPI have these
streams of messages.
And so I have a lot of similar
ideas we've seen before,
like partitioning
and application.
But what's different
is that the systems we
looked at before have the
data living somewhere.
Maybe I have HTFS,
and I have some PCA files that
are living there long
term, or I have asadra.
I have rows that are
living there long term.
KACA is really for getting
data from one point
to another, right?
So we have some things
that are producing
KAFKA data that other places
are consuming it out.
And so that will be a
very different concept
of what we've seen before.
There's a few things
we'll do. We'll talk
broadly about Kaka concepts.
The kind of programming
you'll do if you're
writing FCA code on Friday,
give some hands on demos.
And then on Monday, we'll
talk about reliability.
Just like all these
other systems,
we have to handle
situations where a machine
dies or is otherwise
unavailable.
The cluster should keep working.
And so we'll take a
look at that on Monday.
There's a lot of
interesting kind of
differences in how they
do that than say,
Cassandra does it.
And then to round out next week,
what we do is we we look
at Spark streaming.
So Spark, as you're well aware,
co loaded data from a Part
file HDFS or other sources.
It could also use the data
source M Kaka Stream,
which is, there's possibly
new data coming in.
And see that sometimes
we might have a
rolling computation.
Maybe you have a group
by with some counts.
And as there's new data
rather than be run
that whole query,
maybe I can keep my
results updated, right?
Oh, a new roll of data,
your counts change a little bit.
So we'll see how we can use
a spark in combination
with Kafka.
Alright, C. So I had
a head over here.
And there's a few things I
want you to walk away with.
One is that we're a to visit
ETL, extract transform load.
Remember that sometimes
you extract data
from one system and load
it into another one.
We're a to see that
there are some benefits
if we could do that
on a rolling basis.
If we have a constant
stream of changes,
tubing out of one system
and getting loaded
into another one.
Second, I want you to understand
what you have to do to
actually go and write
code for CAPCA.
You're going to be writing
consumer code that's reading
these updates or producer
code that's generating them.
All of these changes
or messages that
we're worried about
are going to show
up in different topics, right?
And those topics are going
to be stored on brokers.
So you won't really be
writing code for brokers,
but you're going to
have to understand what
they are and how to
interact with them.
And then finally,
we're going to be
concerned with
scalability as always.
So we're going to
figure out how we
could scale out to
more brokers with
partitioning and how
we could also share
work across different
consumers and consumer groups.
So I want to frame this
in contrast to RPCs,
remote procedure calls that
we've been using the
whole semester, right?
There's some similarities
and some differences.
Let's just look at
regular procedure calls.
Here I have an example of
a procedure or a function
called increase.
It's associated with
a dictionary of data.
When I get a key and amount,
then I look at the
value for that key,
and I increase it by the amount,
and then I return the
new final amount, right?
I can just call like a
regular function down here.
That's fine. If everything's
already a one computer.
I I have multiple
computers and I want them
to have access to
the same dictionary,
then what I'll probably have
to do is have that data,
that dictionary, and some
kind of centralized server.
And that increased function,
that's using the
counts dictionary,
will have to be a
log slide, right?
I have a separate
machine over here.
And then I can have lots
of different clients.
And what I'd like is for
the to be able to call
that increased
function for me to
trigger that execution and to
see the centralized
data that's updated.
And so how can I do that?
Well, we have to have
remote procedure calls.
The remote procedure
calls gives us
some stub code over
on the client side,
it gives us some server code
over on the server side.
And GRPC will automatically
generate that for you.
This is kind of a
simplified version,
but it gets across
all the key points.
Right so over here, I have
that increase flection,
which doesn't actually
do the increase work.
It's just code to send the
call over to the server.
So how does that
actually happen?
Well, When I call increase
on the client side,
those arguments are going
into those parameters.
And then the code and side of
my crease stub is sending
a message over the network
to the server, right?
That's listed at
some kind of port.
I send that request message.
The code over there is
going to have to extract
those values out again
that key them out
and then it calls the
real increase function.
And then the reverse looks
much the same, right?
I have some kind
of return value.
It gets returned back
to the RPC server,
so I send a response back.
And then finally, I
get that return value
back on the client side, right?
That's just a classic RPC.
And hopefully that's
just bringing
back memories about
why that's useful.
Some things that we have to
do with both streaming and
RPCs are serialization
and deserialization.
Right? I can have this key,
which is maybe a Python string,
which is a python integer.
If I want to send those
over the network,
I actually have to
represent those as bytes.
It's sub a standard forbat.
So serialization is converting
those values to bytes.
Deserialization is converting it
back, and I have to
do the same thing.
When I send back a return value,
you have to serialize it, so
it's bites over the network.
And deserialize it back, so it's
a Python type of the receiving.
There's lots of different
ways you could do that.
One would be JSO, right?
If I have some type
of dictionary,
I could in tote it as
a JSON string that I
could convert that
stra to bytes,
using some of entity
like maybe UTF A.
So I can be seding those values
back and forth using JSOD.
I could alternatively
use protocol buffers,
which is what GRPC uses,
and that might be
a more compact way
to represent those same things.
I mean, JSON is easy to look at,
but it's not a very
efficient format.
I could use protocol
buffers for messages here.
Just a little bit of
review about RPCs.
And now I want to compare and
contrast that with
streaming, right?
So RPCs are an example of
synchronous communication.
It only works if the
client and the server are
up and running at the same time
and communicate directly
with each other.
When they are, then the
client to directly send
that message to the server and
get some kind of response.
You're all familiar
with synchronous
communication from
the real world.
I mean, we're having synchronous
communication right now.
As I'm talking to
you, if you tell
somebody out on a phone,
that's synchronous.
RPC calls are synchronous.
Now, of course, humans also
like to communicate
asynchronously,
and there's equivalence
to that in computing.
So I mean, if I'm trying to
communicate asynchronously,
maybe I send somebody
an e mail or
a text message or
something like that,
and streaming is an example
of asychres communication.
And so just like with
e mail and texting,
there has to be
some kind of server
somewhere that
stores my message.
When the receiver is
not looking at it.
And the same way, the
simple client server motels
may be a little bit
more complicated.
We have to have
something in the middle
that stores the message if
the producer and consumer
aren't online at the same time.
So instead of a client I
may call it a producer,
instead of a server I'll
call it a consumer,
and we have a broker in
the middle where the
messages are being set.
And in this case, I've
tried to draw it so that
the consumer is not
currently online.
That's fine. The producer
computer is online.
It's sending these
messages to the broker.
The producer could
go off line and
the consumer can come
back on line later,
and then they could
start getting
those messages a sacredously.
Right? So there's
some differences
here, also some similarities.
Maybe we might want to use
protocol buffers with
a streaming service,
for example. All right.
So well,
any review questions or
kind of any question about
that broad frame before you go a
little deeper. All right.
So let's see how
this is all relevant
in terms of extract
transform and load.
And again, this is maybe a
little bit of a review first.
Remember that a large
organization might
have lots of different databases
for different purposes.
A lot of those might
be OLTP databases.
Therefore processing
transactions.
A transaction might mean
that I insert a row,
or I edit a row or look up
a row, that kind of stuff.
So I have all these transaction
processing databases like that.
The storage layoff
for that is probably
row oriented because
that's most efficient
for these row oriented
operations that
we're doing, right?
This setup, right, if I
look at the left hand side,
database one and two are
terrible for analytics.
For a couple of reasons.
One, a lot of analytics,
I'm looking at entire
columns of data,
and that's not efficient if
I have a role oriented layout.
And second, you might imagine
I might do some
analytics that needs
to combine data across these
two data sources, right?
So I'd have to pull
it off before I
could do any kind of analytics.
So what people do is they'll
go and they'll write
theseETL jobs,
extract transform load that
extract data from
the first database,
transformer subway, and then
they'll load into a
separate database.
And maybe I have an OLAP
database over here,
so online analytics processing.
And that has a very nice
column oriented format.
And if I have these two
Python jobs I wrote,
they can pull data
from both of these and
provided one big
database over here.
And that database is
called my Data Warehouse.
So I could do that.
And if I've run
these Python programs I might
need to think about
how often they run.
Maybe they run what's a
night or what's an hour.
At some kind of granularity,
they have to realize what
data has changed and then
load that into the
new system, right?
There are tools like Cron.
In Linux, rod is a
program that runs
other programs on some kind of
schedule that I predetermined.
And the Cloud, there's
similar things.
There's Google Cloud
scheduler that can lodge
tasks or do other stuff on
some kind of a schedule.
With any of these approaches,
one of the things I might be
worried about is freshness.
Even if it's happy every hour,
for some things, that's okay.
And for some, that might
be too sale, right?
So I'm worried about
freshness in this situation.
Another thing is that in more
complicated organizations,
there might not be just
one data warehouse
that meets all the needs, right?
Maybe I want to do this
to my data warehouse,
but maybe I also
want a data lake,
where I'm, you
know, writing this
as a bunch of Park
files at HDFS,
so I can run map reduced
jobs, park jobs.
Whatever, right?
I might have multiple
things on that side.
And so let's just generalize
this a little bit.
On the left hand side, I have
different OLTP databases.
And on the right hand side,
I have y different stores.
They are really
like derivatives or
secondary copies of the data
I use for various purposes.
So if I have this X and Y,
I'm wondering how many ETL
jobs I'm going to have to write?
How does this scale thoughts?
Yeah, go ahead. It'll
be X times Y, right?
So maybe two times
two isn't a big deal,
but you could imagine
that becoming a problem.
Maybe it's straight,
right? It means that we'll
all be well employed
for a long time.
But it's certainly
not efficient, right?
So there's this great
blog post called
the log that some of you might
be interested in reading.
It was written by Jay Kreps,
who was at Lichen and identified
this X times Y problem,
where we have to go from
every combination to
every combination.
And so at Liked, he had some
other people built Kafka.
Then, you know, he
left with some folks,
and they built a
separate company
around Kafka called fluid.
But this is an early blog,
really motivating why we need
to deal with this problem.
This kind of X to Y
every possible pairing.
And so, you know,
they had a much more complicated
example here than what I had.
This is, you know,
straight off the blog.
You know, in Likon, they
had all these kind of
primary data stores like
Espresso, Baltimore,
Oracle, other various things,
and they would pull the
data into HDFS for do.
They had some type
of data warehouse.
They would have other tools
that would search over logs.
A lot of these type of Aalytics
things people would do.
A lot of the
secondary stores were
also more like customer facing
or more product oriented.
So, for example,
let's say that you
were building an application
for Piazza, right?
I do question answering.
You know, I kind of like ask
a question or have an answer.
Those things could be
rows. OLTP database like
M Sequel would make
a lot of sense.
But there's some use cases
like if I want to do
a text search and
find messages that might
answer my question,
that's a little
bit tricky, right?
It's not like an exact match.
You can imagine
building specialized
systems for doing text search.
And people do. And
so maybe I have
some kind of elastic search
or some other thing down here,
that's a production
oriented service.
And maybe whenever somebody
inserts a message into
the primary database,
I also want to add
that message to
my text search thing so people
can have other services
built on top of it.
Right? So we have all
these primary stores,
all these secondary stores
and lots and lots of work for
data engineers kind of to
handle every single
combination of these.
And so what that blog
proposes is that we
should have one centralized log,
you know, at the
core of our company,
at the core of all data, and
anything that's a primary
store that's producing data,
should send copies to that log,
and anything that's
a secondary store
should be pulling from that log.
And if you do that, then
instead of having it x times y,
then you'll have an x plus y,
which scales much better, right?
And of course, if you're
building something like aa,
you're very happy
then your product is
at the center of
everybody's company, right?
It's kind of the one place
where everything is.
But it also makes a lot
of sense, too, right?
If you have a very
complicated a organization
of your data across all
these different systems.
It makes sense to have one
place where you have a copy of
everything as a way to
kind of be a data broker,
be in between the primary
and the secondary stores.
Did people have any
questions about that idea?
Yeah, right here. Yeah.
What is the derivative stores.
So what I have imagined here is
that any kind of data,
these derivative stores.
It's not that they
have unique data
that's not in other systems.
It's just that maybe I copied
data out of other systems,
and I have a new copy, that's
a different format, right?
By derivative, what I
mean is that, you know,
let's say that let's say
that HDFS just died here,
and I lost all my data
for whatever reason.
I could set up a new HDFS and
rerun those ETL jobs.
I could repopulate it.
It's not my primary data.
It's really like, kind of
secondary or derivative data.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, it would be
an extra format.
Yeah. Yeah, other
questions people have.
You know, maybe I have
some other apps that
are sting marketing e
mails on here, right?
Lots of kind of
secondary purposes
for my data. All right.
So that big log in the center
is what Kafka can do, right?
So let's take a look
at how Kafka is built.
Just like with RPCs,
messages are one of these
key concepts that
we worry about,
and messages are organized
into what we call topics, right?
Some messages are about
the same subject, right?
So what I may imagine
is that I have
some kind of news organization.
Maybe the news organization has
lots of different apps that
they might build
around it, right?
It could actually be
quite complicated.
For example, maybe I have a
tornado warn app, dos, right?
And so we have all these
different messages that
are organized across all
these different topics.
And these topics live on
machines called brokers.
That's where they're stored.
And if you want to,
you can create new topics
relatively easily.
There's different
Python clients where
we use this one
called Taka Python.
And within there, you can create
a Kaka Amin client and you
can create new topics.
So, for example, here, I'm
creating a sports topic,
and then that's a place for
messages to live, right?
Where do these
messages come from?
They come from programs
called producers, right?
Maybe there's some sensor,
something that automatically
detects the tornado,
that it sends a message to
the weather topic about that.
So one of the things I want
to throw at is writing
code for producers, right?
I see, Okay, here
producer three,
is sending a message to sports.
Again, the code for
this is not terrible.
After I have that
package installed,
I can create a CCA
producer object,
and I just say dot send.
I say the topic, and then I have
some information about the
message that is being set.
And then that will end
up on some topic on
some producer or on
some broker somewhere.
On the other side,
we have consumers,
which are also programs
that you write.
And each consumer can
subscribe to different
topics, right?
So some of them,
like, you know, say,
Consumer three is getting
messages from all
three of these topics.
Consumer four is some
kind of application that
only cares about sport
related messages.
Right? So when I write
the code over here,
I can create this
CPA consumer object
that I say dot subscribe,
and I have a list of the topics
that I'm interested in, right?
So one of the ways people
describe these systems
is that they're
a pub sub or a published
subscribe model.
And so that's another
difference between GRPCs.
And the GRPC, it's like Ib
sending a message to you.
Here, it's kind of like the
producers and consumers
don't necessarily have to
know about each other, right?
They both decide
what topics they're
sending to and what topics
they're receiving from.
You can imagine more
complicated programs,
that might be combinations
of consumers and
producers, right?
Maybe I have maybe I have
a consumer that's like,
consuming all this data
from weather stations,
and then maybe it produces
predictions about
tomorrow's weather,
and it might write that
to another channel.
Alright, This is kind
of a big structure
that you really have to
be familiar with, right?
The producer broker consumer.
Those are the three big pieces
here that we're gonna
be talking a lot about.
So I'll just pause
there and see if people
already have any
questions. There here.
Consumer is the consumer that
That's a great question.
So when a consumer is
subscribe to a topic,
is it that the broker is
sitting or the
consumer is receiving?
The answer the
consumer is receiving
because the consumer is to
often have to process
that in some way,
and depending how many
compute resources you have,
right, it might take who
knows how long, right?
And so the consumer will try
to run as fast as it can.
And if the producer or if
the broker was just
sitting stuff out,
then maybe the consumer
will not be able
to keep up, right?
What kind of work a
consumer be doing?
Well, Oftentimes, these
messages are going
to be describing changes
to a primary data store.
And so the consumers to say,
Oh, there was this update
or change of the data,
and that consumer is
going to be updating,
you know, HDFS or data
warehouse or whatever.
That could take
some time, right?
So the consumers will kind of
go along at their own pace.
And the brokers are to keep
those messages there
because who knows
who will need it in the
future. Yeah, great question.
I saw another hand upper
around here somewhere.
That was a related question.
Other question so
far. Alright, cool.
So maybe this also helps
answer the question.
If you do the optional
reading for today,
they describe this polling loop,
and that's like the
most important loop
described in the chapter.
Here I have an example of
a pulling loop over here.
Consumers do pulling.
So here I have this
consumer three object,
and I say, Wild true.
So most consumers just keep
looping forever
because you know,
streams never add, right to
have an infinite source of data.
And what we'll do
is we'll say batch
equals consumer dot poll.
There's some arguments
that we can put there.
And whatever you call that poll,
I give you back this batch,
and this batch will contain
a bunch of messages.
And those messages are
organized by topic.
Right? I have a net loop.
I get a batch. And then
the batch has different
topics and messages,
and I can loop over each
message for each topic.
Right? So that
generally runs forever.
And one of the
interesting things
about Kafka that was different
is that early systems,
they were just worried about the
asic nature of it, right?
It would just be kind
of a broker would
be place you'd send a message,
and then when a consumer
consumed it would
be Guad, right?
But Kafka in addition
to trying to do that,
they're trying to handle
this Mi to Mei scenario.
And so Kafka does
the Asic stuff,
but they're also kind of a
longer term storage, right?
They might keep the
messages around for weeks,
or depending on
you can figure it
maybe maybe forever, right?
Because as we can see here,
if there's a message
about sports,
Consumer three and consumer
four are both
interested in that,
you can't delete
the message after
consumer three had it is there's
other applications
that might need it.
Yeah, question right here.
Message Yeah,
you're asking, what are
the messages deleted?
Like the key word
is like, there's
some needs to be some
kind of retention policy.
So when you were describe,
like, Oh, if I sat sometime,
The word I would use
for that is like,
Okay, that's a retention policy.
I'll retain messages for
two weeks or
something like that.
Absolutely, the person
who creates this sets up
this cluster will choose
a retention policy.
And you know, I could say,
like, two weeks or you know,
if it's like low volum but
I have a big hard drive,
maybe I say I want
to keep it forever.
You know, they have other kind
of things you can plug in,
where if it's like too
old, they'll kind of,
like, shove it off on HDFS.
So this is integrated
with HDFS too.
So sometimes they'll
keep messages forever,
sometimes they'll have a
retention policy that's shorter.
Yeah, question right
here. This exact example.
Is the reason that
consumer three
does not get a message
from politics?
I probably has already
seen that message before?
Yeah. Maybe Consumer three has
already got the message from
politics or maybe maybe
it can process three
messages at a time,
and maybe it'll grab it
in the next batch, right?
So they're trying to have
nice sized batches as well.
If the batch is too big, well,
it takes a lot of
time to process,
if it's too small,
there's all this extra
network overhead.
Yeah, Consumer three either has
seen that message or it
should see it at some point?
Yeah, great point.
Yeah, right here.
That's a great question. I
guess maybe in the question,
I maybe hear a couple
of observations.
What is that? There's lots
of things where we have to
worry about scalability
bottlenecks.
So you were talking
about the consumers
keep up and we're talking about
how we scale the consumers.
You were talking about
the brokers keep up,
we'll talk about how
we scale the brokers.
Right? If this thing
is literally the
center of our company,
and it's pulling all
data from all places,
this thing really
has to scale, right?
That's tricky for both
brokers and consumers.
Producers, I think is
the only case that's
easy because the producers
don't talk to each other.
They just generate
whatever they want,
whatever they want.
But yeah, absolutely, we're
going to have to worry
a lot about how to scale
brokers and consumers.
Yeah, good. Alright, ah,
lots of good questions
and good points today.
Alright. So we have
these messages,
and I want to talk about
what exactly is in them.
There's a few things. I mean,
but there's two important
things I want you to remember.
One is that they can have a key,
and the other is that
they can have a value.
And the value is really
what is the message.
Both of those are bytes.
The value is required,
and all has to be there,
and you can choose whether
or not you want to have
a key on your message.
And so I have some
examples here.
I could say produced
or not said.
I say what topic, and I
could just have a value,
or I could send
to that topic and
had both the value at a key.
Either either are reasonable
depending on what
you're trying to do.
What we're go to
see is just like
with Spark or other systems.
Sometimes we'll want to
bring related data together.
And the key is how we're
going to do that, right?
I I two messages
have the same key,
that are related to
each other, okay?
And so what we'll often see is
that that value we're sending.
I mean, it just
bites in general,
but it will often
be some kind of row
of data or dictionary of
data or something like that.
And what we'll often do is
the key will be one of the
entries inside of the value.
And so it'll be a
little bit duplicated.
We'll have that value with a
bunch of kind of sub values.
And one of those sub
values will be the key?
B that's how we're a group
related messages together.
I have some examples out here,
if I had like a
Python dictionary.
I could use JSI to
du it to a string,
and then I could use bites
with a UTF A and Tding.
So I could basically
take a Python dictionary
and turn it into a
value that's bites.
Down here, I'm using
protocol buffers,
right if I have a
protocol buffer message.
I could serialize
it to a string,
and then it's not a real string.
It's actually bytes. And
so what we can see is that
we've used protocol
buffers a lot with GRPC.
Here, we might use protocol
buffers with Kafka, no GRPC.
Who have any questions
about messages.
All right. Yeah, right here.
Something of value.
Oh, oh, how could be?
Like you're saying,
like, why could
the key be something
inside of values?
So let's say here, right?
In this case, I have
value is my dictionary
D. And so there are
probably a bunch of
different entries inside
of that dictionary.
And I could choose
one of the entries of
that dictionary to be my key,
right? And that would
help me know that.
Oh, all these different
dictionaries are
related to each other in some
way. Does that make sense?
Yeah, good question. Oh, right.
Cool. So back to the
scalability questions, right?
Some topics are be higher
volume than others.
Let's say I'm like an
e commerce company,
and I'm trying to do athletics.
I'm trying to see like, Oh,
people click on these pages,
and then maybe they buy
something or maybe they don't.
And so I have one topic,
which is about people clicking,
and there's lots of people
clicking on my website.
Sadly, I have a very
low volume stream,
which is related to purchases.
Okay. But regardless, I
have the technical problem
of kind of dealing with
this high volume topic,
which is people clicking, right?
So we do what we literally
always do in this situation,
which is, we partition
our data, right?
And so we as
the programmer, right,
when you get the topic,
you'll say, I want
this one to have
one partition or ten
partitions, whatever.
You decide that, and it's
fixed forever, pretty much.
All right. And so what I'll
do here is that we don't
have any purchases,
so we'll just have one
partition of purchases.
And for clicks, I'll
have three partitions.
I'll have Partition zero,
partition one, petition two.
And then, you know
I have some number
of brokers, and, you know,
each broker has some number
of topic partitions
on it, right?
Ideally, I have enough brokers
that can try to spread out
that work for my high
volume partition, right?
Now, each topic
partition behaves
kind of like an
array of messages,
and you can see
these indexes here.
Better I use the word index.
Im to use the word offset.
And that is because once
I have a message and it has
offset associated with it,
it will always have that offset.
It never changes.
Okay? So I have that.
Each producer using a stream
will work with all of
the partitions, right?
If I have a producer
to produce a message,
the producer has to
figure out which
topic partition to send it to.
Okay, so how do we
modify these partitions?
On the right hand side,
we can append things.
I can see on the first one,
I'm appending a message,
t at offset eight on the
click zero partition,
I'm deleting these
messages based
on some kind of
retention policy.
And when I do that, the offsets
of the other ones do
not change, right?
So when I first start
a new partition,
the first mesion will be at
partition will be
at offset zero.
After I delete some messages,
then the first message will be
a an offset that's
bigger than zero, right?
So I do that. There's some
things we'll never do.
We'll never change an
offset or an index.
We will never modify a message
after it's been readed.
Once it's there, it's
reded in stone forever.
I'll never delete a
message in the middle.
I delete from the left
hand side, right?
So I kind of have all these
kind of sliding arrays for
each of these topic
partitions that are
spread across
different machines.
That's the main
structure we have.
All right, so now, when
we write these messages,
we might just put a value or we
might have a value
and a key together.
If I only have a value,
then what the producer will
do is the producer knows
that there are
these three different
partitions for clicks,
and it will just round
robin between them.
That means that rotates will do
partition zero, one, two, zero.
One, two, I'll just keep
rotating between all of
the different ones,
if there's no value.
And that means that
there's no kind of
grouping on the messages
within a partition.
Sometimes I don't care.
There's no natural grouping.
If I have a key, then what
we'll do is we'll do
hash partitioning,
which is exactly the same
as Spar hash partitioning.
I'll take the hash and the key,
modify the partition count.
Here I have three
partitions of clicks.
So I will get zero water two,
and that will tell me
where it should go.
And what that means, if I have
two different messages
with the same key,
they're going to end up in
the same partition, right?
There's other things
you could do, like you
could plug in a
different policy there,
but that's what I'll just
assume that's a default.
That's what I'll
assume in general
for Kafka this semester.
All right. Any questions
about that grouping of data?
Yeah, right here.
Oh, that's a good question.
So are the messages sent by
the producer in a
consistent for bat?
Seriously, are they serialized
in the same way or
something like that?
Oh, oh, oh, that's
a good question.
C a producer sometimes
produce messages that have
keys and others that don't.
Yeah, that would be fight that
if there is a key that
it'll has partition it,
if it doesn't have a key,
that it'll round rob at it.
Yeah, that's totally fight.
Yep. Yeah, good question.
Oh. All right.
Cool. So when we're
reading this date,
if we're a consumer,
something we have to think
very carefully about is the
offset that we're reading it.
Because offset is re to tell us
what is your next message.
Alright, so let's
imagine now that we have
one consumer and it's
subscribed to both topics.
And it's only consumers,
so I go to have all of
these different partitions.
I'm sorry. I'm drawing
a simpler picture.
Let's just pretend
like we are going
to worry about
purchases for now.
Let's just worry about clicks.
And so the consumer
has already seen some
messages and some it has not.
And so these little
arrows up here refer to
the next message I should
it for each of these
partitions, right?
You know, for clicks two,
it's at position four,
so that means that there
is no message four yet.
There's nothing more to see on
that topic partition. I've
already read everything.
And so somewhere, and
we'll talk more
about where this is,
we have a state that kind
of looks like this, right?
We have an offset corresponding
to each of these partitions,
and that describes basically
the same information that
those arrows are showing you.
Okay? Now, the code
inside of the consumer looks
like this loop up
at the top, right?
It says dot pull.
And when you pull, you say
some number of milliseconds.
And the idea here is
that poll should return
to you within that.
So this is say, Poll should
be return within 1 second.
It might be faster, right?
So what Tropica is trying to
do is that it wants
to give me a lot
of messages at the
same time because
it's more efficient
to do bigger batches,
but it doesn't want to wait
so long that the data is state.
And so poll will return,
either when I have
enough messages
or when 1 second has passed.
After that returns, I have
different topics and messages.
And actually, this is a little
bit kind of strangely
named, right?
So the topic here is actually
the combination of a
topic and a partition.
And so I can loop
over each of those.
I can print off what the topic
partition is that I'm on,
and then I can loop
over all the messages
associated with that
topic partition.
And so what I want you
to think about here
is that in this state I'm in
right now, it's
not deterministic.
There are some outputs
that I might get,
and some that would
not be reasonable.
And so I'll just show you a
few different things that
this consumer might pret
in the situation, right?
So there's different things
that could be in the batches.
Maybe I get two messages
from Partition zero.
So I pret Partition
zero, then CD.
That's one thing
that could happen.
Maybe I get messages
from two different
partitions, right?
And so maybe I'll
put all those off.
I pret Partition one has FGHI,
Partition three has R. I can
just something like that.
And you see whenever I do that,
the arrow moves from
the light pak to
the dark pak and I can see
that the offsets change
depending on what I get.
Another thing I could
have got it, right?
Is that maybe I just
did one message
off of Partition one, right?
It would just advance
that that there, right?
So there's some things
that it'll never do.
It'll never, like, skip over
a message or droll backwards
or anything like that.
It's strike consecutive on
partition partition by basis,
but that still means there's
a lot of different things that I
might get when I asked
for a batch of messages.
Okay? All right. Any
questions about that?
Kind of guarantees we
get. Yeah, right here.
Offsets maintained per
consumer per partition.
Yeah, our offsets maintained
per consumer or per partition.
What would you save
that question?
There's going to be
more dots to it.
You have to talk
about this thing
called a consumer group.
And so the answer will
involve talking about
consumer groups.
But yeah, you're thinking
about the right way.
Yeah, right here.
Oh, you're saying,
You're saying could the
offset numbers overflow?
I'm not sure how
they handle that.
Is say they just have like,
big enough numbers that it will
just never
realistically overflow.
So I think that's fine. I mean,
you could have a
consumer that gets
farther and farther
behind, right?
And then you would have to
figure out how to scale
up your consumers.
But I'm not aware
of the offsets being a
problem. Yeah right.
What of Right. Uh huh.
What if it offset Da
of storage reasons,
then a consumer could come
along that data just
is not there, right?
And so you probably want
to have some kind of
very generous policy like weeks
or months that you
keep the data,
or you could say I want
to keep it forever.
Because, yeah, if a consumer
is down for too long,
and it rows pass by
retention policy.
Yeah, I could lose data.
Yeah. But hopefully
somebody would not just leave
it broken for two weeks, right?
It would require data engineers
to keep an eye on the system,
right I just row
and run by itself.
Yeah. Alright, Yeah, lots of
good questions. All right.
So what I want you to think
about is a concept you might
have run across at the math,
of course, and the concept
is called ordering, right?
Some things in life are what
we call totally ordered.
For example, integers
are totally ordered.
If you give me an integer
x and an integer y,
it doesn't matter what they are.
One of these things
will be true,
either x is less than
y or y is greater
than are equal to x.
Lots of things in life
are totally ordered.
There are also some
things that are
partially ordered. Like Tom.
So it Comets, if you branch
out and merge back together,
it really looks like this
directed acyclic graph.
And sometimes I could look
at two commits and say,
this one happened
before that one,
for example, you know,
A happened before
B or A happened
before C or D happened
before E. Those are
all things I can say.
It's partially ordered. Other
times I cannot compare.
I cannot say between B and C,
which one happened maybe
there's some types, but
I don't care, right?
If I have B and C, that
means there's two different
programmers that were
independently working
on something and
improving it separately, right?
I don't care what type of day
they were working, right,
neither one of these
commits is necessarily
the newer version
of the code, right?
There are some commits I can
compare, and some I cannot.
And KAFKA messages are
going to be partially
ordered, right?
It's a partially ordered system.
And what that means is that
the producers are creating
messages in some order.
But the guarantees I have about
the order which
they'll be consumed
are somewhat limited, right?
And so here's how
it works. Right?
If you are a producer
and you're sending
multiple messages to the
same key of the same topic,
then they end up in that same
topic partition together,
and we enforce ordering
on the granularity of
topic partitions, right?
So if it's the same
topic and same key,
then things will come out in
the same order that
they go ad, right?
So let me just give
you an example.
So let's say that A
and B are messages,
and they have the
same topic and K,
and B was produced
after A, right?
So first A and the B,
The technical word
we'll use as happened
after, right?
That's often used in
like a literature here.
So we'll say that B happened
after A because it's
the same topic in
G. And that means
that A and B will be in the
same partition of the topic.
Assuming we don't change
the partition couch,
which is a big nota with Kaka.
You're never supposed
to change that.
And then because of that,
the offsets will determine
ordering, right?
And so anybody that's
consuming both of
these is going to consume
A before they consume B.
Those are the guarantees we get.
We don't get any
guarantees beside that.
And so what we can see
here is that to have
any kind of guarantee,
it all comes down
to the key, right?
I have to choose that key very
carefully if I want related
data to be in the same place.
I have to choose that key very
carefully if I care about
the order in which messages
get processed, right?
But another piece of advice is
that if I change the
partition count,
well, hash partitioning
is totally broken,
like we've seen
before with Casandra.
That's why Cassandra went
off a consistent Hashig.
They don't do anything
so clever here, right?
So the advice of Kata is
never change your
partition count,
which is not great because you
can't perfectly anticipate it,
so it's better to
overestimate rather
than understimate
the partition count.
Yeah, question right here.
Broker, you're saying,
like, if all our
brokers are empty,
is already probably change the
partition account, I mean,
given that they hang on to
messages for a long time,
maybe indefinitely, W
you say it's empty,
just there's never ever
been a message set yet?
You're say all the consumers
have consumed all the messages.
Could you change the
partition count?
Not necessarily, because I
guess what we're going to see is
that we want all
the related data
to go to the same consumer.
And if you change
the partition count,
that won't happen
even if somebody
has handled keys correctly.
Yeah. Lots of things can,
you're writing all the code.
So maybe you could
write some code
to handle some tricky cases.
But in general, if
you change that,
the nice things Kafka
does for you it won't
do that for you.
So then you have to
figure out how to solve
some problems on
yourself instead
of letting Kafka solve it.
Yeah, that's a good
question, though.
And again, I just
want to stress,
if you don't specify any keys,
then there's no guarantee
on what order the
message will come out.
They can draw in what order,
they come out in a
different order.
Maybe you care, maybe you don't,
depending on the application.
Oh, right. So these offsets
are going to be very important.
In general, we just go
forward with our offsets.
That's the normal
behavior, right?
Sometimes, though,
we want to go back,
we want to re read a message.
Let me think of an example.
These messages are probably
describing changes to
the data that I'm supposed
to perform in some database.
If I try to update
that database,
the database is doubt or
something like that,
it might fail.
And so what that
means, I want to go
back later and retry that.
I want to reprocess
those messages.
I can do that with
a SC operation.
SC means that instead
of forward like
normal, go backwards.
So I could choose an offset.
For a topic partition,
I could seek to it.
And then at that case,
that arrow would
go backwards instead of forward.
I see, that's something
that we might have to
do if there are
failures in the syst.
Like, we'll see the prob
project. Yeah, question here.
Turn off offset.
It would bring the
offset back to sex.
So the next message you
would get would be
an offset sex from
that partition. All right.
Cool. Now, remember
when we first started,
we said that one of
the unique things
about COPPA is that
there could be
different applications that are
processed the same message.
That's what makes it a
published subscribe model.
So the way we do
that is we create
these different things
called Tsumer groups.
And within each consumer group,
we're going to see all the
messages that I subscribed to.
And so when I start
thinking about the state,
it's more complicated now.
I almost imagine you know,
there's not like a table in
one place that looks like this,
but that's what I imagine when
I think about the offsets.
I have every partition,
and I have all the groups,
so G one and G two.
And for every combination
of a topic partition to a group,
I have an offset,
which is, you know,
where do I read next
for that group?
Right here, I have two groups,
so I have those two
sets of offsets, right?
So let me just show it
at a simple case
here at the bottom.
I'll look at this.
Both groups are at offset
three, which is putting to our
So when the message R
goes to consumer two,
then I update that
offset to four,
but the consumer group one
still is at offset three,
so it can also get R, right?
So we have to be a
good topic programmer,
you have to be thinking
about offsets all the time.
Ofsets are very important to
everything that's happening.
You can see how I
did this up here,
but I created a sum up here.
I just said group
ID equals G one.
You can just put whatever you
want and if it's
like a new string,
we all of a sudden,
you're a new group
by yourself, right?
So it's pretty easy to create
a consumer in a specific group.
If I had a bunch of
different applications
that are all fe consumers,
I know we would all decide.
They each have a
different string
to identify themselves. Alright.
Let's figure out how we
actually aside partitions.
And when we're doing this, it's
because we have more than
one consumer in a group.
If I just have one consumer
in a group, Is all of them.
What if I have
multiple consumers.
So here I may I
imagine that consumer
one is in its own group,
and consumer group two has
two consumers two and three.
So I have the same
information as before.
Each group has its own
offset that didn't change.
But now I have to have
additional state.
I have to remember for
each for each partition.
At each group.
I have to know which consumer
specifically is going
to be in charge of it,
right? Why do we even
want to do this?
Because maybe one
consumer cannot
keep up with the high
volume of traffic.
We want to share it across
multiple computers, right?
So I have over here.
Of course, group one
only has one consumer.
So that whole column
is consumer one.
Group two is split across
consumer two and consumer three,
both of which are there.
So I can manually assign
this. Like I end up above.
I just say out a side, and I say
which ones I want
it to be logged to.
I could also ask Kafka to
automatically do this for me.
Because I could just say, Oh,
here's a bunch of
consumers of this group,
you figure out Kafka,
who should do which ones.
Right? I could do that.
They just show up.
In this case, I guess I have
consumer two and three.
They just showed
up, and they got
split like this down here.
The challenges is
what happens when
a new consumer
comes along, right?
Consumer four table log,
and it's part of group two,
but the existing
consumers in group
two are already account for
all of the partitions, right?
So how do we give
consumer for some work?
We have to be very careful about
this because we're taking work
away from the other ones.
And what we never
want to happen is
have two different consumers in
the same group process
the same message is,
what are these messages?
These messages say something
like A row was inserted
in the original system.
And what are these
consumers doing?
They're probably
inserting a row in
some other system like
a data warehouse.
If I process the same message
twice in the same group,
then I'll probably end
up with duplicate rows.
I don't want that, right?
So I have to think about,
I have this consumer four.
How could I reassign some of
the partitions in
group two, right?
And the key here is that
there are certain points in
time where it's good to
steal our partition.
What is that if the
consumer exited?
If the consumer says that close,
I'm show you out of a schade
or something, then we're like,
great, I know I can
give that partition to
somebody else. What
is another good time?
When you call that pull,
that's a fantastic t you
basically you say pull,
process a batch, p,
process a patch.
If you're calling
pull right now,
that means you're
between patches.
Which means it's a great time
to take away some of your work.
You can say, Hey,
give me a batch.
I'll be like, here it
is, and by the way,
you don't have the same
partitions you used to.
So you want to do that
at a key time, right?
So at this point in time, is
when we would hand it
off to consumer f,
and then we can scale this.
If the consumers are
following behind,
and we have a bunch
of partitions on
our topic, no problem.
We'll just start some new
we'll start some new
consumers of the same group.
Let Povka give them some work,
and hopefully together, they
can catch up. All right.
I want to talk a
little bit about
how Kafka stores
all these messages.
They store the messages,
is something called
a segment file.
And so if I look at a
topic partition, right,
I have two on this machine,
I break it up across these
different segment files.
Once a segment file is
written, it's finalized.
It might be deleted,
but it's never changed.
I will have one segment file
for each topic partition,
which is special.
It's active one, as there
are new messages, it's
appended to that.
These segment files are
just the normal file system
like EXT four or whatever,
running on top of, like,
a hard drive or SSD.
Alright. There you see.
I have a new message. It gets
appended to the segment file.
Now, eventually, the segment
files might be
getting kind of big,
and so I might do a rollover.
Rollover means that I ftalize
that file and I start
writing to a new rollover is
something that happens in
logging systems in general,
not just KAPCA, so it's going
to have that terminology.
Another thing that
we might do is we
might delete old data.
When we do that, we always start
from the smallest offset first,
and we never partially delete.
It's like, we delete that whole
segment file or we don't.
But eventually,
we might clean up
depending on the
policies, right?
So those are the
things we worry about.
Rollover and deletion.
Both of these have
configurable policies.
So for rollover, I could say,
both, like, how big
can the active segment
be and how old can it be?
Right? I could do that.
And then for retention.
I guess I either delete
it or I retate it.
So people often say, I
have a retention policy.
For that, I could say, how
old is that file allowed to be?
And how big is the tire
log allowed to be, right?
I could set one
or both of those.
And one thing I want
to talk about is
that when I talk about
how old the segment is,
that's a little
bit tricky because
there's multiple messages in it,
and those messages might
have different times staaps.
And so they don't want
to delete it too soon.
So if I say how big is a segment
or how old is a segment,
the answer is, however old
the newest message is.
So you have to be a little bit
careful because if I say, Hey,
delete it after seven days,
There might be messages in there
that are older than seven days.
If you have legal
reasons for delete after
a certain reason after
a certain time period, then
that might not help you.
Right? If you're in Europe,
right, there's this right
to be forgotten within
some time frame,
and that might not
help you there.
Alright, so I want to
wrap up and do a top hat,
and then we'll come back next
time and do more
examples, right?
So my question is
about consumer groups.
And after this top hat is done,
feel free to go, and we'll
just come back next time.
About 30 seconds left.
Alright, so people are mostly
say two which is correct, right?
We have two consumer groups,
so we have two
distinct applications.
Each group needs to
get the message.
But within the consumer group,
the idea is not to
have redundancy,
the idea is that we split up
the work within the group.
So we wouldn't want each
of them to have their own.
Alright, I have a fantastic.
Able will come back Friday
and do some programing demos.