So we have a lot
of fun stuff ahead
of us in the semester.
We've been learning about
Docker Containers so far,
and now we're going to be
learning about networking,
which will set us
up for next week.
Next week, I want to learn
about Docker Compose.
Docker Compose is to have
a way that we can de fide
a few containers that we want to
start all together that
interact with each other.
So compose de fight how we have
these little clusters
of conttors.
And then when we
have programs running in
different containors,
we want them to be able to
talk with each other, right?
That's why we're learning
about networking today.
How can we communicate
over this Docker network?
And in particular
where be learning
something called RPC on Monday.
That stands for remote
procedure call.
A procedure call is
just a function call.
And you all have called lots
of functions in your life.
You should be very
familiar with that.
But there's may be a difference.
Normally, when you're
calling a function,
that function runs in
the same process or program
where you called it.
What we're re do now
is that when we learn
RPC is that we can trall
a function in one
process and one conttor,
and that function can run in
a separate process
and a separate tator,
and RPC is what is
really unable to do it.
And if we can trall flexions
acros different tators,
well, then we can unlock
a lot of capabilities.
But first, we just need to get
some networking basics down
before any of that
will make sense.
And that's the goal today.
I also just want to
wrap up the example
from last side that we were
doing with Docker files.
So I may come over here.
And this was the Docker file
that we were working
on last time.
When you build a Docker file,
you get a new image, and
you usually don't build a
new image from stretch.
You usually start with
an existing image.
And in this case, the existing
image was but 224.10.
So we start with a
directive called
F Then usually there's a bunch
of run statements in here,
and when we build the image,
each of those run what?
That stuff is installed.
And then if we create a
container later for that image,
we don't have to do
it again, and we'll
already have all these
things installed.
So I just want to review
a few things here.
One is that when I did
app to get install,
I had to say Y.
Can anybody rebind
me why I had to
do dash Y? Yeah, right here.
Excellent. It's
start to prompt me
to say, do you really
want to install it?
And if we're interactive,
that'd be fine, but
it's not interactive.
So I need to tell it to
say, Hey, if you ask B 80,
the as ser is, yes, get it
installed one way or another.
Another thing that was
a little bit strange is
that I used and here,
which is kind of different
than the previous a
percent we've seen?
This lets us run one
command after another.
First, we do Atget update,
and then we do this one.
I got a little bit
long, so I split it
across lines with
this back slash.
But ultimately, I tried to shove
two different commands
on the same run line.
Can anybody remember why
I'd want to do that
instead of having
two separate run lines?
Yeah, right here.
Yeah, so because of cashing,
that's the correct
answer, right?
So, Doctor, when it
builds something,
is trying to try to avoid any
run steps that it's done before.
It'll kind of cash or remember
the output from them.
And that cashing
happens on a run
by run line basis, right?
So it might have done
like three run lines,
and then it might have
to build the rest.
And What I never
wanted to happen is I never
wanted to do an install,
unless it's also doing
an update, right?
Because update helps it find
all the software that's
available for me to install,
and install actually does it.
So unless I'm doing those
pretty close to each other,
then it might have
an incorrect view
of what software
is available for you to install,
and then the install will fail.
So since that thing happens
on a run by run basis,
if this was a separate
run line than this,
then it might just do
an install without
doing a recent update.
Yeah. Question here.
Is there a way to go run that
because line every time.
Yeah, I mean, is there
a way around it?
And the way is you'll
see trolled like this all
the time where people
have kind of a big
long line with
a bunch of commands
on the same line.
That is the way around it.
Yep. Yeah, thanks for asking.
If somebody has a better
shortcut they see,
I mean, that'd be cool,
but I've seen this in a lot of
different docker file, so
I'm guessing there's not.
Yeah, other questions
people have so far.
All right, so I do all of that.
And then the other
weird thing I had to
do is I had to say this
brake system packages.
Canby remind me what that does?
Yeah, right over here.
Yeah, so
PIP doesn't complain to me if I
try to install it system wide.
And kind of the rationale
for that is Python has
these virtual environments
where you can have
different versions of packages
in different environments.
And these different programs
need different versions,
and their kind of idea is
that every program should
be its own virtual environment
that has exactly what its needs.
And you should never install
kind of something
system wide anymore.
In some sense, like a Docker
container is a
virtual environment.
I know I'm only going to
have one program in it.
So in this case, I know that
PIP is being a little
bit too paranoid.
It's okay to install
a system wide,
so I just say that to say,
Hey, I know what I'm doing.
I actually do it. Okay, so
we have the fro,
we have the run.
These will happen when I build.
What I can also do is I
can set a command that
will run by default when I
create a new container, right?
So this is for every
time I build an image.
This is every time I create
a container from that image.
So I'm just going to
say for now echo hello.
And then I'm going
to build this again.
And that was pretty fast,
actually, because it was
caching it from last time,
and I can do a Docker run demo,
and it's going to
say echo hello.
And I see that right there.
If I want to, I can override
that default behavior,
and I can say something
like echo by.
You notice that it's
suggesting that
I have a slightly
different format for it.
So I think that format is fine,
but another common thing that
you can do that will also
make that warning go away,
is I can put in a JSO list
of all the arguments.
And so the first one is
the actual program name,
and then I could have any
other arguments after that.
If I do that, it'll
do the same thing,
but it just doesn't tm play out.
Maybe there's some part
scenario where it's ambiguous,
who knows, but that's what
they kind of recommend doing.
So you might see that sometimes.
What I'd like to do
now is I'd like to get
a Python program actually
running in here,
and that's going to
be kind of similar
to what you're doing
for your project.
We installed We installed
Pandas in here.
So let's try having
a little Python program
that uses Pandas.
So I'm going to call that
Python program test so Pi.
I'm going to import
Pandas as PD.
I'm going to create
a Pandas series
with some numbers in it, one,
two, three, and I'm
just trying to print
off the sum of those
three numbers, right?
So it should be six, right?
Have a simple Python program.
Let me try running it.
And it's not try to work
here because I do not
have Pandas installed
on my virtual machine.
It is, however, installed
inside of inside of my image.
So I'm going to do is I'm
going to come back here.
And I am going to
edit my Docker file.
And I'm going to
say up here, copy,
and I can copy something from
my virtual machine
into the container.
I'm going to copy testo Pi
from the current tratory,
and I'm going to put
it to test doop Pi,
kind of the root of
my Docker image. I'm
going to do that.
This would be fine,
but it would actually
be kind of slow to rebuild it.
Does anybody have any
idea as to how I can make
this docker image rebuild
faster? Yeah, go ahead.
C he copy would change a
copy to run make it faster,
interest idea, but no, it
would not. Other thoughts.
So yeah, right over here.
I could try to combine
the two run statements.
No, I don't think
that would really
make it faster either.
The reason, normally,
installing Pandas takes
a long time, right?
And the reason I've
been able to build
so quickly is that it
remembered that build.
Now, Docker is not
super smart, right?
It's kind of hard to tell
if I have this file here,
will that change the behavior
of App to get installed?
Probably not, but how can
you really prove that?
Right? So just the fact that
I added this copy before,
it's like, Well, I better
do an app install,
again, just to be safe.
I better do a pip
install just to be safe.
And so the order of
these really matters.
I'm going to put this
down here at the end.
And in that way, it still cash.
It already has a version where
it's app installed these,
and then on top of that,
it can do something else.
So this will be relatively fast.
I'm going to build that.
And then I have this there.
Maybe the other thing
I should do is I
should go back to
my Docker file.
And now I would like
to say Python three.
Slash test so Pi. All right?
And then I can do
a Python run demo.
Actually, I need to
build it again, don't I?
And then a Docker run demo.
And then it should start
the Python Interpreter
in Port Pandas.
Add those numbers, print it
out. Yeah, question right here.
Will it cache what? Yeah, well,
do any kind of caching here.
So, not in the sense that it
does like the other caching.
So every time I run
a new container,
it will run that
line again, right?
So if I run this again,
then it will re execute Python.
So if, for example,
testo Pi takes a
long time to run,
then every container I run
will take a long time to run,
because the CMD, that's
what it's running every
time I create a new
container, right?
That makes sense? Yeah,
Yeah, right here.
Line test PY shows
up twice in a copy.
Does test PY show
up twice on my Oh,
yeah, normally, when we copy,
we do like copy from
source to destination.
And in this case,
just the format
here is the source is
on my virtual machine.
So it's copying from test
on my virtual machine
to this test inside
of the container.
In some sense, it's more
like an SCP, right?
SCP is kind of across machines.
This is from my virtual
machine to my docker image.
Following. In this case,
it really depends.
So here I have an absolute
path to that file.
And so it depends on what
the current working
directory is.
If the current working directory
is the root directory,
then we don't need this.
I actually think
it is by default.
There's other directives
where you could change it.
So I didn't remember what the
default working directory is,
so I just did an absolute path,
but it would probably
work without.
Yeah, other questions
people have. All right.
Fantastic. So you're going
to do something like that.
I mean, for you, you
all are writing a
little shell strip.
I'll be like a dot SH file.
I think there's going
to be like a WG,
like an Zip, maybe some catting,
grabbing, word count,
all that stuff.
To answer a little question,
but you will have a little
shell strip that's bundled
up inside of your docker image
for your P one homework.
Alright. Fantastic.
So let's head over
here and learn a little
bit about networking.
So I have a few goals for you.
You know, we have to be able to
send packets or messages kind of
across different machines or
maybe different processes
on different machines.
And just like if I send
a letter in the mail,
I have to put like
an address on it to
make sure it ends up
in the right place.
And so we have to think
about what the equivalent is
when we're kind of sending
messages on the Internet.
And so there's a bunch of kind
of addresses that we're
going to talk about.
We're going to talk
about M addresses,
IP addresses, port
numbers, all those things,
if we understand them, will
help us figure out how
to get a message from
point A to point B.
You know, your virtual
machine or most machines,
there's going to be multiple
IP addresses you could use.
And when you are
starting a server,
you have to bind to one of them.
And so I want you to figure
out how to bind that and
also think about
what that means in
the context of something
called a NAT, right?
So a NAT might be forwarding
from one IP address to another.
And so kind of the
big goal here,
right is that if I have
a server somewhere,
And then I want to
talk to that server.
Oftentimes that just doesn't
work on your first try,
and you have to troubleshoot
it a little bit.
You have to figure
out why can I not get
established communication
from this client
over here with that
server over there.
And so you really have
to kind of understand
how this binding works and how
NATs work to get all
of that working.
Another thing that
happens when you're
troubleshooting is you like
try to start a server,
and it's trying to use a
port number, and it's like,
Well, there's already a process
using that port number.
So you have to be able to figure
out which process is
using a port number,
and then you probably will kill
all the process so
you can run yours.
And then finally, we learned
about different
transport methods.
TCP is the main one
we'll use this semester,
and then there's
another one UTP.
And they kind of have
different trade offs in terms
of reliability and performance.
And so you need to think, like,
what is the best use case
for your particular application.
Alright, so those are the goals.
Let's learn about networks,
and we'll start
with the most basic
networking hardware
which is a NIC,
a network interface controller,
maybe network interface card.
Here's one right
here. I could imagine
plugging this into a
card on my motherboard.
Maybe I might have a NIC
actually built into the
motherboard itself.
And different NICs will
support different
communication mediums.
Maybe I guess this one right.
I can say I can plug
an either net table
in there if I wanted
a wired network.
Maybe other ones might have
an antenna built into it,
and that would be
useful if I want
to be like a wireless
Wi Fi network.
And anyway, so we have
to have these necks if
we want to connect our
computer to other computers.
And each of these necks has
a unique address called a
MAC address, MAC address.
And a MAC address
is 48 bits long.
So some combination of zeros and
ones identifies the neck.
That turns out to be 28 trillion
possible addresses
that it could have.
And the guarantee we
have is that every neck
in the world should have a
unique mac address, right?
We shouldn't have the same
mac address showing up
multiple times in
different places,
right? How do we guarantee that?
Well, they break it up into
a prefix and a suffix,
and so then maybe
like this prefix
is for a particular
manufacturer.
I don't know, maybe it's like
Apple or some other
organization.
And so they have that prefix.
All of their devices
will have that prefix.
And then it's their
duty, every one they
make should have a
dif suffix there.
More recently, there
are some devices,
and some NICs that can actually
change their mac
address dynamically,
right, especially
like in your phone.
If I have my phone and I walk
into like a grocery store,
there's like a
wireless connection
there and they can read,
like, what is the mac
address on my phone.
And so they could
maybe tell if I
come to the grocery store
and I come again later,
maybe I know who I am, but
they could certainly identify,
like the same person was
there before. Who knows?
Maybe by the time of the
checkout and Temmy and leaving,
they can maybe figure out, what
the person with that mac address
bought and I don't know.
Maybe I don't want to be tracked
in that way. Yeah,
question right here.
So do all the manufacturers
agree to make them distinct?
Basically, I don't know
that's like I don't know,
like the governance,
how that works,
or if you're like a drolroge,
and just like, choose one
to start making stuff,
if anything bad happens to you.
But, yeah, that's the
intention that they
all have a unique
prefix and yeah,
I don't know the
governance behind it.
Yeah, but that's the
goal. Yep. And so
sometimes they'll be randomized,
so still a lot.
So hopefully we you
know, have enough.
Cool. If you're on Linux,
there's a tool called IP.
And just like the Docker command
has a bunch of subcommands.
The IP command has a
bunch of subcommands,
one of which is address.
And so if I draw you could
draw your virtual machine,
you can say IP address,
and it would list all the
NICs that you have, right?
And in this case, I have two
attached to that
virtual machine.
And I'll look at the
second one for now.
It has a name ENS four.
That's probably for
either net network,
and then I don't know.
Maybe you can imagine
there's different
virtual slots that might plug
in to They have
some naming scheme
that will automatically
generate that for you.
And then I can actually
see down here,
this is the MAC address
for that particular Nick.
And if I had a few attached,
right, then they would
probably all have, you know,
start with 42 something
because they're
all something that
Google is allocating for
me. So, I assume they had.
This is a 42 or how many
bits did I say it was?
It was a Yeah, 48 bit number.
This is a 48 bit number,
but it's actually
represented as hexadecimal.
That's why we aren't seeing
those zeros and ones.
This one up here
is what we would
call a virtual network
interface card.
It's called the loopback device.
There's no physical hardware
corresponding to it.
But it still looks
like that, and it
might look like it
has a MAC address.
And this loopback device,
what you can imagine is
that there's a network with
one computer on it and
that computer is your
computer, right?
And so some people
might use that
if you're trying to
develop like a web server,
you don't want people visit
your web server from wherever,
you just want to do
development on it.
You might start up a
web server and using
this loopback device
for that development.
There's no reason
a machine can have
a bunch of NICs
associated with it.
So when you're creating
your virtual machine,
you could actually go in
and network interfaces,
you could add more than
one, and then in this case,
I'd have one machine
with different NICs.
I could do interesting
things like
maybe there's
different networks,
and my one machine could maybe
be like on different networks
with maybe different resources
available on those networks.
Here's what it
looks like after I
configure that in
the Google Cloud,
and I came in and
I ran IP address.
I can see that I have
these two different,
ENS four NS five,
I have these two different NICs.
They have two different
MAC addresses.
Like I said, they
start with the same
prefix as you can see.
S. All right.
So a lot about NIC.
How do we actually use that to
get computers talking
to each other?
We have to connect them somehow.
And so one option
is that I could
directly connect a NIC on
one computer to another.
That's not a super
common scenario,
but it's definitely possible.
And then when they're sending
communications to each other,
they would use that
MAC address as kind
of an address when they're
sending data over that one wire.
More often is that we
would have something
called a switch,
and a switch might have
a bunch of different places
I could plug cables into it?
I could connect a lot of
different computers to it.
And the idea of the
switch is that if
Node A is trying
to talk to Node C,
Node A would send a message,
or we might call it a frame with
the mac address of
C to that switch,
and then the switch knows
where the machine with
that mac address is,
and then it would send it to
the appropriate
machine over there.
And so I'll generally
draw networks in kind
of a picture like this,
and I'll often refer to
either computers or
switches as nodes, right?
Because it's really like a graph
with a bunch of nodes on it.
There's nodes, there's edges,
sometimes a node as a computer,
sometimes a note as a switch.
All right. So I
have this network.
What really defines
a single network?
One thing that defines
it is that it's going to
be all the same
communication medium.
It's all going to be wireless,
it's all going to be either
net. It's all the same thing.
And all these different devices
can communicate
with each other by
sending frames to a specific
MAC address, right?
So I have a single
network there where
all these computers
can communicate.
Any questions about that so far?
Yeah, right over here.
Yeah, absolutely.
So nodes have multiple
network interface cards.
They absolutely can.
And so they could maybe
have those multiple
network interface cards.
They might be connected
to the same network.
I could have one that
is maybe connected to
an either network network and
a Wi Fi network
at the same time.
I could have a
computer that maybe
acts as a kind of forwarding.
They could try to take on a
role of forwarding things.
I mean, really, the switch,
has a bunch of places I
could plug in tables.
So a switch also you won't
really call it neck,
but would have a bunch
of physical ports where
I could plug in
different tables.
Absolutely. You could be
on a bunch of them. Yeah.
Yep. Yeah. So the MAC addresses,
associate with the
network interface card.
So actually, kind of
going back, right?
Here I have two necks,
and they each have their own.
This is just one
computer, right?
But those two necks have
different MAC addresses.
Yeah, great question.
All right. Cool.
So I have that
network. Of course,
I can have multiple
networks, right?
I have another
network over here.
Maybe this computer
has two NICs,
and maybe each one
is attached to
a to a different network.
I mean, you can
imagine different
interesting scenarios for that.
Maybe there's on this network,
it's more private, maybe
I have a database server.
Maybe I don't want random people
trying to communicate
with my database server,
but maybe I have a
web server on Node A,
and I want that a lot of
computers people communicate
with my web server,
and then it will decide
what data to pass on
from that database.
Often have more and less secure
networks or more locked down.
So Node A, I guess,
can send messages to computers
and either network based
on the MAC address,
Even if Node C somehow knew
the MAC address of
node D over there,
it would not be able to send
a message it's on a
different network.
I cannot use that MAC
address to communicate.
Okay. So we're already
talking about two networks.
It's time we talk about what
happens when we have a
bunch of networks together.
We might have a
corporate Internet.
You know, if you have
lots of networks,
trying to across
different organizations,
maybe we would call it on
Internet or the Internet.
And so we're going to talk
about that situation.
And so here I've drawn a
bunch of different networks,
maybe they have different media.
And I have a new kind of
node in here called
a router, right?
So the switch was sitting
within individual network.
The router is sitting
in between networks,
and it's able to
get communication
across across these
different networks.
So for example, let's
say that node A up here
wants to send a message
to node B way over there.
Right? Obviously, it
cannot do it with
a mac address because it doesn't
even know the mac address of B,
and MC addresses only
work on a single network.
But what we could
do is we could send
a message that could go
to this node over here,
and then maybe it passes
through a network,
maybe some switches, maybe
another router over here.
And eventually, we could get
the communication to where
we want it to go, right?
And so the challenge
here is that if I'm trying
to send out this message,
and let's say the
message gets from
no to A to the router,
the router needs to know
where to send it next, right?
And the router is
actually sitting
on a few different networks.
How does it know
which way to send it?
Right?
We have to have some kind of
routing table where you can
look at a message and kind
of look it up and say, Oh,
it should go this way, or
it should go that way and
somehow get it to its
final destination.
Now, you can imagine
in theory that
that routing table
could know about
every single mac
address in the world,
and it could know
where basically
everybody is located any time
and it could forward in
the right direction.
That'd be really hard
to keep up to date.
And the table the routing
table would be too big.
It's not practical
for every router to
know everything about
everybody, right?
And so when we're
sending these packets,
and I should have
introduced this term.
A packet is some sequence
of bytes we're sending
with some metadata,
maybe, like, where we're
trying to send it to.
We're trying to
send these packets.
We're going to need
a better way to
address nodes instead
of just MAC addresses.
And that leads us
to IP addresses.
So IP addresses are part
of the Internet protocol.
And that's where we
get the acronym IP.
You have all used IP
addresses to some extent.
Here's an example
of an IP address
IP with these four
parts right here.
There's four bytes
in an IP address,
and they kind of spelled
out with those four parts.
The four bytes or 32 beds.
That kind of works out to having
about 4 billion different
possible IP addresses.
I really not quite
enough, is it?
Right? There's more than 4
billion people in the world.
And me as an individual.
I mean, I guess I
have my laptop here,
I have my tablet here,
I have my phone,
maybe I have a smart thermostat,
smart toaster, maybe
I have a smart watch.
I could imagine lots
of different devices
that need to be online.
And that might be
using up IP addresses.
So 4 billion clearly
is not enough.
There is a newer addressing
scheme called IPV six,
that's replacing
what I'm describing.
I've been describing IPV four,
and that one has, you know,
the AddresR four times longer,
and basically, it's like
impossible that humanity,
whatever, have enough devices
to exceed the IPV six.
It's just not possible, right?
But if I'm using that,
then really kind
of all the routers
in the system need
to support it,
and we don't really have
universal support for it.
And so it really, you know,
it's not what we're using.
Usually, we're still
using IPV four,
even though it's this
limited resource.
We're a talk a little
bit about how we kind of
deal with that scarcity problem.
Okay, so we have
these IP addresses,
and y are these better
than MAC addresses?
Well, we split it
up like before,
where there's a prefix and
a suffix with the MAC addresses,
the prefix was a manufacturer.
But now for an IP address,
the prefix is going to
be a network number.
Each of these networks has a
number associated with it.
And so then all of
the computers on
the same network should have
an IP address starting
with that prefix.
And so when this
router over here gets
a message coming from A
that's supposed to go to B,
it's going to look at the
prefix of that IP address,
and it's going to be I
don't know exactly
where this computer is,
but I know it's somewhere
over in network three,
and to know that to
get to network three,
forwarding through network
six is the way to go, right?
So now, instead of our
forwarding tables,
having entries for like
every device in the world,
they can have an entry for
every network in the world,
and that's kind of a little
bit more manageable and
we can figure out
which way to send it.
So do people have any questions
about this routing
problem? Yeah, right here.
So different IP address
complication my laptop
one IP address here.
Yeah, absolutely.
Could the device have
a different IP address
in different places?
Yeah, it could even
have different IP addresses
at the same time.
If you have multiple
necks, so each neck
can have its own IP address.
And then yea, as you move
to different networks,
then you end up with
different IP addresses.
Some networks are kind of
like very statically defined.
Stting it side like this is
the IP address on this
network. Other networks.
Obviously, all of us, nobody,
like manually sat down and
chose it for us to get
on the campus network.
So there's protocols, DHCP,
if you want to go read about it.
There's ways like
you jump on the
network and then it says,
Oh, here's the new MAC address.
Here's an IP address for you.
And then I go to a
different network,
and he'll give me a different
one on that network.
Yeah, absolutely, can change
if you're mobile, right?
Yeah, good question.
Other questions
people have? Yeah, right here.
Oh, you're saying, Okay, so
if I want to send a
message from, like,
here to California,
like how many,
like, routers might
it hop through?
Yeah, it's a really
good question,
and it'd be like on
the order of, like,
tens, not on the
order of thousands.
And there's a little
tool you can use.
It's called trace route.
And you can run a trace route
to a different destination,
and it will try to
figure out what
each hop is, and it'll show you.
I mean, some of them
don't want to share
information with you so because
it had some holes in it,
but you can run trace
route and say, like, Oh,
from here to there, how
is it getting there?
And sometimes that's, like, very
interesting, for example,
I think once, like I was like,
doing something like on
the West Coast, right?
And then it was like,
super high latency,
and then I'm like, I did a
trace route and it's like,
Oh, it's forever stupid reason.
It was like sending
my traffic to, like,
Virginia first, and then it
was like sending it East, right.
So you can actually
kind of troubleshoot
these things and do it.
So take a look at Traceroute.
I sent another hand up over
here. Yeah, right over here.
Would two computers on the
same network have the same IP?
They're not supposed to, right?
I mean, you can, and then
I don't know I think
things get weird.
It's not clear like who
the traffic should go to.
I mean, it would be
considered misconfigured.
And I know I mean,
I guess nothing
blows up, but yeah,
just kind of I've actually
misconfigured things that way,
and then it's just
it's weird, right?
Yeah. Yeah other
questions people have
Yeah, right over here.
Some networks will
automatically do it for you.
I was at the HCP thing
I was talking about and
I will go in depth on
that or in other cases,
a system administrator
will say, Oh,
I'm plugging you into
the network, and they'll
manually can figure what
it's supposed to be.
So they're both it could
be manual or automatic.
I see another hand up somewhere.
Yeah, right over here.
Our IP addresses
and MAC addresses.
MAC addresses are used
when we're trying to
communicate on a single network,
and then the IP addresses are
used when we're trying to
communicate across across
different networks.
Yeah. Uh huh. Oh, it's
trying to send it
to It's trying to
send it through six and three
to get to B. Yeah. Okay.
Oh, sure. So once it's onto
a specific network
and it could use
a MAC address to get it
to that specific machine.
But as it's traveling, across.
We have to use the IP address
to figure out where
to send it to.
So once we're in a network
and we can use the MAC address,
when we're across
networks, then we
would use the IP address.
I mean, a little bit of
this is hidden from you
because if you are on a
single network, right,
you probably are
using IP addresses to
refer to other machines
on that same network,
but it's still looking up
the MAC address for it.
There's a protocol
called RP where you
can I guess I'm getting
off on a tangent here.
But you can actually
for a given IP address,
you figure out, Oh,
on this network,
what is the MC address for it?
So I can communicate
with it. Yeah, we here.
Networks, if you have a
there's a new network here.
So I guess and
then I guess what it
would be plugging into
an existing router
and then how would
it kind of like report
like, Hey, I'm here?
Yeah, I'm not sure kind of
like the bootstrapping of it,
how it happens if there's
new networks added.
I'm not sure. Yeah, that's
of great questions today.
Thank you, everybody.
Cool. So we have
the sense that we have
these IP addresses now.
If I run back to that
IP address command,
it is going to list off
all these Nicks I have,
and it is going
to show me the IP
address for each of them.
And so then what I can do is
depending on who I want to
be able to reach my web server,
I could choose one
of these, right?
I could let's say I'm
starting a Python web server.
I can say Python
three, HTP server,
and I can say Bin.
Bin means that this
program is going to
be listening to that
particular neck.
And so I could use IP address
for that neck or this
one for this neck.
Or there's a couple
of other ones.
The loopback device I talked
about that always has 127001.
That's an IP address you
should memorize, right?
You're probably going to
use that whenever you want
somebody to just be
listening locally.
The other one you should
memorize is 0000.
That's not a real IP address.
What that one is is it
means that I want to
listen on everything I
can at the same time.
People often do
that because it's
more convenient
than having to go
look up the one that's public
facing. Yeah, question.
Yeah, that's just
a Python module
that acts as a web server.
Maybe if I have time, I
might even show it later,
but it's just like a
simple web server that
comes with Python.
If I just have some static
HTML pages or something,
and I want to spin up a website.
Yeah, follow up.
Yeah. Maybe I'm
in a bash shell and then
I run Python three. Yeah.
I mean, sometimes when
you say Python three,
you'll say the name of
a program like maybe
myprogram dot pi.
Other times you say
the name of a module,
and a lot of modules come
preinstalled with Python.
Some modules are
unable as programs.
So I could say and then
I could say the name of
a module that can be
run as a program.
You might also see
sometimes that people say,
Python three PEP PP is
a module that can run as
a program. Good question.
Other questions people
have. All right, fantastic.
So let's talk about this
idea of private networks.
Private networks are really
trying to solve two problems.
One is that we don't have enough
IPV four addresses in the world.
The other one is that sometimes
I might want to
have a machine that
is not really visible to
everybody on the Internet,
maybe for security purposes.
And so what they've
done is you could have
kind of a public network where
these IP addresses could
be visited from anywhere,
or I can have a private network
where I can control,
who can send to it.
And so for the private networks,
what they do is they've defined
three ranges of IP addresses.
And anybody can use those to
create a private network.
So you can see this last range,
anything that begins with
ten is a private network.
You could use an IP address
starting with ten
on your network,
and I could use the
same one on my network,
and that would be
totally finest private,
so we wouldn't collide. You
can see that here, right?
There's this 10012 is
the same on network
A and in network B.
You know, a big
organization like
UW, our university, right?
We might want to have
more than one network,
but there's only
these three ranges.
And so there's a way to create
something called subnets.
So subnet is basically it's
basically like a network,
but it would use sub range
of this space. All right.
So let's think about what
happens here, right?
So when I do my IP address,
I see that there's this
network interface,
I see it has this IP address.
So I would naturally probably
want to bind to that.
And I would tell people,
check on my website.
This is the address you use,
and they'll go there,
and it won't work,
because it's a
private IP address.
It's not visible to them.
Yeah, come right here.
Yeah. That's a
private That's a private.
So it'll be always
considered private.
So there are certain ranges that
are set aside to
be private, what?
Oh, that nobody tries to
create it like a public
thing with that.
Yeah, I'm not sure how the
governance of that works,
right if you I mean,
even they divide it up,
different countries
are supposed to
own specific IP ranges,
and then they can sell
those different companies
will own differ IP ranges.
So I don't know how
they deal with,
like if somebody
is like vogue and
they try to hook into a
route or somewhere and say,
h, I'm network with
this IP range.
Soo else doesn't know. I don't
really how they police it.
I'm not sure. But these
are well understood
to be private,
so you could even imagine it
would be easy to say, like,
Hey, like, we know that
it's not a public
one. Yeah, question.
Series I don't know.
I mean, it's semi arbitrary.
I guess you can see there's
different numbers of zeros,
and so they kind of
correspond to networks
of different sizes,
kind of a small, medium
and large. I don't know.
I think they call
them like class ABC or
something like that.
So they wanted to have
like one of each, right?
All right, so how do
we actually I ran
this web server and it's bound
to my private IP address?
That's really all I can
bind to because when
I'm on the virtual machine,
that's all I can see, right?
But what if I want
somebody else to be able
to communicate with me? Okay.
So I have my virtual
private network over here.
I'm bound to this
one. And there's
something called a network
address translation layer.
And one of the things you can do
is it can forward traffic from
a public IP address to one of
these private IP addresses.
And so when you create
a virtual machine and
you're looking at
these things here,
you'll see it has
both the internal
IP and the external IP.
When you see that
there's the two there,
that means there's a
NAT being used, right?
And that NAT is sitting
between different networks.
On this network, it has a public
IP address associated with it,
and then it could forward
traffic to one of
these private IP addresses.
So that can influence whether
traffic can reach me.
The other thing is that
alongside that NAT,
there might be a firewall that
lets some messages through
or maybe not others for
security reasons, right?
So we're going to be
looking at at that as well.
All right, so I did this
bind thing down here.
I'm starting my web server.
That's a private IP address.
That's all I can bind to.
This machine doesn't even know.
Like, it has traffic
being forwarded to it,
but doesn't even know what
its own public IP address is.
If I want to tell somebody
to visit this website,
I would tell them to visit
the public IP address
that corresponds to it.
And when they visit that,
it will forward
to my web server,
and I can see what's going
on. Same thing with SSH.
SSH is a server that is
bound to the private IP address
of your virtual machine.
But when you do an SSH command,
we're putting in the
public IP address
to actually get access to it.
Now, these public IP
address are kind of
a scarce resource.
So if you like shut down
your V, they'll like
take it away from you,
give it to somebody else.
When you reboot again, they'll
give you a different
one temporarily.
If you want to
have it long term,
then they're happy to do
that for you for a fee.
Probably not an exorbitant fee,
but you can pay to keep one of
these public IP addresses
long term associated with
your virtual machine.
All right. Any
questions about that,
NAD or that idea of
forwarding? All right.
Cool. So let's talk about
transport protocols.
And in networking,
everything is trying
to build in layers.
We kind of s at bottom, like,
how do we build like one network
around these MAC addresses?
How can we build an Internet
with these IP addresses?
And then on top of that,
we have different what
we call transport protocols.
And I might be talking about
two transport protocols,
and they both add
the same feature,
which they differ, but they
have one thing in common,
that they both give you
port numbers, right?
So I might have different
processes running on a computer.
And when I'm sending
packets to that computer,
I want to specify which
process am I talking to?
And the way I do that is
with port numbers, right?
So IP address will get
me to a neck on a
specific computer,
and then a port
number will get me to
a specific process that's
listening on that neck. I
have a little example here.
I'm starting actually
two Python web servers.
They're hosting HTML files
in different directories.
They're binding on
the same IP address,
and therefore the same neck, but
they're using different
port numbers.
Port 8,000, port 9,000.
You can see both of these are
running in the background.
And In both cases, right,
if I want people to visit
these two web servers,
they would use a
public IP address,
not the one that's
bound up there,
and they would use different
port numbers to get to
one process or the
other process.
All right. Let's head over here.
We're going to do
a quick top hat.
And my question today,
right, we kind of talked
about MAC addresses,
IP addresses, port numbers.
I'm just wondering what
this is an example of.
20 seconds left.
Alright, most people are saying
an IP address, which is track.
That's a special IP address.
That's the one for
the loopback device.
That's the one I'll buy
into if I want to listen to
local traffic.
Alright. Fantastic.
A, head back here. And
All right. So we're talking
about port numbers.
Okay, so there's these
two transport protocols.
One is called UDP
that stands for
user datagram protocol and TCP,
the transmission
control protocol.
We're also going
to be using TCP.
And both of those provide
this idea of port numbers.
We talked briefly about this to
be four, socket statistics.
Like if I have a
file and I open it,
then I have like a file
handle referring to it.
If I have some port
number and I open it,
then what I'd have
is a socket, right?
So it's a little
analogous there.
That's why they call
it socket statistics.
And so if I'm running
socket statistics,
I can say, I either want to look
at all the TCP or all the UTPs.
I either put a U or T there.
I'd say I see process or
listing like a server.
I might want to see process
information with the P,
and the end might want show me
the port number, of
some abbreviation.
So here I can see those two
web servers I just launched
before running on port 80009000.
Alright, so that's something
they have in common.
What is different between these?
The different in
terms of reliability.
So if I'm sending a
packet somewhere,
there's a lot of things
that can go wrong.
O is congestion?
Congestion means
that there's a router that's
a little bit overloaded.
If too many packets are
coming to the router,
the router's just like, oops,
and it drops some of them if it
can't keep up. So that happens.
There might be
different ways through
the Internet to get
0.8 to point B,
and maybe some packets go one
way and some dos the other.
So it's totally possible
that a packet that started
later might kind of catch
up and arrive sooner.
These routers might
take a big packet
and split into smaller packets.
And so the gist of all
this is that if I'm
sending this nice clean stream
of information on one side,
on the other side, it's
a jumbled mess, right?
There might be holes in it.
Things are out of order.
And so TCP and
UDP differ in terms of how
they help us with that.
What TCP will do is it
will buffer those up in
memory and kind of present
them on the receiving side in
the same order they were sent.
It has sequence numbers
that help it do that.
It can maybe see like, Oh,
I have a packet like one,
two, four or five,
03 is missing.
There's a protocol where
it can try resending it,
eventually get all
the information.
So that's straight,
we mostly use TCP.
We usually want reliability.
UDP doesn't do any of that.
So UDP is generally faster,
but not as reliable.
There's cases where
you don't want to
retry when data is lost
because maybe kind
of the moment is
lost and it's not
worth repeating.
Like if I'm on a Zoom call,
for example, and like
the Internet cut out
for a little bit,
it'd be kind of weird if
it came back on and like
a replay of me
like sitting there for the
Internet to come back.
I just humans will solve that.
I'll say, h, what
were you saying?
And humans will figure it out.
Alright, so this is
kind of where we
are and what we're
doing next time, right?
So we learn about TCP and UDP.
Next, we're learning
about applications,
we can build on top of
that. And I have 5 minutes.
So I'm going to do in
just like a demo on
the shell and try to
get some more hands
on experience with
some of this stuff.
And so what I'm going to
do is I'm going
to come over here
and I am going
to create a directory
here called Lecture two,
and I'm may try to start
two different web servers.
I may have different
directories for their contents.
I may have a directory A and B,
and I may echo like Server one
to index that HTL
is what you typically
use for a home page.
And I'm not writing
like real HTML.
That's not my point
in this class,
but I may create,
different home pages for
each of them, right?
If I look at the index
HTML for server A,
Is going to say server one.
Okay. What I want to do now is
I want to start a server
on each of these.
And so if I say Python three M,
I can put a module here
and run it like a program.
HTDp dot server is a
module that comes with
Python that I can use
to start this thing up.
And it has a few options.
I can say, like, what
directory I want to look at.
What address should I bind to?
And then finally,
at the very end,
what port number are we using?
So, I am going to be doing
something like this.
I'm going to say
the directory is
A. I'm going to say
bind to something,
and maybe I'll say like
port 8001st, right?
So I'm just going to
leave that as a comment.
What address do I want to do?
I am going to do this.
I can see that this
is my IP address.
There's like the loop back.
There's some Docker thing.
This is the one I want to have.
And I just have a
few minuts left.
Maybe I'll try to make sure
I get through the demo,
and then I'll take
some questions
at the end. I'm
going to do that.
I'm going to go ahead.
I'm going to start
that web server.
If I copy this, this is
a private IP address.
It starts in ten, so
it's obviously private.
If I do that, I'm not going
to get anywhere, right?
Where I have to go instead
is look at my Cloud console.
And under my Cloud console,
I can copy this
public IP address.
And if I go there on port 8,000,
the NAD is going
to send me over,
and it'll just be fine, right?
And if people are visiting this,
you could visit it too, right?
And then if you visit
that IP address,
then you would be seeing
my server as well.
And if people do that,
then I'll probably start
getting a bunch
of web logs here.
Maybe what I might do is I
might send all this output
to some log one dot TXT.
And I might run it in
the background, right?
So if people are visiting
that, then I could tail
that log and kind of
see what's going on,
like if I refresh
this over here,
then I can see that
showing up, I refresh it.
I see more output there.
So that's cool. That's
running in the background.
If I try to start it again,
let's say I try to start it
on I'm going to
try to just run the same thing
by my do Directory B now.
If I try to do that,
I'm going to get
that error about
Address already in use.
I know that I was one who
kind of created that process,
but I might want to figure out,
like, who is using that poor.
So then I would use the
Stocke statistic tool.
I would say, tell me about TCP,
who's listening on TCP.
And then I might want to say,
I can see right here,
8,000 is the troublemaker.
I want to see what
process is doing that.
And then I could do pudo to
get that full information.
Then I could see, well,
Here is the process, right?
If I want to, I could kill
that, kill that process.
All right, so I could
kill that process.
I think instead,
what I will do is I
will start on port 8,001.
All right, so I'm on 8,001 now.
Let me come over here and
I'm going to try 8,001,
and it should say server
two, but it's not.
Maybe I'll actually even just
do this in a separate one.
So why can I not
hit that server?
And the answer is the firewall
is not configured
to let me do that.
I'm going to come back
here in the C Consil and
I'm going to go under VPC.
That's virtual Private Cloud,
and there's networking
firewall settings.
And under the firewall settings,
you can see, Oh, there's
my rule for port 8,000.
That's why that one
worked. Let me create
a new firewall rule
to open up 8,001.
So I'm just going to call
this rule port 8,001.
And dress means that the
traffic is incoming.
I want to allow the traffic.
I can say, do I just want to
be some BMs or all of them?
I want to be all of them,
which IP addresses.
I'm not trying to talk about
this too much right now,
but this basically means
anybody can talk with me.
And then I have to choose.
Do I want all ports or
specific ones and
specific protocol?
So I could choose UDP, TCP.
I just want to open up 8,001.
And I'm going to create
this firewall rule.
And if this works successfully,
then this server should
be up and running.
Fingers trust, and
why is it not?
That would be such a
great. There we go.
That's a nice way
to end the lecture.
And so I apologize
that every thing was
trying to rush through
there at the end,
but you can see you can tend to
navigate this firewall settings,
figure out the Nt stuff.
You can figure out
how to get a server
that's reachable from the
people you want to reach it.
All right. So I'll stop
there. Feel free to
come up and chat if you
have any questions.
I sorry, I got a little
rush there at the end.