Learning about Spark, and
Spark is built in layers.
At the heart of it is
this abstraction of the
resilient distributed data set.
Right to do a couple more
examples with that today.
Most people do not interact
with Spark at that level.
They're interacting
at a higher level.
So a top of the RDDs,
they built Spark SQL.
It's visually be getting that.
U On top of Sparks Equal,
they built data frabe.
Even though the later
that things are built.
I'm going to do
data frames and xs.
I think a fair portion of
you probably have experience
with data frames from Pandas
and maybe other courses.
So we'll do that, and then
we'll move into Sparks equal.
So I'm going to
head back to this
notebook that we
were in last time.
And there were a few
things going on here.
Remember that first, we had to
create a Spark session up here.
From the Spark session, we
could have a spark context.
And once we have
that spark context,
we could parallelze thing.
So I could take any kind of
dataset in Python and
turn it into an RDD.
And then I could apply
transformations to it.
So we're seeing how we
could do that last time.
In some cases, we
could filter or map.
Those are transformations
where I have an RDDDN,
and I get an RDD
out as a result.
I could also have
actions, right?
If I have a transformation,
I don't actually have to do
any computation
until I want to see
some result or write
some results somewhere.
So things like me or
take or collect at
the end would actually
trigger all those
transformations to run,
and then I would finally
get some results
there at the end.
So I want to talk a little
bit about how we can
partition our data.
We can have some
control over that,
and also about caching.
These both of those
things are going to have
a big implications
for performance.
So the first thing I do is
I'm going to look at my RDD,
and I could say,
get num partitions.
And by default, Spark chose
to give me two partitions.
And that was up here.
So if I wanted to,
I could get a different
number of partitions.
And I'm going to do that now.
I'm going to see what would
happen if I have instead ten.
Remember that when I am running
a task for some purpose,
there's going to be
a task corresponding
to each partition of an RDD.
And so if I have
more partitions,
I'm going to have more tasks.
If I have lots of compute
power crust from machines,
I will let me spread
that work out.
But it also means
there's more of this
fixed overhead to starting
all of these things.
Right? I'm going to
run this right now.
And then at that point, I
can check it and I can see,
well, this one actually has ten.
Okay. What I want to do now
is see how I might have
a case where I want to do
some caching and maybe change
that partition account.
And what I do is I'm may start
with this large dataset,
and I may sample it
to shrink it down.
Before we were doing
things like mean,
if I have a sample and I
can't take the sample mean,
that will be faster, and
the result might also
be pretty similar.
And I come down here, I may
say sample equals dd sample.
And when I do that, there's
a few things I can pass
in The most important
is the fraction.
How many of these do I
want? I'm may say 10%.
When you're sampling, there's
this idea of replacement.
If I have replacement
true, then it
might sample the same
one more than once.
And then there's also a seed
here to maybe make it
more deterministic.
I'm just going to say that
I do want resampling.
Let's have 10% of the results,
and our seed will be 544.
This is a transformation,
so nothing
actually happened yet.
That was quite fast.
And then what I'm
interested in is
if I can take the mean of it.
And a simple operation,
but what I'm really
interested in is
the performance of
this operation.
And so I'm going to import time
here and I'm going to measure
how long it takes. Right?
So maybe I'll print
off what that mean is,
and I will also time,
how long it takes.
I'll say t zero equals time dot,
t one equals time dot.
Then I'll just print off how
long that operation talk.
I'm going to do that.
We can see that there's ten.
Maybe I can actually copy this.
There were ten tasks
running because,
well, there were ten
partitions up here.
So let me make a note of that.
I think that's
useful to remember.
So right?
Is this going to help
you debugging things,
right? So what does this mean?
This means there are ten tasks,
eight are done, two
are in progress.
Gues just chapter there
at the end. Okay, great.
So I'll talk about 4 seconds.
And unfortunately, I mean,
it was kind of cool,
this was lazy because I could do
this very quickly
and I didn't have to
do the expensive sampling
operation earlier.
Unfortunately though if I
run it again right now,
that means I may have to
resample original dataset.
So just to rerun this, I have to
again sample all those
million numbers.
It has to do that again.
And maybe it's a
little bit faster,
maybe not. In the
morning lecture.
The second one was actually
a little bit slower, right?
Because I have to have
that big expensive
thing each time, right?
Yeah, question right
here. Exactly, right?
Because I have two
cores to run on.
So when I started this up,
I had two worker containers,
and I told them each that
they may use one core each.
So normally, it'd be a lot
more in progress
at the same time.
Yeah, thanks for clarifying.
So what I want to do is
I want to see if I can
avoid having to
resample every time.
In both these cases,
it's basically re
running this sampling up here.
And so I'm going to just come
back to this line up here.
And this time, I'm going to say
a sample dot cache, right?
And neither of these two
lines actually do anything.
So caching does not immediately
materialize those bytes,
but it's saying that
when it does eventually
have to materialize those bytes,
we should save that in memory.
So we don't have to keep
doing the same thing.
Again and again.
Remember that an RDD is
a recipe to have some piece
of data that you
can do on demand.
By default, there's no bytes,
but in some cases,
you can say, well,
this would actually be a
scenario where it makes sense to
have those bytes in memory
for performance reasons.
So I do that. And so
given that it's not already
been in the cache yet,
I've just marked it so that'll
be in the cache later,
this should actually
be a little bit slower
because I have to do all
the same work plus I have
to write that intermediate data
to memory and my workers, right?
So this was actually
a little bit
slower than these
other two cases.
Now, in theory, it should
be a bit faster this time,
but our performance gains
are not going to be as
significant as you might
expect. 3 seconds.
This is not great. I
mean, we were talking
about 3.25 seconds earlier.
Shaving off a quarter
second by having
all our data in
memory is not great.
I mean, we went from having to
scan 1 million numbers
to 100,000 numbers.
It feels like should
be a lot faster.
The reason is not
a lot faster is
that we have to
start so many tasks.
100,000 number is can actually
be processed relatively quickly.
And so the cost of starting
a JVM process to do that
work is pretty significant.
And I chose this specifically
because there's a lot of
cases where you have
a large data set,
and then you filter it down.
You crunch it down a
lot, and By default,
Spark is trying to have,
while one input partition
is one output partition.
And they have a good
reason for that, right?
They don't have to shuffle
data across the network.
But what that often means
is that the partition
account originally
for the big data is
not a good partition account for
your later data after you
shrink it down by a filter
or a sample or whatever.
And so what I want to show
now is that if we are
smart about how we use
repartitioning in
combination with caching,
then we can actually get a
good performance
improvement, right?
So I come back here again,
and you can see I'm doing
it in pairs, I did
it twice up here.
I did caching, got a lot slower,
a little bit faster
with the cash.
I may do it again, but
this time after sampling,
what I may do is I may say a
repartition, and I want one.
What that means is that
I may have one partition
and that's what's going to get
cashed and I may run that.
Again, nothing happens yet.
That will just happen
later when I do it
for the first time?
This one is going to be
slower again, right?
Because it has to do
the original work
plus cah that one
partition somewhere.
But when I finally get to speed
up should be after this one,
when I finally run this because
my data is going
to be in memory,
and there's only going to be
one partition of the data.
So now I get down
to 1 second, right?
So, be fast, you have
to figure out, well, when
should I cash something?
When should I be
partition something and
you'll kind of build
some intuition for that.
But those are some
important decisions you're
going to have to
make to get the best
performance out of the system.
Any questions about either
of those techniques?
Yeah, right here. Is there
ever a benefit to having
more partitions than cores?
Yeah, there could be, because
not all the partitions
might have an equal cost, right?
For example, I
mean, I might have
some partitions where let's
say I'm filtering, right?
Let's have ten partitions,
and they're all filtering.
Maybe the first partition,
maybe half the rows,
kind of pass through the filter,
maybe other partitions like
almost none of them do, right?
So what I'm going
to say is that even
though we might equally
partition the data,
doesn't mean the partitions
are equal amounts of work.
If the number of partitions far
exceeds the number of CPUs,
then even if the partitions
are different sizes,
probabilistically,
I'm more likely
to be able to evenly
distribute the work.
Does that make sense? Yeah, hm.
Yeah. So lots of
factors in play, right?
You have to think through
those things to decide what is
the right partition
hunt in your scenario.
Okay. Yeah. Any questions
about that? Cool.
So I am going to head over,
and we are going
to do some stuff
with data frames now and I may
be using somewhat bigger data,
and it's going to
be a new notebook.
So first, let me just show
you over here in the
lecture snippets.
I have some stuff about Swap.
We've talked about Swap before.
Remember that sometimes if
you're tight on memory,
and there's some
memory that you're
not accessing super often,
maybe you can write some of
that data to swap instead.
There's no swap
enabled right now.
I'm just going to copy and paste
those commands
from the notebook.
There's a few things
it's doing. Maybe I'll
just run in then
I'll talk about it.
Allocate is like it's
touching a file,
but int of creating
an empty file.
I can say I want to
have a 1 gigabyte file.
Here I'm changing some
permissions on it.
Thesenumbers correspond to read,
write, and execute bits.
I won't worry about that
too much right now,
but this is basically
saying the owner
should be able to
read and write it,
and nobody else can
read and write it.
The owner is the root
since we did pseudo.
I'm turning into a swap
file and I'm enableing it.
And so now if I say H top,
I can see that I have
about one tick abite here.
You'll probably have to do
that on next Project five,
because it a little
tight on memory.
If you don't do that, you might
be running out of memory,
the system might be freezing up.
It's a trick you
can push so far,
and I've played with
it a little bit.
If I can have a bigger data set,
and I'm trying to use more swap.
Sure, maybe it runs, but
it's constantly reading and
writing data back
and forth to desk,
and that so slow that
it's like, Well,
it's going to be like hours
to do something simple,
and it effectively feels
like it's frozen up.
So you can try to push the
boundaries a little bit,
but not a whole lot.
Right, great. So I
have that swap there.
Another thing I'm going to do
is I started a new
notebook actually.
I was just easier for
me to keep this in
the same Jupiter lab instances.
I'm kind of working at
the boundary of two
lectures right now.
I'm going to create a new
notebook and I will call
this one Lecture two B,
why did that not rename?
That was kind of
weird. Okay, I'm
to start this new notebook.
And the hand do
is I come over here and look
at my not running notebook.
If I have all these
other ones running,
I'm going to run out of
memory too quickly, right?
I'm actually shut
down all my kernels.
Most importantly,
when I shut down
those kernels, some of
those had spark sessions.
I'm closing out those
spark sessions.
Even that data cache, right?
I want to free that up.
So that will all
be freed up now.
I have a fresh
notebook over here.
I need to create
my spark session.
And so I have a
snippet for that,
so I don't have to
remember all those things.
And this is very
similar to last time,
except I'm making a few changes.
I highlighted that and read so
you can see what is different.
This one I changed
because I actually
want to show an
error and talk more
again about how we walk
through reading these errors
and dealing with them,
so that was an
intentional error.
And these two lines are going to
apply more to the next lecture.
So I just thought it was easier
to have one snippet here
that if I move
into the next content,
we'll be ready to go.
Otherwise, this is the
same as last time.
So we come over here and I'm
going to create
this spark session.
Remember that when we get
errors in this environment,
it's usually pretty
awful because
we have this combination
like Python,
scala, Java, all in
the stack trace.
So fairly intimidating errors,
but we're going to dig
through and see how we
can find what's relevant
for us in this case.
And so lots of things going on.
In this case, the error was
actually deep in
the Java and scala
stuff and I got this error here
coming out of the
Spark library itself,
and it's telling that the
executor memory must be
this and that I actually
set it to this.
That's in bytes. I
have somehow figure
out how to change
that executor memory.
I'm just trying to
pull this out and
see what are they telling me,
how many bites of memory
are they actually
asking me to have?
And somebody say 24 squared,
and they say, Okay,
for whatever reason,
they have a minimum
of 450 per executor,
and somebody come over here
and maybe just do like 512,
make it a nice even
number, so I can do that.
When I run this the second
time, I get an error.
Another Spark context
is being constructed.
Well, it was, but it failed.
And so this is a warning.
Spark tends to be
kind of verbose
about having warnings that
are not actually problems.
This is one of
those cases, right?
So if you're trying to
fix something, I could
just restart everything
and have a clean slate.
But if you see something
like that, well,
and you just fixed the
problem, you're good to go.
Right? I'm going to
carry on. I have
my Spark session here.
I can start working it if I
would like to. All right.
Cool. The data I'm going to
do is from Lecture Snippets,
and it's down here.
I have this station data.
This is basically a file
containing all these
weather stations
from around the world.
And I already downloaded it,
so just save a little time.
You could do that.
I'll just open it and
take a look at it.
It's a text file. And just
like my DM is trying
to go on slow today.
But I think it's coming.
There we go. It's a text file.
Definitely not a CSV file.
It's not comma separated.
We can see that to
analyze this data,
we'd have to read
the documentation
and see the offsets for
each field and maybe do
some string slicing
to actually extract.
I'm so how we can do that.
How we can use Spark to
extract individual
columns of this file.
All right. I'm to
come back here.
And what I will do now is
I will try to read it.
And the reading and
writing and Spark is
a little bit differ.
If we look at the style up here,
they're going to kind of
borrow from this style.
One way to write constructors or
functions in general
is that you just
take lots and lots of arguments.
And that's not
necessarily great.
It gets more complicated
than necessary.
And if you don't have default
arguments, it's not great.
An alternative for that is
that you have these builders,
and the idea with builders
is that the builders are
doing the ultimate
creation of objects
for you or ultimate invocations.
I can do a bunch of different
method trawls on it,
and each one changes
something about the builder,
and then it also
returns the builder.
If it returns itself,
then I can call these
different methods on
the same object and create
something in the end.
The style for
reading and writing
files is actually going to
be very similar to that.
The read write style,
is going to be
something like this?
It'll often be like
Spark dot read,
do a bunch of stuff,
and then it might be
load at the end or
Um, the one I may
see right now is
that it's going to be dot text.
In this case, I
don't actually have
any extra arguments I
want to do with it.
And then when I'm writing,
I say data frame dot right,
and there's a bunch of stuff,
and then I might say
write table or something
like that at the end.
Anyway, that's a style we're
going to be working with.
So down here, I'm going
to have a spar dot read.
In this case, I want
a text file and I
may pass in the name
of that text file,
which is right over here.
Let me just actually,
I'm going to do
a NLS and I may
just py paste that.
I'm to try reading this in.
All right, and I'm may
get that in a data frame.
So, that's cool.
That should work. And
then I look at this.
Because it's a text
file where there's not
necessarily well
defined columns or
at least not columns
that it understands,
it's trying to give me
this data frame with
a single column called value.
Okay, that's fine and well.
I can see the schema.
What if I want to do
something like take
the count of all the rows in
it. I'm to try running that.
And just going to hopefully
count up how many lines there
are in that file and
wait for a moment.
And I got this error right here.
This file does not exist?
This N B, and then is that
true? It doesn't exist?
Let me just take a look at that.
Maybe I might try pasting
that directly and say,
well, can I see the head of it?
Well, it seems like
it does exist,
but Spark is not
seeing it, right?
The executor is giving me
this error that I cannot
read that file, right?
Hm. Does anybody want
to speculate about why?
Since the file is clearly there,
I wasn't able to read
it. Yeah, right here.
One idea is that doesn't
have permission to read it.
That's a good jest.
It's not the case.
It's going to be
something very specific
to how Spark runs
code. Yeah, right here.
Could be like the types.
Yeah, often there's
type trouble,
there's not any type trouble
going on here. That's
not my problem.
So give some hints and
then maybe see if let
me ask people again,
what do you think
might be happening?
So, when I started this
inside of my notebook, right,
I have a spark driver,
and the spark driver
has some insight into
all these nodes in the cluster,
and I can inspect that.
If I actually come
over here, right?
And I say, doctor PS,
I can see that I have
my notebook down here.
I have 5,000, right,
so I can actually talk to my
notebook from the outside.
And I also have this
40 40 and 40 40,
there's a little
server that shows me
a summary of the
workers in the cluster,
and so I'm already
port forwarding there.
I have an SSH tunnel
for 40 40 as well,
so I can actually
just row directly
in here and I can type in 40 40.
And what I can
see is there's all these
jobs that are running,
and I can come over here
and look at the executors.
And the executors,
I guess there's going to
be a few of them here.
One of the things
I can see is that
these failed tasks are
actually showing up for me,
and I can see where they are.
There's actually
three executors here,
which is a little
bit strange, right?
Because I have two executors
that I actually started,
right, the Index zero and one.
And then it's
showing the driver.
In this case, It's a little
strange they're calling
the driver an executor
because it'll
never ever execute
a task for me.
The reason I think they
might have put it here
is that if I have
a different mode where I'm
doing like, local mode,
I don't have a cluster,
then in that case,
the driver would execute tasks,
but when I'm in the
cluster mode like this,
then then it'll never do that.
So anyway, it's there.
But I'm writing my code
through this driver,
and then my code is
actually running on these.
I can see that executors
have different IP addresses.
And those are the IP addresses
actually of these
containers, right?
I have a worker here, and
I have a worker here.
These are responsible for
running all the code.
I'm writing the code in here,
but I'm running
the code in here.
So on that note, any thoughts
on why it cannot find that file.
Yeah, right here. Is that final.
Excellent. Those files
are not copied to
a place where those executors
could see them, right?
So sure. I see that path here.
But if I were to do
a docker executing,
to go into the containers
where the executors are,
and I tried to run this,
it would be like, well, I
don't have that file, right?
So I mean, one way I could
get rid of this and make it run.
It would not be a good way.
But one way I could do it is
I could take that file and
copy it to every container
where there's an executor.
If there's like 1,000
executors because I
have a giant cluster, that's
kind of waffle, right?
The other thing I can
do is instead of having
this in a local file system,
I could put this in a
distributed file system
that's visible to everything.
What works better for
that than HDS, right?
We've already learned HDFS.
We're going to be using Spark
in conjunction with HDFS.
Because we need all
these executors in
different places to have
visibility into the same files.
HFS is perfect for that.
All right. So I'm
gonna come down here.
And I'm just going
to upload that,
and I will say,
maybe I'm going to I'll
leave it here for
everybody, perhaps.
One more question
before I fix it.
Any thoughts on why Diven that
this isn't going to work,
why it didn't fail on this
line instead of later?
Yeah, go ahead. It's lazy.
It doesn't realize
that the file is not
there until I actually
try to access it.
Okay, great. So what
I'm going to do now is,
I'm going to try
to copy that file,
so I can use that HDFS
command like before,
and remember the
distributed file system
has all these things like copy.
And so I could grab this file,
and I want to copy it to the
I I called my name node N N,
and so I may copy it to there,
and the root directory
works just fine for me.
And then after I do that,
I should be able to run
the same stuff again.
Going to come down here. And now
I actually have to have
a full path to HDFS.
And this is great because
all my executors are
going to be able
to use that path
and they can find that data.
And then I should be able
to do something like count.
Take a while. Are there's a
couple of partitions there.
It'll take some time to do that,
but then it should be working.
And over here, hopefully I'm
going to see some executors
soon that have actually
successfully
completed some tasks.
All right. Any questions or
any confusion about
why it wasn't
working initially? All right.
Cool. So let me
just peek on this.
So underneath our data frame,
which we're working with now,
there's actually the RDDs
that we've been learning
about previously.
And one of the ways
I could see these
is if I say a data frame dot t,
I mean, I could get some number
of rows here if I wanted to.
And that will come back to me as
a list of these row objects.
If I wanted to, I could even,
you know, just take one
individually, right?
If I take the take one of
them and I index out of it,
I could get this row object,
and this one only has
one cell in that row,
but I could pull it out, I
could get strings out of there.
Now, if I want to, since
my RDD is basically
this collection of all
these row objects,
I can do the same RDD stuff
that we did previously,
and I can do things like
root value as I saw here,
but as part of RDD operations.
So, for example, one
of the things I could
do is I could say RDD I'm sorry,
data framed dot RDD map,
and that's t get called
on each individual row.
And from that row,
if I wanted to,
I could get the value, right?
And then you know,
that's just a
transformation, that
does nothing, but
then I could say,
like, give me, well,
this is going to give
me five strings, right?
But I could also say I want
the first 11 characters
of each of these.
I could just jump in
and start writing code,
RDD level of code on that
and do various operations.
So you can do that.
More often, though,
we're going to be doing calls
at the data frame level.
And so just like there's actions
and transformations on RDDs,
at the higher level,
we'll also have
these actions and
transformations,
and often they'll have
the the same name.
So I want to look at how
we my goal right now is to
add a station column
to the data frame.
And first, I'm may to
show how I could do it
in Pandas because some people
are familiar with Pandas,
and then I'll show how it's a
little bit trickier and spark
because data frames are
immutable because
RDDs are immutable.
So what I'm may do is I'm may
say data framed a two Pandas.
This is an action,
right? Because I
actually have to
materialize the data
and put it in a different
format, but I could do that.
I could get a Pandas DF.
If I did that, my notebook
would probably actually crash.
There's probably
too much memory.
But just for the
sake of showing,
I can work with some
smaller data here.
I could get that Pandas
DF to work with.
And when I have a Pandas DF,
I can pull out columns, right?
And when I pull out columns,
I can pull SR methods on them.
And so one of the ster
methods is a slice, right?
I could slice each of these.
And if I wanted to, I could just
put this right back
into my data frame.
I could have station, and then
Pandas DF and problem
solve, right?
I could do that. Pandas
data frames are mutable.
I can make those
changes as I go.
All right, how would I do it?
In Spark. I cannot modify
my Spark data frame.
So instead of I have to
something like this,
data frame two dot I
need to make a new one.
And the way I do this
is I say with column,
and then I put a name here,
and then basically
some kind of like code
or expression that
will calculate
the values in that new column.
So what I'll call
this is station,
and then over here, I
have to put something.
Now, a lot of the functions
that we might do in
data frames correspond
directly to function in SQL.
Remember that data frames are
built on top of Spark SQL.
And so I can get some of
these functions up here,
I can say from Pi
spark squal functions.
Import two of these.
Two of the most
important ones here
are column and expression.
From P Park, Pi Spark.
Great. What these will do,
let me refer to
different columns
of output data I might want.
I could say something
like column X,
and I get that column x object.
Later I could select that if
I wanted to or do
things like that.
I can do other
computations on it,
I could do something
like that, where
I have some computation over it.
I could also do an
expression that directly
would modify it as
so that would give me a
column with that computation.
In SQL, we have
SQL, rename things.
The equivalent of that is Alias,
I could say Alias plus plus
one, something like that.
I could hit these
different columns, right?
And so what I have
to put here is
some column object that is doing
the computation I
want to do, right?
And so I may say an expression.
I can put some string here.
And what strings do
I have to work with?
Well, whatever I put here is
referring to one of the columns
of my original data frame,
and I only have one
column, which is value.
So I can do various computations
over the value column.
Those computations
are going to be
different functions
that show up in SQL.
So SQL doesn't have a simple
syntax for string slicing.
You actually have to call
the sub string function.
So do that and we do that,
I have to say some start
index and some length,
but I can do that,
and I can run that.
That was a transformation. So
no work was actually done.
But Spark is smart enough
to know that if I were
to do this computation,
I should end up with two Tolus.
I have the original
value column and I have
a second column called Station.
I I actually want to look at it,
then I could do a
couple of things.
I could say dot show.
That would give me
some kind of preview
of the data, right?
I'll have to do a job, right?
That's I actually
has to do some work,
or I often just like to limit,
you know, get a few rows
and then do two Pandas.
It's okay to convert a
few to Pandas because
it's relatively fast.
So I can do that same
thing. I can figure out how
to do that computation
with more work than I
would have in Pandas,
but it will be highly
scalable, right? All right.
Any questions about
how we can do
those inds of transformations?
Yeah, I'll probably
give you a project
at some point where you're using
the station data and you have to
do some of that work on it.
So hopefully that's a
helpful example. All right.
Cool. What I want to do now is I
want to move on and
use a bigger data set,
which will be the fire
department data set,
and let me just get
that as marked down.
I have some lecture
snippets over here as well.
And if I come up here a little
bit, there's a link to it.
So some fire departments,
including the one,
San Francisco, just publish
this dataset about all
the stuff they're doing.
It's usually not just fires.
If there's a water rescue
on in the Bay or
something like that,
then the Fire Department
would probably help
with that as well.
Anyway, have a larger file.
So I have a WG command here
to download it. I've
already done that.
I've extracted that as well.
You can see it over here,
this San Francisco CSV.
I've also uploaded it, right?
So if I say LS, actually,
let's do like a DU and
then HDFS name node 9,000.
All right.
Let's run that and just see
what we have to work with.
Alright, cool. So we've
see that we have both
these files here.
The first one was
like 10 gigabytes.
So I'm doing a two
gigabyte file,
not like the biggest file,
but I don't have a lot of
compute resources here.
I don't have a giant cluster,
and I don't want
you to be sitting
there for 5 minutes
while the job runs.
So if I had more time or
more compute resources,
I'd do much bigger data.
This is of nice size
that nothing takes more
than like a minute
or two to run.
Alright, cool. So I
have that data there,
and I want to figure out
how I can work with it.
So before I was working
with a plain text file,
now I want to see how I can
use Spark to work with CSVs.
And in particular, we're
going ahead with this,
I'm going to see that
CSVs are terrible.
Once again, we're
going to use Spark to
get the data into Park, right?
Park and HDFS. All right.
Cool. So again, I
have this note,
which I just want
to copy from above.
Maybe here's an even
better place to
do it since we're doing
this in more detail now.
But this is the style
to load these things.
It's going to be a little
bit more complicated.
I have more options here now.
First I say spark dot read,
and that gives me the
data frame reader object,
and I can add other
options here.
What format, I can say
I want to do a CSV.
Great, I have returned itself,
so I still have the data
frame reader object.
Then at the end, I could
actually go ahead and try
to load that data from
that CSV. Let me do that.
And before we saw that this
was a purely lazy operation.
And what we see now
is that there's
actually a little bit
of work being done.
Maybe it was felt a
little bit slower
than before. Why is that?
Because even though it's
trying to do things lazily,
before it does the
work on E RDD,
you should be able to go and see
what the scheme is,
what the types are.
And so I had to peek at
that file just briefly
to figure out,
for example, that there are,
you know, 35 columns, right?
So I had to read it,
even though I wasn't
reading it fully. All
right. So I have that.
And if I say data frame dot
limit three dot two pandas,
I see that this was
not necessarily
done the way I
might have expected
Pandas will do a
lot of automatic
things that are kind
of ice for you.
For example, they
will automatically
recognize that
there's some kind of
header row and make that the
header. That didn't happen here.
I thought that was
just a row of data.
Pandas would automatically
look at your values.
Figure out this is
a flow. I would
do schema inference,
in other words.
This is not doing that. So here
everything is a string up here.
And so if I want to have a
header and schema inference,
I'm going to have to modify
this up here, right?
And so first, I'm
going to come down.
And when these start to
get a little bit long,
what I'll actually do is I'll
split them on multiple lines.
So it's almost like this
little pipeline, right?
I can have a bunch of stages in
my pipeline to actually
get my result.
And so one of the things I
can say here is I
can say option.
And I can say, I actually
do want to have a
header of data here.
And when I do that, then
I can see I'm going to
get actual column
names, which is great.
Again, everything is a string,
which is not so
great. All right.
Now I'm going to say, let's
do some schema inference
because I don't want to have
everything being a string.
I'm going to say infer schema.
We saw that this
was slow before.
Now it's trying to be painfully
slow this is a bigger file.
2 gigabytes isn't that big,
but it's still big enough that
this is not going to
be very fun to do.
I see it's actually running
17 different spark tasks to read
in the whole file and just
try to figure out
what those types are.
When I look at the data frame,
even before I do any
computation on it,
it has to tell me
what the types are,
and that requires
some significant computation
in and of itself.
Okay, so I'll wait
for a bit for that.
Any questions while
that's running?
Yeah, right here. Yeah, the
DFS command that
was like this one.
Oh, sure. So here's
where we might have
different things like
A survey move or M. I was
using disc utilization.
And that was showing me
both the logical size,
and then the size,
if I consider
replication and HDFS.
And then H said that
human readable.
Human readable means
there's nice suffixes
like G instead of just
having like a giant
number and bytes.
Yeah, Yeah, thanks for asking.
Cool. So I think, Rand and now
I can see we call numbers and
integer and call
type is a string.
I did a pretty good job.
But maybe I want to do better.
If I look at let's just look
at a few of these, right?
Some of the things I might
want to do is I might
want to get these call
dates as actual dates.
The call dates are still
strings, that's not great.
Some of these other things
like the call type,
which I guess is
head in the case
might not be very uniform on it.
I want to do some
cleanup on this,
and I want to show how we can
do various computation on it.
Ultimately what I do is
I'm to do some
cleanup where I take
this file and I create
a Park where I have types
in it and I have Mlthmtls,
I'm going to try to get rid
of the spaces in the columns.
Some tools might not
play well with that.
Anyway, let's see how we can use
some of these things
from before we
saw before how we
had EXPR and column,
and we can use those again.
The way we'll do this
is we'll say select.
In here, I can have
different columns.
I can have something here, I
can have another column here.
I can put whatever columns
I want and select those from it.
Let's just look at a
couple of these and
see how we might transform them.
I'm going to look
at, for example,
the call date. What else?
I'm going to look
at the call type.
Let's see if we can just
take a look at those.
I'm going to select those,
and then I might say that
limit five to pandus.
I can just look at
a few of these.
All right, rolls. I want to
turn this into a proper date.
If I look at the dtypes, right?
They're both just
objects in Pandas,
which means that they
are actually strings.
I guess I can see
it a little bit
more easily that
there's strings here.
They're both strings. All right,
great. How can I fix that up?
Well, let's say for
the call type first,
I may do is I may have an
expression instead
of the column,
and then I can say things
like in SQL, there's
an upper function.
I could transform
that if I wanted to,
I can make that a little
bit more uniform.
Why is it unhappy with that?
Extra t person extra
input type online one.
Oh, why it is unhappy
is that it doesn't
expect spaces in here.
And so I may use BA tex.
That's the way we can in SQL
have column names
that have back tex.
I could transform that.
Then the call date is a
little bit more tricky,
but I can have something
called two date.
And when I do that,
I may put in that value and
then may put in some
format strain over here,
that'll specify the format.
I already looked up the format.
I guess this is month year day.
Some people do month year day,
some people do day month year.
I just have figure
out what the case
is here. I'm going to do month.
Day and then year
is four digits.
I always read at this up, but
I looked up before a lecture and
capital M means month and
lowercase M means minutes.
That's why I'm doing that
a little bit strangely.
I could get that as well, what
is it unhappy about
here this time?
What would I have to
do? Oh, Excellent.
Thank you. I have to
do call to expression.
There's no column
with that name.
Okay, great, great troll.
No fun intended. Great.
So I have both of these.
Then if I want to, I could
put aliases on them, right?
This could be like
my new troll date,
or maybe I might
even at this point,
get rid of those
spaces if I want to.
This might be troll tight.
I can just do some of
this cleanup work.
Okay. That's one thing
I might want to do.
Now, for the sake of
the next example,
only I try to do is
get into a Park file,
and try to try to get rid of
all the spaces in the names.
I want to see how
I might do that.
So I can, C right here.
Oh, yeah, when I have
this value here.
I think that let me
do it like this.
I see that it's
actually a call date.
So for example, you know,
I I have a float,
and I just print it it like in
one format, just like generic,
whatever the language
likes to do,
or I could do like a print F
or have some format string.
So the same thing here.
So given that it's like
an actual proper date,
it's going to show me in
whatever standard
way it does dates.
This is just referring to
the format and the
original string,
not in any kind of output.
I could tvert it back to
an output string in
whatever format I like.
Yeah, thank you for clarifying.
So I could look at
the columns here.
One of the things I could do is
I could just loop over these,
I could say C for C in columns.
And then what I
can do is I could
convert these to one of
these column objects.
And this would be
a nice way that I
could automatically
well, automatically,
but quickly select all
these columns from
that data frame.
And then I can also
alias them if I want.
I can alias them as
the name replacing
spaces with underscores.
I could do that, and I get
this result right back here.
If I want to, I can
then select these.
Now I'm going to be
in pretty good shape.
I have no spaces in my names,
and I have types, at
least for most of them.
I can go through and
clean up the dates too,
like I just showed.
I won't do that now
though. All right.
So far so good. So
now that I have this,
I could do other things with it.
For example, I could
filter it if I wanted to.
I could have expressions here.
I could say something
like the column
of call type. This is
starting to get long again.
So whenever it gets long, then
I split it up across
lines like this,
I could Then I could
filter where the call type or
something starts with odor.
Oftentimes something smells bad
that people call the
fire department,
maybe it's natural gas smell
or something like that.
Call type has underscore in it.
That's probably not the
most fun call to take,
but anyway, they do that.
Then I could take a look at this
and let me just see if
that's working correctly,
I could do all this cleanup,
and I could process it later.
That's going to be slow because
every time I re run it,
it's ring back to
the data frame,
which is ultimately
reading the file
and so it has to do all
these stages of work.
What I want to do
instead of always going
back to the source and running
all these slow things,
I want to take this data
that was cleaned up,
write it to our Park,
and then I'm always going to use
that park as my starting point.
Okay. Well, that's running
this going to take a while.
Let's see how we might start.
And that was strange.
Because I forgot to have
it do the upper case,
I'm running a little
short on time.
Maybe I'll come back to that.
To do fix case on Odor.
Maybe what I should do
is I should just do
this example on the
earlier one up here.
That might be a
little bit better.
Let me just filter
this here, great.
Then I can just do the example
a little bit more
quickly, right?
What trouble did I get into now?
So I think maybe I didn't Sorry,
as I'm going between examples,
I'm just making a little
bit of a mess here.
Let me clean this
up. Okay, great.
Then I can actually see.
I could filter down
and do analysis on it.
Okay. But what I really want
to do is I want to take
this data that I've
cleaned up to some extent,
and I want to write
it to a Park file
somewhere instead
of just viewing it.
What I'm going to do is I'm
going to say dot write.
When I do that, I get
this data frame writer.
Just like before, when
I had all these things,
I can specify, I can keep
building on top of it.
So I can say, I
want it to be Park.
I still have a
data frame writer.
Then at the very end, I can say,
Save. I can save it
somewhere in HDFS.
Where I will save it
is HDFS, name node,
9,000 and San Francisco
dot Park. I could do that.
Often when I'm doing
this kind of stuff,
I will just try it small
first because the job is
going to take a while
and I want to see if
I have it working before
I do something large.
So that seems like
that works fine.
What if I get rid
of the limit now?
Well, in that case,
I'm going to get a
little error because
that file already exists, right?
And so that brings us
to this idea of mode.
And for the mode,
I can tell it to
overwrite something or I
could this could be a no off.
I could just get it if
it was already there,
or I could raise an error,
which is the default.
I can specify all
these things and it's
going to write that
write that out.
Okay. But why don't
do a top pad,
and this will take a
couple of minutes.
And so let me just Let me see
if I can fix this up here.
I have a nice time where I
have a couple of dead minutes.
Great. All right.
This is just trying to
testing your knowledge about
what kinds of things are
fast and slow and spark.
A 30 seconds left.
Okay.
Yeah. I guess if there's
technical issues,
you can just follow up with Top
A. I didn't build the app,
I can't really fix any
technical issues with that.
Or you can always try
another device to and start
bring another device if
it's a common occurrence.
C. People are saying Line
D, which is correct.
In this case, we have a
bunch of transformations,
and transformations are just
recipes to get the
data on demand.
It doesn't actually do anything
until we actually say,
I want to see result.
Mean is an action that
forces us to see the result,
which brings us back
nicely to this, right?
I did some transformations here,
but at the end of the day,
when I actually say write some
bytes to a file somewhere,
that's an action that's actually
triggering all the work,
which we're watching
run right now.
Okay, so I don't know
if people caught it,
but as it was running,
it was running 17 tasks.
And the reason it was
running 17 tasks was
that this data frame has
an RDD underneath it,
and if I look at the
tam partitions on it,
it has 17 partitions.
And So that makes sense.
Each of these partitions
is being handled
by a different spark task.
And it would actually
be difficult
to have all thes
different spark tasks
writing the same park file
because they'd have
to coordinate,
and we want to have this
massively parallel system.
So what they actually did is
each of the tasks just wrote
its own park file in a
different place, right?
And I'm going to
take a look at that.
If if I do HDFS LS,
I'm going to look
at name node 9,000,
I'm sorry, DFS. All right.
There's going to be San
Francisco dot p, right?
It seems like it
would be a file,
but it's actually
just a a directory,
and I can look inside
of it if I want to.
And what I can see
is that each of
these partitions
written separately.
They're trying to
different sizes, right?
Maybe they had different
compressibility.
Who knows what, but it's
not perfectly balanced,
but it was trying to
roughly balanced.
And if I look at the
part number over here,
I can see that the very last
one has a part number of 16.
So parts zero through 16,
those correspond to
these 17 partitions.
They each wrote their
own own file up there.
Where did 17 come from?
Well, Spark tried
to automatically
decide based on the
size of that CSV file.
It seemed like 17 was
a good size for that
two gigabyte file.
Now, what if I want
to load this back in?
Somebody come down here. Now
I can say spark dot read.
This is very similar. I
have a data frame reader,
I can say format, Park.
Then I can say dot load,
and then I actually
put in the path to it.
I can say HDFS,
name node, 9,000 and
then San Francisco park.
And in this case,
it's a directory,
but it's such a common pattern
that Spark knows about it.
Spark knows that this is a
directory containing a bunch
of park files and it should
read it automatically, right?
So I'm going to bring this
into a data frame like so.
And now a lot of
things are nice.
So that was fast, and I
actually have types
on everything.
I didn't have to that
painful schema inference
that took close to a minute.
It's also interesting if I
look at this, and I say,
what is the RDD partitions.
There's actually six.
Why are there six? Because It's
based on the size of the file.
This park file or the set
of Park file should be much
smaller than the CSV
file I started with.
The number of partitions
here does not
have to be the same as the
number of files, right?
I created six partitions
and they each read,
you know, roughly, what,
two to three files,
it doesn't have to
be exactly on file boundaries,
and they pulled
that data back in.
So file smaller, so I can
have fewer partitions.
That probably helps
me downstream as well
because I have less overhead
of starting all these tasks.
If I do something like count,
it's going to be actually
very fast because
Part A files already
have that information
about how many rows there are,
it's baked right
into the metadata.
If I had something
like a CSV file,
it's text and each line
might have a different
number of characters.
The only way you could count
is you actually have to
loop over all those
lines of code.
It's a common pattern, right?
L For the Spark stuff,
maybe you have a bunch of CSVs,
and those are not
fun to work with,
but you do this extract
transform load suf.
I'm extracting the data from
the CSVs, transforming it,
loading it into Park and HDFS or
some other distributed
file storage,
and then I can have
this nice environment
where I can analyze that
in a distributed way.
Alright, thanks. So
we'll stop there.
Feel free to come up and chat
if you have any questions.