Last lecture where we're
looking at new course content.
So may look at a few
different Google Cloud
services a little
bit more detail.
We'll probably have
a little bit of
time to review today as well.
So I printed off the
last two final exams,
so people can ask
questions about
those if they want or ask
questions in general.
And then Wednesday will
just be dedicated
totally to review,
whatever questions you
all have, I'll be here.
I'll print some maybe
old quizzes out too.
Just bring a bunch of materials
for you to ask about.
Okay. So before we
jump into that,
I just wanted to do a quick
tophat review from last time.
Is this one is about the
Big query Billy models.
A 30 seconds left.
So people are saying
Closs storage, which
is correct, right?
If I create a bunch of
files Big query, right?
To are stored
classes, and then I
have to pay for
that storage space.
Great. I'm going
to head back here.
And this is where
we ended last time.
We had talked about
Docker and Docker images
a little more detail.
And then we'll try
to see how that
could fit into other tools.
I show three tools
like that today?
First, we've been pulling
stuff from the Docker hub,
which is an example
of a registry.
We're see how we can create
our own registry on Google,
that's private, and we already
see how we can push
an image there.
And then we see two different
ways we can deploy it.
The first way is we deploy
it on an operating system,
called the container optimized
operating system that is
really it's only purpose
is to run ptators.
It's very secure because
it's just locked down.
It does just one thing.
Well, so we can see how
we could drive from
that image or the
directly deploy it there.
And then finally, I'm
going to show you
Google Kubernetes
engine briefly.
And we see how we can deploy
that image there as well.
Google Kubernetes Engine
actually uses COS,
the container operating system
to run its containers, right?
So all of these three
pieces we're looking at
today are going to
be working together.
So the artifact registry can
have lots of different kinds
of resources out there
like Docker images
are one of them,
but you can imagine pushing like
APT packages that you install
a new Bunto there or
Python packages or really
whatever you'd want.
To use these things, I have
to do a Docker log in, right?
So if I'm employing from
a public repository
like Docker Hub,
I don't have to be
logged in with Docker.
If I'm employing
from my private one,
I have to authenticate.
Now, you could pay Docker hub to
give you your own
private registry,
then you can authenticate
it to a password.
For Google, what they have
is called an access token.
And so we have an access
token instead of a password,
and we have to feed that into
Docker so that we're logged in,
and then we can do a docker
pull from this other
other source, right?
Now, when we generate
this access token,
we're to specify
very specific things
that it can work with.
And then we to give it to
something called a
service account.
A service account is
kind of like a user,
except that the user
is not a human.
It's like a program or
something like that.
And so in this case,
Docker needs to have
a service account so it
can access Gogle stuff.
And so When we give
that Docker service
account, this access token.
We want to really give it the
bare minimum access we can.
And there's a
security principle,
called the security
of lease privilege.
The idea is that if you give
every tool the bare
minimum it needs,
that's trying to
minimize your risk
if something gets
compromised, right?
So we give it the minimum needs,
and then we're going
to be logged in.
And to get that, we have
to have this thing
called a key file.
It's kind of similar
to an SSH private key,
and that's how we're going
to get signed in. Right?
So head over here.
And I have a bunch of
things under the
lecture snippets
that are kind of walking
you through some of this.
So the first thing
we're doing is
we're creating that
service account.
Remember that's that
non human user,
that can do stuff on
behalf of a program.
And so we're creating
one called Docker.
IAM stands for identity
and access management.
You'll see that acronym and
a lot of different Cloud stuff.
And so what we're doing now
is we're attaching a project,
we want to create a
member that we just
created with some
specific roles.
And the role we want to have
now is we want to be able to
read from an artifact registry.
We also want to give it
the role of being able
to write to one of these
registries, right?
So we're basically creating
this new user and then
associating it with
these capabilities.
And then if I actually want
to do something as that user,
I need to be able to sign
in as it I need to have
something like a password
or this access token.
And so the very
end, I'm creating
this stocker T file
that's associated
with with this access account
that has these
privileges, right?
And so I've already done
that if I come over here,
I can see that I have
this docker dot K.
I show you that
because I'll be showing
you my SSH private,
right, that would
allow you to gain
access to my stuff, right?
So I won't do that. But what I
will do is I will
were to run this.
I would basically activate
it, which I've already done.
If I were to do this, then it
would show me what
that access token is.
And if I want to, I can feed
that into a doctor log in.
If I just do a regular
doctor log in,
I can say like my user
name and password.
In this case, what
I'm saying is that
the password is
coming from standard.
And so I'm piping
that in, right?
That's going to print
the access token
and then it's going
to feed that in.
And then that will sign me
into a registry over here.
In the very end, I could
log out if I wanted to.
So I'm ma I set these
things up over here, right?
What I'd like to do is
I'd like to sign in
to a different artifact
registry other than that.
I may come over here. I
may create a new one.
So I may come over here,
and I already found
it and I penned it.
But if I go to
Artifact Registry,
I see that they have all of
these different repositories,
including one that I may
just to prep for this.
Right? So what I'm
may do now is I may
create a new repository.
And here you can see that
I can give it a name,
so maybe I'll call
this like Section one.
And I'm going to do a Docker one
because I want to push
docker images there,
but you see there's all kinds of
different suff maybe MPM.
If you're pushing Java strip
packages or you go packages.
Whatever you really want?
All right. So I
have all of that.
I can say which region
or if I want to,
I can say a multi region
that it would be in.
I'm just to have it be in
the US broadly and
they'll figure
out where they want
to place that data
in specific regions.
There's some encryption
stuff down here,
which I won't worry
too much about,
and I'm going to go ahead and
create this new registry.
Okay, I'm going to be creating.
And right now there are
no docker images in it,
but I want to push a docker
image to this registry.
Okay. So I'm going
to come over here.
And in this directory,
I have a little server,
I look at server dot SH.
What is this doing? So it's
a making a directory
called Test.
And inside of test,
I'm printing off my host name,
and I'm writing it to a
file called Index HML.
So I'm just making like
the simplest possible web page
that has my host name on it.
And then I'm starting a little
simple Python web server.
So it's just like the simplest
possible little web server
we could get up and
running, right?
And so if I look at the
Docker file over here,
I see that we're installing
some python stuff. I don't know.
We don't really need to
install Jupiter lab, but fine.
We're copying that server,
then we're actually
running it, right?
And so if I want to, I can
go ahead and build that.
I'm build it, I
may call it demo.
Excuse me.
And then what I'll do is
I'll show how I run it here,
and then I may push it
to the registry and
then see how we can
run it from there.
All right. So I built that. Do I
have anything running right
now? Let me just check.
I looks like it's
already running,
so I'm going to do Let
me just delete this one.
Oops.
All right. And then if I look at
my images, there's a bunch here.
And what I will do is I will
run this demo one
that I just right?
So I'm to do a Docker run.
I'm running the background.
I want to do port forwarding.
Let me just take a look quick
at that server on SH again.
I see that it's listening
on port eight inside.
And so outside I'll
do port 5,000,
I'll map to port 80.
And then I want to run demo.
A be running that thing,
and I can curl it.
Local host, 5,000.
And that's putting off
the container name.
If I do a talk or PS.
I see that well, I'm sorry,
it's the container ID.
Remember that inside of that,
we are just printing off.
Like the web page has the
host name in it, right?
And in this case, that's
the container ID.
Alright, that's
fine. That's kind of
stuff that we've done a
bunch of times before.
What I want to do now is I
want to get this image into
the Google Artifact registry
so I can start running
it in the Cloud.
Okay. And so to do that,
I'm going to have to tag
it to indicate where
it's going to go, right?
I'm going to say Doc tag,
and I'm going to say demo.
Then I have to give
it some new tag.
Okay? And the way this will work
is they'll be
something slash demo.
And so what this part is
really going to do is t to
indicate a new home for it
in that artifact registry.
Right? So when I come over here,
I can copy this artifact
registry if I want.
And then I will just paste
that in front of
the demo, right?
Let me just check
my notes here and make
sure I got it right.
Okay, that's my
artifact registry,
and at the end, it's the demo.
And I think that will
work just fine, right?
So now if I see Docker images,
I can see I have the Demo one,
which has this image ID,
and that's the same as this one,
which has that name as well.
And so what will happen
now is if I do a docker,
we've done lots of docker
polls this semester.
But if I do a docker push,
I can paste that in.
And what I push it is
trying to figure out from
the name what the registry
is that it's supposed
to push that to.
All right. So I'm going
to do that. I'm going
to do all that stuff,
and then it uploaded it, right?
So if I come over
here, and I refresh,
I can see that I now have
this demo image here,
and I can see there's
a name there.
Maybe over time, I I get
a bunch of things here,
if I change the image
and I repush, right,
I can see different
IDs corresponding to
my different versions
of it. All right.
You know, what else might I do?
If I did not have that for
whatever reason, right?
So let me just do a RMI.
I could, for example,
I could pull from
that, and if I'm
signed in, I could get it back.
If I was on a different machine,
I could also log in
via the same process.
If I have access
to that registry,
and I could pull this image
down on other machines as well.
Alright. Cool. So
coming over here.
If I click on this,
I see that there's a
bunch of deploy options.
I'm to talk about Cloud
run this semester.
But I'm may I talk about
how we can deploy to
the Google Compute engine
that refers to their
virtual machines, right?
So how could I deploy this
Docker image onto
a virtual machine?
And then this is the Google
Cuber Daddy's engine.
How how could I deploy it there?
So, just tell me back here.
Let's talk about this container
optimized operating system.
So maybe a lot of you are
familiar with Cro OS.
You can go buy a Crow
book if you want.
It's a relatively locked
down security oriented
operating system.
And so they modified it
to also be something that
can run containers, right?
So they have the
container optimized OS,
which they just
abbreviated COS for short.
It has Docker installed with
it, They made it really smooth.
I can just say, Hey, I
have a container image.
I want to run it,
and they'll sped up
a new VM for me that's
running those containers.
And because everything that it's
doing is just real de contators,
they make it really
locked down, right?
So the root file
system is read only,
and you cannot install packages.
That makes it more
secure. Right? A lot
of vulnerabilities come through
installing packages that might
have security vulnerabilities
in them, right?
So all we have to do
is run containors,
then we can lock down
everything else.
So it really look like
that. I have a VM.
Running, there's COS audit,
Docker is running on COS,
and then I have containers
inside of that.
Alright, so ray come over here.
And I'd re to run this sake.
So say, Let's deploy to
the Dole Compute engine.
Excuse me. And what I
see is that they
have to create a new
virtual machine for this,
right? Bring the COS.
I come down. And I
think for this one,
I will just do an E two small.
And what else did I do?
I want to see some of
these advanced options.
Let me
I could
have sworn I had
more options there.
Last time.
Alright, I think
that, here it is.
They moved it over
here, just like
they kind of changed
the layout for me.
Right? So I can see
that here is where I
have the image that it's
deployed that, right?
So that's this right here,
right that section one.
That's that artifact
registry that I have.
So it'll be deployed that
for me. But what else
do I want to do?
If I look at a network?
This is a web server,
so I want to allow HTTP traffic.
And I think that's all
the custom stuff that I
need to do for this one.
Let's go ahead and create it.
And I come back and I can see
it's creating right here,
and I'm sure be able
to refresh it shortly.
And pretty quickly because
there's not a lot
that it has to do.
I start to bids.
I may copy that IP address,
and then let's see if I
get SSH to it, right?
So SSH.
TRH at that IP address.
What I'm here, I should be able
to see a bunch of things, right?
One, is that if I look
at the OS release,
I can see that they
automatically deploy that cotaor
optimized operating
system four B, right?
If I touch a test, that's fed.
And why is that, right?
So if I look at the
Mount name space,
there's a bunch of things here.
And for my home directory,
which is right here, that
is indeed a readable
writable but, right?
So Mounted sub that's
readable writable here.
But like I said,
the route is, right?
So if I touch sub I test here,
Even if I do a pseudo
touch test, I can't do it.
It's permanently read only.
I wonder if I could
fide that in here.
It's kind of a little
bit log, right?
But here it is right here.
I can see that that's
a read only but point
at the root, right?
That's one of the
ways that they're
locking this stuff down.
Alright, so I can
see that. What else?
So if I say Docker PS,
I can see that when
this Vb starts,
they automatically start
running that contaor.
That's the whole purpose
of having this Vb.
Excuse me. If I want to,
I could jump inside
of it, right?
So I could say Doc Exact IT,
that it has this
name right here.
Somebody paste this, and
get a bash session here.
And inside of here,
I should be able
to see that Then
I have my server running.
And so if I curl to
it, if I do, you know,
local host, eight, I could see,
well, this was the name
of that contor, right?
So the server is up
and running here.
What if I exit out
of the contator,
and I'm on my VM,
when I look at Docker PS,
I don't see any
ports be forwarded,
but I'm still going
to be able to do it.
Right? Let me just
try this quick.
I'm going to do a
curl local host, 80.
It still works. So
why is that, right?
So if I drove back to my
name over here and I say,
Docker Inspect,
I should be able to see under
the network settings
that they have something
called host
networking. I wonder.
So the network mode is host.
So basically, normally
what they'll do,
what I normally create
a Der contator is,
they create a separate
virtual neck for it.
It's a separate
networking space.
Here it's just sharing
with the host.
That'll be a little bit faster
because there's less
overhead there.
And I don't have to worry
about port mappings.
Right? It does mean that I
couldn't have deferent Cttors
that are usually the
same port internally.
When I created this
thing, I also opened up
I said allow HGP and
that automatically
opened up port 80 for
the firewall for me.
So if I come over here and
I go in to a web browser,
if this works, then I should
be able to access
my server there.
Right? So it's
relatively slick, right?
I could just build
a docker image on
my Vb or my laptop or wherever.
I push it to the
artifact registry.
I click Deploy with
a couple of things.
And all of a sudden,
I have a server,
you know, in this relatively
secure environment.
Alright, Cool. Do people
have any questions about
COS or this whole
deployment process?
Right.
Cool. So I'd bet to
go kill that VM,
so I don't use up too
many resources, right?
So let me go ahead
and delete that one.
Alright. Now, let's talk about
uber D etes in particular,
the Google uber dts engine.
So Google built uber detes
and they offered as
a Cloud service.
They also open source,
which is cool.
They have a couple of
different bili bottles of
The main thing they're
charging you for is
that you create these
things called clusters,
where you can be running lots of
different containers in them,
and they charge $75
a month per cluster.
But fortunately, the free tier
covers one cluster, right?
So it's fine to like create
wood and play around with it,
but if you create
more than wood,
then you'll pay for more.
Now, there's additional
fees on top of
that depending on
what mode you have.
If you have a standard mode,
then what they'll do
is they'll create
VMs for you to run your
containers, right?
And you have to pay for
those VMs like you
normally would.
They also have something
called autopilot,
where you just pay
per container.
They figure out
where it's running.
So the cluster workers,
which are these VMs look
like this out here.
I have a bunch of VMs,
that are already COS.
They run pods like we
talked about last time
Go Kubernetes has these pods,
each of which can have
multiple containers.
So we have all those
things running.
And I want to quickly go through
a few features that
Kubernetes has.
So you get a sense of what
a full orchestrator could
do beyond something that,
doctor Compose could do.
So one of the things
that could do
is have replication, right?
It could say, Hey, we want
to have multiple deployments
of the same pod on
different worker machines.
I could do that.
I could do load
balancing, right?
If I have a bunch of
web requests coming in,
it could maybe I
alterate them in
some way across these
different replicas.
It could have fault detection
and fault tolerance, right?
So it can monitor the
health of these pods,
and if it seems like
it's down or maybe
the machine hosting
the pod is down,
it could basically start
running it again on a
different machine, right?
So I can do all these things
automatically for you.
Those are things
that Door Compose
could not do right?
Docer Compose.
It is talking about one machine,
it does exactly
what you tell it.
It's not realizing, Oh,
your container is healthy,
I'm going to run it elsewhere.
That's more of a
berates level feature.
And it's why, right? Like, it
takes so much time to actually
get at Tuber Nate, right?
It's a pretty complicated
piece of software.
The other thing that it has
to do is something called
Bin packing Bin Packing is a
general problem b systems.
I just want to
kind of introduce.
I'm trying to talk a lot
about how they do
the bin packing,
but it's something that
should be on your radar if
you're doing any kind of
distributed systems work.
The idea of Bin Pack is that
we have different machines,
and maybe they have
the same amount
of resources or
different resources.
That resource can be Rab,
it could be CPU, it
could be whatever.
And then we have a bunch
of different containers.
And we have to say which
containers go which machines.
And depending on how
you do that, you might
get more or less efficiency.
So that problem is
called Bin packing.
Down here on the bottom left,
I have an example
of bad Bin packing.
So I had a three containers
already running.
O had 1 gigabyte,
2 gigabytes and 3 gigabytes,
and I spread them evenly
across by two worker machines,
each of which had 4 gigabytes.
Why is this bad bin packing?
Well, if I want to
start another contator
that uses 2 gigabytes of rab,
there's no place where
I could put it, right?
There's 2 gigabytes total,
but there's not 2
gigabytes in one place.
I didn't pack the beds well.
In contrast, on the top right,
I have an example of
a good bin packing.
Maybe I put the two
and two together,
and then I put the one
and three together.
And of course, this is a hard
problem because You know,
sometimes you get to
see everything at once.
Sometimes you're like, Hey,
here's four containers,
bring them at the same time,
find out where to put them.
More often, like somebody will
run something, they
run somebody else.
And so you can imagine to end
up with a good bin packing.
If you saw two in a two,
like, how do you really
know to put them together?
It would be kind of more
natural to put two of
two at each VM to
spread out the work.
But bin packing means
you're trying to free up,
you know, big pieces of
memory somewhere, right?
So it's almost conflicting
with load balancing.
Anyway, that's a
complicated thing,
like people write a ton
of research papers,
on different approaches
to bin packing,
and I that something that
Tuber Nettie history to
trying to do for you.
Alright, cool. So let's
do some demos with
Kubernetes and soda
come over here,
and going to the menu down here,
I will go to The
uber Dates engine,
I throw to an overview.
And if I go to clusters,
I already have a
cluster up and running.
And I see I have an auto
pilot cluster right here.
That seems like it takes
like four or 5 minutes.
I just did that before
lecture, right?
So we would have to
sit and watch it.
And then down here,
they have these things
called workloads.
There's different
types of workloads.
You can imagine some workloads,
might just like run
once an exit, like,
maybe it like trades a model
based on some data and exit,
so I could do a job.
What I'm do it set
is a deployment.
That will be somebody
that's running
long turb that would be a better
fit for like a web server
like I've been using
for my examples, right?
Somebody deploy a web server.
And so there's lots of options
here I have to go through.
I have to say what
cluster it's on.
I only have one,
right? Be have to
start paying quite a bit.
And, you know, I
can give it like a name
and stuff like that.
That's not too
interesting. I'm going to
move on to the
container details.
In this case, I can
either create like
a new container image.
If I'm doing that, maybe
I have to say, Oh,
you have to build some
docker file somewhere,
or I can say I want to use
an existing container image,
which I want to do because
I already built one.
They're giving me kind of
a generic one. So I select this?
And I could browse to that
artifact registry where
I pushed it under
Section one, right?
Soy come find it here.
I will click click on it
and select that wood.
Then going down
here, I say I can
expose some ports, right?
And so I want to expose this
to something called a
Kubernetes Service.
And when I do that, I can create
some port mappings, right?
So say that 80 outside is
ready to go to 80 inside, right?
Now, they have different
options out here,
and I'm going to do
the load balancer one.
And what that means is
that they're going to have
one IP address with port
80 that's a load balancer.
And as I'm sending
requests there,
it's going to actually forward
them to different places.
They're going to start up a
few different replicas of
my web server because they're
imagining this is some
kind of scalable service,
and they're going to
be trying to send
it to all of them, right?
So go ahead, I'm deploy this.
And it's kind of slow,
unfortunately, but
we'll wait for it.
Any questions that is deployed?
Well, there we go.
Okay. So it seems like that is
kind of getting up and running.
So If I scroll down, right?
I see my deployment, I
see they're running it
on three different
cottors right now.
And I see wa way at the bob,
they have this exposing service
with an endpoint, right?
So when I go to this. What it's
doing is it's forwarding
to one of those ctaors.
It's showing me the idea
of that ctator here.
And I think due to caching,
I probably won't see
it changing, right?
It's probably just
remembering it.
But if I go to curl,
curl will not do
caching the same way
my web browser will
curl to port 80,
and I see that as
I'm doing this,
it's sending it to di
to different ctators that I
have up and running, right?
I just balancing the work
across those in some way.
Alright, how is it doing that?
Well, it started
three automatically.
If I go to details,
Is it details, I think?
And I see that what they're
doing is something called
auto scaling, right?
So they have these replicas,
and they're trying to
figure out, like, Well,
how many do I need to
service this workload?
And there's some
complicated rules for that.
I can put some
bounds. I always want
at least one replica,
never more than five.
If I really want to scale, maybe
I'd increase it to
more than five,
they're trying to
determine, like, Well,
when should we add more, right?
So I can say, well, You know,
when the CPU usage
is more than 80%,
and we'll start more.
Odds are if I read
this long enough,
they'll realize that my
CPU usage is tighty,
I'm not hating this
server very heavily,
and they will probably drop
me down to what replica.
But there's lots of
things you'd tune here.
And you'd say, like, Well,
what metrics do I care about?
Are there head of upper
and lower bounds?
They'll try to automatically
do the right thing for you.
Ah, right. Any questions
about load ballots the
uber Dates engine.
Oh, right. So let
me shut this down.
Alright, folks, that's
all the content
I have for the semester.
So let me just head over here.
And we have about
20 minutes left.
And you know, if you want
to stay for a review,
you can, otherwise, I mean,
we're done with a content.
You're also free
to go if you like.
But I have two exams.
These are final exams from
Fall 2023 and Spring 2023.
And so if people have
questions about these or
just any about the
final, go ahead and ask.
Anybody have any questions?
Yeah, right here.
A question exam.
At least combination question.
Yeah. It's a cumulative exam.
So I think everything from
the semester is fair game.
You know, I might put a
little bit more emphasis
on the newer stuff,
like, you know,
big query was new.
What did we have after the exam
Kafka was after the exam, right?
Let me just check it over
here, right? What
was the exam one?
I'm still writing the
exam, by the way.
Or maybe it was under mid term.
Alright, so Kafka was new,
all the Spark streaming
stuff was new.
Big query was new. Now, I also
think I may significantly
look at all these systems.
I really feel like
there's like five
major systems that we learned
this semester, right?
We learned about HDFS.
We learned about Spark, we
learned about Cassandra,
Kafka and bi query, right?
So I think there's maybe, you
know, some number of ques,
at least a couple of
questions about each
of those, right?
So you have to be
familiar with those.
There's a bunch of like
minor systems that
we learned, like,
we talked about like Map reduce
and H base and stuff like that.
You know, there's like
the earlier stuff about
like RPCs there's always,
like docker and stuff.
But I think where I'd
start is I'd try to
make sure you are
very comfortable with
those five big systems,
especially the two that
have the Big C charts.
Maybe start there, first, like
get really good at Tovka,
Sparks Stree Big query,
then try to get d at the
other major systems,
and then kind of after that,
look at all the more
miter things we did.
Yeah, there are
questions people have.
Yeah, right over here.
P. Yeah.
Spring 2023, you
said question six.
Question 16. All right,
great. Let's take a look.
All right. So a Spark
Stream equery is
Bata count for intervals
already at six Ab.
At what time could Spark
reasonably discard
the running count for events
occurring at this time interval.
Okay. So first off,
I see that the time stamp
that we're grouping by with
the window is 1 hour, right?
So basically, we have six
Ab to seven Ab, right?
And we're trying to see,
like, how many events
are in that window.
Now, it's possible right if
these events are in
Kafka or wherever,
they could be delayed, right?
So maybe over here,
I have a new event, right?
So kind of maybe like a
new Kafka message, right?
Right? So the question then is,
how long do I have to keep this?
And this water mark tells
us it is 4 hours, right?
This would be 11:00
A.M. After that,
we're assuming that
there's going be
no more late events coming
in for this window, right?
And so the answer would be 11:00
A.M. Yeah, thanks for Aster.
Yeah, you follow ups on that
or other questions people have?
There here.
Oh, yeah, that's a really
good question, right?
So I guess, does group B
only work I guess this is a
question about water bark.
Does water Mark work
with group by or
does it work with
other things as well?
The other thing that
group Bi can work
with is streaming joid.
And in particular, we talked
about, like, different
joids, right?
The simplest case is we have two
tables that are a fixed size.
A little bit more
complicated is we have
a fixed sized table
and a growing table.
And the most complicated is we
have two tables
that are growing.
When you're oid, you try to.
Can I pair up this row and
the first table with another
row and the second table.
And by default, that could
take a lot of memory, right?
Because if I see a row, I
don't know what story
happen to the future
on the other table.
I'm like, do I have
to remember this row?
The answer is, yes,
because I never know what
at to have a new pair
of the other one.
So if I'm joining
on Type windows,
then I could also
use watermarks for
that stream stream Joi.
Are there other use cases?
Maybe? Those are the two that
only two that I know about?
I gro grouping by a Te window or
stream Stream Joid a
like on a type window?
Yeah, thanks for Ay.
Yeah, other questions people
have about that or other stuff.
Right here. Question I
can't remember which one I
saw something to do
with text Oh, yeah.
There's the texting your
friend question that I asked.
So what was about item pots.
Cody remind me what item
potent is want to defin it?
Stuff. Yeah, maybe it's related.
Anybody pop it does to
fight item pots for me?
Yeah. Yeah, go for it. Does it.
So item pots means that
whatever the operation is Like,
when I do an operation,
it changes the state
of some system.
Maybe it changes the
values of database
or whatever. Some operations.
If I do them a bunch of times,
I'll have a different result,
and if I do them what,
that's not item potent.
If it's item potent,
it means I can
do the same thing
a bunch of times,
and I have the same end result.
And that means that when we
have systems that have retry.
When I have retry,
that's how I end
up with a bunch of
duplicate operations.
If I have retry in combination
with itepots, that's fine.
I'm still going to have
exactly what Semantics,
because it doesn't matter
if I do it one time
or many times.
So it's really important to
remember the context of retry.
Ip means that if you
do it multiple times,
it's the same as if
you did at once.
Yeah, other questions
people have.
But he
Yeah, right here.
Yeah, aabicity related
to apoda, right?
Well, I guess, topic
means that there's multiple
things we're trying to do.
We either all or nothing, right?
Yeah. It's often
related I guess,
if we are, Like,
if I'm trying to perform
some operation, right?
I might try to do it multiple
times. What is that?
I want to make sure if
I do it multiple times,
I end up with the same result.
If that operation is
kind of complicated,
I also want to make sure
I don't at a state where
the operation is
half done, right?
So yeah, it's another way I
might describe an operation.
Oftentimes we want both, right?
Yeah, question. Yeah other
questions people have?
All right. Well, let's
other questions.
I'm happy to end
early today, too.
I said, there's a question
right over here. Yep.
Yeah, can we do Q Saba.
Okay, so Spark uses
the plant algorithm to
trade decision trees.
The type of job that runs
on a set of decision tree nodes,
depends on whether
those nodes have
few enough rows to run
the abbery algorithm.
For the abbary case, the
job uses hash partitioning.
What does it partitions, right?
Okay, so, would we have
this decision tree,
like we're constantly
growing it, right?
So at given point in time,
we have a decision tree,
even if we're not done, and
I also have my full dataset.
And if I look at any given row,
I can place it somewhere
in the partially
complete tree based on,
like, the questions
in each node, right?
And so if I look at
my whole dataset,
and I look at my
partially complete tree,
There are some nodes that
have a lot of rows in them.
To many rows to fit in memory.
And there might be other nodes
that are partially
complete tree,
where all of those nodes would
fit in memory somewhere.
And when they all fit
in memory somewhere,
then the fastest thing to do is
just put them all in memory,
and then keep growing
the tree, right?
I have that node and
maybe I split it.
I have like two
children. I split those.
I have four grandchildren.
I just I kind of bring
it all together,
and I keep running that in
memory algorithm fast, right?
And so b rows, right,
they're kind of spread over
lots of different machines.
And so I have to bring them
all together in one place.
And that should kind to remind
you of a group by, right?
Like, if I want to count
everything for some group,
I have to bring
together related data.
Same thing if I want to
trade on all the rows
of decision tree.
So this case, what
are we grouping by?
We are going to group
the decision tree
node that the row
belongs to, right?
So all the rows that belong to
the same decision
tree node are end
up in memory on one single
computer at one place.
Yeah. Any follow ups on
that or does it make sense?
Yeah, good question. Yeah
the questions people have.
I guess I can opt
I just want to
clarify what they're
outputting after working
on those partitioning.
If they're outputting a
statistic or some type
of condition and then the other
notes I I forgot what
they specifically out.
I know it's not Yes.
So what is our final output
for the planet algorithm.
We want to have a description
of all the nodes of the tree,
and we want to know
for each node,
what question it should
be asked, right?
So that job input is, well,
all the nodes for that all
the rows for that node,
the output would be
a sub tree that we
could place inside
of the bigger tree.
You, relative to
the data itself,
like the tree is of
a reasonable size,
it's fine to send it
around over the network
and collect it all in
one place in the area.
We aren't worried about
the tree being too big.
We're just worried about having
too much data in the tree.
Yeah, thanks for asking.
Yeah, maybe I'll just seems
like people are
already out question.
If there's more, that's fine.
So I'll just leave
the last thoughts.
Like I said, right, we care
about those five big systems.
Something that we
talked about repeatedly
was partitioning,
so we can be, scaling out.
And so you should be, ask
yourself, like, Well,
how does partitioning
working smart,
work at HHF,
be able to think
about that and try to
write it down, right?
Same thing with replication.
How does a system
replicate data, if so?
Where does replication happen?
Be able to write that down
for each of the systems.
Now, based on replication,
that's often for fault
tolerance, right?
So you should be able to ask
yourself in this system,
what happens if a computer dies
or there's some other
type of problem, right?
I think maybe Smart is a
little different, but
for most of these,
we want to think
about, well, how do we
avoid losing data, right?
How do we cover that?
Right? So what I do.
You start with all the
major systems and say
partitioning replication,
fault tolerance, right?
Try to write all
those things down.
And once you do that,
then you can start
to have you know,
there's lots of smaller
details fed at Ed,
but that's probably, like,
a big picture for each of these.
Alright, so feel free to
come up and chat if you
have any questions,
and I hope you all have
a great rest of the day.