Streaming. And in particular,
we're going to be looking
a little bit more
at how Spark works
for streaming.
Spark could be
reading from Kafka,
or it could be reading
from other sources.
When you're using Kafka,
it's totally fine to write
producers and consumers
yourselves, right?
When we're using Spark,
then Spark totally is
either a producer or a consumer
of Kafka. So we'll do that.
If we have time today, we
might even do a little bit
ahead and start talking
about the cloud a bit.
But first start by
looking at some top hat.
So won't you whip out
your phone? All right.
About 30 seconds left.
Oh, right. So people are saying
empty the cat's litter
box, which is correct.
The question you're trying
to ask here is that
if you do the same
thing more than what,
will the vital state be
different than if
you did at Oly Was?
So, for example, if
I feed the dog and I
feed the dog again,
the dog will be more full
than if ally fed at wts.
If I decrease the thermostat
by two and, I do it again,
well, it would be four degrees
less instead of
two degrees less.
So the only one here
where we really end up in
the same state is if we
empty the cat's litter box,
and we et again, the vital state
is still an empty litter box.
All right. Any questions
about item pot? All right.
Cool. Sundry ahead over here
and go back to these slides.
So where we were
ending last time
is we were talking about
these different output mode,
and we're doing spark
streaming, right?
And a lot of these have to
do when we get a
new batch of data,
how can we process it, right?
And what will the output be?
So we saw in some cases the
output mode would be a PED.
And what that means
is that, you know,
we have some previous
data that's computed,
but we can just a
pen new results,
new output based on
new input without
really thinking about those
previous results, right?
So we can just ignore
what's previous.
For complete, that's usually
used when we have some
kind of rolling cout or
some other kind of rolling
aggregate In that case,
what we're doing is we're
dumping out the whole state of
the results based on
both the new data and
previous data, right?
So in this case, we
previously had A seven B A,
when we get a new
B and C coming in,
then we're putting out
the couts for A and C.
We're out putting
A aga even though,
A was just purely
old data, right,
where we have a kind of a
complete snapshot every time.
That's okay if the complete
snapshot is small enough, right?
And then finally, this
one only works with
some systems where you could
update a row in the middle.
In this case, I'm
doing a count again,
and I have A and B before,
and I have two B values.
What I could do
is I could update
whatever final storage system is
there without changing
the other things, right?
So, you know, if I have like
a biccal database or
something like that,
maybe I could do it.
If I have par K files at HDFS,
I cannot just modify a row
in the middle of a
par K file, right?
So sometimes I could do
that or sometimes not.
Alright, I want to
talk a little bit
about crash recovery in Spark.
And that's something
I kind of de
emphasize for most of it.
If you look at the different
systems we've learned about,
we have three systems that
can store data, right?
We have HDFS,
Cassandra, and Kafka.
And in each of
those cases, right,
if the system goes down, we
might lose some data, right?
With Spark, a lot of the
data that we're processing,
while it actually lives
somewhere else, right?
Spark is using data
that's in HDFS,
for example, and anything
that is producing,
right, we might
produce other data,
but it's something that
we could draw back and
recalculate it if we
needed to, right?
And so fault tolerance is not
quite as critical in
both Spark cases.
But We might sometimes
worry about it for
performance reasons, right?
So sometimes kind of a
fault tolers problem
becomes a performance problem
in a system like Spark.
So I brat a show here how I
have a Spark stream again.
I have all these batches,
and they're depending
on each other.
And what I want to
do is I want to
imagine what would happen
if I lost some data,
you know, maybe for that RDD,
maybe one of the
partitions of that was
Ata Mashed that died, right?
And so how are we going
to deal with that?
Okay? So one of the things
that we could do that they do,
like the default, is they
just reproduce all
of those results,
right? They'll run
all those things.
And if you have a large cluster,
they could actually
use the whole cluster
to quickly recover.
That's one thing they will do,
right, to get back
to that state.
But even still we have
some problems, right?
It's possible that,
If it's like PCA,
we have some retention policy,
maybe I can't replay from the
beginning of time, right?
Or even if I can,
maybe it would take
too long, right?
So what they'll do is they'll
just checkpoint that D stream.
You know, every
somebody batches,
I think, like, ten by default.
And so, yeah, we lose something.
They'll go back
and recompute it,
but they don't have
to go as far back as,
you know, to the
beginning of time.
Alright, so those are D Streams.
That was the fundamental
idea of Spark streaming.
I'm re look at some different
operations you could do with it,
and how they differ from
just static analysis
on fixed data.
Okay. So one of the things
we'll often want to
do is we will have incremental
aggregates, right?
So in this case, maybe
I'm counting dim,
sharks dolphins and sea gulls,
and then I will have a new
batch of data coming in.
And we can actually write
this in the same way we would
write a normal
sequel query, right?
I can say select dim cout
star from sightings, right?
So a lot of things that we could
do just like regular SQL,
we could do here as well,
now that we are streaming.
Now what I want you
to think about is
as we read these operations is,
how much state do I
have to keep in memory?
And in this case, it's
really the size of those,
you know, partial counts, right?
Those kind of ever
up dated counts.
However many rows are there.
That's how much stat I have
to keep in memory, right?
Sometimes it's a problem,
and sometimes it's not.
I also want to talk about
if we're doing a group by,
how we would actually
do that tputation.
And so what I see here is a
picture we've seen before,
where we have a bunch
of input partitions,
and I'm trying to do a group
bi and some aggregate.
And what I have to
do is I have to
bring together related data.
So by default, what
we're going to do
is we're going to hash
the key for that row,
and then we'll mod it by
the number of partitions.
And that could be anything.
If I mod it by ten, then
I'd have ten partitions.
If I mod it by 200,
I have 200 partitions, and
200 is a default, right?
So I have 200 ptitions here.
And that can be
a problem because if I
have 200 partitions here,
anything downstream, well,
we have to start one,
spark task for each partition.
That's a lot of partitions,
and there's going
to be a start up
overhead if those are small.
So normally, right, they have
a feature called
partition coalescing,
we'll realize a lot of
these partitions are
small they'll automatically
combine them for you.
And it's doing that by actually
looking at them and see,
these two are kind of
small or that one's big,
so I'll leave that one alone.
What we're doing streaming,
we can't really get
that kind of histograb,
or those stats about
how it's distributed
across that because most of
the data is still
coming in the future.
Maybe the distribution
might change later.
And so they don't have
that optimization.
And so it so be very
important that you tube
that SQL shuffle partitions,
right, to make it something
reasonable for your jobs.
Oh, right. So, a couple of
things there to keep in
mind for performance.
Let's talk about watermarks.
So we've already
seen how group buys
have to keep those kind of
rolling counts for each thing.
You know, the more
rolling counts you have,
the more state you have.
One situation where
we're doing a group
by is we're grouping by
time intervals, right?
And so here I have
animals, I say group by.
And instead of having
just a single column,
I say a window,
which is based on
the time sap in
15 minute intervals, right?
So I kind of want to chuck in
50 minute intervals and
know during each chuck,
how how many couts there were.
Okay? And so this is a problem
because we have to keep
that state up here.
Why we have to keep a count
for each time window.
And, of course, time
goes up forever.
And so this in memory state
that I keep is just
going to grow.
And definitely, if
it grows too fast,
and eventually, I'll
run out of rab, right?
So we have to worry about that.
And so what we would like
to do is we'd like to say,
You know, we have
the dt of coming in.
Is there ever any point in
time where I could throw
away some of these rolling cots.
For example, you
know, in a few days,
I'm probably not getting more
records from today, right?
You know, Kaka has delays
for various reasons,
but those delays are probably
within reason, right?
And so to deal with that,
they attribute to something
called a watermark, right?
So I have the same
kind of group by over
here by the window,
timestamp window.
But I may say that
these rows that are coming he
will not be delayed by
more than 8 hours, right?
How do you choose that? I don't
know if there's a good
way to choose that.
It's a little bit
hard to say, right?
Because if I have Kafka and
some machine style, well,
how long does it take
me to actually get in
the data center and
maybe replace those?
Maybe if it's in the
cloud, maybe it's fast,
but who knows, right?
So things could be delayed.
But if you have some kind
of conservative estimate,
you can say, Hey, like, data is
never going to be
more than eight.
Hours late, and then
you could potentially
start deleting some
of these, right?
Now, in this case, right?
I have time window
starting at 12:00.
Okay, it's a 15 minute te
window that goes 12-1215.
And data can only
be 8 hours late.
And that means at 8:15,
the system can assume
there's going to be
no more data coming in
for that rolling cout,
and it could delete that it
can free up some memory.
Do you have any
questions about that
strategy of a water bark?
Alright. Cl. I
want to talk about
some operations that we
cannot do with Spark Strab.
One of them is a
pivot operation.
Pivot might be new
to some folks.
The idea of a pivot
is that I have
two columns that are kind of
relating beach to animal.
And what I want to
do is I want to get
a table that's kind
of shorter and wider,
that's going to
help me basically
cross tabulate, like, Well,
for a given beach,
a given animal,
I'll have the beaches on
the rows and the
animals on the columns.
I can see. For each combination,
how many there are, right?
That's called a pivot, right?
I'll be able to do a pivot here.
And all these
values that were in
the animal column actually
become their own column, right?
So Bach A Seagull,
I have two of them.
And so what happens
if we have this data,
this data frame that's
always growing,
and what happens if we
get a new row of data?
Let's say that it's edible or a
beach that we've
never seen before.
Okay. So what might happen is I
might end up having to
add rows to the output,
or I might end up having to
add columns to the output.
Right? And if I'm
adding new rows,
that's totally okay whether
I'm doing either streaming,
which what we're doing
now, or batching,
which is everything we did
with Spark previously, right?
The problem with
adding a new column is
that we can only do it
for batching, right?
When I do this pivot, I'm
creating a data frame,
and other jobs should be able
to query from that data frame.
And when you're querying
from a data frame,
you need to know what
columns are there
and what types are there, right?
And so if it's batching, fine,
we can just look at
the data and figure
out what the columns are
going to be in advance.
But if it's streaming, right if
I have a streaming data frame,
and somebody needs to know
what the columns are.
Well, we don't know yet
because we don't know
what data is going to show
up in the future, right?
If you try to go, for example,
and try to do a pivot,
It'll work fine for a batch job,
but if you have a
streaming data frame,
you cannot do a
pivot audit, right?
Because downstream, other
people cannot compute over it.
Does the difference
make sense there?
Why it's okay for batching,
but not streaming?
Any questions there? Oh, right.
Cool. Let's talk
about joining too.
Now, when I'm doing a oid,
right, I have different
data frames, right?
And it's possible that
it's either just like
a regular fixed sized
data frame or it's
one of these stream
big data frames.
Okay. And we could do the
different combinations,
right, maybe they're
both fixed size.
I mean, that's what we've
always done so far.
Maybe one of them is growing,
the other one is fixed, or
maybe they're even
both growing, right?
And so Spark actually
supports all of these.
I just want to remind
us of the context here.
Everything we've done so far
was just having two fixed,
and we had two different
strategies for that.
There was SMJ, which is
the shu sort Merge oi.
And then the broadcast stoid.
And the idea for
those was that with the
shuffle sort mergtoid,
we bring related data
together in the same place
with hash partitioning,
and then we would sort the data,
that after we have the data
sorted we have a chunk of
data for both of them,
and they're both sorted,
we could loop over them
and order and pair
them up, right?
That's like a merge sort, right?
With the broadcast astoid,
what we do is we take
the smaller table,
convert it to a
dictionary and send it to
literally every single machine
that's involved in the joy,
right that all those
machines would
loop over pieces of
the bigger table,
and they could do look ups on
that smaller table, right?
So those are we
covered before we saw
two different strategies
for two fixed tables.
Now we're looking at cases
where one or more of
the tables is growing, right?
One of the challenges
here, right,
is that when we're trying
to pair up these rows.
If I see a row and I'm like,
Well, what does it pair with?
It's a little hard to know
what it pairs with
because there's
more data potentially
coming, right?
So when we're doing joys,
rough going to have
to hang out to
rows longer than we
would want to, right?
And so water marketing,
just like for
the grouping is ready
to be useful here.
Okay. Let's look at this
first case where we have,
they call it a
streaming data frame
is joining with a
static data frame.
Alright, here I have
animals up here, which
is a fixed table.
And down here, I have sightings,
where people are saying
animals on beaches, right?
So I guess on Bach A,
somebody saw Adimal three,
which is a sea gull. All right.
And so what I'm saying
here is a big ergoid.
I want to say what node
animals do we see?
They're known because
the ergoid will not
produce an output row
unless I can pair them up.
So, for example, what I
see on Beach C, I
saw Adimal four.
Well, there is no animal four.
It's not a node animal,
and so that will not
be in the results.
Okay, so we have this
as the sites increase,
the outputs, which we'll
think this over here,
will also be increasing.
So I'm wondering if this is
to be a stateless operation.
I just try to see
what people think.
Why do you say thumbs up?
If this is a
stateless operation?
Thumbs down if it is not
a stateless operation?
People are t divided 50 50 here.
It is stateless. Does
anybody want to volunteer?
Why this is stateless?
Somebody who had a thumbs up?
Why do you think it's stateless?
Right here. Ext. It doesn't
depend on anything that
happened beforehand.
So the question
we're asking, right?
Is if I have a new
edible sighting,
and I need to figure out what
new output rows to output,
do I care what happened prior
to the table that straying?
The answer is, No,
if I have a new input sighting,
I can pair it up with animals,
and then I can output it.
It doesn't depend on the
history of the table a straw.
This is a stateless operation.
All right, Let's do this.
So I want to see, are there
any sightings of no animals?
And that would be what
I want to do is I want to
make sure that the
sightings show up,
even if it doesn't
pair with anything.
So I do a left oid.
That means every
single sighting is
to show up after the left choid.
And then after that, I'm saying,
well, the name animal
name isn't all.
And so not only am I making
every animal show up,
that I'm filtering
to the ones that
could not pair with
the original table.
That will help me
quickly identify,
well, there is no animal four.
We saw some mysterious
animal on Beach C, right?
I could do that. All right.
Let's do a right
oid in this case.
Alright? I want to know,
are there any animals that
have never been seed?
And so what I'm trying
to say is y animal up
here should be in the output.
And I specifically filtered out.
So I only have these
beaches and well
those names with there was
no associated beach, right?
So it was an animal that
was never seed on a beach.
Okay? This is something
that we would
do all the time for
a static static oid.
But now that I have
the sits growing,
why is this not a
reasonable operation to do?
Yeah, right here. Changing.
Right. Yeah. The second table
is changing as I'm
writing the query.
And so at no point could I say
this animal was never seen
because I'm always
concating new data, right?
How can I say it was never
seed? Once that output,
I say this animal is never seed,
I can't retract it later, right?
This is going to be run with
some kind of like
a pen moot, right?
I said Oh this animals
never seed it was.
I just said something
that was wrong, right?
So there's some types of joins,
right? That we're used to doing.
Normally, joins will work the
same way as you'd expect,
but there's some
joins like this where
Spark will just like not
let you run the query.
What I do here is build
some intuition, right?
If you're trying
to do like a pivot
or certain types of joins.
Sobody all reject it.
If you kind of think
about what it's doing
internally, right?
When we have some
data that's growing,
you can see why
that's not possible.
People have any
questions about that?
Right. So one of
the things that we want to do
is think about how this
is happening, right?
So we get a new batch of data.
Remember that we have this
table that's growing,
and we're processing at
one batch at a time.
And so if I get a
small little batch
of data here from
the growing table,
what I have to do is I
have to join it across
that entire fixed table.
And that could potentially
be expensive because I
get a small new batch,
and then I have to read
it the entire fixed table
from some PA files
and HDFS ahead.
Right? So one of the really
important performance tt,
if you're doing this
kind of streaming joid
is that you really well,
you will hope that the
fixed table fits in memory,
and if so, you're
definitely going to
want to cache that, right?
Be something that you're
repeatedly going to.
Again, and you have
to go to it for
just a very small amount
of new data, right?
So you'll try to cache that
if you can. Oh, alright.
Let's talk about the
stream stream oid,
which is the most
complicated one.
And so in this case,
what are we doing?
I guess we have Beach
closures, right?
On a specific date,
they're closing
the beach either for some of
the day or all of the day.
And then we have animal
sightings, right?
I guess here, like, you
know, seagull or shark.
And what we want to know is
how many sharks are seen
on days when the beach
is closed. Okay?
So what are we doing?
I guess we're joining
the sightings to the
closures, right?
And then we want to see, right?
We're matching the up by date,
we're looking for when
the animal was a shark.
And then we want to see, well,
how many of those
shark sightings
were there on those days
where there was a closure.
Okay? And so the
challenge, right, is that,
as I'm getting these
new sightings, right,
I cannot forget about
previous closures, right?
Like, if there was a beach
closure on the 14th, right?
Need to keep that
in memory, right?
Because I might get a sighting
on the 14th at
some point, right?
And so what this means
is that I'm going to
have to keep all this
data in memory forever.
Because I never know, I'm
going to have to pair it with
something in the other table,
right? Spark will do this.
I just know, eventually,
you're about out of
memory, if the data is
coming in at a reasonable rate.
And so the only time you can
really do this
reasonably with you have
a lot of data is where
you have to have
water marks, right?
If we say, for example,
that the Adimal sightings,
which I pulling off
some Tropica stream,
are not delayed by
more than a week,
then eventually, right, that I
could forget about that
there was some closure.
All right. Do you have any
questions about water barks or
why they're useful for
the stream stream joid?
All right. I want to talk
about exactly what sematics.
That was something we talked
about a lot when we were
looking at when we
were looking at Kafka.
We also have to worry
about when we're writing
Spark code because we
saw that to get
exactly what somatics,
you have to do some
careful things
in your Kafka consumers,
and guess what?
Well, Spark is a Kafka
consumer, right?
So how can we make sure we
get exactly what sebatics,
right? And in particular, right?
We're running the spart task
and a spart task could crash,
maybe the machine that was dies,
and maybe that task
restarted somewhere else.
So to get exactly
what Semantics,
that means that when we crash
in the middle of a
task and then restart,
we don't want to go back
and double coded y row.
And we also don't want to
skip a rows we restart it.
Okay? So if Spark
We'll make sure that
we have exactly what if
you do three things.
First off, you need to have
your code be derbstic, right?
If they restarted, run
it somewhere else,
it has to do exactly the same
thing it did the
first time, right?
There can be no
randomness involved.
Okay? The other thing
is that if it's crashing
and restarting,
your system has to support
that task to be able to go
back and re read those
same messages, right?
All right, so we have
to support that.
And with CAPCA, right, as
long as we have some kind
of reasonable retention period,
we're ready to be able to.
And then finally, we need to
have some kind of sake of
data that could suppress
duplicates, right?
So what we're really
doing, right?
Is like, we're dating
these messages,
and then we're outputting
something somewhere,
and we want some kind of
system that can say, Oh,
these outputs were based
on these messages.
And if I have the same messages
that are producing
this output again,
well, I don't want to
have duplicate output.
Okay, so often will be
the file sake for us is maybe
some part files at HTFS.
They actually support that.
In addition to just having
a directory of park files
that we keep populating,
there are going to be these
checkpoint files that
have some metadata
describing well,
which output files correspond
to which messages.
So we might actually end up with
some duplicates of the output,
but we'll have metadata
that says, Hey,
there's some of
these messages in
the park files that you
should ignore, right?
So if you want to
get that, remember
that we have some
kind of query, right?
That some type of
streaming data frame,
and we're writing it and
we're writing to Park.
We have some path in HTFS
where we're writing it to.
What we have to do is we have to
have some checkpoint location,
directory where we're store
that extra Mt metadata.
That can help us supress
duplicates, right?
That will all be
fded well. And then
there's some caveats
here, right?
If you have this directory
of Park files with
the checkpoint,
and Spark is trying
to read that later.
Spark knows about this kind of
checkpointing addition
to Park files.
And so Spark will suppress
the duplicates when you
read that collection
of Park files, right?
If you have this collection of
park files and
you're trying to use
subsystem that's not Spark,
then you can have
duplicates, right?
Because not all tools
that know about
Park files know about
this checkpoint thing
that Spark does.
All right. Well, we
any questions about
exactly what semantics
there? All right.
Excuse me. So just a
few conclusions, right?
The original big idea
in Spark was RDDs,
resilient distribute data sets.
So, of course, they built
D streams on top of that.
You know, they built data
frames on top of RDDs.
And so that's very natural
that to have a
streaming data frame on
top of RDDs that are part of
a D stream as well, right?
Most of the things you could
do are the same, right?
We saw a couple of
caveats like with
the suydes of joins or pivots,
but mostly it's the same.
One of the things
that was a little bit
different from Spark to
prior Strivi systems
is that a lot of
prior Striv systems we just
try to put one row
through at a time,
which was not necessarily
as efficient.
So Spark, you know, there's
a little more of a delay.
We're waiting till we have
kind of a nice batch of data,
but it probably has
higher throughput,
and it also makes crash
recovery a little easier.
That we kind of have these
batches that we have to
just rerun through the system.
There was a performance sip
that I shared along the way.
Maybe the biggest one
is that you're often
doing group buys and joins.
And so you have to
really choose the
shuffle partition
count carefully.
200 is often a bad default.
If we're doing like a
stream stream joid,
or if we are doing
a group by on time,
we're going to keep having
more and more state
and memory to keep
these rolling couts.
And so watermarks
are the solution.
Watermark say that input data
cannot be delayed by too much.
Therefore, eventually
we can delete data.
And then finally, if you're
doing a stream static joind,
we don't want to have
to keep rereading
the static table from HTFS,
so that's something we
should really try to cache
in memory, if at all possible.
Alright, C. So
that's all I have to
say about streaming
this semester.
Any questions about streaming
in general? Alright, Fantastic.
So I have a chance to start,
actually get a ahead for
one before we start
talking about the Cloud.
Really that's the third third
and final piece of the semester.
While we're on the cloud,
I also want to bring
your attention to an announcement
I just made on Tavis.
Let me just slide it here.
So, you know, I've
been e mail you back
and forth with Google.
They finally just
approved us for
some more credits, right?
So you should d row it, and
you should redeem this.
The main reason is that
for Project eight,
we're going be using Big query,
which is a service that's
all the ogle Clouds.
You'll definitely need
credits. The CSL VMs
will not be relevant to P eight.
And also, I think for P seven,
it's nice to have a
backup system, right?
I shared some tips
last time about
how to recover your CSL VM.
But, you know, this is
a nice backup where
you can try to get up and
running a little
bit more quickly.
Here you do is here
you go to this lake,
there'll be some
e mails back and
forth where they
confirm your e mail,
and then you fill out
some information.
They send you a coupon code.
And there click through,
and you're going to apply
that coupon code
to your account.
And let me just show you
what that looks like.
So when I pm here,
I go to billing,
There's this badage
billing accounts.
And one of the things
you see is that every
time that you redeem one
of these new coupon codes,
they create a new
billing account for you.
Right? It's a little
bit confusing because
I guess they have
this billing code ID,
but they have exactly
the same name.
So it's a little hard to tell
which one is which, right?
So if you're using the wrong
one, you have to switch.
And the way this works is
that you can have a billing
account for either,
like a credit card or
for these free credits
they gave you.
We also, the way you
organize this is
that you're creating
a virtual machine
and the virtual
machine belongs to a project,
and the project is associated
with a billing account.
So I can see that if I
click on these projects,
I've been using the CS
544 fall of 24 project,
where I create my Vb,
and that's associated with
this billing account right here.
And so what's do happen, right?
Is that you're a run out of
credit on your first
billing account.
They'll probably shut
down your VM for a while.
And go here say,
Well, I want to change
the billy, right?
So I still want to be a Bill C
for education, but not this one.
I want to switch to other
one. So I will change it.
And then, you know,
it's a paid because I
can't see which is which.
So you try what if
it doesn't work,
then try the other one.
I need to switch it over to
the Bill account that has
that new $25 credit, right?
And then, you know,
you can keep cred VMs
until we use up that credit.
Any questions about that
credit credit system
or the Bill accounts
versus projects? Alright, Col.
So let's head over
here to the slides.
And I'm just trying to give
a broad overview of the cloud.
And I think it's a
hard lecture to give,
maybe relative to some of
the other ones because,
well, what is the Cloud?
There's a lot of different cloud
providers out there,
like, you know,
Amazon has AWS and
Microsoft has Azure.
And each of these things have,
literally hundreds of services,
and all of these services
are changing over time.
And so if I'm just like
talking about like the Cloud,
it's a little bit hard
to say things that are
generally This is a
little bit subjective
at times, right?
I try to see, share
some things that
I've seen that are
kind of commonalities,
right when you're
doing cloud computing,
that will kind of
help you navigate.
Oh There's this new
Cloud service out there.
Like how should I start
thinking about it?
Okay. Alright, I have
a few goals for you.
One is that I want you
to be able to recall
some different things
that might show up
on your Cloud bill, right?
Maybe you have your VM
or maybe you have the
storage for your VM,
or maybe you're paying
for some network yo.
Right? You should
understand a little bit
about the kinds of things
they're going to charge you for.
The other one is that there
are all these cloud offerings,
which are called platform
as a service offerings
that resemble various systems
we've learned this
semester, right?
There's systems out there
that resemble HDFS.
And so I want to look at
some of these, non free,
no open source systems that
are equivalent, right?
Try to see, Okay,
if you want to just
like pay somebody to
manage this for you,
instead of managing yourself,
well, what would that
system look like?
And then finally,
you know, as I said,
there's hundreds of different,
cloud services out there.
I just want to go kind of do
a deep dive on one,
which is big query.
I I want to be able to describe
a big query and how it
relates to other systems
that interacts with them.
All right, so a little
bit of background,
right, is that, you know,
back in 2006, Abazon Cloud
launched this service called
EC two Elastic Compute.
And that was on AWS,
which it was the Cloud.
And what they would basically
do is they would have
a bunch of physical machines
in their data seer,
and they would
have VMs on there.
They would rent
them to you, right?
And this is what we call
we called infrastructure
as a service.
So things like CPUs or
RAP or something that
looks like a virtual debt.
All those things really kind of
look like hardware, even
if they're virtual.
And so infrastructure
service means that you're
renting those resources
from a cloud provider,
instead of actually owning
that hardware yourself.
Right at the blog they
originally released it,
they pointed out something
that is really interesting.
Sometimes you need a lot
of processing power,
and sometimes you need
just a little bit,
and sometimes you need a lot
for a short at of time, right?
And so Even if they're kind
of marketing up the rate at
which they rent this to you,
you might save money
overall, right?
Because your needs for
hardware resources
are probably not CTs.
If they are, it's probably
cheaper for you to buy
your own hardware,
but most of the time,
they're not, right?
You can kind of pay and rent
more or less based on
your current needs.
This really powerful cot set.
Let me just give
an example here.
So this billing that I have
here is for E two media sets,
and it says that you're paying
$25 a month. Okay, so great.
So we can have one BM
for a month for $25.
Now, I also want to think about
how many hours are a month.
There's 744 hours in a month.
And that means instead
of having one Vb
for a whole month,
something you could
do is you could have
744 Vb running for just 1 hour.
And that would cost you $25.
That's affordable,
and it's something
that you could even get
free credit for, right?
It's very powerful, right?
You think, like, Oh,
like, 700 machines.
Well, that's actually something
any of us could do, right?
We could set up 700 machines
and get something done.
Right? How powerful
is that, right?
If you have your own machine,
and you have to wait
a month, right?
But now it's the same price
that we could get done at
an hour if we can figure out
how to distribute our work.
There's a extremely
powerful concept, right?
That's, you know, available
to anybody, right?
There are some caveats
there. What is that?
You can't just spit up some of
our machines like start
debugging and being slow.
Cause all of a sudden you'll
be debugging for a few hours,
and you'll run up the cross.
If you want to do
that, you have, have
all your code ready to go,
have tooling around
it, you know,
get it running, get
your job done, right?
Another thing is that, I
think when we talk
about optimization,
a lot of what people think
about for optimization is,
they're trying to make
something run faster, right?
And in the cloud,
it's often possible to write
very in efficient code.
And work with very big data.
It still haven't
run extremely fast.
But the consequences that you
have a very large bill, right?
So when you're in the cloud,
maybe we think a little
bit less about time,
we think a little bit more
about how much you're
paying to get certain
jobs done, right?
Now, the costs are
going to be expensive.
I want to highlight
the different areas where
the costs will come from.
And what you should
always be doing is doing
a little bit of a back
of envelope computation.
So, how much will this do?
So you don't get
surprises, right?
It's time that people
get billing surprises.
And you want to think, well,
these are the main things
they're charging for.
This is about what
they're going to charge
me if I'm doing X Y or Z.
Okay, so that was
how it started,
right? We just would rent VMs.
And now, of course, AS has
over twoter different services,
very broadly, we
might categorize
those services in two buckets.
So what we call
infrastructure service,
and that means that,
the definitions
are a little bit fuzzy people
might define these differently,
that means like the
thing you're renting
resembles relatively low level
resources is maybe kind of
close to raw hardware
or maybe slightly
above that, right?
So I can have like
virtual discs or
virtual networks or you know,
certain storage siss
fall into that category.
It's relatively
cheap and flexible.
It's cheap because a lot of
the cloud providers
are providing
similar infrastructure service.
And so if they
urge you too much,
while you just row heelsewhere.
And it's flexible as you
whatever you want it, right?
You could putch a sandra or
Kaka or anything, right?
The other bucket of services is
called platform as
a service PAAS.
And in this case, right rather
than just giving you like
the virtual machines,
they deployed some
software on it.
Maybe they deployed Cassandra
or something like
that for you, right?
Maybe they have some
kind of cloud database
or some kind of
programming framework
or some ML model trading system,
right? All these things.
These things are less flexible
because they're deploying
very specific software,
but it's easier to use.
I think what you've
all seen is that
big challenge in this course
is not just like
writing the code,
it's actually like
getting your cluster
up and writing and
connecting to it.
You know, it's easier,
somebod else does
that for you, but
then you pay them
for that, right?
These things are usually
more expensive, right?
Because they're
providing more service.
But that's not
always true, right?
Because they have the
ability to kind of
scale up and down, whereas,
if I'm, you know,
deploying casado myself,
maybe it's harder for
me to do that, right?
And again, right,
the lie between
these two categories
is a bit subjective.
On a related concept,
I want to talk about
this idea of locked.
The idea of locked is
that you start using
a specific cloud provider
or some of the services,
and for various reasons,
it's very hard for
you to move to a
different cloud provider,
even if they're
increasing the cost.
If they're increasing the cost,
and it's hard for you to move.
That means you're
locked in, right?
There's a couple ways
you can be locked in.
What is for these
platform as a service?
A lot of those things
are very unique systems
that are built by
that cloud provider?
There's to be another
cloud provider
that has the exact same systems.
That means that migrating to
something that's
cheaper will actually
mean you rewrite the
code application, right?
So for any kind of
platform a service,
you have a little
bit worried, right?
Not just about what
the cost is now,
but how much paid will you
be in if they, you know,
double the price, how road
will you have to
rewrite to go use
something somewhere else, right?
Infrastructure for the
service, it's less risky.
I mean, a VM on Azure
feels like a VM on
D Google feels like a VM
on AWS. You can try
to move around.
The other way they try to lock
you in is with your data.
So what they'll often do,
and they'll look at this in
more detail is that they'll
make it free to
have data address.
They'll make it free to upload
your data to their systems.
But then when you try
to pull your data out,
they'll charge you per
byte of data you're
pulling out, right?
That could actually
be kind of expensive.
Right? So in other case,
we have to kind of think,
are they go to lock you out or
maybe you should have some of
your own data that's
outside of the Cloud.
So if you need to
move somewhere else,
then maybe you don't have to
download everything, right?
So a different consideration.
But let's look a little bit
at how important the
cloud is, right?
So this is the kind of
worldwide revenue across
all the different
cloud providers.
And what we see is
that even though,
you know, we're talking
about the Cloud b,
something like 10-years-old now,
more than 10-years-old, we
see it's still growing
exponentially.
And we're talking about
this case where maybe
the different cloud providers
are jostling for position,
who's the biggest cloud or not,
but even though they're
all jostling for position,
they aren't fighting over a
fixed size market, right?
They're all growing, right?
And, you know, of course, they
all want to be the
biggest provider.
You know, all these major
cloud companies are
building data ceters
like crazy, right?
Like, this was last
year it was Google,
which, as you saw
was maybe like the
third biggest player.
And so they have all these
data ceters around the world,
and they're constantly
billing them.
And that's good, too, because
if you have some kind of
application that
people are using,
you want to pick a place
to run your application
that's near your
customers, right?
Your websites will feel
less laggy, right?
You'll have lower latency
as people are using
your applications.
Alright, cool. So let's talk
about the way we organize this.
I want to kind of
go back to things
we learned earlier
this semester.
And so at the very
start of the semester,
we talked about CPU,
Maury, storage, and network.
I I'll be looking at
those four resources
and say a little bit
about each of them,
as we're kind of using those
resources in the Cloud.
We're talking about
billing models
and how we pay for
those resources.
And then the fourth
piece will be platforms.
And I'll be look at
the four major systems
we've learned in the second
piece of the course,
and I'll see what are some
similar cloud based systems.
Alright, let's talk about
compute first, right?
So when we create a VM,
one of the things
we could do is we
could We could specify
the size, right?
That will tell us how
many GPUs we have, right?
So that's one way you could
pay for more or less compute.
The other thing you
could do is you
pay to attach GPUs, right?
In this case, I'm attaching
to a Video GPUs here,
and you could choose the
type of GPU and how many?
GPUs are kind of expensive,
but they're useful for a lot of
machine learning trading
of models, right?
So this VM example I had here,
this is about $400 a month,
so definitely not cheap to ret.
On the other hand, the
great thing is that we
sometimes just need a lot
of compute for a
short period of time.
If I only want this
VA for 1 hour,
well, that's $0.50, right?
It would be better
for me to rent
this machine with a couple GPUs,
and I maybe pay $0.50 to trade
my model that I shut
it down, right?
So there's lots of
stuff that's very
expensive, and you wouldn't
want to use that stuff.
And definitely, you want to just
sitting there idle overnight,
but it's affordable everybody
to run it for a very
short amount of time.
There's other ways you could
buy tripute instead of Vbs.
O, which is kind of like
the classic that we've done
this semester is that we'd
have what we call multi
tenant hosts, right?
So in this case, right,
Google or the cloud provider
bought a physical machine,
and they have Vb belonging
to different customers. So tenet
You know, a tenant to be like
a renter in an apartment.
A tenant is also what we call
a customer who's renting
services from the Cloud, right?
So in this case, we
have different tenants.
So a multi tenet host has
VMs for for different customers.
Asultent host. What
that means is that
all the VMs on that
single machine
belong to the same customer.
You can imagine where
that might happen.
So even though the
multi tenet host,
they're trying to protect
these VMs from each
other and make sure there's
nothing being leaked.
There's actually been some
more arity even at Wisconsin,
where they showed
like, Well, sometimes
you can, you know,
watch the performance
you're ding very cleverly
infer things about
what other VMs
are doing on the
same hosts, right?
So it's a little bit paranoid,
but the military, right?
They use cloud
service all the time,
and they do not want their VMs
anywhere near anybody else,
any other organization.
So that case, they would
pay for S tenant hosts.
In that case, you're probably
talking thousands of
dollars per month, right?
Bus these are big,
powerful machines,
and they cant anybody els.
So you better make
sure you're packing
enough VMs on it to make
it worthwhile, right?
So we have VMs in
both of these cases.
We've been running a lot of
Docker containers this semester.
There are services out
there that will let you,
for example, run like potatos
and uber etes, right?
You could pay to run a
container instead of paying
to run a virtual machine.
Even kind of further down,
there are a lot of what we
call serverless platforms now,
like AWS abd is
an example of it.
In that case, you
don't even have like
a VM or a container.
What you're doing is,
you're just writing
like little functions,
and what you'll do is that
whenever your function runs,
you start paying, and whatever
your function returns,
you stop paying.
It's just like you'll
pay by the millisecond.
That's how it story is we
get more more services.
Could pay with fighter
and fighter gradularity,
is how this is evolving.
Alright, cool. Let's talk
about memory, right?
You could Often when
we're crating a Vb,
where it gets memory for it.
It's usually roughly proportional
to the CPU resources.
You could rent,
memory optimized VMs,
and it's kind of
craziest even possible,
but you could rent a Vb that
has over 10 terabytes memory.
That's just like M blo B,
but that's possible now.
So you could be using
memory like that.
There are also memory
oriented platforms
that you could read as a
platform as a service.
So for example,
we learned M SQL,
if you wanted to, you could
have something called MTD,
which would be
cash rows for you.
I would keep them in
memory that would help
ER SQL be quite a bit faster.
Or if we want to have some
type of in memory database,
Redis is an open source thing,
but it's often provided as
a platform as a service.
Alright, let's talk
about storage.
So, in this case, I have a
bunch of virtual machines.
And they're attached to
different virtual disk.
You can see that the first
virtual machine is odd.
It's attached to
this virtual disk.
The second virtual machine is
off and it's attached
to a different disk.
They have different
kinds of hardware.
There's a hard disk drive SSD.
They have kind of, like
some weird ballat ones
where maybe have a bit of both,
or maybe very high
performance SSDs.
I can totally have a VM that has
multiple disks or maybe I have
a disk that's not
attached to anything.
Well, what I have to do is
where I have to pay for
the storage of all of
these disk devices.
I I shut a VB off like
this one right here,
that I don't pay to run the VM,
but I would still pay for
that disc capacity, right?
So these are virtual disc,
I can move them around.
I can detach it from one VM,
reattach it to another.
You know Sometimes when I
messed up my virtual machines,
I've been able to
recover data that way.
Right? So we have all
these different types,
and you pay if it's
bigger or if it's faster.
So here's an example,
like when we
created our virtual
machines a semester.
In this case, I had
like an e two medium
and I gave it a
ten gigabyte disc.
In this case, we'd
be paying $24.46 for
the actual VM and $1 per
month for the storages.
If I If I turn it off,
I'll still be paid $1 a month.
If I turn it back
out, I'll be paid
something like $25 a month.
Do you have any question
about any of these resources
so far? All right.
Well, let's talk
about networking.
So in general,
we're building all these data
centers around the world,
and we want to understand
the topology of
those like between them
and both within them.
And so very broadly,
the way a lot of these
providers will do it is
they'll break things
into candidates, right?
And for them, kind
of how they divide
a cadate might be a
little bit different
than you would from a
geography perspective,
because what they're interested
is not the land maats,
but the connectivity, right?
Anyway, but they'll define
different candidates,
which kind of roughly
related to like
the real candidates that
we're familiar with.
Those will be broken
down into regions.
A region is probably
like, you know,
one big building or
maybe a few buildings
that are close to
each other, right?
And then within those regions,
they're going to have
something called zones, right?
And within a given zone,
they're going to have like
faster networking within it,
and a single zone might
share networking resources,
it might share power,
things like that.
And so if you have two
VMs in the same zone,
they can probably communicate
very quickly and cheaply.
But if that zone dies,
it's possible all those VMs
would go down together.
It's like I have that picture
here different regions.
Each of them has
different zones.
I might have some
VMs in the same one.
I actually went on a tour of
a data center once I got
to see a zone. It was
kind of cool, right?
So the region was
this big building that we
were in and we
could walk around,
and we could see, it
was like, you know,
they would have,
these big kind of,
like, shipping
containers, right?
That are full of
servers, right? I like,
Oh, well, that's a
zone. That's a zone.
If a tornado destroyed
that building, right?
All the zones are going
to go down together.
But if there's kind
of a more localized,
like power outage
or network issue,
then maybe only
one of those zones
would drown down at a time.
So let's start to make a impact
on how you deploy some
of these systems.
So we learned about Cassandra,
for example, we learned
about with Cassandra.
I have a given row of data.
We walk the rig to figure
out which machines
are going to own
that row of data.
And we learned that
sometimes we'll skip a
Venous we don't want
to have two Venoes
on the same physical machine.
In the same way, right if
you know about
zones and regions,
maybe you want to have some
more complicated rules
about what you skip, right?
Maybe I don't want to
have all my copies
in the same availability zone.
Or maybe I want to
make sure that I have
at least one copy in
a completely different
region, right?
It depending on
how paranoid art,
you could have different
skipping rules to make sure that
your data is safe from
either kind of like
localized power failure or,
you know, safe from
things like tornadoes or
hurricanes that could
do more massive damage.
Now, you might be paying for
these network resources.
And there's two categories
of network I o.
What is drass means that
the data is coming in?
The letter is grass
that is coming out.
Eras in a lot of cases is free.
And again, it's one of
the things, There's
all the deferent
cloud providers,
they all do different things.
I'm just say broadly, what I
usually see is that
NDraSs is usually free.
And that makes sense because
they want you to move your data
into the cloud and start
using their services.
If you want to switch out,
well, do they want
you to pay for that.
So usually pay for the egress,
how much do you pay for egress?
That's an incredibly
complicated topic, right?
There's like multiple pages
of like giant tables,
and you have to look up and
figure out what you're paying.
But there are some big factors
that will often
determine, right?
So I just put an example here.
These are kind of
ballpark figures for GCP.
It was from last year.
And if you're sending
data out of one VM
to the other, well,
they will actually
have that B free,
If it's the same region,
well, then you'll pay one
sets per gigabyte, right?
So if I pay of sitting
data across these
two different zones.
If it's the same continent.
Well, it depends
on the continent,
but for Asia, it was
five sets per gigabyte.
And then finally, there's just
like the broader
Internet, right?
So I mean, what is
the broader internet?
It could be like a di data a
different continent, right?
Or maybe it's the
same continent,
but it's like outside
of their cloud, right?
You're sitting maybe a
different cloud provider
or some other service,
or maybe you're spotty
to a web request
to some user, wherever, right?
So, kind of, depending on that,
you're pay different
amounts, right?
Alright. Well, I don't want to,
you know, I don't have
time for a tophat.
So maybe we'll come
back next time,
and we'll start off
with this top hat.
Have a fantastic day.