Everybody for coming today.
I know there might be a lot of
other things on
People's MDs Day.
I know there is O Md, but
we're a plow ahead
with the course,
and I appreciate
you're all here.
Some announcements.
What is that?
We have the Mid term on Monday?
So hopefully people are
preparing for that.
If they have it already, again,
it'll just be here, kind of
the same deal as last time.
Also, we only have
$50 of credits for the
Google virtual machines.
And that let us make
P five optional.
We would either be like on
a Google Virtual Machine
or these CSL virtual machines.
Starting in P six, it
will have to be on
the CSL VM because
I want to save
a little bit of
credit for PA, right?
And we should have just like
a couple of dollars left.
And so as soon as you're
done with P five,
please shut off your Vb.
Well, back up
everything on your VM,
then shut it off and
delete it so that we can
save that last couple of dollar
for the end of the semester.
We've been learning
about Cassandra,
and I'll head back
to our slides.
We're going to do some
worksheets today,
we're go over some
more concepts.
And the main idea here
with consistent hashing
is that we have
something called a token rig,
and it's a rig because it's
a number line that wraps around.
If you go all the way to
the end on the far right,
you'll wrap around to the left.
And the idea is that we have
a bunch of rows of data,
and we have a bunch
of worker machines,
and we want to somehow
put them each at
a specific location on this rig.
And if we do that, then that
naturally gives us
a way of saying,
this row, be logs to
that worker or node.
And so we had a couple
of different approaches.
For the rose, What
we would do is we'd look
at their partition key,
right, remember
this is Cassandra,
and we would just
take a hash of it.
We call that the token, right?
And that works great
because we might
have millions or billions
or even trillions of rows.
And so I don't want
to have some giant
data structure to keep
track of it, right?
Just a little bit of math with
the hash function is enough
for me to decide for
all these different rows where
they go on the token rig.
We're also putting
computers on the token rig,
but we do not hash those.
The reason why is that if
you did something like
hash partitioning,
and you add an additional node,
and then you recalculate that.
The number would be
very different, right?
So what we're going to
do with these nodes
is that we're actually to give
them a token that
will choose, right?
We could pick something,
maybe it's random.
Maybe it's picked carefully.
And because we're picking it,
rather than having some
formulaic way to choose it,
we cannot just use
a little bit of
math to re figure
out what it is.
We have to have
some data structure
somewhere to remember,
and what that data structure
is is a token math.
It's basically like a dictionary
where the key is a node,
and the value is the token.
So once we've done
that, we've got
every computer and every
row on the token rig,
then what I may be
talking about a lot.
I'm may keep using this
phrase is where they say,
we're going to walk the rig.
And we walk the rig.
What we want to figure
out what machine a
specific row goes on.
And the way we'll do that
is we'll choose a row.
For example, let's say
I choose the row B,
and I will walk the rig to
the right until I
pup into a node.
Right? So if I buy B, I may say,
oh, well, that's node two.
And in some cases, it's
a little bit trickier,
like if I have E, and I keep
walking to the right, well,
it'll just wrap around.
I'll say that E goes
on node one, right?
So that's where we
ended last slide.
I want to show you another way
people often visualize this.
I think sometimes people get so
caught up and like,
Oh, it's a rig.
They insist on
drawing it that way,
and I think that adds
unnecessary complexity.
I don't even know why
there's something
about two Pi here
or degrees, right?
Anyway, if you go on Wikipedia,
this is the way people visualize
consistent Ashley.
That's very common.
I just want to realize that's
the same as this picture,
but I find this picture
easier to work with.
Alright. So any questions
about last time before we
talk about adding a new row?
All right.
So I may imagine that
we're adding a new row,
a new node, and we'll have
to choose token for it.
So you chose a token, let's
say it lands right here.
When that happens, what
that means is that
for some of these other rows
where we were walking
the rig before,
instead of hitting node three,
they might hit node four.
In other words, node
four is to steal
away some of the work
from node three.
So I'd up looking like this.
Instead of having C
under node three,
now it's under under
node four, right?
This is good because we
talked about before,
if we're doing hash partitioning
and I changed the
number of nodes,
then I would really have to move
every single piece of data.
And in this case, I did not
have to move that much data.
And and I could estimate
it publistically.
If I do hash partitioning
and I you know,
have Ed computers,
I'm drawing to Ed.
Only one e of the data is
likely to be in the same
place as it was before.
And so almost all of
it, if it is large,
almost all of it
is going to move.
In this case, how much
of it has to move?
Well, I can look at the
size of the whole rag,
and I can look at the
size of the new range,
and I take the size of the new
range divided by
the whole thing.
That's a relatively
small fraction,
especially as I have more
and more nodes, right?
These kind of ranges
will be smaller, right?
So I have to move a very
small fraction of the data.
This is what we would
call an elastic system.
I can add and remove nodes,
and that's not an
expensive thing to do.
Now, there's a
couple of problems.
One is that what happens if I
get two nodes with
the exact same token.
That's called a
collision. Sometimes in
your starting cassa you
might get an error about it.
Why does that happen?
Well, in the old days,
they would pick the token
randomly for a node,
and so this would
be very unlikely.
But now they're trying
to pick it so they
space the ranges
relatively evenly.
And so if you have two nodes
adding at the same time,
it's actually very common that
they will collide
with each other.
And after you have a
cluster up and running,
one solution is just as you
add nodes, add one at a time.
Don't add a bunch of
nodes at the same time.
When you're first
starting a cluster,
you might say, I want to
start these three nodes.
Then this is more
likely to happen,
and that's where I've seen
this error message before.
So what we can do
is we can identify
a few initial starting nodes
that are called s nodes,
and those will not use this
kind of smart technique.
They'll have a better
approach to make sure
that they all can
see each other,
and so we'll have those s nodes,
we get those up and running,
and there will not
be any collisions.
Now, there's another
problem here.
Even though this is
an elastic system,
it's not going to be
super ballots, right?
I added this new node,
and instead of helping all
of the other existing nodes,
we only helped
node three, right?
So in the long term,
there's a problem, right?
We aren't getting good ballots.
In the short term, there's
also a problem because
node three needs to send a
lot of its ta to node four.
So node four can take over
those responsibilities,
and that's a lot of network
IO truing from node three,
and that could actually
make node three,
who maybe needs the most help.
I could actually make it
slower in the short term,
right? That's a real problem.
And It's kind of similar
to if you just imagine a team
of engineers working
a something,
imagine a team that's
kind of overworked.
And like, Okay, we're going
to hire a new engineer.
What you would prefer is
that engineer kind of takes
a little bit of work
away from everybody.
So things are balance.
Instead, imagine that new
engineer is like, Okay,
you're just to help this
one senior engineer,
and they're going to
have to trade you.
So they're already busy,
but now they have to trade you.
And then after their trade,
then you're going to
have half to work it so
that they'll kind
of have less work
than everybody else. Right?
So instead, we want to
have something that
looks like this,
but we want to when
we add a node,
we want to take a little bit
of work away from everybody.
And that leads us to
approach called V nodes.
And the idea of vetoes
is instead of just
having one token for each node,
we can have more
than one, right?
You can see before, You know,
I just had one token for each.
Now, maybe I have
two tokens for each.
And every time I have
a token on the rig,
that defines an
inclusive range from
that token left until
there's another token.
And so when I do that,
now there's more small ranges.
And the good thing then is
that when I add node four,
this is taking a little
bit of work away from
node wood and a little bit
of work away from node two.
And you can actually
configure out.
How many virtual nodes
do you want for
each physical node?
I think the default is be
like 16. But we can do that.
We can divide up the work
a little bit more evenly.
We'll have to have some more
space in our token map,
but this is still going
to be an improvement.
All right.
Do people have any questions
about virtual nodes
so far? Oh, right.
Another thing is that
it helps us deal with
machines that are really
not equally powerful.
You might imagine
that when I buy
a new set of machines
for a casadric cluster,
I probably bought a bunch of
machines that are identical.
I have the same CPU
and memory resources.
Now, over time, if
I have more data,
I want to add more machines,
maybe the state of the
art hardware is changed.
Maybe we have bigger memory
capacity and more cores.
And so I might want to give
the newer machines I'm
adding to an old cluster.
More work than the old ones
because they're more
capable, right?
So one of the ways I could also
use V nodes is that I could say,
Okay, I have this node for
which the more powerful.
Let's give it four tokens.
The more tokens you
have, the more rages
you'll have on the token rag,
the more work you're probably
going to end up with.
It's all probabilistic,
of course.
When I'm doing that, what I'll
say is this is a
heterogeneous cluster.
Heterogeneous cluster means that
not all the machines are equal.
In contrast to
homogeneous cluster,
all the machines are
identical to each other.
Yeah, right here. Ode
rages which node row.
Yeah, how do I figure out
which nodes which row?
Yeah, who gets D. So the way
I do it is I would start on D,
and I would walk to
the right and I'm
re bump into node two.
So D will go to node
two. That makes sens?
So I can either
think of it like from
the node perspective,
I walk right, or I can think
of it I say nod a row.
I can think of it from
the row's perspective.
I start there and I walk right,
or I can think of it from
the nodes perspective.
I say I on this token and
everything to the left,
like up until, but not
including another node, right?
Yeah, thanks for asking.
Yeah, there are
questions people have.
Yeah.
Yeah, how is this helping solve
the problem of only one node be
responsible for
the data transfer?
Well, in this case,
Node two used to own
all of this range here.
And so Node two will have to
give some of that
data to node four.
I also see over here,
another place where
none four is adding,
node one is to its right.
So in this case, node one is
sending some of its
data to node four.
Right? So instead of just having
one node sending a lot of data,
we have more nodes, each
setting a smaller
amount of data.
We're kind of spreading
out the work a little bit.
And you can imagine some
trade offs here, right?
I guess, more V nodes we
have for physical node,
the more we could break that up.
But also, you don't
want to have a
giant token MAP data
structure, right?
So you can 16 is the default,
which is probably fine.
If you have 16 machines
helping one new machine
come up to speed,
that'll probably get done pretty
quickly. Does that make sense?
Yeah, thanks for asking.
Yeah, other questions
people have.
Oh, yeah, how does it decide
where to place these new ds?
Is that That's a policy
that's evolved, right?
Originally, they used to just
choose it randomly, right?
They started to see, like, Oh,
well, if I have this rage,
let's try to cut it evily,
let's try to look
for a bigger rage.
And so, they're trying
to be clever about it.
I'm guessing that
will evolve, right?
How they choose it, right?
And I'm not sure what the
state of the art is, right?
They probably just keep
adding more and more,
clever things to it over time.
Yeah, thanks for rest.
Yeah. Question.
Function. Oh, yeah.
What is the rage of
the hash function?
So I guess in this case,
they're using at 64, right?
So it's quite a big range of
numbers. Yeah, they're here.
Yeah, for the rows,
it's just a hash function,
so it's not rand,
it'll be deterministic, right?
I kind of the key
insight there is
that we're choosing the tokens
differently for the rows that we
do the nose because we
have a lot of rows, right?
And so we don't want to have
any kind of data structure,
I even if we choose randomly,
we have to remember
what we chose.
When we're citing Rosa Token,
we want to just do
it with math, right?
Because math doesn't
take any memory,
and everybody can
do the same math,
no matter where they are.
So we have lots
and lots of rows,
so it's just like a simple
hash flection for the rows.
For the nodes, we have a
little bit more flexibility.
There's not that many rows.
I can put all a little
bit of meta data about
every single row in a
big Python dictionary
or whatever data
structure they have.
That make sense? Yeah,
Thanks for asty.
Yeah other questions
people. All right.
So one of the questions is,
where should this
token Map live?
That's a very important thing
because unless you have
information about the Token Map,
You have no way of
tracking down for
a specific row where
I can find it, right?
And the solution
in a system like,
you know, HDFS is that
they have a name node.
They have a centralized name
node that has all that data,
and if you want to get access
to the data, you talk
to the name node.
That's not great, right? Because
the name node could die.
It could become a
performance bottledck.
And so what they do,
instead, is they put
the token map on
every single worker.
If we have 100 workers,
they all have a token map that
describes all 100 workers,
right? And that's fine, right?
That works pretty
well. We're very
unlikely to lose that data.
The holy trick is that,
you know, when I
change the token map,
for example, because
there's a new node
entering the system, I
have to update that.
And if I have to
update 100 copies of
the same thing, that
could be a problem.
How do I do it efficiently?
And more importantly,
how do I do
it if one of the machines
is temporarily down, right?
So I'm imagining this here.
This machine was rebooting,
or having some kind
of other issue.
And when that happened,
node four table.
We're trying to add node
four to the cluster,
and so I can tell nodes one
and two about that new node.
But what about node three,
right? Like, what do I do?
Do I have to wait until
the cluster is perfectly
healthy with all nodes
online to add a new node?
I mean, honestly,
I might be adding
the new nodes specifically
because another node
is down, right?
So I don't want to have to wait.
And so we have to have
a more clever approach
that can let the system
proceed even while we
can update everything
at the same time.
And so the approach is
called Jos or maybe we call,
like an epidemic algorithm.
And the idea is that node
four, right we're adding that?
We'll just let a
handful of nodes know.
Maybe even just like node two.
So no two knows about it.
And then what will
happen is that
the nodes engage in Joss.
And Joss upp happens randomly.
I think it's like every one
seconds, but it's tunable.
Each node will randomly
choose another node,
and they'll exchange
information.
L node two will say to node one,
Hey, have you heard
about node four,
and node one will say, no,
Node two will be, here are
its tokens. Now you know.
Right? You can
already see, right,
how fast gossip spreads
in real life or
how fast like a virus
spreads in real life.
And this is not
even engineered by
somebody to try to make it
spread as fast as
possible, right?
So this will happen
very quickly, right?
There's, you know, every
second gossips happening.
I'll quickly spread to all
the nodes that are available.
And the good thing
is is that when
this node three
comes back on line,
whoever it gossips with
will very quickly tell.
Within a matter of
seconds, they'll
have it. That's
how I end up here.
This How much does the network
I owe slow the efficiency?
I guess it depends on how
frequently you do it.
You could trade off
like if I want to toss
up more frequently and
spend more network I owe.
My intuition is that probably
it's not a big factor because
when you're trying to say,
like, Hey, do we have
the same token map?
There are ways to have
a check sum or like a
hash of your token map.
And so it's not necessarily that
I send you everything
I know every time.
It's like, we might
first of say,
Hey, do you know what I know?
And if the answer is yes,
then you could be done,
and if it's like,
Oh, we actually have
a different view
of the world, then we
could actually do it.
So I think it'll be
pretty fast in general.
Yeah, I sought a question.
Yeah, every node chooses
another node every
second to gossip with.
So they're just trying to make
the news spread as
fast as possible.
That will kind of
go exponentially.
The information will
quickly be everywhere.
Yeah, right here. When two nodes
disagree, how do you
determine who's?
Oh, when two nodes disagree,
how do you determine
who's right?
Something.
Yeah, you're saying
like, Oh, maybe
somebody deleted a note
or something like that.
I don't know what
they do. I mean,
I could speculate based on
how people build
other things, right?
You can imagine like putting
times staaps on the events.
You can imagine this is
called like a tombstone.
Sometimes when you
delete something
instead of having
no information,
you keep some information
like this thing was deleted.
And so if you had a time
statap and a tombstone,
you could say, like, Oh,
you think it's added, but I
actually think it's deleted,
and I'm more up to date, right?
So I don't know how
exactly they do it,
but it's probably
something like that.
Yeah, so I had up over here.
Us all the time.
Yeah, they're just
like literally
gossiping all the
time forever, right?
So they're just like sending
these little messages like,
Hey, like, what do
you know, right?
You know, I mean, there's
some overhead to it,
but, you know, there are
changes that everybody
knows quickly, right?
Yeah. Yeah, thanks for asking.
Yeah other questions
people have. All right.
Now, how would you actually
go about reading some data?
Well, if you were a HDFS,
then the client would talk
to the name node first
because name node
has the block map.
But this isn't HDFS.
In this case, the
client could talk to
literally Eddie node of
the system because all the
nodes have the token map,
right, Edy node can
help them figure
out how to do the IO.
And so the client
will just maybe it
chooses like one randomly or
maybe it chooses
from a small set.
It's not too important how.
But what will happen then is
that what it talks to
will be the coordinator.
And the coordinator I'd
actually have the data,
but probably not.
We generally happen if I
try to read the node f,
who's the coordinator
in this case,
will find the data for me
based on where it knows it is,
and send it back, or maybe
it'll write it there.
And, you know, different clients
will connect and have different
coordinators doesn't
really matter.
Any node can be a coordinator.
Alright, cool. So let's do a
couple of top hat questions,
and then they'll do some
worksheet problems.
All right.
My first question is about
how much space do we have to
use for the Token Map.
About 30 seconds left.
Most people say the number
of nodes in Cassady,
which is totally correct, right?
We wouldn't want to have
information there
about individual rows
because we have too many rows.
The token map would be too big,
but it's very
reasonable to remember
all of the tokens for
each node of the cluster.
All right. Well, let me
pull up another one.
Oh, right. And this one is
about the wrapping rage.
About 30 seconds left.
Okay, so people are saying B,
but answer is actually C, right?
So remember if I'm a row,
and I'm trying to
find my vetode.
I first check if I have
an exact batch of the token.
That usually doesn't happen.
But if I do that I'm
drug, otherwise,
what I do is I keep
walking to the right,
I go bigger and
bigger and bigger,
until if I don't find anything,
then I wrap around to
the smallest, right?
So only if the token of
a row is bigger than
all the vetodes,
that I'm in the wrapping range.
Alright? A question about
that I see that threw
people ahat. All right.
Cool. So let's throw ahead,
and we will head over
to the document camera.
And and hopefully people have
the worksheet printed or on
a tablet or something like that.
And there's really
two sides of it.
The first side assumes that
there's only one
replica of every row.
Even with all these
vetos, right?
We only have one
replica of every row.
Later, I'd be to show
that we can have
multiple replicas of
the same piece of data.
And so this side is all
partitioning with
replication of one.
And then the second part,
which we'll get to is
what happens when
we have multiple
replicas of the
same piece of data.
Alright, so the
first question is,
for this token map up here,
how many nodes are
there in the system.
And so I ask that first later,
I'll ask about how many Vodes.
But for the first question,
maybe people can hold up
some number of fingers.
How many computers or nodes
are there in this cluster?
I'm seeing some threes,
which is correct, right?
There's nodes. There's
nodes one, two, and three.
Okay, great. And how
many V nodes are there?
You might need
more than one had?
All right? I'm S sevens,
which is correct, right?
Because I have two plus two
plus plus three over here.
All right, great.
So another one,
I may ask, and people up
su number of figures.
I'm asked of nodes
one, two or three,
which one probably has
the most resources in terms
of either computer battery?
I'm S three, which is correct.
We gave Node three more tokens,
and that means that
probabilistically
on more of the token rig,
which means it's probably
going to get more work.
Yeah, question. I don't
know if the exact sees.
Oh, oh, that's a
great, great question.
So is it possible
that one V node
has more than one token?
No, by definition, one
V node has one token.
And so what we're really
the problem we're really
trying to solve is we wanted to
have one physical machine.
We wanted one physical machine
to have multiple tokens.
And so the ranges,
corresponding to each
of those token is,
what we call a V node, right?
So a V node is one range,
a node is a machine that
has multiple V nodes.
That makes sense? Yeah, Yeah,
thanks for bringing that back.
Yeah, if anybody else
had any questions,
pop up a head at
any time. Alright.
So let's see how we can
actually draw this out.
I think it's helpful
just kind of go
through the steps of
visualizing this.
And so I can already
see that node two,
one of its tokens
is negative six.
Let's just label all
of these on the top.
You know, normally, it's like,
you have every possible at 64.
I like to just try to draw these
tidy ranges for these examples.
Okay, let's do node wood.
Node wood is at T
negative two and four.
All right. Node two is at
negative six and zero.
And Node three is at
negative four, two and five.
So negative four. Two and
five. Alright, great.
So if I give you
a token bath and ask
some questions about Waki the
rag or something like that,
hopefully, like,
you would first,
you know, make a picture, so
you could reason through it.
Alright. So my first question,
I'll just get like one
volunteer for this.
I'm wondering what
ring positions
are in the wrapping range?
Re, right here.
Excellent, right?
So six and seven are in
the wrapping range, right?
If we're trying to find a note
and the token of our row
is in that wrapping range,
then we'll wrap around
to the right over here.
Alright, great. Let's do a
couple of these quickly,
so I'm wondering which note is
responsible for each
of these tokens.
So let's say that a row
gives me Token four.
That's actually an exact match.
I'll just do that
one for us, right?
So node four. I'm sorry.
So the row with Token four is
going to give us node one.
All right. And now I have
another row with Token one.
Maybe people can hold up
some number of fingers.
Which node will take this one?
I'm seeing a mix of answers.
When we walk the ring,
we walk to the right.
So I walk to the right, and
I bump into node three.
So node three is the
one that owns this one.
We always walk the ring to
the right. Alright. Great, cool.
And now I have six and
some number of fingers,
which node I you're
going to own this row?
Se kind of a mix
of answers again.
Right? So the
answer is node two.
So I always walk to the right
and I have to wrap around,
and I hit node two
over here, right?
So node two.
Hey, I threw people off
with a couple of these.
I want to just pause and see if
anybody has any questions.
Yeah, right here.
Yeah. Question is
walk to the right would
not be consider values.
We do consider values at equal.
If it's an exact match, then,
if a row and a worker happen
to have the same token,
that rows that token.
And it's always
hard to remember,
h, what's inclusive or
not? I just remember.
Once I kind of formulate
it to myself that way,
if a row and a worker match
that row is on that worker.
That's the very first
thing. The second thing
to remember is always
walk to the right.
Yeah, question.
Yeah, the wrapping range
means that you're past
the biggest V node because
you always walk to the right.
And so if you're past
the biggest V node,
you're able to walk off
the end and wrap around.
Yeah. Yeah, thanks for
clarifying. Yeah, right here.
C node one be
responsible for what?
Okay, so I'm on Token one.
So I'm right here.
And you're asking,
could which node be responsible?
Node one could not be because
I'm not really interested in
like the node number, right?
I'm more interested in
the token number, right?
And so Node three has
the first token number
when I walk to the right.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, I guess it's kind
of like a little weird,
but I'm not And maybe
I should have called
these node ABC just to
make sure that there's
no confusion there,
but it doesn't
care what that is.
Yeah, thanks for
asking. All right.
So yeah, right here. 62.
Yep, I start at six,
and I walked to the
right until I find it.
So I fall off the end and
I find node two over here.
The first one I run into.
Yep. That's called
walking in the Ring.
And I saw another
hand up over here.
Oh, yeah, why is it a
negative eight to seven?
It could be anything.
For, you know,
for n 64, it's a
much bigger range.
And so I'm just trying to have
something that is kind of small.
So I think that I guess
like if I had like
a four bit number,
then and it was like signed,
that would be the range.
But I mean, I guess I
could have drawn anything.
I could have said
like five to five.
I'm just trying to
draw a simple picture.
Makes sense.
I don't Oh,
could you're saying,
like, could a negative number
be in the wrapping range?
Yeah, yeah, it
absolutely could be.
It'd be kind of,
like, a funny ring.
But for example, if
for whatever reason,
like, if I had, like, my tokens,
like if the biggest token
was negative three,
then the whole wrapping
range would be here, right?
So I guess, like I
guess I'm drawing like tokens
in our signed numbers,
but like thinking about,
whether it's a
positive or negative
number doesn't help
us answer anything.
I'm just interested in
the order of the numbers.
If that makes sense? Yeah,
thanks for polling that out.
I didn't think about
the sign. Yeah, right.
87 These are not part of
the wrapping range, right.
Right. Be if I'm walking
the ring to the right,
I don't have any kind
of special case.
The rapping ring is
the only special case.
Yeah, yeah, thank you.
Yeah. Other questions
people have? Lots
of great questions.
So I'm glad people are
really digging in.
We really have to have
a firm foundation here
because we don't even
have a replication yet.
Everything gets more
complicated with replication.
So I really want people to
be solid on this. All right.
Now, We've talked about
how we draw this.
This is based on what's
on the Token map.
Down here, I kind
of just imagine
that I have rows
with these Tokens.
But where do those come from?
Well, they came from
The token function,
which is really just
a hash function.
And so I'm imagining,
remember this is
Cassandra, right?
So my rows have a primary key.
And let's say the
primary key is A B.
And the primary key consists of
one partition column followed
by one fluster tolumn.
And so I can imagine
taking the hash of,
like, A or B or of both.
And so I want to
figure out, given
what we know about Cassandra,
how should I choose a
token for for this row.
Any thoughts? Yeah, right here.
Yeah, you said it has
just the partition key,
which is correct, right?
These are actually irrelevant
pieces of information.
So remember, when
we learned about
Cassandra and how we're like
creating these schemas
and all of that.
What we said is that we
want all the rows with
the same partition key to
end up on the same same machine.
And so that's going to boil down
to walking the ring, right?
If I was hashing over
this whole thing,
then I might walk starting
from different places.
And I could have two rows
that have the same
partition key,
but they could end up
in different places.
So we will only hash
on the partition key.
Excellent. All right.
So, this next one is about
the incremental the elasticity,
the kind of incremental
scalability.
And so I'm imagining
that node four is
joining the cluster,
and it has two V nodes,
and those v nodes are negative
three and negative one, right?
So it's joining here. And
so this is negative three.
And I'm sorry, what
am I drawing here.
This is n four.
And this is n four
here as well, right?
It's joining with
those two. And so
maybe people can use two hands.
What two existing nodes
are going to have
to send some data to
this new machine?
All right, I'm seeing some ones
and twos, which is
correct, right?
These nodes one and
two here used to own
this whole range.
And so node four is taking away
some of the range from
these two V nodes, right?
So these two are have to send
them some of their data
and hand that off.
Alright.
C, do people have
any any questions about
sander partition?
Right?
One. Partition mention
row. Yeah.
Yeah, each of each
of these nodes
here might have rows
across a bunch of different
partitions, right?
And each of those
partitions belongs to
a unique point on the
token ring, right?
So like node one
is going to look at all the rows
across all these
different partitions,
and it is to say,
well, these partitions
of rows now belong on
a different machine.
Y, we will never
split a partition,
so we can never hand off
part of a partition.
We'll either hand off the
whole partition or none of it.
That makes sense? Yes Yes. Yes.
That's a great great point
that I should have made, right?
So Nodes one and Node two,
are going to be sending
whole partitions to.
Yeah, follow up here. Beat.
Node four will only be
taking partitions that
map to negative one
and negative three.
Yeah. Negative three is why.
That's why Yeah,
because Node one used
to own negative three,
and now node four
owns negative three.
Yeah. Yeah, thanks.
I appreciate all the
great questions today.
Yeah, any other questions
people have? Oh right.
And again, even though we
have all these V
nodes and stuff,
everything we've done so
far is replication one.
When I walk the ring, I
find this is the one
worker that owns the data.
This idea of walking the ring
is something that we're
going to keep doing,
and it's going to
get more complicated
because we're going
to find ways to
walk the ring that will give us
multiple replicas.
Question right here.
Yeah, let me think about that.
So you said that I
have two rows that
have different primary keys.
Okay. So if they have
different primary keys,
they might have the
same partition key,
or they might not.
So, for the example, what
are you interested in?
Are you saying, like,
you have they're
different primary keys,
but the same partition key?
Okay. Oh, oh, yeah.
You're saying that I might
have completely
different partitions,
but they happen to
have the same token.
Yeah. Wherever those go,
they're going to be together,
not because we want them to,
but just because
that's how the system
works. Will that happen?
No often, right? Because we
have every possible N 64.
But if it does, that's fine.
The two partitions will just
row with each other
wherever they go.
Yeah, thanks for
asking. Yeah, right.
This is the primary So
the primary key is uniquely
identifying a row, right?
And so the A,
we're going to look at that to
figure out what machine it's on.
And then then the B is
helping us figure out, Okay,
well, there's a partition
on that machine,
which row from that partition
am I trying to get?
Yeah, lots of great questions
today. Alright, Troll.
So I'm going to head
over here. And we're
going to talk about
the replication.
And so here's some
Cassandra replication.
I have a few things
I want to do.
We're able to keep walking
the ring like we have been.
But we're going to
walk farther now
because we have to find
multiple replicas.
And one of the tricky things
about when we're walking,
sometimes I might have
two machines that
are near each other,
maybe like they're
the same data center,
maybe even the same
rack, and they
might be likely
to fail together.
So when we're walking the ring,
sometimes we're going
to skip over some noes.
That's maybe one of the skills I
want you to walk
away with today.
Second, After you've walked
the ring and you've said,
Okay, this row belongs to
these three machines
or however many.
Well, if we're
reading or writing,
we have to interact
with them, right?
And if let's say I say like, Oh,
it belongs to these
three machines,
one of those machines is down.
Can I still use the system?
Maybe, depending on
how I tune it, right?
I have this notion of quorums,
where even if the three replicas
I identify it for a row are
not in perfect condition.
Maybe I can still
use the system.
And then finally, we introduce
this idea of eventual
consistency,
where maybe if I have different
replicas of the same row,
and maybe they disagree
with each other.
They're ty of
different versions.
And it's almost like get
history where I can say,
Well, I have different
versions of the code,
but neither one is really
strictly the latest.
How can I resolve conflicts
in that situation?
Okay. Let's talk
about replication.
Remember that when we create
a keyspace in Cassandra,
we say what the
replication factor is,
and then we can create
tables inside of a keyspace.
So I can have a bunch of
tables inside the keyspace,
and each of those tables
might have a bunch of rows,
and all those rows
are going to have
that same replication factor.
And I may usually
abbreviate that
as RF RF is replication factor.
And one of the reasons
that we want to
replicate is for durability,
if I have a higher
replication factor,
I have more copies of
my data in the system.
If some machines die, I'm
less likely to lose my data.
So I want one purpose of
replication is to have
greater durability.
All right. So let's
imagine this cluster here.
I have four nodes
and eight V nodes.
And I have these two key spaces.
So one of the things I might
ask you is that, Okay,
I have a row with such
and such a token,
and it's in this key space.
Well, what nodes are
responsible for it.
And so the difference now
is that we're going to walk
to the right like before.
But the difference is
that we're going to
walk until we get two replicas,
because this is a row on table
x and x has two replicas.
So I'll keep walking,
and I'll say, Okay,
nodes four and two are what
we need in this situation.
Right.
This one's kind of tricky,
so this is a row and Table Y.
So any volunteers?
When I walk the ring,
what nodes am I
going to give it to?
Yeah, go ahead.
Three, one and two. So I'm
may to wrap around just
like I did before,
and I'm going to walk until
I find three of them.
Okay, so far so good.
We have a strategy now
for finding these.
All right. Now I have
another one in table,
and this one's very tricky,
rather than answering for
an answer, I want to see,
does anybody see
the problem here?
What is the problem?
Yeah, over here.
We hit node four twice.
And so if I was
naive about this,
I would put two copies
of my data on node four.
Does that actually help
if there's a problem?
There are some
problems. Maybe node
four has a bunch of hard drives,
and maybe one of the hard
drives fails and one doesn't.
But there's lots of problems
that that wouldn't
help me with, right?
If Node four, if the
whole computer dies
or there's like a power
outage or a reboots.
Lots of cases where I wouldn't
want to have multiple copies of
the same data on node four.
And so well first, we're
going to call that,
is we're going to call
that a failure domain,
or sometimes we call
it a fault domain?
The failure fault domain
really consists of
different units that
fail together, right?
L2v nodes are in the
same failure domain.
They're likely to
fail together because
they're on the same
physical machine.
And so as we walk the ring,
sometimes we skip, right?
If we find a V node that's in
the same failure domain as
the ones we already found,
we can just skip over, right?
So what what'll actually
do in this case
is we'll get four,
three, and two, right?
So walking the ring is
getting more complicated.
Sometimes you wrap around,
sometimes you skip.
Okay, so when do
you actually skip?
Well, it depends. What does
a failed domain actually mean?
I mean, does that mean multiple
V nodes in the same server?
Does that mean multiple
servers in the same rack?
Does that mean multiple racks
in the same same data center?
Right?
It's kind of a lot of
different ways you
could think about.
All these things might
have reasons that they
all go down together
at the same same time.
And so this policy
about when to skip is
actually pluggable.
You could write like
a little java class
and plug it in and would decide,
when should we skip or or not?
And so There's
different strategies.
The simple strategies
is what one that
we'll actually use
for our projects.
And what that one
does is it skips over
V nodes if they're on the
same physical machine.
Otherwise, if it's two
different machines,
it says, good enough.
We'll assume that their
failure is independent, right?
A more complicated strategy is
called the network
topology strategy,
and that one thinks about,
like, well, where are
the data centers?
What are the racks on them?
And it might skip over
some nodes just because
they're on the same rack.
Yeah, right here. What is
it What is the most
common strategy?
I don't know. I mean, I guess
I don't know if
people survey it.
And I'm not really sure
because Cassandra, right?
It's like one of the most of
the systems like
we've learned about.
It's like, while it's
in one data center.
It doesn't work efficiently.
But Cassandra is
built to work across,
you know, geographically
distributed
data centers around the world.
And so I don't know
how many companies can
afford that, right?
How many of them
actually have different
data centers around the world.
Like, I'm sure there's
a few big companies
that definitely do, you know,
If you have everything
in the same data center,
maybe you just like,
Well, hope there's not
a tornado and say,
different machines
is good enough.
So, I'm not really sure
what's more common.
Yeah, it's interesting, though.
Um Cool.
Let's head over here
and do at least a
couple more worksheet problems.
So I will head to my doc
cam and put this down here.
And this is exactly the same
token ring as on
the previous page.
I just wanted to have it
here for easy reference.
And so, assuming two
times replication,
what are the positions
of the V nodes for
a row with Token negative one.
All right, so maybe people
maybe I can did a
volunteer for this one.
What are the right here.
It would be two and
three. That's true.
So I may say node
two and node three.
And so those are the
physical machines.
Then in this case,
I'm asking, what
are the positions
of the V nodes?
I'm kind of interested
like more specifically,
like which V notes of
the machine in general.
So in this case, I
would also want to
want you to say zero and two.
Alright, because those
are the positions. Okay.
Won't we just like
everybody spend like
a moment doing this.
I'm assume three
times application,
and I want to know what
are the positions of
the V nodes that are responsible
for a row with Token
one, right here.
So how about if
everybody just like
goes and writes it down
on a piece of paper?
Just take a moment
to think about it.
All right, let's do
it together, right?
So we start a token one, and
we just walk to the right.
I hit. I'm hitting at position.
A two. All right.
I keep walking. I hit node one
at position position four.
Alright, I hit node three again.
Well, that's in the
same failure domain,
so I just skip over
it. Keep going.
Now I also have to
wrap, so I wrap around.
And then finally,
I find node two.
Node two at position
negative six, right?
So it's just like
a scalar one you
have like walking
the ring, right?
Like you start on the
thing and you walk
right until you get as
many replicas as you need.
You skip if it's in the
same failure domain,
you wrap if you get to the end.
And if you do that, then you can
figure out for any
given piece of data,
what machines will it be on?
Yeah, question right here. Two.
So these labels up here like
N one and two and three,
there's three machines,
and those are
the names of my three machines.
And then the way I
know that there's
two V nodes is I see that n
one shows up up twice, right?
So I have the token four V node
and the token
negative two V node.
And I see hand up.
The right here. How good
is the hash function even
its distributing data?
Probably pretty good, right?
If it wasn't, I'm sure
somebody would try to
find a better one.
I mean, more so what we're
worried about is if you choose
a primary key in a way
that you have one
partition that's like,
very large and other ones
that are very small, right?
Because then there's nothing
you can do to split it up.
So that's usually more of a
concern rather than having,
like a bad hash function.
Yeah, yeah, good
question. All right.
So we have time for
maybe a couple.
We'll actually come back
here to the slides.
Any more questions about
the worksheet for now?
All right, so we keep building
up these skills for
reasoning about this.
And there's another piece here,
which is about quorums.
Has anybody ever been on,
like a committee where
you vote on stuff,
but you have to have a quorum
to make any decisions.
Hs anybody ever been on
a committee like that?
Most Somebody must have been.
Anyway, oftentimes,
if you have a committee and
you're voting on stuff,
if one or two people
messages fine,
you can still make
some decisions.
But if a majority are drawn,
then maybe you don't
really feel empowered to
make decisions with so
many people in absence,
and they may just cancel
the meeting because
you can't do anything.
And that same thing is going
to happen here, right?
Like, we walk the
ring. We like, Okay,
these three or four
or however many nodes
are going to be involved in
reading and writing the data.
But if some of those
nodes are currently down,
then maybe there's not
much we can do, right?
So we are going to be talking
about quorums and how
we interact with them
for reads and writes.
Now, when we're reading and
writing with some quorum,
we have to define a
couple of things,
and one of them is
acknowledgment, right?
How many of you are
WhatsApp users?
So a few of you, I love
WhatsApp because they took
a deeply technical detail
that's normally heading
from user and they
just like make
it visible to everybody, right?
So they have
a very sophisticated view
of acknowledgments, right?
So if I'm trying to send
somebody a message,
I will see one of three things.
A single check
means that the data
got off my phone onto
their data centers,
double check means
that it got onto
at least one device
of the receiving,
and blue double check
means that they
actually saw it, right?
And so there's different
levels of acknowledgments.
And each of those mean that
my data is somehow
committed, is the word
I'm going to use.
Committed me just means that
my data is safe if
something bad happens.
So, for example, if I
have one great check,
And then my phone
runs out of battery
and dies. I'm not
worried about it.
I know that eventually
it can make it there.
So we come back next time,
we'll talk about different
ideas of how we have
acknowledgments and what they
mean in Cassandra, right?
Because if I have
my data on two of
my three nodes or
three of my three,
there are different
levels of how good
I feel about my data
and how safe it is.
Alright, I hope you
all have a great day,
and I'll be around if people
want to come up and
have any questions.