We've been learning about
these different resources,
and right now, we're
on compute resources.
And we've been learning about
how modern CPUs kind
of what they give us.
The clock speeds have not really
been getting faster
in recent years,
but we tend to get more
and more cores over time.
So we want to figure out how
to take advantage of those.
One way is you could
just have a bunch of
different single
threaded processes.
What we learned about on
Friday is that we could also
have a single process with lots
of different threads in it.
So that solves one
problem, right,
being able to use
these compute cores.
But we also saw that that
introduced new problems.
If we aren't really
careful on how we do that,
there can be race conditions.
If we get context
which is at bad times,
maybe we get bad output or
maybe sometimes we
get dread output.
It's kind of very hard to
test that sort of thing.
And so maybe last Friday
was a little pessimistic.
Today we'll be talking
about a solution,
which is to use locks,
and so we're going to
be learning about how
to use locks effectively.
And that will couple
with its own problems.
We're going to learn
about another kind of
concurrency bug today
called the deadlock.
So I have a few
learning objectives
I want you to walk away with.
First, in order to be able to
think about concurrent code,
there's a skill you
need to develop,
which is looking
at your code and
identifying critical
sections, right?
We can't think very deeply
about code it all the time.
But there are certain
pieces of code where
these concurrency bugs become
relevant, and we want
to identify those.
Second, I want you to be
able to have a mechanism
where you can protect
those pieces of code,
where we can basically say, Hey,
I'm trying to do all
these lines of code,
and I don't want to get
interrupted at a bad time.
And that mechanism
is called the lock.
Third, we're going to
be able to learn how
to write code that
avoids common concurrency bugs
in particular race conditions,
which we all have already
seen and deadlocks.
And then finally,
I'm probably going
to push this to
Wednesday honestly.
We're look a little bit
more specifically at
an infamous lock and
the Python interpreter called
the Global Interpreter Lock.
You know, this might actually
be going away, maybe not.
It's a little hard
to see. We're going
to do a little bit
of a deeper dive and
see how things actually
run in Python,
whereas most of what I'm
talking about today is kind of
general to a lot of different
programming languages.
Alright, so first, let's talk
about some critical sections.
And so I have a piece of code
here called transfer EOs.
And it's a little bit similar to
the banking example
I had last time,
but it's a little
bit more general.
So what I'm may to imagine
here is that I'm a bank,
and I have bank
accounts X Y and Z.
Everybody has some number
of dollars in there.
And those are dollars,
by I'm calling this
transfer Euros function.
And I'm may have a
source in a destination.
Those might be
things like X and Y,
and I'll specify
which bank account
I'm transferring from and two.
Um, since these are in dollars,
I'm may have to first convert
those zeros to dollars.
And then I have some
code down here.
I'm going to say that my
bank account cannot
draw negative.
I'm going to check?
Do I have enough money
to do this transfer?
If so, we subtract from
the source, add to
the destination.
And then finally, we'll
say whether or not
the transfer was able
to succeed, right?
And I'm going to imagine that
since let's say I'm a big bank,
and I have lots of
users, I want to be
able to do multiple
transfers concurrently,
and I'm going to have
a bunch of threads.
And, of course, I have
There might be some
context which is going on.
So I want to look at this
very carefully and see,
are there some lines of code
where a context switch
would be convenient.
What would be a bad time
to have a context switch.
So I'm going to look at this.
And if you think you
know pop up a hand,
and then you can
tell me what some of
these lines are that
you're worried about.
Yeah, somebody here is
worried about some lines.
Great. So you're saying
lines nine and ten?
Absolutely. That would be
kind of bad context switch
in between those, potentially.
Anything else that we
should be worried about?
Yeah, right over here. Is
that a handout? Or no.
I could switch in
between these two lines,
but I think there's a
little bit more I
have to worry about.
What else might I
have to worry about?
Yeah, right here.
Switching between these two,
I'm worried about that.
And I think I'm
also worried about switching
between these two, right?
Like, what if I check
that I have enough money,
and I'm like, Good.
One of the things we
need to remember is that
when we have an F
statement we evaluate
whether it's true or
false, that's final.
It doesn't re evaluate
it again later.
So we might decide, Oh,
we have enough money.
Context switch, and maybe
the money goes away,
context switch back, and
then we would do a transfer,
and we could potentially
go negative.
So we have to worry about that.
So I think what we have
to identify here is
that these three lines of
code are a critical section,
and we have to
figure out some way
to make sure that those are
not interrupted at
a bad time, right?
And so for these
critical sections,
there's a couple of properties
that we want to get from them.
And I'm going to
throw out a couple
of words, Adamicity,
inconsistency.
Where I see those
words again, later,
sometimes in different
communities,
people mean different
things by these.
I'm going to give
one definition now.
Adamicity means that we really
want all or nothing, right?
And so I'm doing two
changes, right? And
Even though I can't, you know,
magically snap my fingers and
make two things happen
at the same time,
I want it to kind
of appear that way.
If there's another piece of code
that's looking at
the bank accounts,
they shouldn't see that my money
disappeared before it
showed up somewhere else.
That would probably cause
a phone call or
cause some alarm.
So I want antimicity.
I want either both of these
changes or none of
them to happen.
And then the other one which
is a little bit harder to
pin down is this
idea of consistency.
Consistency means that all
our invariants are satisfied.
And variant is another kind of
funny word. What
is an invariant?
Well, it's some rule that people
make call about
what makes sense.
And so I actually kind
of slipped in an in
variant earlier.
I said a bank account
cannot go negative.
Is that true? Maybe
for this bank?
I don't know, maybe I
was pre approved for
some amount of
loan or something?
Maybe some banks it is
okay to go negative.
Right? That's a rule
that humans made
up for our circumstances.
And I think that consistency
in these invariants is one of
the reasons it's hard to have
a computer do this
automatically for us.
Humans have to be involved and
think about how to do locking
because humans are making
up these rules, these
invariants, right?
Like, if I have some program
that's trying to automatically
add locks for me,
how does it know whether or
not it's okay for a bank
account to go negative?
Right?
That's why we have to think very
carefully about these things.
Alright, so once we identify
a critical section,
by thinking very carefully,
then we have to have
some way to protect it.
And the way we're
going to protect it
is with something called a lock.
So I'm up here using that
threading library from
last time I'm painting this
lock object right here.
And the two most important
methods you're going to
call it a lock are
acquire and release.
And so here I'm calling
a qui at the beginning
of my function,
and I call a lock at the
release of the function.
And for all this
code in between,
what I'll say is that this
thread is holding the lock.
It's held in between the
acquire and the release, okay?
Now, what does the
lock do for me?
It has this guarantee here.
A lock may only be held at
one thread by one thread
at a time, right?
That's very helpful
because if I'm
running this function here
and I've acquired the lock,
and then there's another thread
that's calling the same function
as trying to acquire the lock,
it's not trying to be able to.
It's going to have to wait.
It's going to be blocked, right?
It's going to block
until I release it.
And so only one thread can
be running this little
bit of code at a time.
And I want to be very
explicit, right?
Sometimes people think that
a lock does more than that.
I might be able to
context switch to
a different thread during
this because maybe
some other thread is
doing some computation
totally unrelated to what
I'm doing here, right?
So context switches
can still happen.
But if somebody else is
trying to run some code that
might mess up with what I'm
doing, they're going
to get blocked.
They're going to have
to wait until I'm done.
We're going to take
turns. Any questions
about what the lock is
giving you or what it's not?
Yeah, question right here.
Oh, how does it
know if a context
switch will interfere with this?
It doesn't. The scheduler can
contact switch anytime it wants.
So where I get safety is that
if there's a switches
to another thread,
and that thread is about
to require that lock.
At that point, we'll say, Oh,
that lock has already held.
I have to wait.
Right? So the scheduler
doesn't know anything.
The scheduler can
contact switch wherever.
But if somebody
else tries to get
the lock, they're
going to get blocked,
and the thread will
not be able to
run until that lock is released.
So that makes sense? Yeah.
Thanks. So all the
Smarts is in us,
people, the programmers who
are choosing where
to put these locks.
Other questions
people have. I saw
another hand up play just a
minute ago. Yeah, right here.
Exactly.
Here, it's protecting
this segment of code,
so only one thread
can run it at a time.
Other functions can
be doing other stuff,
that's fine, but I'm
protecting this piece of code.
Yeah other questions people have
about this locking mechanism.
Yeah, right here.
That's really
interesting question.
You're saying like one lock
one function is
conflicting with itself.
You mean like a recursive
function or you mean that
different threads are
calling the same function.
Yeah, uh huh. Oh.
Yeah, that's a good point.
You're saying that,
like, a, like,
I kind of have to make sure
people aren't touching
this data structure at the
same time or threads or not,
but you're saying
that there might be
other things that might
conflict with each other,
but they do not conflict
with me here, right?
Yeah, absolutely. I
can make as many of
these locking objects as I want.
I cannot have two threads
holding the same lock
at the same time.
That's like the one
thing I'm guaranteed.
Totally fine to have different
threads holding different locks.
That happens all
the time, right?
This is the one
guarantee I have here.
Other than that,
there's a lot of
flexibility in terms
of what can happen.
Yeah. Lots of excellent
questions today. Thank you.
So when you're doing
locking,re's different ways
you could do it, right?
This covered my whole
critical section, right?
And this is actually a
reasonable thing to do, right?
It's hard to think about this
if you're not quite sure.
And even when I was asking
you all, we're like,
uh, is it these two lines
or is it these three lines?
You're not sure.
It's not necessarily
a bad idea to just say, Hey,
I'm gonna hold the lock for this
whole duration of
this whole function.
Now, if we tighten
it up a little bit,
then that might mean I can run
more things at the same time.
There's kind of, like,
how hard do I think
about it versus how fast
is my code going to be.
What I'm going to
say is that what you
really want to do is you
want to look for lines
of code that might
be really slow and
that don't need a
lock and really
make sure that those
are not part of it.
Something like success
equals false. That's fast.
I don't really care if
it's in or out of it.
What about Euros to dollars?
Is that fast? Didn't
show it, but maybe.
I mean, if I'm just multiplying
by some constant as fast,
but if I'm doing some API and
growing over the Internet,
then that might be slow and
I definitely wouldn't
want to hold
the lock necessarily
while I'm doing that.
Right?
So you can have to figure out
how tightly do you
want to do it.
And you have to be
careful because
if you go kind of
too tight around it,
maybe actually some
of your critical
sections outside of your lock.
This would be an example of
an incorrect implementation.
I can't do this, right?
Because then I could
grow negative.
It wouldn't be a
consistent implementation.
All right. So people
have any questions
about that idea of
lock granularity.
Yeah, up here. I caught
the first part of it.
So it protects bank
accunts and then what?
What I mean by protecting
bank accounts?
I don't want different threads
messing around with the bank
accounts at the same time.
You're saying the bank accounts
are the same across all.
We, well, yeah, I
don't I don't want
different threads
to be modifying
the bank accounts
at the same time
because we saw even before,
something like you know,
adding one to an integer.
That could be interrupted
at a bad time, right?
So if there's multiple
concurrent accesses to
the same bank account and
there's a bad inter leaving,
I could get weird
results, right?
So by protecting it,
what I mean is that I
only want one thread
touching it at a time.
And that kind of brings
us back to how we
actually identify these
critical sections, right?
What I'm looking for are
things that multiple
threads might touch.
So global variables are one of
the first things I'm
going to key in when I'm
trying to identify
a critical section.
You know, a local variable could
also reference something
that's shared on the heap.
I might have to worry
about that as well.
But that's what we're trying
to do. We're trying to
identify things that
might be accessed by
different threads at the
same time and then make
sure those are protected
with these locks.
Yeah, question right here.
Mm hm.
Yeah. First off the comment
was that local variables
are on the heap.
That's actually true
in some sense, right?
Let's create like
a string variable
or something like that.
Then I have that variable,
which is on the stack, but it's
referring to something
on the heap, right?
So just because
something's on the heap
doesn't mean I have a problem.
I start worrying when I have
multiple different references
to that thing on that heap,
and maybe different threads
can see different references.
If I know I'm the
only one who can
see it on the heap,
then I'm fine.
I don't have to worry,
right? Does that make sense?
Yeah, y, you're right. There's
some more nuance there.
Yeah, lots of excellent points
today and questions. All right.
Let's do I'm going to do
a couple of worksheet
examples and then do
some coding demos and
try to make this all a little
bit more concrete for us.
All right.
And so I have two
snippets of code here.
And I'm going to
try I walk through the
data structures first.
I have this y variable, which is
kind of not that
important to the example.
Honestly. I have a list,
which has two elements in it.
And then I have this x
variable, which is two.
And I'm imagining that
the variant that I as
the programmer I'm going
for is that I want
x to be equal to the
length of the list.
And right now I can see that
the variant is satisfied.
At this moment in time, right?
And so when I look
at thread one,
thread one acquires a
lock, it appends three.
It increases X, it releases it.
Great. So the logic in thread
one is maintaining
that in variant.
And then thread two is
acquiring the lock,
and it's saying
length of minus x,
and it's storing that in depth.
And so if everything's working
well, what would d be?
Zero, excellent, right?
So if x is equal to
the length of L,
then D will be zero, right?
So that's what I want. And this
is kind of a weird example.
I want to make sure I
don't confuse people.
What I've done is I've
drawn an inter leaving with
some context switches,
and I wrote out something that's
actually impossible, right?
If locks are doing what
they're supposed to
do, this cannot happen.
And when the thing that
happens that shouldn't,
then lots of other weird
things happen, too.
That's the point here. I'm
not saying this can happen.
I'm saying it actually
cannot happen,
but I want you to
help me pinpoint
what is the thing
that cannot happen.
So L et's walk through this.
So y plus equals one, so
we're running thread two.
Great, so y goes four to
five, context switch.
Thread one acquires
a lock. Okay, fine.
Now, context switches
to thread two,
and I want everybody
to gi me a thumbs up.
Yeah, this is something
that could happen,
or no, that's not allowed.
It's impossible.
In kind of a mix of things.
This is totally okay, right?
Holding a lock does not
prevent a context
switch. And why what?
Right? This? Why
stuff is totally
unrelated to what the locking
is with. That is totally okay.
That happens all
the time. Locks do
not prevent context switch.
This is common misconception,
I see again and again.
Okay, great. So, I
context switch back here.
I have penned three
to L. So now,
instead of 54, it's 543.
Great. I context switch here.
And then I call
a qui return successfully.
Can that happen?
Give me a thumbs up
if it can happen,
thumbs down if it
cannot happen. Awesome.
People are getting
it. This cannot
happen. This is impossible.
Right?
If locking is working
correctly, right,
which it generally does,
then this could
never happen, right?
And I should, maybe, honestly,
finish the example there be it
kind of confuses
people think about
like if something
impossible happens,
while other weird things happen.
But let's just cherry
on for a moment.
So D equals length of L
minus x, that would be one.
So already, I kind of
broke my invariant.
If locks were not giving
me what they're
supposed to give me,
then weird things like
that would happen.
Here, I would release the lock.
Okay. And so this point,
nobody's holding the lock.
And then let's say we
contact switch over here.
And then, oh, this is
actually a double release,
so then I would have
a double release
exception over here.
Again, this can't happen
because we'd have never
gotten this far, right?
So so this would be a
double release exception.
And you might see
that at some point.
Why is it an exception to
release a lock that's
already released?
Well, if you write code
that's releasing a lock,
that kind of implies that
you were holding it,
and if you weren't
actually holding it,
that's almost certainly
a bug, right?
So if you see a double
release exception,
it's probably not there.
It's probably earlier
that you meant
to acquire, and you didn't.
All right.
Questions about that
example. Alright. Fantastic.
So now we're going
to do a top hat.
And so I have an
example down here.
And what we can see is that
I have this Q variable.
It starts off being like two,
and then thread two is
trying to change it to zero,
and thread one is trying
to take the verse of it.
So you can already see like
1/0. That's a problem.
And so I'm using some locks.
I want you to help me write out
an example where I'm going
to get that divided by zero.
And rather than doing
kind of a full, like,
back and forth trace,
I want you to say
something like, you know,
like, line X ran
and then line Y Rn.
Just have something
simple like that.
I might leave that up there,
and meanwhile might open up
top hat on here so you can all
whip out your phones
and when you're ready,
you can submit what
you think will happen.
And I'm going to give you
2 minutes to do this.
And I'll just remind
you when there's about,
like, 1 minute left.
So go ahead, kind of
work through that and
then put it on top hat
when you're ready.
Oh, left.
All right.
15 seconds. I'll put
something in soon, please.
Alright, fantastic, things.
So let's come over here and
work through this together.
Let's just do it as a
group. There's a couple
of right answers, but
let's just do one.
Does somebody want to shout
out? What should we say?
What line executes first?
Let's say an A executes first.
Okay. That sounds good
to me. So we'll say A.
And at this moment,
A is t. And again,
the really important
thing is that
once we've decided it's true,
the instruction is going
to keep moving on.
We're not trying to reevaluate
that again. All right.
And then somebody else.
What happens next?
Yeah, right over here.
L et's context switch and
say that x runs next, okay?
And then at this point,
I mean, we could
context switch back,
and we might try telling a qui,
but acquire will not return
successfully until Thread
two finishes, right?
So maybe we might context
switch here and
context switch back,
but we won't actually be able
to acquire in T thread one.
And that means at
this point, we just
have to run this through, right?
So x y z.
So this point we've
finished thread two.
All that's left to
do is switch back.
We're going to do B.
And then C. And at this point,
we get a divide by zero, right?
Because when y ran, right?
Then we had then we had what?
We had Q equal zero.
And then here we have a
divide by zero, right?
Divide by zero, right?
So we have to be really
careful about kind
of getting those.
That locking granularity, right.
Alright. Fantastic.
Any questions about
that before we do some
programming demos?
All right. My head over
here to my laptop.
And the first one I might do
is the one we were
working on last time.
So what were we doing last time?
I was starting up these
two different threads.
And in each case, I was passing
1 million into this ad function.
So looping 1 million times,
and I was adding one to total.
And you might remember
from last time that well,
I had hoped for 2 million I
wasn't getting it. Why was that?
We did a little disassembly
down here and we saw
that When we look at
the byte road level,
like this one line of
code is actually a
few things, right?
We're loading the
variable, we're
loading a constant
adding, storing.
That can get interrupted
by the scheduler, right?
So even something as
simple as like this,
I could have a context switch in
the middle of that
plus equals one,
and then the math
doesn't add up.
Okay, so let's actually go
ahead and fix this now.
I am going to say my lock
equals threading, dot, lock.
And then down here, what I can
say is lock, dot, acquire.
Locked out acquir
and I could say lock
dot, release. All right.
So let's do that. And I
think that this will also
probably run a little
bit slower now.
So I want to import some
time and I want to see
how long this whole
business takes, right?
So I may say start time
equals time dot time here.
And then down here, I may
say n equals time dot.
And then I can just print off,
how long did this whole
thing take, right?
So I'm going to run
that for a moment.
And let's do a little bigger.
So I have something that
actually runs a while.
Let's do like 10 million.
Alright. We're going to do
that. We can see first off,
I got the right answer,
so that's good news.
So that will run for a while.
And then finally, I
see that it took about
5.5 seconds to get that
20 million, right?
Okay, great. That
solves a problem.
A quick question for you all.
Now that I have locking here,
do I still need
join for anything?
Is that useful? What is Join
giving me? Now that
I have locking?
Yeah, right here.
I need to make sure
the road actually
finishes before I
look at the results.
So what Locking is really good
at is to make sure two pieces of
code are not running at
the same time. That's
what locking does.
Sometimes I further
care about that
this piece of code runs
before that piece of code.
Joining is one of the things
that will help us do that.
There's other stuff out
there if you like to go take
the OS course 53070 to learn
about some other things.
The two primitives we learn
in this course is
locks for making
sure things don't happen at
the same time and join
to make sure that,
you know, Code A runs before
Code B. Alright,
so that's great.
We solved that problem.
And what I'm doing here is what
we might call fine
grained locking.
I kind of acquire a lock, and
I do a small piece of work,
and then I release a lock.
Okay? And if I do
fine grain locking,
maybe I can be having lots
of different threads doing
things maybe roughly
at the same same time.
Now, a lot of people have
this intuition that, oh,
I need finer drain locks
to get better performance,
and that's not always true.
Unfortunately, locking has
a lot of overhead to it,
and so doing just a little bit
of work with each lock
is not always best.
So I'm just try to
make a note here.
This is what I would call
fine grained locking.
What I'm going to
do is I'm going
to copy this whole business,
and I'm going to come down
here and I want to see
what is core strain
locking like.
So I to do some core
strain locking.
And here, I'm just going to
the opposite of doing one thing.
I'm going to do
10 million things
before I release that lock
and I'm going to run that.
And what I'll see is that
instead of taking 5.7 seconds,
it is 1.5 seconds.
One of the takeaways
here is that
all this stuff with locking
and the performance of it,
a lot of it is very
counterintuitive,
and I want you to
get in the habit
of measuring your code.
Don't take some
code that's simple
and make it super complicated
to have a bunch of locks.
And then accidently
make it slower.
That's just like the
worst of all worlds.
It happened to me once.
I was working on this
bioinformatics open source thing,
and I was like, really slow
and I was kind of diving in.
And what I saw is that they
had to read this large file,
and that was like the slow
thing they had to do.
And so this bioinformatician,
what they did is
they had a bunch
of threads and they
would acquire the lock,
read the line of the file,
and then release the lock,
and they would draw line by line
and they probably saw it was
slow and they're just like,
I'm going to optimize this and
break and pat
themselves on the back.
I deleted all of that, made
it a single thread version,
and was like ten
times faster, right?
So measure things. Don't assume
that you're making
things faster.
Yeah, question right here.
What's that?
Yeah, what is the reason
for it to be faster?
So in this case,
there's probably not
very many context
switches, right?
It's probably just like
going to be running
this one for a long time.
I don't want to get too much
on the hardware details
of it as well.
But we spent all this
time learning about
the cashes like the
l1l2, L three cash.
We kind of have to be a little
bit careful about how cashing
works if we have locking, right?
So we'll maybe
take it as a given
that it's slower without
getting too much details.
And we can talk more offline
as well. Yeah,
question right here.
S Yeah.
Yeah, what actually happens.
So I guess, in this case,
let's say thread
one starts first,
acquires that lock
for a long time.
Now you're saying
Lock two comes along.
It tries to a You're
saying what happens
with T thread two?
Yeah. Yeah, that's a
great question, right?
So we have a little help
from the operating system.
And what we learned last time,
maybe a couple of times ago was
that threads can be
one of three states.
They can be actually
running out of CPU.
They can be ready to
run, given the option,
or they can be blocked on
like Deskio or Internet
or anything, right?
When you try to acquire a lock
and that lock is not free,
the operating system
is going to say,
Oh, you are blocked now,
and the scheduler
will not even try
to run it until that lock is
There's other variants too.
I'm just thinking like one
of the things that could happen.
That's what happened here.
There's other ways
people do locks as well,
but that's what would
generally happen.
Yeah, yeah, great question.
Yeah. Other questions
people have.
All right. Cool.
So, what I want to do
now is jump over to
another example.
And this is in my
lecture snippets.
So if you go to the
website and you like
resources and lecture snippets,
I have that banking example
from earlier, which I will copy.
And I will start that in
a new notebook over here,
and I'm going to
import threading,
and I mean, I guess it's not
really doing anything yet.
We can actually see
that they already do
some locking here.
They create a lock.
It's a very coarse
screen locking.
I think that's all fine, right?
So all is good.
Let me just try running this
code with a few transfers.
I'm going to say, let's
transfer let's say,
from X to Y,
and we're going to
transfer like $5.
And then after
that I want to see
what is in my bank accounts.
Let's take a look at that.
Okay, that worked fine, right?
Now, I'm going to actually
do something that's
going to fail.
I'm going to say, let's
transfer from W to Y.
And that's going to be a problem
because Well, there's no W here.
And if you try to look
up a key that doesn't
exist like this,
if I'm trying to
look up that value,
then I would get a
key error exception.
And so let's see I get
my key error exception.
Okay, fine, right?
I'll make a note here,
right. So there is
no W. And, fine.
Let's do this from something
else. I will do it from Z.
There's a Z. And so
I'm going to say,
let's grow from z to y, right?
I know there's a Z,
I know there's a Y.
Let me do that. And Huh?
Well, that's taking
a long time to run.
I wonder what happened
there. Let me
take a look back at
this code up here.
And let's take a moment.
And if anybody has
any thoughts on why
I'm suddenly stuck,
yeah, pop up a hand.
Yeah, right here already.
Is still acquired from previous.
The lock is still acquired.
Excellent, right?
Be what happened before?
I acquired the lock,
I was drawing lock.
I had an exception,
and I popped out of
that function before we
actually ever ever released.
So that's a problem.
You want to not only
write Dod like threading
code and locking code.
You want to make sure it's
exception safe as well.
And so one of the ways
we can do that with
Python is with something
called a context manager.
I'm just trying to kill this
notebook, if you don't mind.
And I'll come down here
and I'm going to fix this.
So instead of doing the
lock acquisition like this,
I can say, with lock, right?
And what this means is that
the lock is a context manager,
and I can have a
block of code here.
And what will happen
down here is that it
will automatically release it,
even if there's an
exception, right?
So this is the way you should
generally be doing locking
unless you have a good
reason to do it another way.
I don't even have
to do this anymore.
Maybe I can just
print this here,
I can say locked,
and I can say locked dot locked,
and I can take a peek at that.
And then after this
block of code,
I'm going to come
down here, and I'm
going to say I locked down here.
And let's just try calling
it a couple of times, right?
I'm going to say
something like I'll
do this transfer,
which was fine.
I can see that inside, it's
locked outside, it's not.
I am trying to try the
broken one again, right?
I had an exception as before.
And then let's try
one more grod one.
I'll do like another x to y.
And then it still
works just fine.
Right? So we want to
use context managers.
In general, when you're
doing systems programming,
we care about resources.
What is a resource?
It could be a lock. It could
be an open file,
things like that.
We want to use context managers
when we can to free
those things up.
You know, Maybe an equivalent
that more people have
seen is you might have
a try accept finally.
I think that to actually
looks pretty ugly, frankly.
I don't try except finally.
Context manager is a better way
to do that in a very
pythonic way to do that.
All right. Cool. Do people
have any questions about
that example the width
statement? Right.
Cool. So let me head over here.
I want to go back
to this worksheet,
where I do some more
examples on the worksheet.
I'm to go to the do cam.
And let's head to
the other side.
All right. So here's a
little snippet of code.
And I see that I'm using
both doin and locking.
I just want to try to figure out
what I can guarantee
about my variable.
So the variable I'm really
interested in is x.
X starts as one,
and at some point x is
two. And I'm very careful.
Whenever I look at x,
I'm using a lock. I
say with lock here.
Down here, I'm using
W lock as well.
And then the question here is,
what is A, B and C?
And that's really asking what
x is at different
points in time.
I I say A equals x, B equals x,
C equals x. I want to
see if we can reason
through the values of x at
these three points in time.
And sometimes maybe we know
exactly what it'll be.
Other times, the depend, right?
It might depend on the scheduler
and when context
switches happen.
Okay. And so we're going
to do all this together.
And the way we'll do
it is, if I ask you,
you'll say, either one
finger up, two fingers up,
or if we can't know,
kind of, you know,
struke your chin like, Hmm,
I'm not sure about that if
we don't have a good
way of knowing.
Okay, so let's do A first.
So at this point, A equals X,
and at this point in time, I'm
wondering, what is
the value of A?
Is it one, two,
or can't really know.
I'm seeing some ones,
which is correct.
Does anybody who has a one
up want to volunteer y?
Yeah, right over here.
You said to one before
any things happen.
Yeah, I said to one before
retting actions happen.
Yeah. And at this point, we
haven't even started y, right?
So threats are not
involved, right?
We haven't started running
this other threat.
So I agree that will
definitely be one.
Let's skip around a bit.
Let's do C. All right.
I C going to be one, two,
or can't really tell.
People seem less
sure on this one.
I see a few twos up,
which is Correct.
Does anybody want to help
me reason through it?
Why do I know that C
is going to be two?
Yeah, go ahead. C
is changed x after
join in changing x to two.
Yeah, you're like changing
these along, right?
This happens after the join,
and the join happens after
the task finish is running.
Therefore, x equals
two before C equals x.
So I agree it is going
to be two there.
Excellent. A, C. Let's do B now.
Is it one, two, or We can't
really know for sure.
People don't seem to be as
confident about this one.
We can't really know for sure.
We put a question
here. We don't know.
Does anybody who
reason through that?
Does anybody want to
share their thoughts?
Yeah, right over here.
Yeah. Excellent.
Depending on when the
context switch happens,
either one could hit the lock.
Maybe the main thread
hits the lock first.
In which case, it would be
one. Maybe the task thread
hits the lock first and
then it would be
two. We don't know.
Yeah, question right
here. Can there be
a context and the
first line of task?
Can there be a context switch
between start and
which one? Local x.
Yeah, absolutely. When
I say t dot start,
the scheduler really
has full freedom.
When I say to start, maybe it
runs that thread immediately,
maybe it runs it
for a long time.
Maybe when I say t dot start,
it just puts a sign says,
we'll run that later
and it might keep
running the main thread.
Now, when we actually
run the code,
it'll probably do
one or the other.
I'll probably either
often run the task
first or tend to run main first,
but we don't have any guarantee.
Maybe in a week, there's
a minor version update,
and might do something
different, right?
That's why it's so
tricky, we have to
reason through it rather
than just testing it.
We have no guarantee if the
main thread will run first
or the child task
will run first.
Yeah, that's a good question.
Other questions people
have about this.
All right. Cool. So, let's
learn about a new kind of
bug called a deadlock.
And we've been talking
about whether our locks
are kind of like coarse
or fine and drained.
When I've been using ample cab,
what I'm really meaning, like,
is it a lock covering a lot
of code or a little
bit of a code?
Another way that a lock could
be either coarse or
fine and drain might be
with respect to what
data structures that
it's covering, right?
Do I have kind of, like,
one course grained
global lock that
protects everything
or do I have,
you know, different locks for
different pieces of data?
And so this is a lot like
that banking example I have.
And here I have bank
accounts A and B,
but you know, you could
generalize, imagine it's more.
And I'm imagining that I have
a lock for each bank account.
You know, in the
general use case,
I probably have some
weird dictionary where
I have a lock for every
entry in the dictionary.
So I could really have a
lock for every bank account.
That would be totally normal,
reasonable thing people do.
And so what that means is that,
since I now have a lock
for each bank account
and I want to do the
transfer together.
I want to pull from one account
and put it in the other,
and I want that to appear
as if it happened
at the same time.
That means that I
actually have to acquire
two locks before I can
do a transfer, right?
So I have one transfer
that's drawing from
A to B and one
that's from B to A.
And so I'm just trying to
kind of walk through
what might happen here.
So imagine that thread one
does a lock A dot acquire.
All right, so I may
acquire over here?
Let's say we context switch now,
and I may say, right,
now when I say that we
do a lock B acquire.
Ack Bt acquire.
And hopefully everybody can
help with some nodding.
Can Thread two acquire
Lock A right now?
No. The one role we have is
that for any given lock,
it can be held by at most
one thread at a time.
Lock A is already held.
We cannot acquire Lock A.
Okay. So this thread
will be blocked,
and it will context
switch over here.
Can Thread one acquire lock B?
No.
It's already held. Can't
be held by more than once.
So what will happen
is that we're just
going to be blocked forever.
I'm going to write that
down. We're blocked forever.
We're just stuck. Okay? And so
you have to think about
when you're doing locking.
I mean, you can decide,
like, maybe I just
want to have like a
single threaded process.
I don't have to worry
about any of this stuff.
Maybe I have multiple threads
in a single global lock,
then I have to worry about
race conditions but
not deadlocked.
Maybe I want to get
really fancy and I
want to have a lot of fine
grain locking like that.
Now you have to worry
about deadlock, too.
You can kind of choose make
these decisions about.
If I want to get
better performance,
I might have more complexity,
but then I have to worry
about more times of bugs may
or may not be worth it,
given your situation.
And what do people
do here, right?
The way you solve
this? It's really
a circular dependency
like A b4b, B B four A.
To really break this,
we have to agree that
we always acquire locks
in the same order.
If you do that,
it's okay to have
multiple locks and we
won't have deadlock.
And so a very common comment
you'll see and that
you should have in
code like this is we could
say, like, lock order.
And we might say something
like Lock A before Lock B.
And we have to make sure any
piece of code follows that,
otherwise, you could
get a deadlock.
And of course that could
be much more complicated.
I've read some phone in the
Linux kernel, for example,
where they maybe have like
eight or ten different
kinds of locks,
and they have a whole
read me about it.
And a lot of the read me
what it's saying is like,
this is the order you're
going to acquire locks,
and you have to
acquire these ones
to make such and
such updates, right?
It can really get
quite complicated,
right? And that's
not always worth it.
But if you are going
that route, make
sure you document well how
people should actually use
the locking. All right.
Any questions people
have about that example
or about deadlocking in general?
Yeah, question right over here.
Yeah, that's a really
interesting question.
So, how would I know
that I had a deadlock?
Well, first off, like, we'll see
it just like everything
kind of hung up.
How do I know it
specifically a deadlock?
Well, one of the
things you could do is
if you had a debugger,
you could attach to it,
and you could see for
each of your threads,
You could do a
back trace, right?
Back race looks a lot
like an exception.
When I have an exception thrown,
I get some line numbers,
I could do a back
trace for each thread,
and I could see, uh,
program's not making progress.
All my threads are waiting
to acquire a lock,
and I could look at the code,
and I could try
to figure it out.
Or you could do prints, right?
Sometimes I'll do a print
like before and after
I acquire a lock,
and I could t do just like
simple print debugging
to see it happens.
But the first symptom
that will make you
investigate is that
it just hangs up.
Nobody's making progress, right?
And honestly, like,
of these two bugs,
I would much rather
have a deadlock
because it's like
everything's kind of frozen.
I can take my time.
I can look at it.
The race condition
is much harder
debug it kind of
maybe happens once,
and then if I fix it,
do I really know
that I fixed it,
or maybe it's just
that the timing
worked out a little bit
differently, right?
Yeah excellent question though,
how do we diagnose this?
Yeah, other questions about
this example are
about deadlocks.
Right. Cool.
So, in my experience,
I teach people about
threading and locks.
They get excited about
it, and they try to be.
It feels like a puzzle,
right? So it kind of
makes you want to start
being very clever.
And I'm going to show you
about some other weird things,
more advanced topics with
the goal of convincing
you don't be clever,
do simple things when
you're doing locking.
Otherwise, you're
gonna end up in kind
of like a world of
trouble, right?
So let's look at a couple
of advanced topics.
Maybe actually I might just
get to the global
interpreter lock today,
and I'll talk about instruction
reordering and
caching next time.
Oh, you cannot see my
strange. Alright,
let's bring this up.
So let's talk about some
of these advanced topics,
like the global
Interpreter lock.
So here I have a picture
of a bunch of CPU cores,
and then I have a virtual
address space here.
This is one virtual addre space.
I have my Python toward as
the virtual adder space.
Maybe I have maybe I'm
using like Num Pi, right?
That's a library
mostly written in C,
maybe I have that in my
virtual adder space.
And I have a bunch of threads,
and we can see that some
of them are running,
right they're attached
to a CPU core.
This one over here,
it's blocked.
It's waiting for a file, right?
And I see another one here,
which is very interesting.
It's waiting for
something called the GIL.
That stands for the
global interpreter lock.
And it turns out that Python for
a long time has had
this centralized lock.
And any thread that's
currently running
on the CPU has to hold that.
And what that effectively
means is that we
cannot be having
multiple Python threads
actually using multiple CPU
cores at the same time,
even though that's
one of the big
motivations for using threads.
Are threads still useful in
Python as of today?
Maybe, right?
Because I have this
thread over here
that's waiting for a file.
That's still useful.
I can have a few threads
that are blocked on IO,
and then maybe one
that's actually running.
You can also see that somehow,
even though I have this
global interpreter lock,
I have multiple threads that are
actually running on the CPU
cores at the same time.
How did that happen?
Well, if I'm
programming a Python package
in a language like C,
I can do some advanced
things and say,
I'm willing to release
the global interpreter
lock in certain cases.
So the way people have
often gone around this,
they'll use num Pi
or Pi torch or Pi
arrow or any of these
different things
that can solve this issue,
and just like the
straightforward Python trow,
they won't be running
things concurrently,
but in these C libraries,
they will, okay?
That's something to
be aware of. Let me
just show you how
this might work.
At this point, this
one was waiting for
the global interpreter
lock, so it's blocked.
That first Python
thread is done.
So now both of those
are vulnerable.
Then when it starts
running that other one,
the first one will be waiting on
the global interpreter lock.
All right. This one was
waiting on file IO.
When it's done, it can't
immediately run would then
need to wait on the global
interpreter law. All right?
And then they might be applied
to other things as well.
I'm trying to make that
example longer than I need to.
So why do they have
this awful thing that
is limiting parallel execution?
Well, it's related to another
thing called garbage collection.
Let me just give
you a quick idea
of how garbage collection works.
Here I have two threads.
In the first case, I
guess x equals some list,
and they say x equals none.
And then thread two, I say
y equals that same list,
and then y equals none.
And what does that look like?
Well, I have I have
two local variables,
each this x and y and those
are for different threads,
and they each have
their own stack,
and those variables
are referencing
a common data
structure on the heat.
Python is actually keeping
track of how many
references there
are to that data structure
object. Why does it do that?
Well, when I say
run y equals none,
I want to decrease it,
and when I say x
equals none later,
then I could realize
there's no more references
and I could actually
clean it up.
The main implementation
of Python does
this reference counting so it
knows when it can
free up that list.
Otherwise I might just keep
using more and more
memory over time,
and we wouldn't want to do that.
And so Python is doing
this all the time,
is keeping track of
these reference counts
internally on all your
different data structures.
And and that should
try to remind you of this
example we saw earlier,
where we had two
threads that were both
counting to 10 million
is what happened there.
When I had two things
that were plus
equal one minus equal one,
that could get interrupted
at a bad time.
Same thing can happen here
with these integers here.
I have to be very careful
how I make sure that
I'm safely accessing
these reference counts.
And so the Python approach
has been for a long time.
Well we just have one
thread running at a time.
We don't have to have locking
around those reference counts.
Another approach is that you
could have lots of locking,
and that could let us
have multiple threads,
but then maybe constantly
acquiring and releasing locks,
that might slow
things down a lot.
And so the decision
so far has been,
let's optimize for single
threaded performance
because it's a
fundamental trade off.
If we make multiple threads
run at the same time,
and we have garbage collection,
then single threaded
performances worse,
and that wasn't a trade off
they were willing to make.
Now, We're like seeing
history happen happening
in the making, right?
So this is actually Python
3.13 is being released tomorrow.
And they're adding an
experimental feature
where you can run without
the global interpreter lock.
You know, it's experimental.
You actually have to download
a different version of the
interpreter to have it.
And they say if you do
that, you should expect
a substantial single
threaded performance hit.
So what does the history,
how this all play out?
We may likely have
Python interpreters without
the global Interpreter lock,
or maybe you're going to
have to have a PEC, right?
So something you
have to be aware of,
and it'll probably be
something we have to be aware
of for a long time. Alright.
I think I'm going a
break there because I
don't want to get
into this next topic.
I do have 330 meeting,
so I normally stay
in chat with folks,
but I got to book
it out of here.
So, feel free to drop
an e mail or something,
or we can catch up on
Wednesday too. Have
a great evening.