At the start. One is,
I'm sure most of you are aware
there's presidential
election tomorrow.
There's a lot of local things
on the ballot as well.
So if you're eligible
and you want to vote,
you know, I encourage
you to do so.
There's a site for
Wisconsin called
my vote doi dot basically
what I have here.
And that would help you
figure out where to do it.
So you say where to vote and
you put in your address,
and it would tell you um
it would also show you what
your ballot is in advance.
It vari state by state.
Some states you have to
register in advance.
In Wisconsin, you
can actually go if
you bring evidence of residency,
you can actually
register at the poll.
So anyway, just throwing
it out there in case
anybody has not voted and
is eligible and wants to.
Some course related
announcements as well.
I got this quiz
released a little later
than I had intended to.
I normally do that on Friday,
so you can actually submit
that as late as Friday.
This week would be fine.
We also have a mid term one week
from today in class here.
Same deal as last time,
you get your one
note sheet again.
Same amount of time, same
number of questions,
multiple choice again.
Any logistical questions
people have about that,
I'll probably mid term.
Yeah, right here.
Yeah, I don't know
if I'll have time
for review or I pushed
things back a little bit.
Unfortunately at some point,
I was hoping to have review,
but yeah, it's not looking
likely. So sorry about that.
Yeah, other questions
people have?
Cool. So thanks again
for being flexible
about last Friday.
I wasn't feeling well, so I
posted some recordings instead.
Hopefully people have had
a chance to watch that.
I'm going to start off doing
just a little bit of review,
and then we're also going to
do some top hat to make sure
everybody is up to speed on what
I was talking about last Friday.
I am going to head over
to the slides first.
And this is an example
of a Cassandra scheme.
So lots of interesting
things about Cassandra.
What is how we actually
model data in it?
In this case, I have some data
related to weather stations.
So the weather
stations have IDs,
and for each ID,
there's a corresponding name.
I could totally have
different weather stations
that might have the same name,
but a single weather station
cannot have multiple names.
We also have some weather
data on each date.
Each weather station is
sending some reports of,
like, well, what is the
temperature, things like that?
In a traditional database like
my SQL or really a
lot of databases,
these would probably be
two separate tables.
You have a table of stations,
and you'd have a table
of weather events.
You'd probably
have a primary key
on your stations and a foi
and on your weather events
that could associate
each weather
event with the station, right?
Now, Castandra doesn't
really do joins,
and so primary and foreign
keys are not as useful.
And so what we'll often do
instead is we'll have them
in one table like this.
What would really normally be
two tables are going
to be together.
And what we'll do is I
have some rows that are
per partition, right?
So here I have some piece of
data that's per partition,
both the partition key,
the 123, and the name.
That's a static column.
So a static column doesn't
uniquely identify the partition,
but there's only one piece of
data if it's static
per partition.
In contrast, I could have a
bunch of different rows with
regular values within a
single partition, right?
Some part of that, in this case,
the date is a cluster key,
and the cluster key uniquely
identifies a row within
a partition, right?
So if I have a date and
I have a partition,
then I can uniquely
identify one row,
and then there might
be some number of
just regular columns like
temp associated
with that, right?
So in this case, again, right,
Station ID is a partition key,
date is the cluster key.
And the primary key is a
combination of those, right?
Because the primary key
uniquely identifies
exactly exactly one row.
Yeah. Question right here.
C. So that one
is not static because there are
many different temperatures
within a single partition,
if it was static, then
this weather station
could just have one
temperature overall.
Maybe it be like
the current temperature
or something like that,
but if I want to have
a records of it and
multiple things,
then it's just a
regular problem.
So I guess in this case, I mean,
probably most columns
are usually going to
be temp they're just
regular columns.
But in this case,
everything is some kind of
special column except for
temps only ordinary column here.
That makes sense? Yeah,
thanks for asking.
U So another interesting
thing about this is
that we're going to
talk more about how
data actually gets placed
across our cluster.
But a given partition
is going to
be on a specific machine,
or we have replication a
specific set of machines.
And so if I wanted
to get all the data for a
specific weather station,
I know I can talk to just one
specific machine instead of
having to gather the data piece
me all across my cluster.
So I can make some
informed decisions
that are going to
affect performance.
The other thing is
that this cluster key,
in addition to helping uniquely
identify a role
within a partition,
that can be used to
specify a sort order.
And then the data will be
sorted in that order on disk.
And remember that when we
have either hard drives,
we want sequential IO because,
well, what happens
when we read our data?
We have to move the
hard drive head.
We have to wait for
the platter to turn.
We start transferring data.
So if we have a
big sequential IO,
then things are going to be
more efficient because we don't
pay that upfront cost as much.
Even if I have an SSD,
right data is transferred at
the granularity of these pages.
And so if I'm accessing,
just a tiny subset of page,
that would be inefficient
for an SSD, right?
So both case, I
want sequential IO.
And so it's really
important how I choose
my cluster key, right?
Be If I choose my cluster
key, and it's sorted by that,
then consecutive values will
be consecutive in my files,
and I can, you
know, for example,
I can get all the temperatures
in a given range with
just one big IO instead of
having lots of little IOs.
So do people have
any questions about
this idea of data
modeling in Cassandra?
There here. Oh, yeah,
what is the primary
key for the first row?
It would be So I would
do the partition key together
with the cluster key.
So for the first row, it
would be one, two, three,
200303 oh one would
be the primary key.
Was there adding something about
adding a one in the zero?
Oh, you know, sometimes, right?
Like, with my primary key,
I guess you're kind
of referring back
to is that the one in the
zero you're referring to?
Yeah, sometimes I will not
have we'll definitely have
to have a partition key.
Sometimes I don't specify
a cluster key, right?
And then the primary key
doesn't really help me get
down to an individual
row in that case.
Right? Because if I don't
have any cluster keys,
well then my primary key and
my partition key would
just be the same.
So that would be kind
of a weird case, right?
Because you're kind of
losing a lot of the benefit.
Yeah, but thanks for
bringing that back.
Yeah. Other questions are
Thomas people have from
last time. Alright, cool.
So let's do a couple of top pats
and make sure we're
all on the same page.
So come over here and
get that drawing.
Excuse me.
About 30 seconds left.
All right. So people are saying
the partition key,
which is correct.
So coming back to
this picture, right?
For this partition key of 123,
there's a most one static value
associated with it, right?
I mean, it could
also be null, right?
Alright. Cool. So
let's head back here.
We're going to
another one. This one
is just to review a bit
about the planet algorithm
that we talked about.
About 30 seconds left.
Alright, so the second
answer B is indeed correct.
When I'm looking
at both of these,
I see in the first one,
they tried to have each
bucket of with 25.
And that's kind of how a
traditional histogram works.
Now, if you look
at those buckets,
some of them are actually empty.
Like, the 50 to 75
bucket is empty.
The 25 to 50 bucket is empty.
And for our purposes here,
that's not good because
With the decision tree,
what we're trying to do
at each note is we're
trying to ask a question
about the data.
And the question of
the form is my column.
Let's say that this
feature column is called
x. I say is x
greater than or equal to 50
or some other threshold.
And so what thresholds
are we considering
for the questions?
Well, we're considering
the thresholds that are
the boundaries between
our histogram buckets.
And so In the first case,
it doesn't lead to very
interesting questions
because I have a x
greater than equal to 25,
is greater than equal to 50,
is it greater than equal to 75?
Those are all the
same. We want to have
different questions to choose
from that split up the
data in different ways.
And so the latter buckets are
nice because we're
trying to have
an even amount of
data in each bucket.
And that means if I choose
different thresholds
between the buckets,
I will actually be splitting
up the data in different ways.
And that's why the
planet algorithm
will choose thresholds
from the boundaries between
equal depth histogram buckets.
Alright, Cel. So we're
going to head over here,
back to the notebook
we were in last time.
And I had already started
up my Cassandra cluster.
It's running. I have
some Python stuff here
that connects to it.
Remember that a Cssandra cluster
has different key spaces.
Each keyspace has, you know,
maybe a bunch of
different tables in it.
I'm using a key space that
I created called banking.
I just do this in case the
loans table already exists.
I create a loans table here.
We saw from last time that
the bank idea is
my partition. Key.
These two together
are my cluster key.
It's a little bit srange to have
the loan amount be part
of the cluster key.
But I did that because
then I'm allowed
to order my data by amount.
And if I wanted to
then go back and say,
find the biggest
loans for each bank,
I could very quickly
do that, right?
We say there's a static
column here called bank name,
and then there's a couple
of regular columns,
such as, well, actually,
I think just one.
State is the only
regular column.
Alright, so we did some
inserts last time.
So first, I inserted bank
ID and bank name, right?
So this was my partition key
and my static column,
and I did that.
And what was a little
bit strange about that?
I wonder if I doesn't really
quite show it here, does it?
What's a little bit strange
about that is it's allowed,
even though I don't have
a complete primary key.
What does that mean?
Well, coming back
to that picture,
that means I am just inserting
this piece of data here.
So really, I'm creating
a partition that doesn't
have any rows in it, right?
So it's kind of strange
that I'm running this line,
and I don't actually
have any real
rows associated with it.
Down here, I'm doing
an insert again.
I actually has the
same partition key,
and that was strange
that worked too.
The reason that worked
is that Insert and
Cassandra would actually
better be called an Sert.
So Usert means update or insert.
And so since I already
have that, it's updated,
It to change the bank name
from test to test two.
So I come down here and I
query it, and I see a
couple of things, right.
I see that it's test two,
right? So that dot updated.
I also see that all the things
related to actual rows
are just null, right?
So it's just showing me
some information for
our partition with no real rows.
Whatever we query stuff, we're
going to still get
tables, right?
But that's going
to be a little bit
confusing unless you have
a mental model of how we
have some information
that's per partition
and some that is
per actual rows.
For example, right?
If I see that kind
of looks like there's one
row, even though there's not.
So when I insert another row,
and I query it, there's
only going to be
one entry that comes
back to me, right?
So when I insert this,
what am I doing?
Right? I'm inserting into
the bank ID partition,
and then the loan
amount is 300,000,
and then I'm giving it a
UID and I select down here.
I see that I'm not creating
any new partitions
and that row that added to
that existing partition.
So even though I only
had one entry up here,
there's only one entry
back here, too, right?
So the fact that everything
comes back to me,
it feels like I'm getting
a table of results back,
that can be a little
bit misleading.
We have to really understand
how things work internally,
or you know, it'll
just be confusing.
So do people have
any questions about
why that worked like
that? Yeah, right here.
I fail name Would it have
failed if I had multiple
bank names under Oh,
it's fine that I don't specify
the bank name because it's
already there, right?
So I had previously inserted
a partition, right?
And then when I'm
inserting additional rows,
I don't need to specify what
the bank name is again, right?
It's already there
for them, right?
They're associated with whatever
the bank name was before
because I know they're
associated with 544.
And I know that the bank
name for that is Test two.
Does that make sense? Test 12.
Yeah, you're saying, well,
if test and test two were
actually different bank names.
Well, in that case, if
they're actually, like,
multiple inserts
instead of the update,
then that would mean this one
would have to have a
different ID, right?
And so if this one
had a different ID,
let's say it was
like 544 and 555,
Then I would actually
have two entries down
here because I can see
some information
for each partition.
And then the name here
would really depend on,
was it for 544 or 555?
Does that make
sense? So, kind of,
like, looking back at
this picture, right?
I I did a query over let's
say, these values, right?
Then I'll see the station name
as Madison Airport, right?
And the same way here, I'm
seeing the bank
name as Test two.
That makes sense?
Yeah, thank you.
Yeah, there are
questions people have.
Yeah, right here. The
partition key is the bank ID.
And then sometimes we
want extra information
per partition,
but it's not uniquely
identifying. It's a static.
Yeah, so it Yeah. That's
nice way of putting it.
So the way we put down
is that. It's almost as
if the bank name
or in this case,
station name, like, trickles
down to all the rows.
That's a great way
to think about
it. It does that logically.
When I ate the data, I see it,
but it doesn't trickle down in
the sense that it's not actually
making multiple copies of it.
Whenever I ate the data,
it looks like there's
multiple copies internally
to the database.
There's only one copy.
Yeah. Thank you.
Thank you. Maybe
I'll use that again.
Yeah. Column. What kind
of column is bank name?
Bank name is a static column.
Yeah. And then to go back here,
we see that we added
that here. That's why.
Yeah, crush here. Rep.
Oh, why is bake ID?
So that one wasn't static
because that was the
partition g, right?
So the two pieces of
information that are just per
partition or partition
g and static columns.
And the syntax here
is weird because
I'm not explicitly
saying, this is my partition g.
But what they will do is
they'll look at my primary key,
and they'll take out
the first piece,
and that's my partition get.
So I can see, bak
ID is my partition
g. If I wanted to have a
multiple components
of my partition g,
I could have done
like that, right?
But that's why it's look.
It's looking at this.
It's looking at
this year. And you
can imagine nice, you know,
exam questions almost kind
of like read and say,
which things are like per
partition, right? Make sense?
Partition cheese are
not static columns
because they uniquely
identify a partition,
but they're very similar
to static columns because
both partition cheese and
static are per partition,
they're similar. All right.
So I did that. Now, this is
a very strange query here.
So let's think about
what this is doing.
Okay. So this is inserting
a new loan, great.
I'm inserting it into
the same psition
I've been working in, right?
And so all of this stuff is
specifying that
new loan details.
But what's very strange that I
put in something static, right?
That bank 544
already has a name.
And this is Is it up
like, it's an upsert?
Right? Every insert
is an upsert.
But in this case,
what is it doing?
Is it updating or
is it inserting?
And the answer is, B,
for this part of it, it's
creating a new row of data.
Like over here. And for
this part of it, it says,
Well, the name of Bank 544
should now be my bank, right?
So it's like it's
updating this over here.
Right? So when I
come and query this,
I see that well,
there is test two here, and
now they're both my bank, right?
So this one well it's an upsert,
and this is kind of
unique in that it was an
insert and an update
at the same time.
At the partition level
it was updating,
the role level it was inserting.
Any questions about that query?
The other thing I see here is
that because amount is
part of my cluster key,
that's ascending or it's
descending from me.
I have the biggest one first.
Let me insert another
one down here.
And so in this case,
I am going to insert
Let's do a new bank. So
I'm going to say 999,
and this will be the
UW Credit Union,
and we will say it's
a $500,000 loan,
and let's say it's in Illinois.
I'm going to do that.
And in this case,
I'm doing actually two insert.
I'm inserting a new partition,
and it has a new row inside
of it. And so that's cool.
One thing I want you to
see is that this notion
of the cluster and
the ordering on
it is only a a per
partition basis, right?
So within the 544 partition,
amount is descending
Any ordering
over here is independent
of the other ordering.
Okay? All right.
Any question about that query?
All right. So what
I want to talk
about now is how we can
have some custom types.
So custom types.
And custom types are almost
kind of, like, you know,
like a struct in C or a
class in Java or Python,
where you have different fields,
and then there might be some
types associated with them.
And it's going to be pretty
similar up here, right?
When I create a table,
it's also that I
have some fields and types
associated with them.
So maybe I'll just copy some of
this syntax and modify it.
So I'm to come down here.
And instead of creating a table,
I'm going to create a
type, and I'm going to say
that this type is
called full name.
And then I can put
some types in here.
And because it's just a type
and not a actual table,
there would be no clustering or
any of that business. All right?
And so kind of a
simplification of names,
but I'll say that there are
first and last names
in this example,
and I'll say they're both text.
Alright, so let me create that.
And you know, I
should have started
my notebook fresh after
the morning lecture.
I wonder if it'll let me do it.
I'll say drop type fullname
drop type if exists.
I wonder if that will
do it. Finger stress.
Okay, great. And so I can
create that new type.
And then if I want to, I can use
this as a type name
and other columns.
So let me add
a column to my loan
so that we can have a user
name for everybody, right?
I may say Let me
check my notes here.
I'm going to say, Al table.
Let me just clean all this up.
Al table loans.
And then I can I can add a
field and a type in here,
a field. And a type.
Alright. So I'm gonna
do that. And so
the field name will
just be my user name.
I'm sorry. No comma here.
And then the type is going to be
a full name. I'm gonna do that.
And remember that Cassandra
tables are sparse.
And so a took a
noticeable of time.
But even if my table
had been giant,
like I have millions of rows,
that will happen quickly
because it doesn't
actually have to create a
bunch of empty values in it.
Like a traditional
database would
probably have to create
a bunch of null values,
and it might actually
take some time to
add add a column. Not so here.
Alright. So if I have that,
then I can come back and I
can I delete this up here
where I was trying to I guess,
I'll just run it
down here again.
That's fine. I can
see those things.
If I want to, I could also
select specifically user name.
And one thing that's kind
of cool is I can say
username do and username last.
And If x is null,
then x dot y is null two.
It doesn't create an
error like it would in
say like Java or Python
or something like that.
Right? That's safe, just like
I have this chain of dots,
the null just passes through,
and it all comes out clean.
All right. I have that.
Let me actually insert
some values in here.
So I'm going to come
back and I'm going to
look at my last insert.
All I'm going to do
this one, for this one,
instead of having the state,
I'm going to have the user
name for that, what will I do?
I will put in and almost looks
like a dictionary, right?
And the fields in it
are first and last.
Unlike a Python dictionary,
we aren't going to putting
quotes around it, right?
So I'm just going to
put my values here.
So maybe for the first name,
I'll say Tyler,
and the last name,
I'll say C, and I can do that.
These have to be
in single quotes.
That's just again kind of
one of these quirks of,
of the syntax, right? So
I'm going to do that.
Let me come and select
this back here again
just so we can see how it looks
to actually have values there.
And now I can see when I
select the whole thing,
it almost looks like
a tuple with those,
and I can pull out
individual values
from it, if I would like.
All right. Cool. A question
about custom types?
Yeah, right here.
That's a great question.
So did insert or upsert?
And So I can answer that
question at two levels,
at the partition level
and the per row level.
So at the partition level,
this was an existing
partition key.
And so I was updating
the name to be this.
But that happened
already to be the name.
So at the partition
key, technically,
I'm updating, but
nothing changed.
What about at the row level?
So at the role level,
I have to think about
what my primary key is.
My primary key is
the bank ID plus loan
amount plus loan ID.
So because now generates
a new ID each time,
it's a new row.
So this is an insert
at the role level.
That makes sense? Yeah,
thanks for clarifying.
That's kind of a fun question.
Yeah, here. Oh, for
comparing custom types.
Like Yeah, I'm not
sure, actually.
Like to say you're
saying, like, say, Oh,
like, all the, if I have put in,
like a name, can I do it?
I imagine they let you do
it, but I haven't tried it.
Yeah. It's a good question.
They should, right?
It seems like that would
be a very useful feature.
Yeah. Yeah, thanks for asking.
Yeah, there are
questions people have.
Cool. So we have
the custom types.
They say I want to talk about is
something called
prepared statements.
And there's a few reasons
we would have this.
This is like idea in
a lot of databases,
although it's a little bit more
powerful in this environment.
So You can imagine that I
might want to do
a lot of inserts
that are very similar like this.
And each time it does this,
notice that this is
just like text, right?
So for Cassandra to
understand this and
needs to extract that structure,
that's called parsing.
That actually takes
some time to parse
the s query and figure
out the structure.
And so if I do a bunch of
inserts that have
the same structure,
I'm paying that cost repeatedly.
It'll be a little slower
than it would need to be.
And so the idea of a
prepared statement
is I say, well, parse it once.
And within the statement,
there's a few places
where we might
insert a few different values,
and then we can reuse
that parsing work.
And instead of execute,
what I'll actually
say is prepare.
And the way I'll do this
is I will couple line,
and I'll just specify some
holes in this, right?
So I can say, for example,
maybe the amount
might vary each time.
Maybe the first name might vary,
maybe the last name might vary.
I can do this, and this will get
me I'm going to call
this prepared statement,
UW Credit Union Insert.
You can see that I kept
somebodys values in.
So if I use this repair
statement multiple times,
it's always inserting loans
for the UW credit union,
because that's baked
right into it.
You can also see that this
is baked right into it.
So I won't have to
use this repeatedly.
So how would I actually do this?
Well, I can do a
Cassandra execute.
But instead of putting
like some CQL here,
what I can do is I can say
that UW Credit Union insert.
And then I can put in
the different arguments.
I've put in arguments for this
for this, and for this, right?
So maybe I'll come along and
I'll say something like 302,
and I'll say test
first and test last.
I can do that. And so
if I come back here to
where I select everything
from loans, let's
take a look at that.
I can see it inserted
down here for me,
and it automatically
figured out this ID.
If I were to do that again,
I would have did
a new ID for me.
That's going to be a
few advantage of it.
It's faster for parsing.
There's actually a
security angle on it,
too, I If I'm always just
sending strings to it,
and I'm pulling values
from a web form or
something like that,
there's an opportunity
for somebody to do
something called a
SQL injection attack,
I won't worry about it too much.
This helps protect against
that from a security
perspective.
We see it's more
convenient, right?
This is a lot more concise
than using this each time.
And why I care about
it now, specifically,
in this course, is that
we can put other
options on it, right?
So for example, if I
look at this and I say,
There should be something
called a consistency level,
and I could set
it for something,
and we'll cover this more soon.
But what we do is
as soon see that
we can have different
options for
different statements
we're doing.
Sometimes Sometimes I want
my data base to give
me the right answers.
I almost always like that.
But sometimes when machines
are dying, I have
to make a choice.
But I'd rather
have the database,
not respond to my queries,
or maybe I wanted
to always respond,
even if it might
give me information
that's slightly old or sale
or something like that.
And so those ideas refer
to consistency levels,
and we're going to
be able to specify
those on a per query basis.
And so the way we're
going to do that on
the upcoming project is
at the level of these
prepared statements.
Sometimes you're going to
do some operations where we
You know, we want
it to always do
something even if
it might be wrong.
And other times, we want
it to do the right thing,
even if that means it can't
give me an answer right now.
So that's going to be very
important later. All right.
Any questions people have about
prepared statements? All right.
Let's talk about group by.
I'm going to show a group by
query that's kind of boring
because it'll be do exactly
what you expected to,
and I'm going to show
you one that will
probably surprise
you a little bit.
So I'm gonna come back here
and maybe I'll just
grab this one. This
one would be fine.
So the first thing I want
to do is I want to just see
how many loans there
are per bank, right?
And so that's a
classic group by.
So I will select bank
ID and account star.
From loans, group by bank
ID. No problem there.
I can see how many there
are for each of these.
What is more
surprising is that if
I want to say group by state
or something like that,
it's try to turn out that
Cassandra simply cannot do it.
I'm just trying to copy
this error message
so we can have
this in the notes,
and put this up
at the beginning.
And let me comment that out.
So what's going on here?
So group I is currently
only support on
the columns of the primary key.
Why is that? Well, if it's on
the columns of the primary key,
that means the partition
key is included in it.
And as it's doing
these aggregates,
It's doing aggregates
over a group
that is all on the same machine.
Right? There doesn't have
to be any kind of data shuffle
or anything like that.
Grouping over partitions,
and a partition is
on one machine.
So I can do that aggregate
on that one machine, right?
And so if I want to
do something else,
there has to be some
kind of shuffle,
almost like Spark does.
It has to have
a hash partitioning or
something like that.
Ca Standard doesn't have
that built in because
it's not built for analytics.
It's built for transaction
processing workloads
where we insert some rows,
delete some rows, look up
rows, that sort of thing, right?
And so this is a motivation.
This is a motivation
for ETL, right?
Extract. Oh, transform load.
And we could you know,
I may leave this to do.
I'm not actually
going to do it now.
We could say copy
the data to Park,
and HDFS or something similar,
and then analyze with
Spark or some other
similar thing, right?
So I can have my data
in Cassandra that has,
you know, Cassandra is good
at some very narrow things,
and then it's bad
at a lot of things.
But I can have my
data there, and
if I want these other
benefits, well,
then I can have these ETL
jobs that get it elsewhere,
and I could do my analytics and
somewhere else,
right? All right.
Does that motivation make sense?
Alright. Cool. So that
was kind of a hands on,
just, like, get some
practice with Cassandra.
May I have a couple of lectures
on some topics that I
find very interesting,
which is how Cassandra does
partitioning and
replication, right?
And we can get pretty
deep into this.
And the things that are doing
actually show up in a
lot of different places.
Now, we've already seen
a couple of different
partitioning schemes.
HDFS partitions, big files
into these smaller
logical blocks.
Cutting off at byte boundaries.
Spark does hash partitioning.
And so I want you to see
the strengths and weaknesses
of each of those approaches.
And then we're going
to be learning
a new one called
Consistent Hashing.
And we're going to see that one
has some advantages.
Others do not.
Sander uses consistent hashing.
One of the key
structures understand
consistent Ashland is
something called a token ring.
And he spent a lot of time
looking at token rings.
And yeah, just a minute.
Where he spent a lot
of time looking at
token rings and learning
how to interpret them.
And for example, if I
look at a given row,
I want you to be able to walk
the token ring and
tell me, well,
where is that
particular piece of
data located? Yeah,
go straight here.
I think so, but if they're
not, you can always just drop
me an e mail and I'll make
sure they're up after lecture.
Thanks. So we're going
to be learning a lot about
these token rings as well.
And then finally, one
of the other things
that's cool about Cassandra,
that's different
than say Sarka HGFS
is that there's no
centralized boss node.
This is the first system we've
seen with a
centralized boss node.
Now, each of these workers
in the Cassandra clusters are
going to have lots of data,
but we also have
to have metadata.
And when you have
a boss, the boss
is a natural place
to have metadata.
We don't have a boss.
So our metadata
is going to be replicated
across every single worker.
And that's tricky because
sometimes the metadata might
need to change, right?
And you can't always talk to
every single worker in the
same instant and update it.
And so it's going
to have a new way
of kind of propagating
changes called
gossip or sometimes
people call it an
epidemic algorithm,
we're like a change
will be in some places,
but like the data or the
change will like infect
other nodes until eventually
it's seen everywhere, right?
So there's lots of
interesting things
that Cassandra does that
we're going to dive into.
I want to talk a little
bit about the history.
So we've talked about
some of this before.
So the Big Table paper at
Google inspired HBase,
and I think HBase
just try to be as
similar to Big
Table as possible.
HBase was really first
release in 2008.
Cassandra was being
built at the same time,
and Cassandra also took
a lot of influence from
Big Table as we saw,
but it took influence from
another paper
published by Amazon,
AWS called Dynamo Dynamo
Influence Cassandra and
probably more importantly,
influenced DynamoDB,
which is still
an AWS service that
is very popular.
Maybe some of you will end
up using that someday.
And so things about
like the data model
and storage layout that's
really coming from Big Table.
Things about partitioning
and replication
is really inspired by Dynamo.
And there's this great
quote in the paper.
So, again, right,
this is Amazon.
And think about
what Amazon cares
about most or finds
most important.
So they said that
customers should be
able to view or add items
to their shopping cart.
Even if disks are failing,
network routes are flapping,
data centers are being
destroyed by tornadoes.
You still have to shop
at Amazon, right?
So in of sounds
ridiculous and very,
you know, a consumer
oriented mindset.
But, you know, there might
be applications that we
all care about more,
for example, like an EMS,
like an emergency
medical services.
I have some
application for that.
There's a tornado that stuff
still has to work, right?
And so, Sometimes you
really need to have
applications that are
highly available.
They always have to be on
and they have to work,
even in very adverse conditions,
and Cassandra is one
such system like that.
All right. So to review a bit
about how we've seen
partitioning working before.
In general, partitioning
is this question of,
like, a, you have
a piece of data.
We should live, right?
And there's two broad ways
that you could do that.
One is you can have
a data structure.
You check the data structure.
The data structure tells
you it lives there.
The other ways you could
do some mathematical
calculations, right?
I have a piece of data. I
look at something about it.
The math tells me
where it lives.
And so HDFS does
that first approach.
They have a data structure
kind of like this.
It's like a big dictionary where
the keys are blocks of files.
And if I have a
given block name,
it's going to take
me to a list of
data nodes in different
places, right?
And so I can figure out for
that block of data where is it?
That's what HDFS does.
Spark does something called
hash partitioning, right?
So if I'm trying to
do like a group buy or
something like that,
I don't just want to split
up the data arbitrarily.
I want to bring related data
together in the
same place, right?
How would I do that?
I would get a hash of
the key and modify the
partition count, right?
So when I do the hash,
I get some big number,
and then I'll get
it down to well,
some partition number, which
is some specific machine.
And I can use that for grouping
and joining and all
kinds of stuff.
Okay? I'm going to
talk about the weaknesses
of both of those,
and then I'm going to talk
about consistent hashing,
which is what Dynamo
and Cassandra use.
I just want to show
one quick picture for each
of these again, right?
With HDFS, we have
that data structure
we're looking at.
Where does that live?
It's actually something called
a block map on the
name node, right?
And so when a client
wants to read some data,
it asks the name node.
Where is that data?
It its those locations.
And then it can actually
go and find the data.
That's HDFS. And this is what
Spark looks like, right?
In Spar, we're trying to bring
together all the A
values, all the B values.
The way we do that is
that each partition
when we're running a test on it.
If I'm grouping by X,
then I'm going to
take the hash of
root x and then modit by
the number of partitions,
and chase this case,
there's three of them.
And that's how I bring
related data together.
Okay, let's think about
the weaknesses and strengths of
these in terms of scalability.
Scalability kind of broadly
means that as I
have bigger data,
I can use more machines
to process it.
But there's some nuance there.
One is that there's different
ways I can have big data.
One way I could have big
data is I could have
a few objects that
are each very large.
So you can imagine maybe
I have like five files,
but they're each
like a petabyte.
Okay? That'd be one
way to have big data.
The other way is
I could have lots
and lots of small
objects, right?
For example, like a row could be
a small object or
maybe I have lots
of small files, stuff like that.
I'm wondering for HDFS,
which one of these will
HDFS have trouble with?
Is HDFS to have trouble with
a few large files or
lots of small files?
Yeah. Yeah, a lot
of small files,
we have extra
overhead, particularly
on the name node, right?
In the HDFS, the
name node is what we
really worry about for
the bottleneck, right?
If I have, a few very
large files in HDFS,
and they each have
these big block sizes,
then the data nodes are
going to between most of
the work which is
great because I
have lots of data nodes.
But if I have all
these small things,
and thename node
becomes a bottleneck.
You know, Spark doesn't really
have that issue, right?
Spark is built
from the beginning
to be operating on
these small rows,
and it can them around,
and it can just deal
with it, right?
So Spark will be good
at both of these.
So for the first one, right,
in in terms of types
of big data, right?
Spark is better with
its hash partitioning.
But let's talk about another
kind of scalability,
and that's called
incremental scalability.
Sometimes I might
be able to build
a system that works well
on 1,000 computers,
and everything is going well,
but then I'm like, Okay,
I want 1001 computers.
Can I very easily transition to
1001 and start giving the
new computer new work,
or is that, like
a big undertaking
where I have to shuffle data
around and do a lot of work.
And in this case, HDFS
is the winner, right?
If I have a cluster
and you know,
I add in one more
data node, great.
For a while, it won't
have any data on it,
but as new files are ready in,
the name node, we kind of send
them there and eventually,
it'll start helping out,
and other data nodes,
you know, doesn't
really interfere with
their operation much, right?
So HDFS is very incrementally
scalable. What about Spark?
And this is kind of a
little bit contrived
because it's hard to imagine
like what I'm describing,
why you'd actually do a Spark.
But my point is
is I want to see,
k, if we did do this,
there'd be a problem,
and that's why we can't use
has partitioning for Cassandra.
So imagine that you're
doing a group by,
and you have to
shuffle the data,
and when you're
shuffling it, you're
modeling it by the
partition town.
And so each row is ending up
in a different partition.
And let's say partway
through, you say, Well,
instead of five partitions,
I want six partitions.
Well, unfortunately,
you're going to have
to start the whole job over.
The work you did was not very
useful. Let me show you why.
So, I'm going to
imagine down here.
Let's say I'm just create
a section called
hash partitioning.
And the way I do
this is I'm going to
imagine that I have let me
just check my notes here.
I may imagine that I have 26
letters from our Alphabet,
and I'm distributing them
across four machines.
And then I may say, instead of
four machines, let's
have five machines,
and I want to see how
many letters have to get
shuffled to a new machine
so that all the machines
have some work.
Right? And remember that
I can do stuff like this.
I can did a hash, right?
I can, you know,
mod that by four, all
of that dad stuff.
So I'm may get all the
letters from String, right?
And under String, I have Ask
upper case. Tres I have that.
I am going to get
a pandasta frame.
Pour Pandas SPD, and
I'll get a pandas
data frame like this,
where I have a letters column,
where it's basically just going
to be a list of
all these letters.
All right. So I may
get that data frame,
and maybe let's just look at
the first bit of it.
Okay, that's cool.
So what I want to do
now is I want to say,
when I have four machines,
which machine will be
responsible for each of these?
And so what I really want
to do is I want to do
this hashing on each
of these letters.
In that column. The
way I can do that is I
can say data frame letter,
and I can run some
function on it, right?
And I can define
the function on the fly
where I have some argument,
I have some return value.
And so the argument, I guess,
will just be a letter
in that column.
And the return value
will be a hash of
that letter Mod four, right?
So I could do that and
I could determine.
I'll say, Okay, well,
the first letter is d
me in partition two,
and next will be
partition three.
Let me just shove that back into
the data frame, so it's
a little b easier.
I may say this is
a machine be four.
When I have four machines,
this will tell me,
is each letter on machine
zero, one, two, or three?
All right? So that's
all fine and well.
Well, now, let me
do the same thing,
and I want to say afterwards,
right, which will
each of these be on?
So if I add a fifth
machine and I do hash
partitioning again, you know,
at a glance, I can
already see that Well,
sometimes A will still be on
machine two in both fases.
But the more common tase
is that each letter
has to move around for
the hash partitioning.
Let me just see how often
that happens, right?
So say machine before
equals machine after,
how often is that true?
Sometimes it's true
that it's the same,
but usually it's false.
I can actually just
treat this as a mean.
If I do that, this will be
one, this will be zero,
and this will tell me that It
means that 19% of the time,
the letter will end up on
the same machine after
we add a fifth machine.
And so that's terrible, right?
80% of my data needs to be
reshuffled on the network.
That's expensive.
Right? Hash partitioning is
not incrementally
scalable, right?
It kind of works
good at one size,
but don't change the size.
Okay, so for this one,
HDFS is the winner.
Spark with its hash
partitioning is bad.
Any questions I should
leave the code of.
Maybe I'm doing too fast here.
Any questions about
about that example?
Yeah, right here. Yeah,
it's just a hypothetical.
I'm kind of doing like
a little experiment
to say, Hey, I,
and it's silly,
right, I'd probably
have real rows and I'd
have more machines.
I'm saying, Hey, if all our data
is letters and I
have poor machines,
like, who would be responsible
for each letter, right?
That makes sense? A
little bit contrived.
Yeah. Other questions
people have. All right.
Cool. Send a head over here.
And we're going to talk about
the best of both worlds,
which is consistent hashing.
And so it's going to borrow
some from each, right?
So the first thing we're
going to do is that
if we have a row of data,
we're going to
assign it a token,
and that token is just
the hash of the key.
So it's kind of like
hash partitioning,
except we're not going to
modify anything, right?
So we'll get you know,
it might be a very big number or
maybe it's like a
very negative number.
It's just kind of any
number is possible, right?
We have a token for each
row, that's fixed, okay?
Now, borrowing from the mapping
data structure like HTFS,
we have something where
we can look it up again,
but we have way
too many rows to put
every single row into
the dictionary, right?
So instead, what we'll do is
we'll have ranges
in our dictionary.
We'll say that the range
0-10 is on worker one,
range 10-20 is on worker two.
And then we can say, like,
for this token, what
range is it in?
And I can say, well, what
worker should it be in,
right? It's straight, right?
Because I do the math when
I have millions of things.
I have millions of rows, and
math doesn't take up any memory.
I do use some memory,
but it's proportional
number of workers.
If I have 1,000 workers
in 1 million rows,
it's fine to use a little bit
of memory for each worker.
Alright, how do we
actually do it?
I'm going to draw a
picture like this.
So remember that for every
row, we get a token,
and I can imagine putting
that token on a number line.
And I can also look at every
computer in my cluster.
Am I call it a computer,
I might call it a worker,
I might call it a node.
For each of these nodes,
I'm going to pick a token.
And that token is a number,
and I can draw that
node on the numberlne.
Here's node one, here's
two, here's three.
I'm not using any kind
of hash for this.
I pick it. I could
pick it randomly.
And that's what
Cassandra used to do.
Now they have some
clever strategy
to try to pick good tokens.
Maybe we'll talk about
that, maybe not.
Anyway, I can pick it, and
I can draw it on here.
And I have to
remember it, right?
I have to have a token math.
Remember it because it's
just something I picked.
Right? There's no
math that determines,
I chose it. What about our rows?
We have lots and lots of rows,
and so we don't want to have
any data structure for that.
So that's where we're going
to use the hash function, right?
The token of a row is the hash
of that rows partition g.
And so since I can get
a token for every row,
I can say, well, where is
the A row on the numberlne?
Where is the B row
on the number line,
so on and so forth. I
can draw them all there.
And now that I've drawn
this, I have a strategy for
assigning each row
to a computer.
So The easiest case is
that if a node has exactly
the same token as a row,
that node owns that row.
You own your own token.
Okay? Probabilistically,
that won't
happen very often, but it could.
You also own the tokens
to your left up until you
bump into another worker, right?
So we get all these
ranges that are
inclusive on the right hand side
and exclusive on
the left hand side.
And I can see that, node
three owns C and D,
node two owns B. Node one
owns A. I have a strategy
that doesn't take
that much memory.
However much memory
I need for this?
Token map that can assign a row,
I can assign every row
to a specific worker.
Okay? And I've shown
that down here.
I have my cluster,
my three machines,
and I'm putting
these different AB,
CD rows on each of these, right?
Now, the one trick is that
there's no node to the right
of this part here at the end.
And so we call that
the wrapping range.
And so who's responsible
Node one, right?
So we just imagine that
this wraps around.
So as node one is looking to
the left, it'll go left of up,
and I'll wrap around and
grab these as these as well.
Right, generally, you have
tokens that are
smaller than you.
But except for the
wrapping range,
then you might have some that
are bigger than you. So
we'll come back next time.
We'll see how this
is much better for
incremental scalability than
just plain old
hash partitioning.
Have a fantastic evening.