Well for everybody.
I'll try to get
the answers back to folks within
the next couple of days or so
last time before the exam,
we were learning about databases
and by SQL in particular,
by SQL is an example
of an OLTP database.
The T and OLTP beds.
It's for transaction processing.
So we're talking about
like inserting rows.
Updating rows, looking up rows.
They can do other things
like analysis as well,
but it's going to
be slower at those,
B it's to have a row
oriented data layout.
So I may spend most of
the day actually giving
some more examples of my SQL
that we didn't have
time for last time.
And then we can start
talking a little
bit about some of these
distributed systems.
We'll talk about
something called
the Hadoop ecosystem today
and particularly the
Hadoop file system.
And the next part of the course,
I think will be a
lot of fun because
now that we have
this foundation,
we can look at a lot of
different big data systems
and understand what
they're doing.
So I make a head over here
where I was last time.
I had this notebook running.
This notebook was directly
running on my virtual machine.
It's not at a continor.
I was connected to a
MSQL database where
the user was route and
the password was ABC.
I was going to Port 3306
and database CS 544.
Let me just head
over here and show
you what that looks
like on this side.
So I'm going to SSHN again.
And L et me just clear
this up a little bit.
If I do Docker PS,
I can see that there was this
container ting with my SQL.
That was a generic M SQL image.
Port 3306 on my virtual machine
is forwarding to 3306
inside of the container,
and that's where the M
SQL server is running.
And so if I want to, I
could jump into this
Docker container.
I'm going to do that right
now with a Docker Exec.
And what's inside, we
saw that we could run
SQL and connect to a database
and type a password,
which is again, ABC.
And then I could do
things like show tables.
So what we were doing last
time is we were looking at
different ways we could create
tables and add
some data to them.
So I'm going ahead over here.
And I read this from scratch.
Basically, this is the
notebook we read last time.
The main thing I changed
is I added some code
here that would drop tables
if they already exist.
That way, I could just run
my notebook from top to bottom,
and it would recreate
those as need be, right?
So one of the things we could do
is we could create a
table from scratch,
and then we could
insert data into it.
That was one of
the things we did.
One of the other things we did
at the very end is we were
using Padnus to automatically
generate some of
these tables for us.
So I was using Pads to
read various CSV files.
I would do schema puts on those.
I'd have type. And
then I could say,
had to stat a frame two sequel.
I could dump these d. I
was able to create a few
small tables that way.
I also want to create
a bigger table
that I use for a lot
of these examples.
And so I'm going head over here,
and I have that
example right here.
And let me just grab this.
Cool. I'm a re paste
this down here.
And what I'm doing
is I'm reading in
this CSV file with Piero,
and then I'm writing it
back to a Park file,
and then I'm reading
in that Park file with
just a few select columns.
And what I want to
do now is I want to
send it to my SQL. I'm
to get that table.
There it is.
It just has a few columns
that I'm interested in,
and I am going to send
it. Two SQL, right?
So what I will do
is I'll first say,
take this Piero table,
put it to PADs because Pads
knows how to talk to SQL.
I'm ready to call
my table loads.
And the only other
thing I want to mention
here is that if I try to
insert too much data at whats,
I tend to run out of
memory on my SQL.
I actually played around
with that a bit before,
but I can ask it to
do a certain number
of rows at a time.
And so I will specify
a chuck size.
I could have played
with what was fast
without running out of memory.
So I'll insert 10,000
rows at a time and
basically populate that
loads table for us.
And then what I'm
may be doing is
different examples
where I can either
do transaction processing or
some analysis on this database.
Any question while
that's loading up?
Alright, cool. So I was
able to load, you know,
44,000 or something like
almost half 1 million rows.
This is actually a real data.
It's all the load
applications in
Wisconsin for a year. All
that's public actually.
You can see which loads
are accepted and rejected.
So Atom is, of course,
but you can see all that.
It's try to a cool data set.
Alright, so sweet,
I have that there.
And if I do show tables
over here again,
I can see that now
I have these loads.
So Those are a bunch
of ways that we
could get our initial
tables there.
We could either insert
or we could use pads.
I want to take a
moment to look at
how we can make
changes to our data.
And in particular by
making multiple changes,
how can I do it as
part of a transaction?
We learned about last time how
traditional databases have
these acid transactions
that are atomic,
consistent, isolated
and durable.
And I want to just give you
some sense of what that means.
So looking over here,
I actually do select star
from accounts right now.
And last time I had these two
bank accounts that both are for
the same user B. I
imagine maybe it's
like a check account
and savings account.
And I want to write
a transaction that
transfers somebody from
my account A to count B.
So I will come over here
and I can say connection
execute and I will
gib it some text.
And I'm going say
update accounts
and set amount equal to amount.
I'll make this a little
bit shorter, so it fits.
It equals amount plus
one or actually do,
I'll do plus one here,
where the name equals
B. I'm transferring $1
to B. Let me do that.
And at this point, I may
come over here and I may
take a look at this,
and I see that over here,
I cannot see that change yet,
right? That's a
separate session.
It's not part of my transaction.
And for the acid,
right, the I means
isolated, right?
So now we're seeing the
isolation here, right?
We don't see these changes
visible until all the
changes are made, right?
Because this change is really
part of some other things.
It's also part of a
change where I want to
subtract one for bake
account A, right?
So I'm may do that. Of that,
again, I don't see
that over here.
If I come over here, I could
try to see these changes,
and I'll be able to
because I'm going to do
the query over here as part
of this transaction, right?
Ibo to do a select
star from accounts.
And when I do that, I'm ready to
revert it to a list. I
can actually see it.
So I can see that I was able to
subtract one from
A and ibt to B,
even though I cannot see
that separately over here.
One of the things I might want
to do before I say, Okay,
I want this transaction to
go through is I want to say,
am I still maintaining
consistency?
I remember that
consistency is whatever
in variants or rules we make up.
And so one of the rules is that
a bank account did
not grow negative.
I can't make my
checking go negative to
make myself have more money
in my savings account, right?
And so what I'm actually
going to do is I'm
re to select the
amount from here.
Where the name equals A.
That's telling me how much
money is in my u account A.
And it's a list of tuples,
so I could get the
first tuple out,
and I could pull
that number out.
And basically, I can figure out
how much money is left after
I would do this transfer.
And so I might want to check.
I want to say, is that greater
than are equal to zero
because it should be.
But if it is that
I feel good about
committing this
transaction, otherwise,
I realize that I
messed up my data,
and none of these changes I
have made should take effect.
So I want to roll
back my transaction.
So I may say up here, commit,
And then down here,
where I say rollback. All right.
And in this case,
the amount was positive,
so it should commit.
And at that point when we
committed, all of a sudden,
it becomes visible
elsewhere, right?
And so in database terminology,
this was the A and acid.
This was the atomicity
that we really
get everything when
it's committed,
or we're going to undo
it we'll never kind of
end up in between, right?
So yeah, right here.
A roll. Roll back do.
I was in make all these changes.
I just say I want to
throw away any of
those changes I was
trying to make. Y.
Yeah, great question.
Yeah, there are
questions people have.
Let me try this again.
I'm going to try to make
this code a little
bit more concise.
In particular, I just want
to get it all on one cell.
And this time, I'm going
to try to transfer $5.
That also works just fine.
Now, at this point, if
I run the cell again,
it's going to be taking
my bank account negative.
And then it will
roll it back, right?
Because it started
making those changes,
and it sees that we're
violating some invariance.
And actually, my
apologies, right?
I want to do a
connection rollback.
Let me just that was
supposed to row.
I'd be put it out here
just so I can try
to recover my state.
Let me just row this again
so we see it proper.
I'll do a rollback, and it gets
rejected over here, right?
So Acid transactions are great.
They help me make the
data make sense, right?
I can't have other
things that see
data that's time
temporarily weird.
It'd be weird if I
was like, checking,
and somehow I was
doing a transfer and
they had taken the money away
but it didn't show
up somewhere els.
That'd be weird, right? I'd be
weird if somebody went negative.
So it's giving me all those
der different guarantees.
This is what traditional
databases do.
They give you acid transactions,
and I want people to be familiar
with that because
where we talk about
other big data systems that
don't give you
acid transactions.
I want to have this
baseline to see,
what are we giving up in order
to get other nice
properties like
highly scalable systems that can
run on thousands of machines.
One of the things that
this should remind you of
is when we did the stuff
with locking, right?
We had some of these properties
when we were using
locks, too, right?
We might update
multiple variables.
And the database engine itself
internally has locking.
And locking is one of the things
they use to give you
these properties.
So often it's the
case that if you're
using database of transactions,
you would not have
to use locks, right?
Because the database is doing
that work for you
with transactions.
So you can try to figure out, a,
there are these goals
we want to achieve by
doing it with,
stated a database.
I have transactions.
Maybe I have
all this stat in
memory or some files.
Then I'd probably have to do
some type of locking, right?
Yeah, question right. Oh,
that's really interesting.
So you're saying I have
like, two threads that
are interacting with
the same database.
Maybe they're trying to
make the same changes.
Yeah, so different databases
would do different
things, right?
So I actually did
some experiments with
that previously with
SQL to just understand
what it does by default.
And because the database engine
itself has some block data,
what happen if I try touch
that same data is
it would actually
block me much the same way
that I might block
to acquire a lock.
So it's like that one
transaction drove
through before the other
one droves through.
Other things that
might happen is
that Some databases will the
transactions both go ahead.
But at the very end, when you
commit it, they'll see that, oh,
they're actually
conflicting, it might
cause one of your
transactions to fail, right?
Different databases
do different things.
But even if the
transaction might fail,
then you would have
to retry, they can
still provide those properties.
Yeah. Excellent question.
Yeah, all the
questions people have.
Alright. Cool. So what
I want to do now is
transition a little bit.
We've been doing
transaction processing.
And again, I want
to emphasize that
there's two different kinds
of transaction processing.
There's like the
acid transactions
that I showed right here.
Transaction
processing might also
be that I'm doing things
like inserting rows or just
looking at rows or
things like that,
operating on a row by row basis.
People use it in both senses.
Alright, so for
the rest of these,
I want to demonstrate
very quickly,
different clauses
that you have in SQL.
And one of the skills that
I think is actually very
useful is if somebody
asks you a question
of natural language,
that you can translate
that to SQL, right?
To actually get an
answer for them.
And so I have a bunch of
questions here in
natural language,
and we're going to get
practice translating them,
and I'm just going to split
some of these things up.
And that's probably
enough for now.
And each of these is try
to have us practice
adds something.
And the way I usually
like to do this is
with Pandas read SQL.
So Pads actually smart enough to
directly read from one of
these database
connections because
it's integrated
with SQL Alchemy,
which is the module we're using.
So I could put a query here
and then by connection.
And so I'd say select
star from actions.
Oh, from actions.
Great. So this From
is telling me what database
table I'm interested in,
and the select is
telling me what
columns I'm
interested in, right?
So I could have said
just ID, for example,
or in this case,
I'm really interested in
in everything, right?
So I can do that. Hang
on just a moment.
So the next thing I want to
do is I want to take a look
at the limit flaws. Excuse me.
And so the limit will
be useful if I have
a large table that
I can't really just select
the whole thing, right?
So if I ran this
right now would be
pretty reasonable because
the loan table is too big.
When it tries to bring that
into a pandas data frame,
I'll probably run out of memory.
And so I can just say here,
limit to the first ten rows,
and I kind of arbitrarily
get whatever rows
are there, right?
Nearly not necessarily
in any particular order.
So whenever I'm working
with a big database,
this is one of the
first queries,
I'll do on a large
table just to try
to see what the data looks like.
Now, I want to point
out a couple of things.
I can Based on this,
I can control what
columns I have.
And maybe based on a limit
or we're going to
see aware soon.
I might control
what rows I have.
So there's ways that
kind of shraky down
the data with respect
to columns or rows,
or maybe with columns,
I'm actually might be
adding more columns.
And so there's a couple
of words I want you
to remember proj selection.
And whoever came up with
the vocabulary did
a horrible job
because projection is the word
we use for figuring out
what columns we have.
And so projection is
used in combination
with select, right?
So here I'm doing a projection
that gives me all
of the columns.
Yeah. You would think selection
would be with select,
but it is not selection
is when we're figuring out
which rows we want, right?
So maybe like a ware clause or
a limit clause or
something like that.
It's import to have
that vocabulary
because when we're
learning Spark later,
we're going to see for
a given job how it
was answering that.
And when we were debugging,
it might use words
like selection,
projection, and you have
to know what they mean.
So just kind of a
weird thing that you
have to remember, unfortunately.
All right, cool, what are
the first ten interest rates
and the loan amounts
and thousands?
And so I'm going to
grab this one again.
And as this gets longer,
I actually like to just do
a multiline string
and like that.
I'm going to do a select
from loans, limit ten.
And so I'm still
limiting by ten,
and this is asking me about
interest rates and loan amounts.
So I can do that. So that's
an example of projection.
Projection might also involve
doing things like
adding two columns
together or doing other
sort of operations on them.
Right? So projection might
give me a different column.
That's not quite the
same as original.
And of course, I might
rename that, like so.
Alright. So we can figure out
which columns we want with
this select statement here.
Alright, let's see which of
these loans are for
individuals with an
income of over 1 million.
So may come down here.
And I will say let's just
select everything for now.
And what I will do
instead of limiting, I
will have a ware clause,
and then I can have some kind
of conditional statement here,
and that conditional
statement will
be evaluated for each row.
And so I could say
where income is
greater than 1 million,
and then I would get some
number of rows here, right?
So I can see for each of
these people or
maybe organizations.
I guess this one has income
of 94 million a year,
but for some reason,
they still need a loan.
But I can see that.
Col. Let me head down here.
This one's a little bit
of a different question
instead of trying to
filtering something exactly,
I want to get the, n biggest
or smallest of something.
And so what we're going
to do down here, oops.
Is we're going to
limit to ten again,
or I guess here we're
limiting to five.
And it says the biggest loans
in terms of dollar amount.
The way I do that
is I do an order
by before I do the
limiting, right?
So I could limit by
the loan amount,
and then By default,
when I do that, I see these
are pretty small loans.
These are $5,000 loans.
That's because it's
doing ascending,
ascending from the smallest
values to the largest values.
If I wanted to, I
could do descending,
and that would drove from
the biggest to the smallest,
so I can see that the biggest
loan here is actually what?
Hundreds thousands
millions, right?
So a quarter of
$1,000,000,000 for
the biggest loan application
in Wisconsin for that year.
And who knows, maybe you
could go overa the news
and figure out what that
actually is? I don't know.
I'm guessing we did
some kind of coverage.
Cool. So we'll often use
order by in conjunction with
limit to get the most or
least of something
within the dataset.
Any questions
people have so far?
All right. Cool. Let me
split some more of these up.
So I have each one on
its own line. All right.
So what are the
actions and types?
Actions taken and
types for those loans?
And I want to show the texts,
not just the numbers. All right.
And so what I'm
gonna do down here,
is first, I'll just select
everything from the loans,
and we're going to
look at it again.
I'm going to say limit ten.
And I want the actions
taken and the loan types.
And it's saying specifically,
I have to show texts,
not just these numbers.
So I have to figure
out how to take
these numbers and replace
them with the actual
description here, right?
So one of the ways I can do
that is I could say up here,
let's select everything
from actions. All right?
And then I can see for
these actions taken down here,
like, what do they mean?
Like a six means that
the loan was purchased
by an institution.
Okay, or maybe a four means
it was withdrawn, right?
And so what I really
want to do is I
want to have the
table down here,
but I want to fill in
that information
from another table.
So I'm really
taking columns from
different tables
and combining them.
And when I do that, that's
called a join, right?
So what I want to do down here
is instead of just
selecting from loans,
I want to do what is first
called an enter join.
And I want to ter
join on this up here.
This actions table. I
want to eroin on actions.
And when I do that,
I have to specify,
how do I pair up a row
from loans with a
row from actions?
And it's a lot like
a wear statement.
I have to have some
tradition that says,
Oh, this row matches
with that row.
And so I put that tradition
after an on statement.
And the way I can do that is
I can say that what is it?
Action taken down here, right?
So action taken,
equals the ID up here.
Now notice that
there's some overlap.
Action taken is one
column up here with
one meaning in the loans table,
it means something else.
I really have to specify.
I have to say the
loans action taken
equals the actions dot ID.
I have to do that.
And now I'm going to
get all of these columns
from the loans table.
And at the very end,
I can see I get
some things from the
other one as well, right?
So that's straight. I was
able to add in action take.
And eventually, I'll clean
this up a little bit.
It also said we have to say
what loan type we want.
So may come up here, I may
say select star from loan types.
All right. I can
see those there.
So I will say ner
join loan types,
on, and then I have to have
some kind of filter again.
I have to say the
loan type down here.
Loans loan type
equals the D up here.
This is an ID and the
loans type table.
So I can say loan types
dot ID. I could do that.
And now I've added all of
this information in as well.
Then finally, what I
could do is I could get
something like the loan
amount and I could
say the action taken
and then the loan type.
I could specify which table
each of these come from.
This comes from actions.
This comes from loan types.
I could have some combination
where I could actually
understand what's
going on instead of having
those specific IDs there.
Yeah question right here.
You have some. Oh,
could I reverse this?
Yeah, that'd be totally
fine just to flip this.
It would do exactly
the same thing. Yeah.
Yeah, good question.
Other questions
people have. All right.
This is what we call an energy
and that means I only get
an output row if it
finds an exact match.
I might get you know,
given that there might be
different combinations,
maybe I might have more output
rows in some cases than
I have rows in the
original tables, right?
But I only get output rows
when there's an exact match.
Sometimes I might be
interested in seeing maybe
like a loan where there is no
associated action with it.
Maybe that feels empty
or who knows what?
And Sly other kinds of joins.
Here I'm doing inner joins
where I get exact matches.
Other kinds of joins are held
left join and right join.
In those cases, I
might output a row from
one of these tables,
even though there's no
match in another table.
All right, so in this case,
I want to know what is
a loan purpose that doesn't
appear in the loans table.
And for this, we're going
to do a left or right join.
All right.
I say, let me paste this
down here. Read sequel.
Yeah, and I need
to have my great.
So what I will do
is, I'll first say,
select star from
Lane loan purposes.
I shouldn't matter.
What did I do? Let me just
come over here and say,
show tables again.
H, just purposes.
Okay. Fantastic. So I'll
just do purposes. All right.
Great. And I can see those.
And what I'm going
to do is I'm well,
first, let's say I
would erjoin it, right?
If I enter join it to
loans and then have
some kind of on whatever.
What that would mean is
that whenever one of
these IDs matches
something in the table,
I'm going to get an
output row, right?
But what I'm really interested
in is I want to see
each of these at least once,
even if there's no match for it.
So instead of enter join,
I'm going to say, left join.
And that means I want
every purpose to show
up even if there's no loans.
So if there's no loans,
then I'll just have a
purpose row by itself and
the other values from the
other table will be null,
or if there is a match, then
I will get one or more rows.
So I may I say over here
is that purposes dot
ID equals loans loan purpose.
F, let's just limit to ten
so we can see what
it looks like.
Unknown column purpose
ID. Purposes dot ID.
Thank you.
Excellent. I'm going to get
a bunch of these matches,
right? So here's
a home purchase.
And you can see that one row.
We only had three
rows from here,
but each of those rows
has many matches.
But it turns out
that there's one of
these rows and loan purposes
that doesn't have any match.
And I can't see it here.
But if I stroll down
far enough with it,
what look like is I
would see a value here,
and everything else
would be null,
indicating that there are
no loans matching that.
And so I can actually
filter that.
I can say, where, I don't know.
I can really choose any
column, loans at LEI.
Is null, right? I can do that.
And then I'm going to get
this one right here, right?
So refinancing, there is
no refinancing data
in this data set.
It's just not included, right?
So it's a valid loan type,
but they don't have it here.
Yeah, question
right here. Equal.
That's a good question.
Do I say equal?
I think I think
it will actually,
I guess I have to say is null.
Interesting. Yeah, Null
is always weird
because it's like,
Well, I mean,
that column has a specific
type, and who knows?
If something is null, does it
matter if I have two nulls
of a different type.
So sometimes languages will
have special words and
some do it differently.
I don't remember first equal,
but maybe they're doing
it because of that.
Normally equal sign.
Normally for where we
would use an equal sign,
but for null I guess
is a special case.
Yeah. Yeah. Thanks for
pointing that out.
Yeah, right here. So let join.
That's coming here, Yeah.
Purposes is to left and
loans to the right.
Left joint means
that everything to
the left should have at
least one output row,
even if there's no match for it.
And then after the fact,
I specifically said, I want to
find the ones where
there is no match.
That makes sense? Yeah.
Thank you for clarifying.
Yeah, there are
questions people have.
All right. Cool.
So let's talk about
aggregate snow.
I have this, you
know, big data set,
but I can crunch it down to
just one summary
number if I want.
There's different ways I
can summarize the data.
And so one of them is
I might want to just
know how many loans there are.
And so I'm going to
select star from loans.
But instead of selecting
specific columns,
I could put an aggregation
function here.
So count is an example of
an aggregation function.
And I could say how
many are there.
So what does this star?
That means I want to count
every single row regardless
of the values in those rows.
And alternative to that
might show up for SFS.
How many non null
values are in um,
the income column, right?
So if I do this, I
can say select count
from come, and I can see, well,
people usually, but not always
specify their income when
they're applying
for a loan, right?
So what you're doing, you
might be interested in one
or the other of
these. All right.
Cool. Oftentimes, instead of
wanting to get an
overall aggregate,
we might be interested in
an aggregate for a
specific category,
what I want to do
is I want to figure
out which of these loans are
conventional and then get
the interest rate
specifically for those.
Maybe what I'll do first
is I'll try to get
the interest rate overall.
I'll say, what is the
average interest rate?
Overall, this is
a few years ago,
so kind of a very
enviable interest rate
that everybody was
getting back then.
But let's see what it is for
conventional loans
specifically, right?
So I'm going to
come down here, and
I'm going to take a look at
the loans again so
I can try to figure
out how to get the
conventional loans.
And what I have is
the loan type over
here is an ID, right?
And so if I come
up here and I say,
select star from loan types,
I can see there's these
four different types.
And I could hard
code, I could say,
I want to find one because I'm
supposed to find the
conventional loans,
but that's bad because people
couldn't read my SQL, right?
And if that changes
at some point,
well, then my code
would just break.
Right? So what I have
to do here is I have to
combine this with a
couple of things.
I have to do a join to figure
out what does conventional mean?
And then I have to do so
that I only get that.
I may do from join loan types
on loans loan type down here.
Equals loan types ID right
here, so I could do that.
And once I do that,
maybe I should just, I'll
try to jump ahead
a little bit more.
Then what I can say is I'm
only interested in that when
the loan type name.
I guess that type loan type
equals conventional. Try
to do double quotes.
I'm not quite sure.
Let's try that.
And I can see for those
loans specifically,
this is the interest
rate for them.
So I can look at one
specific category
of loans and then
get an aggregate.
And you can start to
see, like some of
these more complex queries,
where we're doing a
few things, right?
We're doing joining, we're
doing filtering. We're
doing aggregation.
As you start to combine
more of these things,
you can answer more interesting
questions about the data.
All right. T a more
complicated query.
Any questions about that query?
All right. Cool.
So come down here.
I'm going to delete these.
How many loans are
there of each type?
That's very similar to
this question, actually.
For this, I was looking for
one loan type and
trying to get it.
But now I want to get an answer
for each of these loan types.
And so I will modify
this a little bit.
Let me let me copy
the whole thing.
Excuse me. So what
I will do instead of
filtering it down to one,
instead of having that,
what I can say is,
I want to group by by loan type.
So the first thing
astray happen is
a stray oid all
the data together.
And then the group
stray split it
up in d different groups.
And I know the average
looks like it's happening
before the group bi,
and that's one of the things
that's confusing about SQL.
The group bi happens first,
and then the aggregate
happens after that
aggregate is to happen
on each of these
individual groups, right?
So I may run that.
And I can see well,
I guess, yeah, why not?
We can leave that
there, too. I guess
how many loans are
there of each type,
right? So I'll say count star.
All right, C. So I can see how
many there are of each type,
and then what the
interest rate is
for each of these categories.
Now, it's a little
hard for me to
see here just what
these aggregates,
what loan type they
correspond to.
So it's extremely
common that whatever
you're grouping by is
also going to go alongside
your aggregates up here like so.
So I can see, like
for a con loan,
how many are there and what was
the interest rate for them.
Okay. Any questions
about that about that,
query? Yeah, right here.
Could you group by
with what? Oh, could
you group by an aggregate.
Oh, that's kind of interesting.
Yes, you could, right?
So I guess you're
trying to say, Let's
say this was like
a smaller number like
one or two or three.
I could then try to
say like how often for
how many groups was
the count three or
something like that.
You cannot do it with a
single query like this.
In SQL, you could have
somebody called a
nested query, right?
So I could have this, and then
I could really do something
like this, right?
I think what you're saying
is I could select something
from And then I
can say and I could put
all this in parentheses.
That would be an example
of a nested query.
We're actually see in
when we learned Spark,
I mean, what you're
suggesting is very natural,
right, that, I'm doing all
theerasformation of data.
I should be a group by
aggregate group by aggregate.
It's just a chain
of transformations.
SQL doesn't let you
do that natural. You
have to do this nesting.
But in Spark, for example,
it'd be totally fine to have
a long chain of operations,
where I have a
bunch of group by,
a bunch of wares, whatever.
Right? So yeah, so it's a
reasonable thing to do,
and it's just a little
ugly to do it in SQL,
but totally doable either way.
Yeah, great question.
Yeah, all the
questions people have.
All right. Cool. I think
the last thing I want to
do is it's actually
the same one,
but I want to filter
down these groups,
so I'm only getting
specific ones.
I only want it where the
count is more than 10,000.
So I should probably
give this a name.
Count is kind of a bad name
because it's the same
as the function.
So I might abbreviate that.
And then it would be very
natural to say something
like where, right?
So where that's straighter than
10,000. But that's
not going to work.
The reason is that where is
operating on my data right
after it does the ins,
trying to filter down the rows
before I do any grouping.
And so the same concept,
but they have a
separate word for
filtering after you've
done group I in aggregate,
and that separate
word is having.
This is another taste where
we eventually see Spark
and Spark has a nicer syntax
like wear and having
are the same thing,
and you could actually use the
same wear multiple
times in this,
kind of, like, how
however you like.
So what I want to end
with is coming back to
this picture that I think
is so important, and I
showed it last time.
I'm going to show it again.
You should really get in
the habit of thinking of
when you're writing a query,
your data is actually
flowing through
a series of
transformations, right?
First to join, takes multiple
tables, and it combines it.
So we have some
columns from each,
where filters down the rows.
Group by pulls
together related rows.
An aggregation like
summer average
gives you a single
row for each group.
Having filters down
your summary rows,
order by reorganize
them in some way,
and then a limit will give
you the top however so many.
You should think of your data
flowing through a series of
transformations SQL forces you
to have them in this order.
You don't have to
have all these steps,
but you choose a subset of
these for a signal query
and then you do the order.
So the systems like spark
them where you learn about,
they have each of
these building blocks,
and you're a little
bit more free.
You could have you know,
join, join, where, and
one big chain, right?
So that's when you
start thinking about.
How can you really
have these pipelines that
your data flows through?
You do a bunch of
transformations,
and then you get
some final result.
SQL is one language for
describing some pipelines.
Alright, Col. Any
questions about SQL
before we move on
to the new stuff?
Alright, cool. I
may head over here.
And I'm really go
to spend the most time of the
Hadoop file system first,
but it's part of a
broader ecosystem,
so we'll start with the
ecosystem of the Darrow Dud.
This elephant, here is
the mascot for the
Hadoop ecosystem.
I have a few goals for you.
One is a little bit of a
history lesson, right?
So, Google did a lot of
this founding work
that has inspired
a lot of big data systems,
and so there's three
famous big data systems
in particular that I
want you to remember.
GFS is the Google File system,
Map reduce and Big Table.
And so we aren't going
to use those things,
but I want you to at
least describe them.
You could row Ue Big
Table if you wanted to.
They sell it as a Cloud service.
I'm guessing it's expensive,
but you could row make a
Big Table if you wanted to.
We're going to be
focusing on Hadoop
Systems that have some
similarities to these.
And respectively, the ones
are the Fadu file system.
Spark and Cassandra.
Those are three of
the big data systems
Rbulary this semester.
For all of these systems,
partitioning and replication are
going to be really important.
We saw that earlier on P two,
actually, how we might partition
our data or we might replicate
it to have multiple copies.
Those are things where
we see repeatedly,
again, and again, this semester.
And then finally, when we're
talking about the
Du file system,
specifically, we're
going to have
this big distributed system.
Most of the nodes of the system
are gonna be what we call
data nodes that are holding
these big blocks of data.
We're gonna have
something called a name
node that coordinates them all.
And then we have clients that
are reading writing data,
and those clients
have to interact
with both the name node
and the data node,
and I want you to be able to
describe all those interaction.
So you could walk
me through what
happens when you write some data
or when you read some
data. All right.
So let's have a little bit of
motivation for where
these systems came from.
I want to go back in
contrast to simple system,
I should say simple, but
a single node
system like my SQL.
So here you are, and
you're writing some
data into MS equL,
and databases and storage
systems in general are layered.
So inside of the MEQL edge,
they have some storage engine.
I think the default
is called ODP,
but you could plug
other things ODP is
re store data as files
in a file system.
The file system is re store
that data maybe at a
hard driver at SSD.
Maybe you have other programs of
the same computer like Excel
that might say files directly
to that file system.
So we have this layer
deside. Almost everything we
look at is going to have
some kind of layering to it.
So the question is,
what if this data
that you're putting
into by SQL is too big.
Maybe too big in terms of
it takes too many bytes,
or it takes too
long to process it.
One option. Doing back to
the very first lecture is
that we could scale up.
That means that
we buy more CPUs,
or we have more RAM,
right? We could do that.
Maybe instead of
having one hard drive,
maybe we have a bunch
of hard drives,
and they're in a ray.
We done a a array of
inexpensive disks.
I could get more
capacity, right?
But of course, if
data keeps growing,
it simply will not
fit on one server,
no matter how much money
we want to throw at it.
So another approach is
a scale out, right?
I could buy lots of
different servers,
and maybe they each
have one hard drive
or multiple doesn't matter,
but they could have
all these different
my SQL instances running
in my cluster, maybe
thousands of them.
And this is not crazy, right?
It's actually something
that happened.
So Facebook, for example,
they started they using my SQL.
And I don't know I'm guessing
they probably started with,
like one server, but
as they kept growing,
then they had to have
more and more servers,
and they were all
running my SQL,
and they all had different
users data on them, right?
They had to kind of figure
out how to make this war.
And that's a lot
harder than it sounds.
Let me show you. So
in this situation,
we have tables that
are huge, right?
A single table of data, I
cannot fit on one machine.
And so you have to
have some logic in
addition to what I showed
that partitions it.
So maybe I'm doing like
some kind of sales thing,
and I have a table of
users and a table of
things they're purchasing,
and they're both huge.
I could split them up, right?
I could put some users data
on each of the machines and
some purchase data on each of
the machines. I could do that.
Here, I just have
two computers instead
of like thousands,
but let's just start there.
So that's all fine and well.
If I have a query,
like let's say I want
to find all the purchases
that are over some amount?
I could send that same query
to both my SQL databases,
and they would both send me
some rows back with an answer.
And I could combine that, right?
I can get some data from one and
some data from other,
and I could say,
Okay, here are the amounts
for each of these.
So that seems like it
would kind of work well.
But I want you to think
about this approach.
I just send the same
query to everybody,
and then I just take the results
back and con ttinate it.
Did anybody think
of some kind of
query where that's not
going to work for me?
Right here.
Excellent, right?
So if I want to get
the purchases for
user three or maybe in general,
I'm just trying to like
group purchases by user,
I have to do kind of a droid
and some other operation.
I'm may be in trouble,
right, because as you said,
purchases for user
three is on the left,
but user three is over
on the right hand side.
So something like a droid
would break with that
simple approach.
If I actually want that to work,
I have to be very
careful about which rows
go on which database server.
If I very careful, maybe
I can make it work.
Can I clearly do that I say
this users on that mache,
that users of that mache?
Sometimes, but not always.
Imagine if I have like a
Facebook message, right?
There's like the
user that said it,
and the user that received it,
like which server
is that stored on,
that gets very challenging
fast, right? People do do this.
They'll have thousands of
my equal server instances,
but then it doesn't work
as well as a si SQL server
does because you have to
do all this extra stuff
to make it even just half work.
And so that raises the question,
right If these basic
things that we're used to,
traditional databases
don't work?
I Joy doesn't work, maybe
acid transactions
don't quite work,
If we're giving those
things up anyway,
maybe that gives us a chance
to redesign everything
from stretch.
So, for example, one of
the databases are we
be learning the semester
is called Cassandra.
And Cassandra has
CQL instead of SQL,
and they don't even try to do
join because they're like,
Well, it's so hard to get
it right when we have
all these different machines
that are involved, right?
So there's just a completely
different database
compared to what
we are learning as this
basic traditional database.
Another thing you
have to worry about
is when you have
thousands of machines,
is what if a server dies?
How many people have had
a computer die within
the last year?
So already, what, like,
four or five people.
And I don't know,
we have less than 100
people in the room.
So imagine if you have
thousands of computers, right?
Then we're talking like
dozens of failures.
I just happens all
the time, right?
You have to be able
to deal with that.
And so this all leads us
to this big motivation for
redesigning systems
for big data.
Some of stuff like
Joint and transaction,
even though we like those, we're
just not ready to get
what we want there.
So we already sacrifice those,
but there are other
things that we do
really care about that
are essential, right?
We have to be able to scale
to a large number of machines,
and we have to have
fault tolerance.
So a fault is like
a hard dry failing,
a machine failing,
a rack failing.
When stuff goes bad, the system
still has to work, right?
So A this motivates
building a new kind of
big data system compared to
that traditional database we
were considering, like by SQL.
So the history of this
goes back to Google again,
and they built these
three systems,
and they are all closed source,
but they published fabs papers
about them that
have been extremely
impactful in terms of
all these different systems
that resemble them in
different ways, right?
So I want you to learn a little
bit about each of these,
even if we don't ever use
them or rever them in detail.
So the first thing they
did is they published
a paper in 2003 about GFS,
the Google File System.
The Google file system is
a file system that could have
say thousands of workers,
each with, you know, a
number of hard drives,
and it would have
a way of storing
files across all
of these, right?
So it had enormous capacity,
enormous bad width potential.
And one of their
insights was that,
instead of trying
to buy the biggest,
most reliable hardware,
it's never good enough.
You have to go to
multiple machines anyway.
So if you're kind
of doing that and
you're writing software that
can deal with failures,
why even spend all this
money on high end hardware?
Let's just buy cheap hardware?
Let's buy a lot of it.
That cheap hardware,
I'm talking about
word for it is
commodity hardware.
You know, you could grow at a
store and buy it off the shelf.
As a no person, right?
So Google had this idea,
let's build these giant clusters
out of commodity hardware.
Recently, that maybe
is changing, right,
their time doing
some fancy things
and building custom hardware,
but this has really
been an influential
decision that was made early on.
Now, we already saw
that by SQL stores
its data in files,
right underneath.
And so they also
built the database
in 2006, call BigTable.
O they built it Ser.
They published that.
And that would store its data
in the Google File
system, right?
So kind of by building
this distributed database
at top of the
distributed file system,
they could take advantage of all
the good things about GFS.
They also built Map reduce,
which was a system for analyzing
the data and these
giant GFS files.
It's maybe a little
bit more restrictive
or maybe more difficult
to use than SQL.
But ultimately, everything
you could do in SQL,
you could also do
in Map reduces.
That was a 2004 paper.
So these three systems
were hugely influential.
Even though they were
not open source.
So other companies came
log and they're like,
Well, we should have some
open source of this.
In particular, Yahoo, Facebook,
and Cloudera, we're
really trying to
push open source
equivalents of these.
And the family of
all these systems is
what we call the
Hadoop ecosystem.
So in the first generation
of this would be the HDFS,
the Hadoop file system,
that's very similar to GFS.
A Duke Map reduce is similar
to Google's Map reduce.
And then H base is similar
to Google's big table.
So all these things are
open source. You can
row use them if you want to.
Now, of course, this is a long
time ago and systems
have evolved.
And so even though some
people still use those,
I want to show you
this semester,
the things that are a little
bit more popular, right?
So for analysis, a lot of
that work is done now with
something called Spark.
I teach you Spark this semester.
And instead of HBase, I may be
teach you a database of Cassra.
Assara isn't maybe
quite as popular,
but it is kind of
interesting from some of
the design decisions.
So I like to talk about
it during the semester.
Did I see a head up over here?
No. Yeah. Any questions
so far? All right.
So let's talk a little bit about
the Hadoop file
system, in particular.
In a do cluster,
here I have a bunch of
different computers,
and they're each
running a server
called a data node server,
and each data node server might
manage some number
of hard drives.
And our goal is
to take files and
store it on those machines.
And because some of
these files are so huge,
we have to break up the files
into what we call blocks.
And a block might
be on the order
of tens of megabytes, let's say.
Here I imagine some
pretty tiny blocks
just to make it
fit on the slide.
But here, right, I have a
file with a single block.
So file wood, block wood.
I could put that somewhere
on one of these servers.
I re imagine that we have
very tiny blocks,
let's say four bytes.
And so this bigger
file F two might
get partitioned into two blocks.
I have one block on the left,
another block on the right.
So I have file two, block one,
file two block, block two.
Of course, these
machines might die.
So when I create these files,
I specify replication.
And if I can specify
I w three replicas,
or two replicas or whatever.
Here I may say triple
replication for F one,
so I have a copy of that
block on each of these.
And for F two, I would
have double replication.
And so I guess I would
really have kind of
four blocks total because
I have two partitions,
and they each have two replicas.
The vocabulary I'll
use here is when
I'm looking at the file itself,
I'll talk about the logical
blocks of the file.
But when I'm talking about
the actual multiple
copies of that,
I'll say, well, that's a
physical block, right?
So if I have triple
a replication,
that each logical
block is going to have
three physical blocks
corresponding to it somewhere.
Yeah, c s here. Yeah.
Yeah. I think in the
first case, I just had,
yeah. So kind of earlier, I
know the database, right?
You say, we don't necessarily
know where the data is, right?
Is that an issue
here? Not quite.
So I think that issue earlier
was that I wanted things
like oid to work and
stuff like that.
So I had to have related
data on the same server.
Here, I'm not building
a database code.
I've been just building
a file system.
So file systems are
a little simple.
I have some file Dave and
then it's just like, Oh,
here's a bunch of bytes.
So what you're talking
about, definitely
is rabia a challenge again,
if we want to build like
a database on top of it.
But if I'm just doing files,
my life is a little bit easier.
Yeah, thank you for
contrasting that.
Cool. So I have this set up.
You know, if this
data note dies, well,
I still have some copies of
all of my data elsewhere, right?
So I'll just leave you
with this question,
maybe I'll get
somebody to answer.
Which of these files
is safer in general?
F one, F two. Everybody
holds it over figures.
F one safer, F two is
safer. Yes, F one is safer.
I have more replicas.
More machines
would have to die for me
to actually lose data.
It's possible, but less likely.
Alright. Thanks, everybody.
And I actually got to run today.
So normally like to chat
with people afterwards,
but I got to scoot out of here.
Have a fantastic weekend.