Alright. Good afternoon,
folks. Thanks for coming back.
Today, we're mostly going to do
some programming
demos with Big Query.
We have a bunch of fun,
more advanced things to do.
We are going to see
how we can query from
Google Spreadsheet
that's automatically
populated with the Form.
This is actually
the only project of
the semester where you all
will go submit the form,
and that will kind of generate
the dataset that we're
going to be working with.
We're going to look at some
geographic data, right?
So we might have
latitude and longitude,
and we're going to
see things like when
people submit that form
and give their location,
well, what county in
Wisconsin are they in? How
can we do stuff like that?
That'll be very similar to
the project coming on Wednesday.
And then finally, we're
going to do at least start
some machine learning stuff
with Big query today.
Before I jump into all of that,
I just want to do a quick tophat
to review from last time.
So please grab your phones.
And I have a question about
the correlated cross join.
seconds
left.
All right. So most
people are saying
four, which is correct.
So the cross join means we're
doing every combination
across like two lists or a
arrays or something like that.
And the correlate
de part means that
we're doing it on a
row by row basis.
So in some ways, it would
make more sense or be
more intuitive if we had
two arrays in the
same row, right?
Because we would be
getting every combination
across those two rays
in the same row.
So why do we call
a cross join here?
Because what we're doing
is we're combining
two with every
combination of BCD.
So we're going to get
for output one A,
and then two BCD.
That's why we'll have four
rows of output total.
Alright, C. So I'm
going to head over here
to the Jupiter notebook
that we were in last time.
And what we had done is
we were trying to load
some data into Big query.
So big query has their
own format that they use,
and they store that format
inside of Closss, right?
So colossus is Google's
equivalent to HDFS.
I would be kind of
the closest system.
And that format, at
least the last thing
they published about
was called Tapacitor.
And so what is this doing?
They are loading data from Park
in somewhere in Google
storage in GCS.
And that Park A data, right?
Is a different format, right?
We could directly query from it,
but that part format
has not been codesigned
with big query, right?
Big Query and capacitor were
designed together, right?
They're designed to inter
operate very efficiently, right?
So we're copying that data over
from GCS over into big query,
and that ran last time.
Now, what I want to
do next is I want to
show two external
use cases, right?
So the first one was we actually
bring the data in The other two,
when we have external data,
the big query is a little
bit more like Spark, right?
Like Spark doesn't own any data.
Spark, you can just say, Oh,
here's some Park files in HDFS.
They don't belong
to you, but start
doing some queries over them.
It's really kind of an
ad hoc query engine.
And we can use big
query in the same way.
We can say, Hey, here's
some different data sources
in different places, Park, CSV,
Google spreadsheet, whatever,
and it'll go and
it'll find that,
but we still have to register it
first before we can do that.
Alright, so how are
we going to do that?
So I have some stuff
here that will help.
And in this case,
what I will say is that the data
is in the Park format again.
And for this source URI,
I'm actually going to use
the same thing that
I did before, right?
So I'm the only
difference now is
that I'm not going
to copy it all.
I'm just going to keep it where
it is in place, right?
So I'm gonna do that.
I don't have to detect
the schema, right?
Be parts have a schema built in.
But I do have to say where
the data is trying
to end up, right?
So we're to end up last time,
it ended up in this
table here, right?
It was project data set table.
And so I'm gonna do
the same down here.
I have to give it
some kind of name.
And I'm just trying to
call this loans external.
Okay. So I'm going to run that.
And if it's already there,
we'll just overwrite it.
So let's run that as so.
And then I should be able to
come over here and I can see
my data in Big query, right?
So if I go under
Section two and expand
it, right I have loans.
And this data is owned
by Big Query, right?
So if I look at details,
for example, I can
see the sizes of it,
how many rows there are there.
And then loans external.
If I take a look at it,
there's no such information.
It's basically just a pointer to
this other data over there,
and who will storage.
Okay, cool. So different
ways I could do it.
If I have other tools that are
using the Park file
in Google Storage,
it makes sense to kind of
leave it there, right?
If I'm just using a big query,
I want it to be in
the capacitor format,
where it's tightly integrated,
so I would probably copy it in.
So the third thing I
want to do is I want
to access this external
external data.
And if you go to the
snippets over here,
Last time I actually have a
link to this form, right?
So if you go to this link,
if you copy it from the
sheets and you go there,
basically, this is a form that
lets us apply for
loans or pretend to.
And so kind of like,
imagine your dream house.
T's say it's a $2,000,000 house.
Imagine your dream
income, let's say,
500 k. Oh, no,
that's too many zeros or not.
And then for the
latitude and longitude,
you can put stuff there,
maybe 45 and, like,
89, and you submit that.
And one part of the project
for you will be to
go and you like,
submit something here
because this is generating
dataset that we'll be
analyzing on the project.
Okay, so Google Forms,
it is really easy to
set it up so that
it will every time
there's a submission,
it'll dump into a
form else, right?
So, lots of people
have been doing that.
I mean, if somebody's on
their laptop right now,
feel free to do that, we
might see some loans pop up.
You know, even as we're
going, you can see
mine right here. Alright, cool.
So what I want to do now is
I want to figure out how to
get this data into
Big query, right?
I'm, come over here. And I
have some starter code for that.
Um One of the first things
I have to do is instead
of having a Parke file.
In this case, my code is or
my data is in Google
Sheets, that's the source.
And then for the Uniform
resource identifier
or Universal
resource identifier.
It's basically the URL
for the spreadsheet
with all this stuff without
all this stuff at the end.
All right. I'm just
trying to copy this here.
And that will identify the
sheet I'm trying to copy in.
And then where do
I want it to land?
Maybe kind of in a
similar place as before.
I'll have it in the same
section two dataset.
But this time, I'm
going to put it in
a table called
Applications, right?
I'm put this in
applications, like so.
And in this case, right?
The Goole Sheet, it just has
a bunch of strings in it.
So in this case, I
actually do have to tell
it you should do Schema
inference, right?
We've seen scheme
inference with Spark.
This is how we do schema
inference with big query, right?
I do something similar if I was
bringing data from a CSV file.
All I'm I do that.
And then hopefully,
if that works, then I
should be able to
query from it, right?
So I can do big
query select star
from from these
applications, right?
And if I'm like, maybe I'll
even like it a chance to see
that maybe somebody is like
submitting it as we speak.
How many rows were there?
There were 22 rows, right?
The last one was 21.
Any questions about that
example? Right here.
Yeah. Problem. That's
a good question.
It's not a problem, right
because I have the scheme.
Does it matter if I tell it to?
No, it seems like it's
happy either way.
I learned that myself.
Is there any harm
to not using it?
Is there any harm to using it?
Yeah, I'm not sure.
I mean, I think you could also
we've seen issues with
scheme inference, right?
It's slow. Like,
you could there are
ways that you can pass in
the schema manually, right?
So if you wanted to be like past
and you want to make sure
it does the correct types,
and you'd probably do it
manually rather
than auto detect.
But if we're telling
something like
a Google Sheet or a CSV,
then we're going to have to have
some technique for
figuring out the types,
either auto detect or
manual specification?
Yeah, good question. Let's
take a peek on this, right?
I think the last index is 21.
I wonder if anybody else has
applied for a loan in
the meantime. Let's see.
Okay, one person did, so
thank you very much, right.
So, that's going to be
an expensive house,
if you're making $1 a year,
good luck with that.
All right, cool.
So we can do that. That's
actually very powerful, right?
Because you often have teams
where different team members
have different levels of
technical expertise, right?
Maybe you have some
people who are
not programmers,
they don't know SQL.
But they can do some
stuff on drool sheets.
And then you have people who do,
kind of think about scalability,
and they can write
SQL or big query,
and they can use
that data as part of
other things as well.
So it's a very powerful
combination. All right.
Fantastic. You're going
to use that same thing
on the Project eight,
which is coming out.
Coming out soon. Any
other questions about
that? All right. Cool.
So the next piece I want to
look at is geographic data.
I'm going to come down here.
And so I think I
want to be up here.
So I'm going to look at
some geographic data.
And you might
remember a little bit
about the geographic
data, right?
We can have some
type specific to
geography, like, you know,
a latitude, longitude point,
or a string of points or
some kind of polygon.
Yeah, go s right here.
Yeah. Oh, excellent question.
So is it doing a snapshot?
And no. It's doing it live.
And so that's that's actually
why I reran the query,
right because I
saw that there was
something like 22 rows.
And then after I ran again,
there was like 23 rows.
And who knows? Maybe. I guess
like the last index is 22.
Maybe in the meantime,
somebody else has
applied for a loan.
I guess we'll find out,
right? Or not, right?
Yeah, This is definitely live.
Whatever is currently there.
Yeah, thanks for
asking. All right,
let's take a look at
the geographic data.
And for these examples,
I'm going to take a look
at at County data, right?
So I'm I come over
here a big query.
And let me try searching for it.
So this is all under that
big query public data,
that kind of public facing
project that we've seen before.
And then what do we
have underneath that?
It was Geo US boundaries,
and I'm just typing,
you could dig around
and find it more manually
if you wanted to.
So I'm I find that
thing? And then we have
this County's data
set over here.
And the key thing there is,
if I look at a preview is
that we basically
have these polygons,
which are a bunch of points that
detrib the shape
of these things.
Okay. And so I'm going
to come over here,
and where is the There it is.
There's the name of it.
Let me copy that name.
And I'm going to do
something like this.
I'm going to say
big query query.
And I'm going to select
star from from that thing,
like, right, I'm gonna do that.
And what I want to do
is I want to limit it.
So it turns out that the US
Census Bureau assigns these,
what they call FIPS codes,
the different
geographic regions,
and if I was doing
this properly,
I would actually like to join
and try to look up Wisconsin.
But I happen to know
that the FIPS code
for Wisconsin is 55, right?
I'm just trying to
paste that in here.
So I'm to say where
the state state FIPS code
equals, I think it's a string.
Let me check my notes.
Yeah, it is a string.
Alright. So I'm I do
that. I have a query.
And when I just type a query,
it doesn't actually do anything,
right until I try to get
some data out of it, right?
And so we've seen before I
could do two data frame.
And the way this works is that,
if I have two data frame,
that will give me a Pandas
data frame, right? Like so.
And if I do two Geodata frame.
Well, that will give me is
a GeoPandas Geodata frame.
So GeoPandas is just a
library that's based
on top of Pandas. And I'm
to do that down here.
I actually want to
get a Geodata frame,
and I'm going to call
this thing, Wisconsin,
I'm to get Wisconsin
out of this.
And maybe after I do
that I'm going to say,
well, what is the
type of Wisconsin?
I I'm run that?
Should take a moment.
I I have an error. Alright.
There's more than one geography
column in the result.
Okay. So I guess there must be
multiple geometry aspects
over here. And that's fine.
I guess the one I'm really
interested in is the
county geometry,
and then also the
county name, right?
I'm t to come back here.
And I'm going to say, give me,
the county name, and then
the county geometry.
Let's try that. Alright,
and I may get this thing.
And as you see it's
a Geo data frame.
You know, if I have
a new type that I'm
trying to learn about,
one of the things
I want to see is
is it inheriting
from other types.
And one of the ways
we can understand
the inheritance of classes
and Python is that we can say
method resolution order.
The idea there, right?
I I have some object, and
I call a method on it,
and the class doesn't
directly define that method,
then it will go up the
hierarchy of inheritance.
I'll try to find
it somewhere else.
That's called method
resolution order,
where it tries to see
where I can find that.
And so when I look at
that, in this case,
I can see that the
Geo data frame
inherits from a regular
Panda stata frame?
Anything you can do with
regular Panda Sata frame
you can do here,
and then of course,
more stuff, right
because we're inheriting
from it and extending it.
So kind of on
that note of things that
we can do additionally,
one of those things we can do
is say Wisconsin dot plot,
and it'll automatically create
a plot of all these
counties for us.
Now, if I want to, I can say,
what is the face color of these?
So I'm I say a face color,
and I'm also going to
say an edge color.
L et me just check my notes
here. Am I putting
this down right?
Oh, I think it's just
color. Okay, great.
And, you know, I can put
things like red or whatever.
If I want to, I can also put on
a gray scale, so, you know,
one would be white, so it
would be completely bright,
and then zero would be black.
And so I'm going to have
the color of this be
a light gray color,
and the lines around it
will be a dark gray color.
So I can plot it and see a
little bit easier.
These counties.
It kind of look like
Wisconsin counties,
maybe differ than
what you've seen.
These are not the
land boundaries.
These are political boundaries.
And so on the right hand side
of Wisconsin, for example,
there's a bunch of
relatively narrow counties,
but they have a bunch of water,
right within their
political boundaries.
Same thing up here
on Lake Superior.
I can see the longitude
on the x axis,
I can see the latitude
on the Y axis.
I wanted to, I could,
look at this to try to
figure out if I'm submitting
that form, right?
I could say, like, negative MD,
negative 44,
something like that.
I could fill out
that form and try to
pick a loan application
for a house
somewhere in Wisconsin in
these coordinates. Alright,
course, I have that.
And there's a few things
that I can do that are
interesting with it.
One of them is that you
might want to be using
a big query in combination
with other tools.
Big query, the strength is
that it's highly
scalable, right?
But it's not like very full
featured in terms of
all this geographic
stuff you can do.
A lot of people doing GS work
are using tools like R GIS.
And what you want to do is, you
might want to move your
data back and forth,
kind of a big query for things
that require scalability.
You to make R GIS for
things that require
more functionality.
And so if I have
this geo data frame,
I can say two GO JS.
And if I look at like
the first thousand
characters of that,
it will L et me just
check my notes.
Oh, just two JSN.
Okay. Fine. That's
GO JSN format.
I can see that some
kind of JN format that
has a description of all
these boundaries, right?
And so if I wanted to, I could
just write that to
a file somewhere,
I could say with
Open Wisconsin at
GO JSN. I'm writing to it.
Then I could say f dot right,
whatever is that JSN
stuff that I have.
And then comb me
over here, right?
I would have a nice
file, Wisconsin GeoJSN
that I could go ahead
and I could you know,
import into other tools or
maybe I import
back to Big query.
I can move fluidly between
these different tools, right?
The other thing I
might want to do
with this is I might
want to create
a Wisconsin data set
that belongs to me and
my project, right?
So this Wisconsin data is coming
from It's coming from this
public project, right?
And if I want to do a study
of Wisconsin, every
time I'm using this,
it's filtering it
down to Wisconsin,
and I'm really paying
kind of proportionally
to the whole data set, right?
The whole United States.
And so what I might want to
sometimes do to save money
is make a copy of it.
It's going to be fast
either way, right?
Because it's very parallel
internally, right?
They're using lots of machines.
And so we aren't going
to do this to be faster.
We're going to be doing
it to save money.
And right? That's the
mind set in the Cloud.
And the cloud, there's
lots of things that are
fast that are also
expensive, right?
So we're more worried about
money than time when
we're in the Cloud.
Anyway, so I want to
get a copy of this in
my own project that is
just Wisconsin, right?
And so the way I will do
that is tum me down here.
I will say a big query.
And I will first just
paste the query that has
the information I want.
And then above it,
I can gibt some name, right?
So the name is BCS 544,
F 24, section two.
And I'm may call this Wisconsin.
Okay. And so the way I
can actually do this now
to complete this is I can
put some ticks around it.
I my quoting style,
and I can say, create table.
I'll create a table like that.
I have to put the
word as down here.
I'll space that a little bit.
That's going to create a table
by copying the results here.
And then further on, right?
I'll be able to more efficiently
just look at Wisconsin, right?
Small tweak on this, I'll
create or replace table because,
you know, I want to
be able to re run it
without any problems. I'm
going to create that thing.
And I'm going to have this
Wisconsin data frame or
this Wisconsin table that I can
use for a variety of things.
If I come over here, I should
be able to see it now.
And that right if
I come and look
at I span that.
Then I think there
are Section two.
Then I have Wisconsin, right?
Alright. Cool. And
then I can preview it.
And I can say just have
the county name and county
geometry like expected.
I'll for Wisconsin.
Alright, cool. Any
questions so far?
Yeah, he? Refer to
everything else below?
Y, Yeah, so what that means is
that first it run this query,
and then it should
create a table with
this name and dump those
results into that new table.
Exactly. Yeah, thanks
for saying it that way.
No Are other questions
people have?
All right. Cool. Okay,
so we have that thing.
Now, what I want to look
at are some different,
you know, spatial or geographic
operations we can do.
And so the general pattern
you're going to see is that,
where I have something like
ST and then some function.
And that's because ST stands
for a spatial type, right?
So I have a bunch of
functions of that nature.
And so one of them I
might want to do is I
might want to union these
shapes together, right?
I have all these polygons.
I might want to combine a bunch
of smaller polygons
into bigger polygons.
Right? I might want to have
some grouping for that.
So, for example,
You know, I forget.
I think we have
something like maybe
like six congressional
districts.
Maybe I might want to have
a congressional district
that is the union of a bunch
of these counties together.
In this case, I'm just
trying to do a simple
thing where I have
union together into one
big Wisconsin shape.
Okay, so to do that,
I will copy this stuff I had up
here and strolling down a bit.
I will hold this on
just data frame, right?
And what I will do
is I will select
from I don't have
to have the wear
anymore because I
only have Wisconsin data.
I'm going to select from
that new table I created.
And the name of that
table is Wisconsin.
And then what I'm
really interested in
is for that county geometry
I want to aggregate.
Instead of having a
bunch of little shapes,
I want to have one
big shape, right?
And so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to say
ST union aggregate, right?
And this is not that different
than other aggregates
we've seen.
If I do like Man, I
have a bunch of rows,
I end up with one
row, or if I say Max.
I have a bunch of
rows, I end up with
one row. Here, I have
a bunch of shapes.
I end up with just one shape.
I can see that down here, right?
If I take a look at it, there's
going to be one row
in that output.
And then if I want to,
I can plot it, right?
And then what will it be?
I'll just try to make
this the same as before.
Alright. I'm just going you
one big Wisconsin shape.
Right? Just like with other
aggregates, like Man,
sometimes you'll do a grouping
by first, and then do it.
I could do the same
thing up here.
I won't right now,
but I could group
the counties in some
way, and then, you know,
union together, the ones that
are all in the same category,
and I could do a
few bigger shapes.
Yeah. Any questions
about that aggregate?
So a lot of these
spatial things will
have different functions that
are doing related things.
So might be aggregates, and
some might not be, right?
So when I see that that
AGG is going to show up.
And some of the other ones
we're going to look at.
Alright, drawing
back a little bit.
I am t to see how we can do
centroid aggregates, right?
And the way this will work is,
I am t to grab that same query.
And I'm going to
modify it, right?
And what I want to
do is I want to get
the centroid aggregate of
all of these together.
And that's going to be
the same thing. I call
this DF two, right?
And in this case,
I'm going to get
one row again because
it's an aggregate.
And in this case,
it's a single point.
So let's just see what that
looks like if I plot it, right?
So if I plot this,
and then I plot
this one as well,
what I'd really like
to do is I'd like
the second plotting to go
on top of the first one.
And that's very doable
because when I call plot,
what it returns is
something called
an A an axis some
plot object, right?
And if I'm plotting
something new,
I can tell it that, Hey,
I want to draw on top
of that previous one.
I may say the color for
this one is red, and draw.
I can see that this
is the centroid
of Wisconsin. What is a cent?
You can define in
different ways,
but kind of an informal
way would be If I cut
out this shape and
kind of balanced
my finger in the middle of it,
that's where it would be, right?
That would be kind
of the center of
mass of this region, right?
So I can see that where that is.
And you know, just visually,
that seems about right.
Right? So, oftentimes, right,
like I said, we will
have versions that are
an aggregate or
not an aggregate.
And And so there's also
a version of this
spatial function that
just called ST centrd, right?
And I'm going to
run this again now,
and I'm going to have a version,
which is not the
aggregate version, right?
So the aggregate version flaps,
it's in one big shape
to get a centride.
This one gets ne
acentride for each of
those individual regions
that we saw before, right?
Maybe I'll just say Wisconsin
down here when I plot this.
And let me plot DF three now,
like so on top of it,
right? That's be the same one.
Maybe I'll use black
for that shape, right?
So DF three is not defined
because I haven't run it yet.
Great. And so now
I can see I have
this red centroid
for the whole state,
and I also have
centroids for each of
the individual
counties. Oh, right.
Well, Any questions so far
about any of these
spatial type functions?
Alright. Cool. So what
I want to do now is I
want to tie this
together because
we have that spreadsheet data.
And I want to see, for example,
how that spreadsheet
data fits into this.
And so if I come over here
and look at my spreadsheet data,
I see that I have this
latitude of linitude.
And that is not a
geographic type.
Those are just numbers, right?
In fact, they're
just like strings
that when I load them in,
I infer that they're
numbers, right?
And so if I actually
want to use this in
combination with other
geographic data,
I have to convert
it to that, right?
That's what I'm I do now. I see,
can I create a geographic data
set based on the
stuff that's in here?
I see that people have
been loading in more,
so thank you very much for that.
Alright. So my head over here.
Or actually over here.
And what I'm going to do is I'm
going to first just
query from it, right?
So let's say a big query,
select star from
This is Section two,
and then it was
applications, right?
I'm going to do that. I'm going
to see that there's
a bunch of these.
And what I want to
do is I want to say,
in addition to all
that, I want to
get a geographic columns.
I'm may say geographic point.
And here I may put
linitude and latitude.
And people often say
latitude linitude,
but they do linitude latitude.
And at least in my head, that
actually makes more sense
because it's like an
x axis and a y axis,
I'll just tell that
as a location.
And then I'll get the rest
of the stuff over here,
that I might have,
right? So let's do that.
And then I have this new
column in the front,
which is this geographic point.
Just like before I may
create a table from.
I'm going to say create table.
And I may call this I'm may
call this houses, right?
So houses are basically the
same as applications with
this geographic column and
I'm to create or replace.
Alright, let's
create that thing.
And now I have a dataset
that I can use in
combination, right?
This is a dataset that
belongs to my project,
but I can combine it with
the public datasets or with
my Wisconsin dataset
if I want to, right?
Alright, C. So I have
those houses there.
Maybe one of the first
things I can do is
I can try to see where
all these houses
are on top of the
Wisconsin map, right?
So let's do that.
I'm going to have
Wisconsin plotting like
this down here as before.
And then what I also
want to do is I want
to get a data frame.
Well, geo data frame
like this up here,
where I'm going to select
everything from
these houses, right?
So I'm going to say select star
from all of all of my
houses. Let's do that.
And then if I come down here,
I can say data frame dot plot.
Me say Ax equals Ax,
and maybe the color
will be black, right?
And it's actually kind
of hard to see, right?
Maybe I have a few on top
of the Wisconsin map,
which is now tiny, right?
But people have been
saying they want houses
all over the world and
probably in some oceans,
too, so whatever suits you.
Anyway, what we're
going to have to
do is we have to combine
these data sets.
For example, I might want
to say, I only want to see
houses that are inside
of Wisconsin counties,
and that's an example
of a geographic join,
right to kind of pair up a point
with a polygon somewhere.
All right? You may show
some different ways we
can combine these datasets.
One is that I can look
up distances, right?
Let me just check my notes here.
Um, I'm going to
show a quick example of the
distance function, right?
And what I may do first,
I may say, Hey, like,
show me the houses that are
near the state capitol,
right, based on their distance.
And so I'm may say, big
query, I may select.
I have a distance function,
which I may come back to and
maybe maybe a houses
dot star from that.
And I may do this from a
section two dot houses.
And what I want to see is,
what is the distance, right?
The distance is going
to be in meters.
I'm may divide by 1,000
and draw that kilometers.
And then I'm may order by
kilometers. Ascending, right?
So one of the
smallest ones close.
Who is choosing houses
near the US Capitol.
All right. So how do
I actually do this?
I have to have two points.
I 0.1 and 0.2.
0.1 comes straight
out of houses, right?
So if I have houses dot
location, I have that there.
And then 0.2, I may a hard code.
If I come look at the
snippets over here,
I paste it in the coordinates
of as a geographic point of
the Madison or I'm sorry,
the stat Wisconsin State Capitol
because I don't want to
type all that, right?
I'm to do that. And so
let's take a look at that.
Maybe I'll limit by ten.
And I can see how close
people are choosing, right?
I guess this one's
the closest so
it's only 263 kilometers,
and then then it just kind
of goes up up from there.
Right? So that'd be one
thing I could do, right?
Instead of kind of
plotting all of
this scatter over
the whole world.
I can look at the few that are
closest to some specific
location, right?
That's one thing we could do.
The other Yeah, question right.
Yeah, I was just drawing
to this is in meters,
maybe I'll just make a
note of that, right?
So returns distance and meters.
And I just want kilometers.
Yeah, that's all.
Good question. Other questions
people have. Oh, yeah, here.
Address something
similar earlier,
but if I were to form
right now and you re Yeah.
Oh, yeah, that's
a good question.
What adapt right now,
and sort of, right?
So earlier, the answer was
yes, because at that point,
I was I had done this, right?
So when I am
registering this here,
I'm not copying the
data and to Big Query.
I'm just try pointing to
it externally, right.
And so this table is
called applications.
So every time I
query applications,
applications will be
the most recent version
of it, it'll keep refreshing.
Now, if I go a little
bit further down,
I start with applications,
and at some point,
I did create a replace table.
No not that one. I did
Trader replaced table
houses down here.
And so when I do that creer
replaced table, to
create that table,
it gets a snapshot
at a single point
in time of applications, right?
So applications will
always reflect the latest.
Houses reflected the state
at that moment. I did that.
Do you have any ideas, like,
if I did want houses
to be updated live,
too, or what I do instead
of creating a table?
Ist of a table,
what else we have?
In Sequel. Right here.
High views Yeah,
we've had high views,
high views, and
that's something that
exists and big query
exists in lots of
different things, right?
So we would just create a
view if we wanted to be live.
Yeah, excellent
question. Alright, Cl.
So I we're in good
shape. There questions.
I say hand up somewhere
at some point.
Maybe it was a related topic.
Alright, C. So what I
want to look at now is,
how can we actually
figure out not just like,
who's closest to a point,
but which polygon
are you in, right?
And so we're going
to have a function
that is called within.
And so let's come down here
and I'm going to paste
this You know what,
we could actually even
just do this again, right?
I'll start here. All right.
So I want to see the ones
that are within some
counties, right?
I'm say DF, and I
am going to select,
you know, some houses, right?
And I'm going to do that
from Section two houses.
Okay. And now I want to pair
it up with that county data,
the way I'm going to do
that is I say a cross join.
I'm going to say cross join
with Wisconsin, right?
I have all those Wisconsin
counties, right?
Somewhere. Here they
are. Cross joining that.
And that's going to pair
up every single house
with every single county,
right? Okay. So I'm to do that.
And then what I may do is I
may say where houses Well,
location is within
that county, right?
So I'm going to do
that with using
this function tel within.
So when that location is
within the Wisconsin
county geometry,
then I'm going to
filter that out.
I'm going to say
where that is true.
This is my filter I'm
use the word predicate for
that. Here's my predicate.
And um When I look at it,
and naively seems like
something that's going to
be really slow, right,
that I have to pair up
every single house with
every single county and then
filter down after the fact.
But people do this all the time.
So then D Google came along,
and they optimize it.
So even though it looks like
something that's
going to be slow,
this is one of the
things that's going to
be fast because they
documented that they have
special optimizations
for this one, right?
So be very careful with
the cross toin unless it's
documented that they
have some type of
optimization. Alright,
so I have that.
And then I think in
addition to those houses,
and I can just say, you know,
the co not geometry,
but the county name, right?
F Wisconsin, let's try that.
And see how many people picked
houses in Wisconsin, right?
So if I look at DF,
only one of them right
now. Okay, so that's fine.
So we have one person
that their dream
houses in Wisconsin, for them.
And what I'm I do now is I'm
plot this on top of
my Wisconsin map.
So if I come back to
here like before,
then fingers cross,
if I do this right,
then I'm only going to
see that one point,
and that's where some
of these dream houses,
and that was in Marinett County.
A right? And then, you
know, I'm sure that
as you all are filling
this out and doing PA,
like, we're going to,
you know, see more stuff
like this on the maps, right?
If people kind of
more carefully choose
their coordinates.
Alright, cool.
Any question about
the cross join
or this predicate filter
here? All right. Cool.
Now, there's another
version of this
called WN or D WN, right?
And so ST D within
means within some
given distance, right?
And you can imagine
lots of things like,
maybe maybe I have
one data set of like
houses and one dataset
of of restaurants.
I'm try to say which restaurants
near which houses,
and then, you know,
I can have a marketing campaign
based around that
Dan concept, right?
So I want to see how far are
things away from each other.
I, what I'm may to do just
for simplicity is I'm going
to have one data set
of houses, right?
And I may have one data set,
which is of the centroids
of each county, and I
can just see, like,
Well, for each house, you know,
which counties are
within some range of it.
And honestly, there
probably won't be a lot
because right now
we only have one
data point in Wisconsin, right?
But we're going to
set a radius, right?
We'll probably get a few of
these on top of it, right?
Alright, so how are
we going to do this?
We are going to
say big big query.
Right? And we're going
to sect something
from the houses, right?
And we're a cross join.
We're a cross train against
Wisconsin, right so.
Remember that I'm
just going to do
this as a different
example of the syntax.
That means exactly
the same thing.
That is a cross join. I
have a cross train there.
And I'm going to say where
the distance All right.
So what I want to say
is that the house
is within some distance from
the centroid over here.
So which points from
the left hand side are
near points on the
right hand side, right?
I may say the
houses do location.
And on the right hand
side, I may say, Well,
I guess I have the
county geometry,
but I really want to have
a single point, right?
So I'm may say, what is
the centroid for
that? S I have that.
And then the last thing that
remains is just
having a distance.
And let's say 30,000 kilometers,
right? So may do that?
Oh, then what do I need up here?
I need to say, like, the houses
Well, let's do everything.
And then section
two or I'm sorry,
the wisconsin dot
county name, right?
So, what am I having
an issue with now?
It's called Section two.
And this is line three on
character this line three?
Yeah. And it's always kind
of I always like a little
bit picky about when I I
haven't quite learned
the rules about when
I need to fully
qualify it or not.
Is that the same thing?
Now I guess I probably have
to put ticks around it.
So let's try that. Okay, I
just gets worse and worse,
Okay, what did I do wrong?
So under Section
two, You know what?
I just have Wisconsin
right here.
I think I can just say
Wisconsin actually,
Wisconsin G County geometry.
County
If somebody sees,
like, some obvious typo
that I did, let me know.
Did you mean county geometry?
For some reason, I'm not
seeing the difference there.
Yeah, that is what I meant.
It's like, did you really
mean to have a typo there?
I don't know if anybody I
mean, this one was working.
L' row back to something that's
working and try one
more time, right?
So I'm to come back to this one.
That was working just fine.
That runs, right? And then
I wanted to do distance within.
And then over on this side,
I wanted to get the
centroid, right?
So I don't know
what I type wrong,
but let's see if that works.
And then I finally
need to have an
argument over here
for the distance.
And we said 30,000.
All right, Now we can see which
houses are within
than kilometers,
maybe like 50,000 And
now there's like a couple that
are within that range, right?
Cool. So we can see
which houses are
near which county centroids.
Alright. Sorry you got
so confused on that one,
but any questions
about that one?
Here. The distance, yeah,
can we get the distance.
Sure. Absolutely.
This is just returns,
that's returning a
true false, right?
If I did this, it
would always be true.
But if I just wanted the
distance, then I would say,
well, what is the distance?
So was one of the
earlier ones we saw.
Sometimes I want to
turn into a boolean.
Sometimes I want
it to not be that.
Then I can see the
distances over here, right?
All right. Cool. Is that
what you're going for?
Yeah, other questions
people have.
Yeah, right here. Both of
these rows have the
same latitude and
longitude and the
same time, right?
Because it's It is
the same time, right?
Yeah, so it's the
same row, right?
Because, you know, I
have a bunch of houses,
and I have a bunch
of locations, right?
And so each house could be
near a bunch of locations.
Each location could be
near a bunch of houses.
It's kind of weird data sete is
I have like one point
actually in Wisconsin.
But in general, right, I would
have an output here that's
much larger than either of
my two inputs. That makes sense?
Yeah, thanks for asking. Other
of questions people have.
Right. Cool. So what
I want to do next is
just show some
other things where
we actually want less
precision, right?
And so I want to look
at some approximations.
And these are for either like
privacy or machine learning.
All right. And the
first one is that
sometimes we want to round
these latitude and
longitude points.
And so let me just do this.
I may say big query.
And so I could select
houses dot star from
Section two dot Houses.
That's what we've
been doing, right?
Alright. And you
can imagine that,
Maybe I want some
data scientists
to do some work on these things,
but I don't want to tell them,
like the exact location of
everybody's house because that'd
be kind of creepy, right?
So for this location,
if I want to,
I can say snap.
Two grid, right?
And then I can have
some drid of some
granularity that I want.
So I could say location.
And then I don't know,
0.1, I think would be kind
of reasonable, right?
So I could do that. And
then I could you know,
they would use this
information over here.
I could see approximately
where these locations are.
They could do a lot of analysis,
but they won't know
exactly where people live.
So you might have some
kind of pre processing in
a pipeline that hide
some information,
but not all the information.
That's one thing you
might want to do.
An Other case where you might
want to lose information is
that Maybe we're doing some
kind of machine learning,
and we want to put
these houses in
different categories based on
how close they are
to each other.
I mean, I couldn't use
the county geometry for
that because I guess
house in the same county
are somewhat close
to each other.
That doesn't necessarily
make a lot of sense
because counties are
different sizes.
You know, metro regions
might cross counties.
It's a little bit arbitrary
in a lot of ways, right?
And what I might want to
do is I might want to
just break up the
world into grids and
assign names to
different squares
in that grid and then say,
well, which square
is each house.
All right, Somebody I do
that. It's kind of similar.
And the function for that
is called Geo, right?
Somebo do it Geo
H. And then I say,
how many, you know,
characters of
precision do I want?
Right? I'm to do that.
And so I'm going to
assign these geo Hah codes
to each of these houses, right?
And if they have the same one,
then they're kind of
close to each other.
I might treat them the same
from a machine
learning perspective,
right if I have some
kind of thing that needs
a categorical variable.
So I could do that.
If I wanted more more grids
that are finer granular area,
I could do that, right?
Yeah, so I might do that as
a pre processing stop.
Yeah, question right here.
That's a good question.
I don't know if it's
26 or if they have fewer.
I'm not sure. I'm not sure
how many would be in that ts.
Yeah, but it's a good question.
Questions people have? A right.
Cool. So that's what I
have for the geographic
computing stuff.
I at least want to
start some machine
learning stuff today to give a
little bit of an overview there.
And it's my head over
to these slides.
And there's a couple of
things in the slide deck.
One is the machine
learning piece.
And then I also want to spend
some more time about
thinking about
cost and building some intuition
about when are things
expensive or not?
So I have three learning
objectives in these slides.
The first, which is for
today is to create and use
machine learning
models with big query.
And I think the interesting
thing here is that,
you know, it's a very
sequel oriented system.
And so they try to make
everything that you do with
machine learning look
like a query, right?
So kind of creating a model
looks a lot like
creating a table,
getting predictions, looks like
you're querying over
those predictions, right?
Kind of an elegant novel
thing that we'll see a little
bit different than the Spark
API for machine learning.
All right, so let's
look at some basics.
One of the first
things you're going to
do if you have some data
set machine learning is
you want to do a
train test split.
And they provide a function
for that called the
data split method.
And I'm going to give
you all the reasons
why you should never use it.
And then I'll suggest
an alternative, right?
But it's just like
Dre and I think that
people kind of
gravitate towards it.
First off, you generally want to
have some data for training
and some for test.
You train on the training data,
you evaluate on data that the
model hasn't seen before.
Otherwise, you might overfit.
Like you might
just t to memorize
a random quirks of the dataset.
And then it looks like
your performance is
better than it is.
So you might decide normally
what that split is.
Now, they made some weird
decisions here, right,
if you have less than 500 rows.
They will automatically train on
all of the data, which
is weird, right?
If you have less
than 50,000 rows,
then you will have 80% for
training, 20% for test.
And then if it's bigger
than that, it'll
be 10,000 rows for test,
and however much
else for training.
Is that about a weird decision
there already that they're
doing that for you?
If you just say, Hey, train a
model and here's some data,
they're going to do that
automatically for you.
Now, the other issue I have,
which they document here.
I have a straight quote from it,
is that after they do
that train test split,
there was some
randomness involved.
But they remember
what the split is,
and they remember
that for 48 hours.
So it'll really feel like
it's deterministic and all that,
and then two days
later, it's like,
your results will change
and surprise you.
Right? And so, my
first piece of advice
is that when you're
doing the training,
you just want to
disable that, right?
You want to say when you
train a model, you want
to say data split,
method equals no split,
and then do it yourself.
How can you do it yourself?
You need some kind of
randomness, and fortunately,
Sequel has this rand function,
which returns the number 0-1.
And that's actually
nice for getting
some sample of a
given size, right?
If I say, give me a random
number 0-1, and I say,
if it's less than 0.2, well,
20% of the 20% of the
time, it will be, right?
So you can specify
a ratio, do that.
And then after you split,
save that somewhere
because yours
is not deterministic either.
Save it in like a train park
file and test park file,
or something like that,
and then drove from there.
Okay, so how do we
actually train this?
Like I said, they
want to integrate
everything with queries.
And before you can
train a model, right,
you have to show
it some features
and some labels with some
data in each of those.
And so what better
way to prepare
that than with a query, right?
When you start doing
machine learning
with big query,
first think, Okay,
let me write a query that brings
all my features and
labels together.
So maybe I'm trying to predict
the temperature today,
and I might look at the humidity
today and the
temperature yesterday.
I could write some
query to do that.
That its both features and
my label. Then what do I do?
Well, we already saw
the syntax earlier
where I could say create
or replace table.
And instead of that we're
going to say create
a replace model. Okay?
We're going to do
that. And then it
has that same as
syntax as before.
And then we put a query
down here that's getting
those features and
labels, right?
So if you know some SQL stuff
and you know how to create
tables and do queries,
well, all of a sudden,
it's not much more work to make
a machine learning model, right?
So like I said, it's
of a novel approach.
They have that in
the same hierarchy
that they do for tables, right?
So a table goes project
data set table.
Here, they'll have
project dataset model.
So why are they grouping
tables and models together?
Well, obviously, I can
query from a table.
It's a little less
intuitive, but
I can also query from a model.
Right? If a model has inputs,
then I could query
and say, well,
what are the predictions,
right? That it gives me.
Right?
Okay.
So there's some options we
have to provide two, right?
So after I do the
creator replace model,
I say options out
here, and you would
say what kind of model
type you wanted to.
Like a lintor regression
would put coefficients on
each of your features.
I say, multiply this
column by three,
that column by four,
add it all together.
There you have a
prediction, right?
So we could do that. A bunch
of these are based on trees.
They don't have straight
up decision trees
like we learned the semester,
but all of these four I've
listed here are variants
on that, right?
They have classifiers
and regressors.
If you're predicting a
category or a number,
all of these are kind
of based on having
a a bunch of
simple trees that are
basically evoding, right?
The random forest, all the
trees are kind of equal.
With the boosted one, they're
trying to intentionally choose
new trees that kind of
counteract the weaknesses
of the previous trees.
Anyway, a lot of the stuff we've
seen, you could do here as well.
They also have some deep
neural network suff
which is terrible.
I wouldn't ever use it, right?
It's just very expensive
and it doesn't
perform very well.
Anyway, they have a
lot of reasonable
stuff in here as well.
Right? And the very
last thing that
you can do is when
you feed this in,
you have to specify which
column you're trying to train.
In this case, I'm trying
to train and say,
Hey, this temperature is the
label I'm trying to predict.
I don't have to specify
the other features,
because it assumes that anything
that's on a label is a feature.
So do your query
carefully, right?
Because I just do a
pretty a bunch of
stuff is trying to try to
turn all of those
things into features.
Alright, I'll end
there, and feel
free to come up and
chat if you have
any questions and
have a fantastic day.