Technically, on the schedule,
we're supposed to be
starting H based and
Cassandra, realistically,
we're going to spend all
of today just touching
up on Spark machine
machine learning.
So I'm back to the slides
where we were last time.
I just wanted to clarify
some terminology that's a
little bit different in
Spark than some other tools.
A lot of machine learning
tools have this notion
of a transformer
where you're pre
processing the data
in some way before
your actual model trades
or makes predictions.
In Spark, they use transformer
a little bit more generally.
They use transformation to
also refer to the act
of making predictions.
So if I have a data frame with
no predictions and then I
added a column of prediction,
that would be transformation.
That's what they call it.
So that's a little
bit different.
The idea of an estimator is a
little bit different as well.
So in a lot of machine
learning frameworks,
models or estimators
are mutable, right?
So maybe you show
them some data,
and then they know
how to predict
or maybe they get
better at predicting.
Given they're
ammutable, if I show
an estimator some data in Spark,
it doesn't actually change.
What an estimator will
do is it will return
a different object that
can do predictions.
That different object is
called a transformer.
Yeah, question right
here. Just a clarify.
Yeah, so this is just, in
terms of neuro
network transformers,
they're using it in a
very specific way here.
The idea of a
transformer here is
something that's
adding su columns to
existing data frame that may be
adding a prediction or it may be
adding other types
of info. Yeah.
So they're using the terms
in a very narrow way
related to Spark.
Yeah, thank you for
clarifying. All right, cool.
So, oftentimes, before
you do any kind of model,
you work, you have to transform
your data in some way.
And so a common scenario is
you're going to do a bunch of
transformations
before you get to
your actual estimator
at the Ed, right?
So this might be kind
of a similar picture
of different kinds of tools.
Let's say that we're
using Spark specifically.
What we'll do if we want
to trade a model is,
we'll pass some data through
multiple levels of
transformation.
And then we'll finally
fit into that estimator.
We'll call F on the estimator.
That does not actually change
the estimator because
it's abutable,
but it will return.
A fitted model.
And remember that fitted models
are transformers in Spark,
so I will get this T over here,
which is the fitted model.
Now, before I could send data to
this model that can
make predictions,
I need to make sure
that it has had
the same transformations
I had during trading.
And so in addition to creating
that transformer
from the estimator,
it will copy any other
proceeding transformers
over just directly as is so
that this model here on
the bottom right is dr to
see the same form of the
data that we saw originally.
So that's called a pipeline.
And they actually have two
types in Spark just like
the pipeline on the
left is fit version,
and then what has the
word model in it,
that usually means it
has already been fitted.
We'll call it pipeline model
on the right hand side.
We want to make predictions that
were to feed some data through
all these transformers.
The early ones that
might be adding
extra information for the model.
And then the transformer
the very last one is
going to be adding an actual
column of predictions.
So kind of unusual API.
Kind of interesting.
Actually, I think there's
some nice things about it,
but probably very different
than what you've seen
if you've done machine
learning in other contexts.
Alright, well, let's head
over here and do a top hat.
What is a method you will not be
using when working
with spark bottles?
About 30 seconds left.
Alright, so people say predict,
which is absolutely right,
rather than having
an explicit predict,
we do predictions by cab spark.
Alright, a head back here.
And and I want to
do some demos now.
And all the machine learning
stuff in Spark is
called ML Lb, right?
That handles a couple of
different frameworks they made.
But under that
general title ML Lb,
there's two different
things you might import.
If you actually import ML Lb,
that stuff that's actually
specifically for RDDs.
We usually are not
programming at that level.
We will be importing
PI sparked on ML,
which is for data frames.
But again, right, the stuff
we're doing under there,
people might refer to
that as ML Lb stuff.
Alright, Sub head over
here to a notebook.
And this is actually on
the new virtual machines
that we're running from CSL.
You can see I've
signed in here with
my net ID and the
machine name to SSHN,
that I actually had to
join the VPN first.
There's some
directions about that.
They've been very responsive.
You know, Suits have
been telling me issues.
I've been talking to them.
They've been resolving them.
I think some people
are having VPN issues.
That's the most
common thing, but
the Duet health test apparently
helps with that. I don't
know if I can fix it.
I'm kind of curious to
see what people are
running into because I haven't
seen anything first hand yet,
but you know, I cat solve it,
the Dot help SS actually
supports the VPD.
So anyway, eventually, like,
we're going to just do
all our projects
on these machines.
That's where we're
headed for P five.
It's optionally
you just get some
extra credit if you do it there.
Alright. So I've
connected to the VPD.
I did an SSH tunnel
to this machine,
and here I am by buddy
with the notebook.
I have a Spark
session as normal.
And then I have some code here,
which I actually copied
from the lecture snippet,
so you could do that
as well if you ought.
I'm learning something new
related to machine learning.
I like to generate random data
with some patterns in it,
because if I know exactly
what the patterns are,
then I can see is the model
inferring what
those patterns are.
And here I have a
very simple pattern.
So what I've done first,
I have random X one values
and random X two values.
I have a column
of each of those.
And the y is just the sum
of those plus a bit
of noise, right?
So the pattern is that
y is an addition.
And so any decent
machine learning model
should be able to recognize
this pattern, right?
And so let's see how
we can work with this.
Ib come out here.
And I'm going to
say data framed at random split.
And remember last time how we
talked about how you
might have trade,
validation and test data,
and we talked about my
methodology for that.
I think for now I'm
strange something simpler,
where 75% of my data is for
trading and 25% is for testing.
That is a spark transformation.
And I'm actually get back
two data frames from that.
No work has really
been done yet.
If I wanted to, I could
look what's in these,
so I could say something
like test dot show.
Let me take a look
at that. Now I
can see actual work
is being done.
And I can see some of
the values here, right?
That first one ends at 873.
Let me try running this again.
You'll actually notice
that these values
are sorted, right?
And so that's why there's
time a lot of small
values at the top.
Let me just run this again.
Alright. And we can
see that my values
came out a little
bit differently.
It's not deterministic.
And so one of the things
that people often do is
they'll try to specify a seed
for that type of situation.
Now, this is actually
a problem in
Spark because seed
gives determinism.
Per partition, but
not overall, right?
I think they're trying
to make it fast, right?
They don't want to have to
shuffle around the data when
they do this random splitting.
And so they do a random split
on each partition of the data.
And you can imagine why
that might be a problem.
If somehow I'm running in later
and I have different
partition sizes,
then even though I have a seed,
I might get different
results, right?
And so what people will often do
is after they do the
train test split,
they'll write the
data somewhere,
and then that's just
something that you do once,
and then you always read
it from that location.
So that we could
reproduce results.
I'm just going to say
both of these I may
say trade dot four bat.
I want to put it in a Park file.
We see we get the data
for a writer as usual.
If the data is already there,
I'm just going to ignore it.
Yeah, right here.
Data every time.
Could you achieve the
same thing by cashing it?
Maybe, but credibly
short term, right?
If I restart later,
then maybe my cash will
have been eptied, right?
So yeah, the best approach is
to keep it there long term.
And that's actually,
I don't know why,
a lot of these tools like,
have the similar problem,
like big query that
we'll look at later
does the same thing,
and they cash
automatically for you.
And so it's actually
really irritating
because it looks like
it's deterministic,
and it will be for
a couple of days.
And then after a couple of days,
your data changes, and then
you'll kind of lose
your mind, right?
So what we will
do in both cases,
we'll just write
it somewhere else.
Co. So I'm going to do ignore,
and I'm going to save it.
And I'm just to look at
my HDFS path up here?
I will save it to
trade dot part.
And how did I get that?
Then I'll do the same
thing with the test data.
I'll just try to
save those things
to make it dearbdistic.
Then what? Then I will
want to read them back.
I'll just start
writing a code for
that. Let's throw it out here?
It seems like I'm having
trouble with my HDFS.
Said something about
there not being
enough data nodes. Let
me just peek on that.
I have a name node of, but I
gs I don't have any data nodes.
I thought I had that all
good and ready to go. Let me
So my data Node died
here. I'm just trying
to delete that.
I'm I say doctor remove force,
and I'm gonna do a
doctor compose up again.
You know, one thing that
might have happened is if
I try to brought it down and
brought it back up again,
maybe the name note and
data note out of sync.
And so I'm I see if this
works any better for me.
Let me come back
here. My apologies.
Let's see if I can
talk to it now.
Well, that seems like
a good sign, right?
So let me I'm just trying to do
an overwrite in both cases
because maybe it wrote
some garbage file before,
because it didn't
have any data nodes.
I'm just going to
run this again,
and then I'm going to
change it to ignore.
So if I come here again,
it won't actually do anything.
All right. So my apologies.
So I'm gonna load this
data back in now.
I'm say spark of P. And then
I can load in those files.
Excuse me. Alright, so
I'm going to get my
train data like that.
And then if I ever restart
this from the top again,
then this will not
be done, right?
Because it's already
there. And I'm
going to get in that same
data I had last time.
So this will may be
more deterministic.
Let me just check on
the sizes of these.
This will not be exactly
75 25 because it's random.
Right. There's some
noise in the sampling,
but it should be kind
of approximately that.
So, 68 training
rows, two test rows.
Great, up and running so far.
Now I can start using this
data to do some training.
All right, so when I
look at my data here,
I see that my label is numeric,
and so that means I
need to do regression.
If it was categorical,
I'd be doing classification.
So I'm going to say from
Pi Spark ML regression,
I'm going to import a
decision tree regressor.
And this is an unfitted model.
And the other thing I might
import is a regression model.
So the ones that
have the word model
on them are the ones that
are actually fitted.
That's a fitted model.
So I will get both of those, and
then may create a decision tree.
I may create from the
unfitted one first, like so.
And then when I do that,
I have to say what my features
column and label column is.
We're going to deal
very soon with the fact
that I can only specify
one column here.
But for now, let's just
see what happens if I say
features column equals x one and
my label column equals
y. I'm going to do that.
And then I could try to fit
it to my training data.
And so the issue I'm running
into is that that
plum I'm fitting in,
it has to be a vector
of some type, right?
And it wasn't. It was just
a single value, right?
So since I can only
have one column, right?
The expectation is
that Tolm will have
vectors with many
different values,
and it is it's common to
have multiple features.
And so how can I get that
column of of features?
Well, I'm going to have
to transform my data.
So I'm going to back
up a little bit,
and I'm going to say from
Pi spark dot L feature.
I'm going to import
a vector as sembler.
All right. And so I can
create an object from that.
I can say a vector
assembler, if I want to.
And I can say my input columns,
like individual columns
that are coming in and
then an output
column which will be
a single column of vectors.
I'm going to say that.
I'm going to say
input columns is going to be X.
One is actually a nice
time to do X two as well.
And my output column is just
going to be features, right?
And so I can create that object,
and let's just see what happens
if I try to use it to transform.
I'm going to say, let's
transform my training data.
Excuse me. And I can
see that before,
I just had X one, X two, and y.
When I transform it, I
get all that same stuff,
plus I additionally
have features.
And if I want to, I could show
that data with that
vector of features.
Right I can see, for
example, here's 12.
That shows up as 12 here.
The only one that looks kind
of funny is this first one.
Okay. So when you have vectors,
there's multiple ways
to express that.
We could have what is called
a dense vector where we list
each number in it, and
that's most of these.
This is an example
of a sparse vector.
A sparse vector
means that most of
the numbers in the
vector are zeros.
And since they're mostly zeros,
it's a little bit
wasteful to keep
saying zero, zero, zero, zero.
And so what we'll do is we'll
say that I have a
vector of length two,
and at these indexes,
I have these values,
which are not zero.
There's no indexes here,
so there are no no values
that are not zero, right?
So maybe you'll see that it's
going to all work
the same afterwards.
Don't get mixed up by it.
Alright, so I have that. And so
what I want to do when
I want to fit down
here is I have to first use
my vector assembler to
transform that training data.
And then I should actually
be in better shape.
But my problem is
that the vector assembler
is giving me a features
column, right?
So I still have to fix that.
Great, so I can do that.
And I'm just trying to
capture this in a model
variable, like so.
All right. And this will
actually have to do
a bunch of different spark
jobs to train that model.
For now, we aren't getting into
details about what the
decision tree is doing, right?
This could be any number
of different models.
After we learn more
about the API,
I'll go back and
talk about, well,
how do we actually train
a decision tree model in a
distributed environment?
Alright, C, I have that.
And then what might I do? Let me
just take a look at the
things here, right?
So I'll look also look
at the type of model.
Again, we have this
pattern, right?
If it has the word model in
it, it's the fitted one.
Otherwise, it is
not. Alright, cool.
L et me try
predicting with this.
So I'm going to say
model transform,
and I'm going to
try to transform
my test data to get
some predictions.
And I'm running into
trouble here again,
and my trouble is
that I don't have
any features column.
I forgot something.
I forgot that I have
to transform this data
in the same way that I
transformed for training.
And so I actually got a little
bit lucky here because
I got an error.
You can imagine that if I
don't do the same
transformations,
and there's not an
error because maybe
I have a different problem
with the same name,
Then I could actually have
predictions that
are just garbage.
So it's very important,
we have to make sure
that however we train the data,
we set up our model with
transformations that are feeding
into our predictor
in the same way.
So I could just say,
Oh, let's be careful.
That's not great if I have
a bunch of transformations.
Instead, we have a pipeline
that make sure we always do
the same things
for training that
we do for testing. And
I'm may to import those.
I may say from Pie
Spark ML pipeline.
I will import pipeline.
This is an unfitted pipeline.
And then I'll also
import pipeline model,
which is the fitted
version. All right?
And then I can use these
to actually make sure I
combine all these steps.
Right so I may say
pipe up here will
be the pipeline, which
is not fitted yet.
And here I can say
which stages I want.
So may say stages equals,
and I have a list.
And so what I want to
do first is I want
to do the vector as semblar.
And then after that, I want
to have a incision tree.
Once again, nesting inside of
this is the same thing
as having a pipeline.
Just a different way of
expressing the same thing.
Great, so I have that, and
then I can say pipe dot fit,
and I can fit on
that training data.
And from that, I'm going
to get a model back.
Going to do all that
same stuff again.
It's a little bit
more elegant, right?
It's a better way to express
express your series
of transformations.
Let me take a look
at each of these,
so the pipe and the model.
Again, this is the unfitted
one, this is the fitted one.
And then if I wanted
to, I don't have to
worry when I take my model,
I can just say
transform my test data.
I can see that a few
things happened.
It's going to run the VA for me.
In addition to my
original columns,
I'm going to get a
features column.
It's sta to run the
decision tree for me.
In addition to
that, I'm going to
get a prediction column,
and I just keep adding stuff on.
This is the style in which we do
machine learning in
Spark. All right.
Any questions so far?
Right. Cool. Let's stig
into this pipeline
a little bit more.
If I come down here,
I can say stages,
and I can see both
of these steps.
And so I might want to
look at the second step.
And this one has something
called two debug string.
Strangely, it's not a method.
It's just an
attribute. That gives
me the string, which
I could print off.
And what we see is
actually that internally
a decision tree is a big
nested FL statement, right?
And so it has a bunch of
FL things and based on which
of those are true or false,
I have different
predictions, right?
So I think anybody who's
done nested FLS will
understand how a decision
tree makes predictions.
It's the exact same. What
will be more interesting is,
how do we actually come up
with this decision tree?
How do we have an
algorithm for that?
That's what we're going
to be doing after
we're done with
these demos here.
So I still keep that on hold.
Now, after you've trained
a model like that,
you might want to deploy it.
You maybe train it once,
and then it gets
used in a lot of
different circumstances.
And so what's actually nice
is that we can save models in
HDFS in much the
same way that we would
save a file to HDFS.
My HDFS cluster is visible to,
you know, lots of machines.
So if I do that, then any
of these different machines
could read in the model and
start using it to make
predictions, right?
So I'm going to me well,
actually, first, I'm
going to save it, right?
So I'm going to save it to HDFS.
And I'm going to imagine where
On a different machine and
want to use the model.
All right, so I
have my model here.
And what I can do is I can say,
dot, let me check
here. Dot writ.
It's kind of strange like
in the data frame API.
They say dot write and then
they do stuff. I don't know.
They just weren't
very consistent about
what's the method and
what's the attribute.
Fine, I'll do it. It's just
a little bit different.
That will give me
this writer object,
and I can do other
things with that.
Another thing that
was different is that
we would have a mode before.
Here, we will actually
just say, overwrite.
Some may say Orte.
And then finally, the end
is pretty similar, right.
So I'll say HDFS,
name node, 9,000.
I'll save that as a
model. All right.
So may save that model
for other people to use.
And then down here, I
could read it back, right?
So I know that model
was a pipeline model.
Right? Let me just
double check that again.
Was it a pipeline
model? Sure was.
And so I can take
pipeline model,
and I can load in and populate
a pipeline model by
those HDFS files, right?
So I could come down here
and I could say dot load,
and I could pass in
the same path, right?
So I could do this,
and then I get
a model down here,
which is great.
And then after that,
then I could actually use it to
start making predictions, right?
So I could say
transform my test data,
and let's just show
what it looks like.
Alright, so this is doing
pretty great, right?
I have my original data,
my features, my label.
These features here are just
vectors over my features,
and I can see the prediction.
And I can manually
go through it and I
can compare the prediction
to the y values,
and I can see the
model is not actually
doing that badly, right?
It's of doing reasonable
things, right?
And so that's good.
We're going to do very soon as
we're going to see
how we can actually
quantify how good
those predictions are.
But this is powerful, right?
That anybody with access to
CFS clusters can start
using the model,
we've effectively
deployed it for use.
One other thing I want
to show is if I go under
HDFS and I list the
files in this directory,
then I won't get too
deep into the format,
but then I can see
that all they have
these different stages,
and I can look under that.
And I can see that
this pipeline model
has the vector assembler,
the decision treat regressor,
and it has details
describing those things.
A common recommendation is
that Even if you only have
one stage in your pipeline,
it's still better to
have a pipeline than
using the decision
tree directly.
The reason why is that
when I loaded it,
I had to say what the type was.
And if I say everything is
always a pipeline model,
then it gives whosever
is training the models
the flexibility
to switch models within
a pipeline model,
and my load will always work.
If they were directly saving,
say a decision tree, then I
would have to know
when I'm loading.
It's a decision tree.
Here, I can use this model
that somebody else trained,
and I don't have to worry about
what kind of model
they were using.
If they find a different model
that works better, great.
They'll just deploy that.
It'll still work the same.
All right. Any questions
about this idea of
model deployment? Oh, right.
So what I'm to do now is I am
going to try to evaluate
how good this is,
and that will come
down to comparing
the y to the prediction.
And so from that,
I can import from Pi spark
dot L dot evaluation.
They have this function
called the regression.
Evaluator. So evaluator.
So for classifications,
we have some set of metrics
for regression, we
have another set.
This is actually
an umbrella that
covers a lot of different
metrics, right?
So evaluation. And so down here,
I can create one
of these things,
and I can say what metric
name I want, right?
And I'm going to say metric
name equals R squared score.
I'm not going to worry too much
about what the R
squared score is
because it's not like a status
class or machine learning class.
Basically, though, if I
have perfect predictions,
it's going to give
me a score of one.
So one is great. Zero means
like I'm not providing
anything useful.
If it was negative, I
would almost be doing
worse than just testing
the average, right?
So I'm going to pass
this, and I'm to say
my label column equals
y. I'm referring to
column names up here.
And then I can say my
prediction column.
Equals prediction.
And I may save that down
here. I have this object.
And just like everything, it's
going to act like a transformer,
it's going to have
a different name.
So I'm may say R two
score to evaluate.
And what I can do is
I can just pass in
data from my predictions.
I can pass in that
whole table like so.
And what happened there.
So It doesn't have,
it's just R two.
Okay. So I'm just going
to call it R two.
Great. So I do that.
And I may get a score, which
is quite read. Not
surprising, right?
It was a super simple pattern
just adding two numbers,
and so the decision
tree did what it did,
and it can pretty accurately
predict how the summation works.
And there was some
noise. So of course,
it's not going to be
perfect, either. Oh, right.
Those are my hands on demos with
the Spark API for
Machine Learning.
Any questions about the
API? Yeah, right here.
So this is an R squared score.
And so I know I'm not trying
to get into the math of it.
We could talk about it
offline if you want.
But you know, if I
like a scatter plot,
there's some variance
in the values,
and if I fit a line to it
or do something like that,
then in some ways, I'm
explaining some of the variance.
This is a really measure
of like, how much of
the variance my
model can explain.
And I can explain
almost 98% of it.
So that's in depth,
I'll go here,
but I'm happy to look
at actual numbers
like if you come up later.
Yeah, there are questions
people have. Right.
Fantastic.
So let's head back here.
And we've seen how
the API works.
A lot of different
models fit that API.
I want to look at
a specific model
and how we could train it
in histri environment.
And so the model I'm going to
look at is a decision tree.
And I'm going to look at it
in a few different ways.
First of'll see, if you
have a decision tree,
how do you use it?
That's the easiest part.
And then I'll see if I have
a small amount of data,
how can I train a decision
tree on a single computer?
That's not the focus
of our course,
but I think we need to all have
that same background before
we understand anything
on top of that.
And then what I'll spend
the most time on is
if we have data that spread
across many different computers,
how can we train
the decision tree
without having to move
data too often over the network?
So decision tree, you could
use them to make decisions.
You could also use them
to make predictions.
And so here I'm imagining
that I don't know,
let's say we have
a candidate for
a job and we make them an offer,
and we want to predict whether
or not they're going to accept
the job we could ask a series
of yes or no questions,
and based on the
answers, we could say,
well, we think they're
going to accept or not.
And so if the salary
is less than 50 k,
they're probably
going to decline.
I yes, then it might come
down to other factors.
If they have to drive
more than an hour,
they'll probably to decline.
If they're closer,
then maybe it comes
down to whether or not they
have free coffee, right?
I could ask all these
things and at the leafs,
I could have a bunch of
predictions or decisions,
depending on how you
want to look at it.
Those leafs could be numbers,
in which case, it's
a regression model,
like we were doing
in the notebook,
or they could be categories,
in which case it's a
classification model.
I could have a little
picture like this
or I could write
it as Python code,
which would be a big
nested Fels, right?
So I think that you know,
even people who are not
programmers can
look at that tree
and try to figure out
how to read through it.
Python programmers
could, you know,
write hard code it with Fs.
What's really
interesting is how do
we actually figure out how to
automatically figure out how
to create a good tree, right?
Alright, so I want to
motivate a little bit
more why we care about
decision trees because,
you know, there's
a lot of energy
around deep learning these days.
And so decision trees,
even though this is a
very old algorithm,
there are newer approaches
that are built on top of
it in particular on
ensemble methods.
And an ensemble method,
you actually have a
lot of smaller models,
and then you have some kind
of aggregation over them.
Maybe each of these
smaller models
are trying to make
their prediction,
and they vote in
some way, right?
So a random forest
would be a bunch of
different decision
trees altogether.
There's other
variants on it like
a gradient boosted trees,
with gradient boosted trees,
Each time we add a new
decision tree to the set,
we're trying to specifically
compensate for the mistakes
that the other ones make.
So we're trying to add
a voter that somehow
counterbalances mistakes
that other voters
have made, right?
So, you know, to do
any of these things,
we have to be able to train
a single decision
tree well, right?
So we need to have an
algorithm for that.
But this unlocks a
lot of other things.
And we won't talk about
more. I just want you to be
aware that this is a building
block for a lot of things.
So, why use trees at all?
Why use, you know, kind of
broadly what you might call
tree based methods in
instead of deep learning.
And I think that Sebastian Raska
has a really nice blog post.
Maybe some of you might
like to go read it.
Sebastian Achal used
to be a professor here
before he went off and is
doing things in industry now.
And so there's a comparison
in that blog between
deep learning and
tree Bates methods.
And one of the things
that it comes down to is,
what does our data look like
that we're working with.
Let's imagine that
we have irises.
Iris are kind of flower,
and we want to classify them.
There's a few different
kinds of irises.
One way you could do that is
you could have
unstructured data.
Maybe you just have
images of them.
And what you might try to
do to classify it is
you might come down to
different measurements,
like how large are the petals,
how large are the sepals,
things like that.
And one of the cool things
about deep learning is
that we can just feed in an
enormous amount of data,
raw pixels of those images.
And at the end, there's a
prediction, and internally,
even though it's it's
kind of opaque to us,
what's ultimately happening
is that it's figuring out
important features for making
the prediction, right?
So maybe internally, it
might be figuring out
the sizes of those petals
and sepals, right?
That's the strength of
deep learning, right?
We can throw on
structured data at it.
Of course, there's lots of
structured data in the world.
Maybe a human actually went
and measured these
things and has a table.
If you already have
structured data,
then tree based
methods do quite well.
They're competitive with deep
learning, and of course,
there's a lot of
important tabular
data in the world, right?
So, we're looking
at decision trees,
it's an old approach,
but there are a lot of new
things built on top of it,
and it's still competitive for
some important use
cases. Alright, cool.
So, the decision trees,
they're still useful.
If we want to build a
good decision tree,
we have to have some intuition
about what makes a tree good.
And so what I may
imagine here is that
I have a bunch of data,
and If I have
a tree where I asked all
these questions, right?
I could take any given row and I
could feed it through
those questions,
and I could see where does
this row land within the tree?
So I actually have two
different decision trees
over here asking
different questions.
The first one says, is
X one bigger than 2.5?
And if I do half of
the rows will go to the right
and half will go to the left,
or I could ask is X
two greater than zero.
And then in this case,
half the rows go each way,
but it's a different
half of them.
So just of looking
at this informally,
I'm wondering if anybody has
an opinion about which
decision tree is
better. Yeah, right here.
You like the one on the right.
Why the one on the right?
Yes.
Yeah. Excellent. The one
on the right is better
because after we
asked that question,
we kind of pulled together
related rows where we have
similar not a lot
of variances there.
And that's really kind
of what we want to do.
If we asked a question that
divides things in a way that
doesn't reveal any patterns,
so that's not that helpful.
We want to divide things
in a way where we
have similar rows
together, right?
And so You also,
I think you use the word
variance, which is correct.
And in the left case,
we have high variance
in our label in both cases,
on the right, we
have low variance.
And variance is an
example of a broader,
what we might call an
impurity measure, right?
So we want everything kind
of homogeneous, the same.
The opposite of that is
an impure set of rows.
And so variance in
impurity measure,
if I'm be like a classification
where it's categorical,
maybe I have something like
an accuracy score,
something like that.
You can imagine lots
of different scores
to measure impurity.
But in general, right,
however we define it,
we want to group
together rows that are
very similar to
each other, right?
Within the leaves.
Alright. So how
would we actually use
this tree that we like?
Well, let's say
we have a new row
of data where the y
value is unknown.
So we'll feed it
through. We'll say is X
two greater than zero.
It sure is. And that one
will go to the right.
And then based on this tree,
what we can say is
that this new row
that we've never seen before,
it's most similar to
these two rows over here
on the right hand side.
And so we can use that
to make a prediction.
Maybe we'll just say, well, it's
similar to these other rows,
and these other rows had
an average y value of 8.7.
Let's predict 8.7 for
the new row, right?
So if we bring together
kind of similar rows and
we can place new rows
relative to the old ones,
then we have a way of
making predictions, right?
We're like, Oh, this
looks familiar.
I've seen this before.
Do we have any questions
about that general
general approach kind of, like,
how we would predict what a
decision tree or why we want,
you know, a tree to
look a specific way.
Right. Cool. So let's
talk about how we
can train a decision tree if
we have a small data set.
It all fits in memory, okay?
So the way it works is
that we will start with the
simplest possible tree,
which is just one node
with all of the rows of
data assigned to it.
If it's just one
node, it doesn't
even have a question
associated with it.
If I tried to predict
with that tree,
I guess what I
would do is I would
just take the average
of all the y values,
and it would always be
my prediction, right?
And so we're going to start
with that. But what we do
is where I keep asking
questions that will
split a leaf node into two
more new leaf nodes, right?
We I recursively keep
splitting until we
have a decent tree.
So what I might do on
the left hand side,
I have that node A.
There's no questions.
In this case, I'm trying to
predict whether it'll rain.
And I have a temperature,
humidity and rain.
I could just, you
know, stop there,
and I could say, I
always say there's
a 25% chance of rain.
Okay? No super interesting.
Or I could spit
and, I could say,
is the humidity greater
than or equal to 40?
And if it is, then I can say,
well, there's a 50%
chance of rain.
Otherwise, there's no
chance of rain, right?
So I could do that. And I
could recursively go further.
After I asked about humidity,
maybe SA is the temperature
greater than 80.
And I've really had it
broken down, right?
So depending on what I asked,
I'll either say, well,
there's a 100% chance of
rain if I end up in OD or a
0% chance of rain if I
end up anywhere
anywhere else, right?
So we're gonna keep
splitting to try
to separate out the data.
Yeah, question right here.
Yeah, we want to
find split points
that reduce the variance, right?
Because whenever
I have a new row,
I'm going to feed it
through the decision tree
and I'm going to find
a bunch of other rows,
where I as as are
the same about it.
And so based on
those other rows,
I'm going to kind of assume
my new row is similar to them.
And so my hope is that
this previous group of
rows were very similar.
They're all yes,
or they're all no,
or they're all the same
number. Yeah, cut on.
How do you Oh, sure.
We'll talk about how we find
a specific split point.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah you're thinking
about it the right way,
but just a little
bit ahead of me.
Yeah, Ts over here?
How do you know you're making
the right split split something
completely arbitrary.
God. Yeah. So you could
split something arbitrary and
you might have a bad split,
or you could split on other
things that have good split.
So we have a notion of whether
or not a tree is good, right?
And we can define that.
And so then based on
that, we can try to say,
well, does the split make
the tree better, right?
So first, you know, you just try
to say, is the tree good?
Then you can use that to
kind of back up and
make decisions.
So everybody's kind of
talking about good things,
and we're going to get there.
So one question is, like,
when do we actually
stop splitting?
There's different approaches.
Maybe people set the
maximum tree height,
like you'll do on P five.
You might say that
if I'm splitting,
I only want to do
it if there's like
a large number of rows.
In some sense,
right, if I get down
here to no D, and I'm like, Yes,
there's 100% chance
of rain based
on this one time it
rained before, right?
Like, that's not great, right?
You want to have a kind of
more rows in each case, right?
So you might set a minimum.
Other times what people
do is, build a big tree,
and then after the fact,
they might prune it to
make the tree better.
Lots of different
appaches. We won't
worry about too much about that.
Some people were using the word
overfitting when we were
talking about that.
And let me explain
overfitting in this context.
I have two different trees.
I mean, they're
both pretty simple,
right? There's not
a lot of data here.
But the one on top is simpler
than the one on
the bottom, right?
And so I want to imagine if
I'm feeding this row in.
I say, temperature is
65 and humidity is 42.
If I fed that through the top,
then I'd end up over
here and I'll say, well,
there's a 50% chance of
rain based on these
two previous rows.
If I feeding the bottom one,
I'll end up over here
and I'll say, well,
there's 100% chance of rain.
That second prediction is not
necessarily better, right?
Because what that second
tree really did is
that it learned the exact
patterns of the past,
but it's overfitting,
perhaps, right?
It's trying to say, Well,
it can't see that maybe I
should be less confident
because there's a whole group
of scenarios that
are kind of similar,
but it might have
different outcomes, right?
So the second tree is
probably overfitted.
Honestly, they're both
probably overfitted,
but I don't want to have
too much information
on one slide, right?
Do we want any questions
about overfitting?
And overfitting is when you you
memorize exactly what
happened before.
But because you're just
so focused on memorizing,
you don't actually
see the patterns.
Alright. So let's talk
about how we actually
choose splits.
And I May 1 just
think about, well,
how many different
splits could be done.
A split is going
to be a question.
And the question is going
to be in the form of
this column relative to
this threshold is X
greater than five, right?
And when we have
new data coming in,
we don't have y values.
We don't have labels, right?
And so we can never ask a
question about the label.
We can only ask questions
about features.
So when I'm looking at this data
here, there are two features.
There's temperature
and humidity,
and I could ask a question
about either of those.
Now, there's four rows. And
any question I should ask
can somehow separate the
rows into subgroups, right?
And so it wouldn't
make sense to have a
question where it's like,
Well, there's four rows,
and answer is always
yes or always, no.
I'm trying to have
ways to split them up.
And so if there's four rows,
there's three ways to split.
And so if two features,
three ways to split
for each of them,
there's six different ways
I could split this data.
And what we're
going to do is were
act to try all of them.
And we talked about this
notion of impurity,
which we can measure,
whatever that is.
We're going to measure
it for all sex,
and we're going
to choose the one
that reduces impurity the most.
In other words, we're going
to choose a split that brings
related data together in
the same place in the tree.
All right? And so
how do we do this?
You can imagine like a brute
force thing where it does
every possibility and does
a lot of expensive
calculation for each one,
but there's a faster
way to do it,
and that way will involve
sorting the data.
So what we'll do is we will
sort the data by temperature,
and then we're going
a loop over every
possible split point.
So you know, I could split
after the first row or
I could split after the second
row, so on and so forth.
And notice, actually that
I've switched my example.
Before I was doing
regression examples,
now I'm trying to predict
a category, right?
Is trying to rain or. It won't.
And so instead of variance,
we are going to have some
more complicated statistics,
which I won't worry
too much about,
but I want to think about
what kind of things
do we have to
measure to have some
kind of impurity metric.
Okay? And so what we're going to
do is for any given split,
I can say, Well, how many rows
go left and how many go right?
And the ones that left,
how many are yes and no?
And for the ones that right,
how many are yes and no.
I I have those four numbers,
I could imagine coming up with
some kind of metric
that will tell me
whether I'm doing a
good job separating
the yeses from the nose, right?
I won't worry about the metrics,
I just want to
imagine that would be
something that you could
readily do, right? So,
Each split, I'm going to
compute those four numbers.
And then on that, there
will be some kind of
impurity metric that we
won't worry too much about.
And what's cool about this is
that as I'm doing over these
different split points,
as I keep going down, I'm moving
one row from the left hand
side to the right hand side.
And I know whether
that was a yes or no.
And so as I do this row here,
I can calculate that as
a change relative to
the previous row.
So even though I'm doing
every possible thing,
I just make one pass
over the data, right?
So the real expense
here is that I
have to sort a bunch of times,
however many features I have.
But once I've done that,
I just make one
pass over the data,
and I can tell you what
the exact best split
is over that column, right?
So I'll get the
three best split,
or I'll get the three split
scores for the first column.
I'll get the three
for the second one.
Now I have six scores.
I choose the best
one, and I say,
Okay, I will split
my tree on that.
All right. Any questions about
that notion of splitting and
how we find the best one?
Right. Cool. Okay, so
the challenge now,
that's the basic algorithm.
And again, I just
want to make sure,
does anybody have any questions
about the basic algorithm
before we talk about the
distributed algorithm?
All right. So our
challenge, right,
is that this data
that we're training
on might not fit in
RAM on one machine.
It might not even fit in RAM on
all the machines
together, right?
It's partitional across all
these different spark workers.
Sorting, it would be
expensive, right?
Because if I sort,
then I'd have to
shuffle the entire data
set over the network.
And in fact, I'd have
to do that many times.
I'd have to do it for
every single feature.
And what does that get me?
I get to split one node, right?
So if I have a decision
tree with lots of nodes,
like even the one we saw in
the lecture demo,
that's terrible, right?
Because I have to repeatedly
shuffle this giant dataset over
the network to just add
two more nodes, right?
So that's not good.
The other thing is is
that if I'm trying
to consider every
possible split point,
that split point
is going to be on
one out of many
partitions of the data.
And so I'm not going to be
able to do this in parallel.
I'm going to have to be looping
with respect to
this split point,
and it should be on
one note at a time.
Right? So lots of things
are challenging here.
I cannot just directly
take that algorithm
we saw and apply it
in this situation.
And that leads us to
the planet algorithm,
which was published by Google.
And so they had
the same problem.
They wanted to trade
these bid decision trees,
and they were doing
it on map reduce,
but the algorithm has also been
implemented in SPA, right?
And that's why
we're learning it.
Okay. And so they use it for
both the decision
tree regressor and
the decision tree classifier.
And there's lots of details
here that we're going into.
But one of the really
important details
is that it's a hybrid algorithm.
They handle big data and small
data in a different way.
And so they're going to
have one approach
where the data is big,
and they're going to
really focus there on
not sending data
over the network.
But eventually, as you
have this big tree,
even if it's large,
you're going to keep
splitting nodes down,
and the leaf nodes of
a big tree might not
actually have a lot of data.
And so eventually
once we get down
to a leaf node that doesn't
have a lot of data,
we will collect all
the data in memory,
and we will run the algorithm we
already learned in
memory. All right.
So I mentioned that
it's going to be a
lot harder now to consider
every possible split point.
And so we're going to
consider fewer split points.
And the way we're
going to do that is
a pre processing step.
We are going to compute
some histograms
over every feature, right?
And so when you do this, right?
For a histogram, you have to
say how many bends
or buckets you have.
And so when you
create a decision
tree classifier regress
or you can do that,
you can say set the
maximum number of bends.
And then it will using that,
get that histogram
for each of them.
Okay? Now, there's
a couple of interesting
things about it.
One is that the histogram it's
doing is what we call an
equi depth histogram,
and that means that each
of these buckets has
the same number of values in
it approximately,
right? That's the goal.
Kind of a normal
histogram, right?
Each of the buckets would be
the same width on the x axis.
That's what what we're
trying to do here,
because that will
not help us find split points.
We kind of want nice
even split points that
break up our data.
So we'll do that.
One of the things we
have to be aware of is
that when you set
that Mac spins,
that applies for the histogram,
but there might also
be some columns
that are categorical, right?
If it's like apple,
banana carrot,
Then instead of having
threshold questions like
x greater than five,
you'll say x equal to apple
or x equal to banana.
And however many
categories there are.
Those are the number of bends.
And so this sets a cap on that.
So a common issue people
run into is they
set it too small.
They have more categories.
The algorithm can't run
it. Now you know why.
Okay, so we get these
histograms. How do we use it?
Well, for the simple
in memory thing,
we could do a split point
on every possible position.
For the histogram approach,
we're just going to
consider between each of
these buckets as
possible split point.
So we're going to cite
all this up front,
every worker involved
in the algorithm.
We from the beginning know what
all the possible split points
are so that they can
work independently.
Yeah, s right here.
Each bucket has explicitly one
each coach let me put it
for the other way, right?
So for each column,
we compute a histogram that has,
I guess, in this case,
four buckets for it.
Was that the same as
what you're saying,
or Okay, a, great.
Yeah, thank you for clarifying.
The other other questions
people have. Right. Cool.
So, let's take a look
at our decision tree,
right? So here I have it.
And I'm going to start
with decision tree that's
half trained and then see,
how we can finish training it.
And so at this point in time,
some of these nodes will have
many rows associated with them,
and some will actually
have relatively few.
What I'm saying few, what I'm
implying there is that
they could all fit
in memory at the
same time, right?
Now, what I'm showing here is
a logical view of
the data, right?
If you tell me, like, Hey,
this is a decision tree,
which is partially done,
and you say, Hey, here's a row.
I can tell you, a, well,
this is the node of the tree
that the row belongs to.
That does not mean that
all the rows belonging to
a node of the tree
are brought together
in the same place.
That's what we're going
to very explicitly try to
avoid is that involves a
bunch of network transfers.
So I can say logically this
row is part of this node,
but all the rows for a
node could be like all
over the place across
different machines, okay?
So that's the tree that
we're working with.
So where is the data
actually physically?
It's in spark partitions,
right? In no particular order.
I'm going to imagine
that, you know,
here's a spark partition
on the first machine.
Down at the bottom,
I have two spark partitions
on another machine.
And if I want to, I could
do some computation,
I could tell you what node
they each belonged to,
but I wouldn't have to
move them to do that.
All right. So I've labeled it
here what node they
each belong to.
And so now we have two
approaches, right?
Sometimes I might be
dealing with say,
nod and nod H.
And those are small. They
don't have a lot of data.
And so that point what I'm
going to do is I you know,
let's just do the
classic algorithm.
Let's bring together all
the rows in the same place.
And we can do that with
hash partitioning.
It's like a group,
right Group BI
brings together related rows.
Here we're going
to bring together
related rows, and
we're going to do it.
The key that we're
grouping on is
what node you are in this
tree, which we can infer.
So we'll do that. So we
get all the nodes for F,
all the nodes for H. And then
we're just going to recursively
run the end memory algorithm,
and we'll finish the tree.
So that's at. Sometimes I'll
run that kind of spart job.
Other times, it's
going to run a kind
of spart job that works
for the Big Data,
which is what we'll
talk about next time.
So have a fantastic day,
and I'll see you on Friday.