Fantastic. Yeah. So somebody
came out and fixed.
Actually, it's funny like
everything is a
computer these days,
and they just had to reboot it,
and that fixed the problem.
So more and more
things like that.
So today, a couple of
announcements about
logistical stuff.
One is that there's
a quiz due tonight.
How many people have
done the quiz so far?
Maybe a third of you. So if
you haven't done the quiz,
go do the quiz tonight.
Most Wednesdays, there
will be a quiz due.
It will tell you
what it'll cover.
So this quiz is
covering Week one.
So anything from Week
one is fair game.
And that's generally
true, right?
Le As soon as a
Friday lecture ends,
it would be pretty reasonable
to go take a quiz or do it
over the weekend or do it
anytime before that
next Wednesday.
So go and take that. Um You
know, there's no time limit.
It's five multiple
choice questions.
Hole place of pressure.
I'm just to try to have
some incentive that
people kind of keep
up with the material
and study as you go
instead of waiting
for the bigger exams.
You're allowed to
collaborate with
it with friends on
it if you want.
You can get together and discuss
and do the questions together.
The only thing I ask
is that that you're
actually actively doing
it with somebody and
talking about it because I
think you will learn that way.
What I don't want
and what is not
allowed is for like
one person to do the
quiz and just say,
Oh, here are the answers,
now you go fill it in.
As long as you're
sitting and talking
about it together, you
can do it together.
And hopefully, it's a nice time
to meet people and work
together on things.
We also have Project one,
which is officially
released today.
I actually released
it last week.
Today is the official release
date because after today,
you'll actually know enough to
basically do the whole project,
maybe, not the last tiny
bit if we run behind,
but you can go do the
project, Now, basically.
I'm going to come over
here and try to make sure
everybody is aware of
the policies, right?
So, in general, I'll link to
the general project directions.
You all should read this
carefully to make sure that you
don't get in trouble with
any rules around
academic misconduct,
know how you can work
with other people,
know what is allowed with
respect to Chat GPT and
other stuff like that.
Trying to read that carefully
and don't get into trouble.
There's a late policy down here
and now is a good time
to talk about that.
I think unexpected
stuff always happens.
We should expect
unexpected things,
like getting sick or getting
busy or things like that.
Basically, if I see
that you're making an effort
to kind of start early,
then there's some
flexibility there.
So the rule is that normally,
if it's one day late,
you lose 10%, two days late,
you lose 20%, we'll accept
it at most three days late.
If, however, you start three
days before the deadline,
and you've made
significant progress,
and the low bar for
significant progress is low.
If you've done
that, then you can
request that that late
penalty is waived,
and then you can submit up to
three days after the deadline.
This is, cover if you get
sick or something like that.
Sometimes people ask like, well,
if I get sick, like,
will you override
the sick policy?
I'm like, Well, no, that
that is a sick policy.
If you were extremely sick,
like if you were like
hospitalized for a week
or something like
that, then yeah,
we'll figure out something
kind of specific
to your situation,
but, you know,
if you have a cold or a flu
or something like that,
then this is the late policy.
What I'd really encourage
you do is get started,
at least do a little bit
of the project early?
Don't do it in the
last three days
because then if something
unexpected happens,
well, you won't have
any kind of buffer.
Another thing where
people kind of run
astray on this is that actually,
like pushing the code to get
lab is part of the project.
Sometimes, that's where
people run into trouble,
and then they try to send you
like e mails or screenshot.
Know you actually
have to be pushing
the stuff three days before
the deadline to qualify.
So really what I
do is I tend to at
least start the
project pretty soon,
and just like as
soon as you have
anything just to push it,
and then you have a little bit
more breathing room at the end.
How many of you have already
started the project?
Fantastic. And today is
the day it's released.
So you're really a
head of the game.
So do you any questions about,
either the quiz policies
or this late policy
I've just described?
All right. Fantastic. So
what else do I have here?
Let me head back
to the schedule.
U We've talked a lot
about shell stuff.
Now we're going to be
talking about Docker.
Docker kind of like
other stuff it's
just a lot of
things to memorize.
So I have this worksheet,
which is, again, notes.
You know, at the end
of this, you just have
to memorize all these things.
Otherwise, you know, you
spend more time in the class.
If you have to Google
it all the time,
just spend some
time, memorize it.
These Anki flash tart decks
will help you with that.
Alright, fantastic,
emery hadad over here.
And today, we're going to
be learning about Docker,
which is maybe one
of my favorite
systems of this semester.
This little whale over
here is the Docker logo,
and it has a bunch of
containers on its back.
And so we're going
to be learning
about something
called containers.
Today. How can we deploy code
inside of a Docker container?
And so I have a few learning
objectives for you.
With containers, they're
created from images.
And so I want you
to be able to take
a Docker image and launch
a container from it.
I want you to be able to define
a new docker image given
something called a Docker file,
you're going to get a
lot of experience this
semester writing Docker files.
And then, you know,
there's all kinds of
things that you might
troubleshoot that might go wrong,
and some might give you
some troubleshooting tips
today. All right.
Before we get into the details,
I want to talk about this
word virtualization,
which you've heard a couple
of times in this course,
and you've probably
heard in other courses,
and it can mean lots
of different things.
When something is virtual,
there's some kind of illusion.
There's not something
real, there's kind of
maybe software is
providing some illusion.
And usually that
illusion is that you
have some kind of private
resources, right?
You don't actually have
those resources yourself.
Maybe they're shared or
something like that.
But you have the
illusion, you can kind of
pretend like you own it.
And so even in just
this semester,
there's four different
ways, we're gonna use this,
we're gonna use it for
hardware virtual machines,
we're going to use it for
language virtual machines.
Today we're going to be learning
about virtual operating systems.
And then in a later
lecture, I'm going to
talk about virtual memory.
Okay, so let's start with
hardware virtual machines.
You could do this
yourself, or in this case,
we're renting from a
cloud provider, Google.
And so what Google
does is they'll buy
a bunch of physical machines
in a data center like this.
This one has 16 gigabytes
of ram and eight tours.
Probably their machines
have much more than that.
And they can put
virtual machines on it,
and then we rent those, right?
Does anybody notice
anything interesting
about the numbers I
put in this example?
Yeah, right here. Of that.
Yeah, it sums up to more
than the actual space.
We might say is they're
overbooking these machines or
overcommitting resources
on these machines.
And this happens in
other industries, too.
It happens with airlines,
for example, with an airplane,
there's a couple hundred seats,
they can say probabilistically,
probably some people
will not show
up or they'll miss their flight.
And so they always, they'll
often sell a couple more
seats and there actually are.
And the vast majority of
the time that works
out out fine.
Now, most people who pay for
a ticket actually
show up In contrast,
most people who are
running a virtual machine
are not using it very heavily.
So, for example, right now,
all of you who have started P
one have a virtual machine,
and it is not using
any CPU right now,
and it's not using nearly
the memory available.
So cloud providers
can actually play
this game a lot more
aggressively than say,
like an airline cud,
and they do that.
And so one of the
implications is that
The actual performance you
get might depend a bit
on what other people are doing
on the same physical machine.
Sometimes that shows up
in weird ways, like,
maybe I do an example and I time
something and you might
do the same example,
and you might get different
timings than I do.
Right? Not all
virtual machines of
the same size are going to
give the same performance,
and it can vary
over time, right?
All right. Let's talk about
operating systems, right?
So for each of these
virtual machines,
I can install a different
operating system.
Maybe I have a couple of
different flavors of Linux,
like ubuntu and Debian.
Maybe I have a windows server.
That's pretty powerful, right?
Maybe if I have an application
that's only built for windows,
I can now run that here
instead of having to have
different physical machines,
that's very efficient.
You know, it's also a
little bit wasteful because
if I have a bunch of
different applications
and they each need their
own operating system,
then I have all that
overhead of having
many different operating
systems, using resources.
Okay, That's hardware
virtual machines.
Let's talk about language
A language virtual machine,
an example that would
be like the JVM,
the Java virtual machine or
the Python virtual machine.
Um In this case,
you do have some kind
of illusion that
you have private resources,
but that's not the main point.
The main point is that we
can have this machine that's
basically just defined in
software that can have
different instructions than
real hardware might have, right?
So when I compile Java,
I get Java byte code,
and that Bite Codes
not run directly on
any machine that anybody
has ever made, right?
It can run on a machine
that's defined by
software, right?
So maybe I have some
programs that are running
on top of the JVM,
some on the PVM.
And then I have some that
are actually written
for X 86 64 instructions,
which might be what
the actual CPU has,
right, and that might run
directly on top of that.
Right? So we have virtual
machines for hardware,
virtual machines for language.
Let's talk about virtual
operating systems.
We have a virtual
operating system
that we have this illusion
that we are the only person,
we as an application
are the only person
using the operating system.
It's not a term that
people use very often.
More often people would
call that a container.
That's the term I'm
going to start using,
but a container is basically
a virtual operating system.
So you can see
here, for example,
On top of my physical machine,
I have some flavor
of Linux running.
And then I have a bunch of
containers on top of it,
and those are actually
different flavors of Linux.
There's a part of the operating
system called the Kernel,
and these are actually
all sharing it.
In reality, we're sharing
the kernel between
these different things,
but we have the illusion that
we're the only one using
the operating system,
and then we can have different
flavors of Linux, right?
This is much more efficient
than having virtual
machines, right?
If I have virtual
operating systems,
and I don't actually really have
a lot of different
operating systems
running at the same time.
If I have virtual machines,
then I actually do have a lot of
different operating
systems running,
and that takes up more space.
It does mean that
it's less flexible.
Since kind of under the hood,
it is really just one kernel.
That means that I
can have a lot of
different flavors of
Linux, but I could not,
for example, have like
a windows container
running on top of Linux.
That's not possible, right?
So, all this container stuff,
it's really a
collection of features
that have been built into Linux,
and then where Docker came
along is that they
made it really
easy to configure all of
these different features.
Before that, you could
still kind of put
together containers
in your own way,
but it would be you'd have to be
quite the expert to pull it off.
Docker has made that easy,
and so we're going to be
learning Docker today.
Yeah, question right over here.
Yeah, if we have
virtual machines,
why would we want
to have containers?
Do anybody think of an advantage
of having containers
instead of having
a virtual machine?
Yeah, right here.
Yeah, I could have
the same results,
but there would be less
resources used, right?
So if I have ten containers,
then I really only have
one operating system
and that maybe that
uses up like 200 megabytes
of ram, perhaps.
Whereas if I had
ten different VMs,
they each have their
own operating system,
each of which might be using
200 megabytes of ram and
be like 2 gigabytes
of RAM total, right?
So whenever we share,
we get more efficiency.
Yeah, follow up here. T.
Yeah, there's a couple of
advantages to virtual machines.
One is that we have
more flexibility.
I could run like a
Windows VM on top of it.
It's also g I want to get
like deep in security.
It's arguably more
secure than a container.
So those would be the
main advantage of VMs.
Yeah, right here. Are there
technique similar to
Docker on windows?
I haven't been following
that space closely,
but I have to assume that
they're doing stuff like that.
Sometimes they'll
have, I know on Mac,
they have a docker for Mac,
and what that's actually
doing is it's spinning up
a Linux virtual machine and
then the running the
container inside of that.
So oftentimes they will
make it look like dockers
running on top of other things.
I'm sure Microsoft is
looking at different
isolation technologies.
And we can talk more about that
offline too. I don't
want to get too far up.
I mean, I worked at
Microsoft for a while,
so I can maybe give a little bit
more of an in depth answer,
but, I mean, they're
doing things too.
Yeah, other questions
people have?
Yeah, over here. Well, we
talk about the difference
between Debi and ubuntu?
No, not really. I mean,
ubuntu is based off of Debi.
A lot of things are
kind of similar.
I don't know, they install
different software on top of it,
maybe you install packages
slightly differently,
but I mean, I don't know.
I even thought about switching
to Debi in this semester,
but it felt like it didn't
make that much difference.
Yeah. Other questions
people have?
Oh, right. After today,
it'd be very easy
for you to try both.
Like in 1 minute,
you could be using
Debi and the next
year using ubuntu,
you can try and see if
you feel a difference.
So some of these
virtualization ideas
are examples of sandboxes
and some are not, right?
If I have a language
virtual machine,
it doesn't necessarily protect
different applications
from each other
because they can touch
the same files, for example.
And then other things
like containers and
virtual machines are what
I would call sandboxes.
They're kind of providing
some separation
and protection from each other.
You can kind of
almost look at this
like a child playing
in a sandbox.
That's a safe place to
play without kind of
doing damage outside
of the sandbox.
It's okay to be messy and
when you're inside of a sandbox.
So here I have an example of
a computer with a bunch of
different sandboxes in it,
maybe they're virtual machines,
maybe they're containers.
I have
the different software
versions and different ones.
That's one advantage. It's not
just about the operating system,
but what packages we have.
I have some processes
that might be
running outside of any sandbox.
Then you see up here,
I actually have
a couple of malicious
containers.
So one over here on the left
is running a Python program.
And I'm wondering if
anybody can just pop
up a hand and tell me what is
this malicious program
trying to do to
me. Yeah, go ahead.
Yeah, trying to remove
everything in the
root fold, right?
So the RM is removed.
That slash is the root.
Recursive means don't
just do the top,
but kind of go down and
find everything you can.
And then force means even with
some permissions
where you might not
otherwise deleted it,
it will do it, right?
So this would really kind
of wipe out everything.
How bad is that? Well, if it
does inside of the sandbox,
I guess that sandbox is
going to be messed up,
but at least my host computer
will be fine, right?
So I'd be kind of a
safer way to run,
something like that
maybe to run code
that I don't fully trust.
Alright. And the way we're
going to be using sandboxes
or containers this semester
is that we're going to
have a virtual machine,
and we'll have a few
different containers on it,
and that will really look
like a small cluster.
You're going to be
familiar with that.
And then if we're good at
that, then we could later,
you know, if you are
on a job somewhere,
you could have a similar set
up instead of containers,
you might actually have
real physical machines.
All the same techniques
are going to apply.
It'll just be much faster.
Of course, if you have more real
physical resources
thrown at your problem.
Alright, cool. So let's look at
some high level ideas related
to Docker before we jump
into some examples.
The first thing you have to do
is you have to go
install Docker,
and that's actually
part of the project.
It's kind of actually
a few steps,
maybe a little bit annoying,
but just do that, right?
That would be like a nice
thing to do today and
then kind of post that
significant start
if you just row
through these steps.
So follow through
those directions
and get that installed,
let us know if you
have any trouble.
Afterwards, can you
can start using it.
And using it might
look like this.
I have a computer, my
virtual machine over here,
and on my computer,
I have these things
called Docker images.
In this case, I have
a Ubuntu image.
And where do I get these things?
One place I could get them is
from Docker Registry, right?
Over here, I have
different registries.
Maybe you're at a company
and they have a registry
of different Docker
images you can use.
The famous public one is
called the Docker Hub.
And so there are a bunch of
different images over there with
different software
installed on them.
And if I do a Docker pull
command like this down here,
I'll basically pull down
that image to my machine.
And When I have an image,
I can almost use
it like a template
to create different containers.
I think you all know
object or programming.
And so maybe the analogy
I'll make is that
a Docker image is
like a class, right?
I have one class and
I can create a lot of
objects from it
when I instantiate.
If I have a Docker image,
I can create a lot of
different containers
from that image. Let's do that.
There's a Docker run command.
If I say Docker, run in
the name of an image,
I might run that a
few times and I get
a few containers from
that image. All right.
Now, sometimes there might
be an image that does
exactly what I want.
A lot of times, though,
you're going to need
to have an image
that has specific
software installed,
and maybe that's not available.
You go to figure out how to
build that image yourself.
And particularly if you're
writing your own software,
you want it to be
in a docker image,
then of course, you're going to
have to build it yourself.
And that will be
kind of the form of,
most of the projects
this semester,
you're going to have
some docker images
that you define yourself,
and you'll kind of hand in
a description of how we
can build those images.
Here's where the analogy
breaks down a little bit
between classes and
objects, right?
I guess, in obit programming,
you don't really take an
object and turn into a class,
but that's what we will do
when we make a new image.
We'll take a container that
has the stuff installed
that we want to use,
and we can convert it
back into an image.
So the way this will work is
we can say, Docker build,
and then I say some
kind of directory,
and then I say T,
and I say the name of the
image I want to build.
So this my image,
directory will contain a file
called Docker file.
That's the name of it.
And that Docker file defines
all the steps you
have to do one by
one to create the image
you want to create.
And so if I run this
Docker build command,
what will happen is it first,
it's starting from ubuntu.
I can see that first
line from Ubuntu.
I'll create a container
from the ubuntu image,
and it'll start running
all these install steps
in or whatever else
I want to do in it.
And when it's all done,
it'll basically create
a snapshot of that container.
And it will give
it the name Pandas
because I said T for tag.
I'm going tag it as Pandas.
And so Ubuntu, I pulled
from the Docker hub,
Pandas I built myself.
Mostly when you're building
something yourself,
you're starting from
something a little
bit more generic, right?
And then once I have that, then
I can start new containers.
And when I start
those new containers,
then it will already
have Pandas installed.
And that's more
efficient, right?
Like I I start a bunch
of different containers,
I only had to
install Pandas once,
but they all have Pandas
available to them.
Any questions about that kind of
general setup? Yeah, right here.
I. So build creates
the container.
And what was the
other thing you said?
Yes. Oh, yeah.
Okay, there's two commands
that create a container.
If I do Docker run, I get
a container just for me to
start using for something.
If I do docker build,
that will also
create a container,
but it will automatically
bun a bunch of
install stuffs in it,
and then it'll snapshot it
back and then it'll
kill the container.
So Docker Run is
the primary way you're going
to creating containers,
but Docker build just as
kind of a side
effect we'll have to
do create a container as
well. That makes sense?
Yeah, I saw another
question over here.
Institution Yeah, the question
is, does the Docer file?
Is it just installations
or copy other stuff.
I could be whatever you want.
Anything you can
run on the shell,
you could put in there.
So I guess you have to say
like maybe data or whatever.
You can put whatever you
want in there, right?
And this is actually
kind of nice because
we're unambiguously
decide describe
how to get a specific setup.
Maybe there's even
data with that.
Especially if we're
like a scientist and
somebody else to reproduce
our analysis with
specific data and specific code
and specific versions
of packages.
This is a way for us
to unambiguously say,
this is how you get
the same environment.
I. Right? If you're a scientist,
you want to have
reproducible work.
This is kind of very broadly
useful to data scientists.
Yeah, other are
questions people have.
All right. Cool. So
we're a head over.
We're going to do a top
hat and then some demos.
So whip out your phone.
And excuse me. All right.
So what I'm asking
about is if I do Docker
pull X. I'm just wondering
what X is. Is it a container?
Is it an image? Is it a
registry? What is it?
Alright, Fantastic. So most
people are saying an image,
which is correct, do Docker
pull by DFL thatt, look
at the Docker hub.
I pulled on that image.
If I wanted a container,
then after that, then
maybe I might go run it.
Alright, cool. Let's
jump in. Yeah.
Crush here. Where's it?
It pulls it from registry.
Maybe that registry
is Docker hub,
Maybe it's like a private
corporate registry.
Alright. C. Let's jump in.
Let's get some Docker
commands going.
I'm going to SSH N. Great.
And Great.
I'll just try to clean
this up a little bit.
Here I am, Fresh environment.
If you already install Docker,
you can just run Docker,
and that's actually
kind of great because
it'll just show you a
bunch of documentation.
And so if I stroll up a bit,
then there's a bunch
of commands here,
which should all be in
your notes, by the way.
Take notes on these
and remember these.
We can say we can
run containers,
we can build containers, we can
pull containers, so
on and so forth.
I'm going to be showing
examples of those in a
whole bunch more as well.
So if I want to
do a pull, right,
I could say Docker pull,
and if I want to learn
more about that,
I might say dash hell.
It's actually telling
me that right here.
That I can read more
about these with Health.
And so I can see I
do Docker, pull.
And a lot of this
documentation stuff if
it's in square brackets,
as it means it's optional.
So maybe I put something
there, maybe not.
I see the name. I have to
have the name of the image.
And then up here,
I have to specify, I can
specify a tag if I want to.
We are these tags coming from?
Let me just head back here
to the slides momentarily.
And we can see, let's take
a look at a real registry,
which is the Docker hub,
here is the Docker hub, has
a whole bunch of
images I can download.
Like, MMC D is
the most popular engine ax for
some HDP hosting,
busybox Alpine.
Here's ubuntu. Let me
take a look at Ubuntu.
I see that Ubuntu has a bunch of
different tags because there
are different versions
of ubuntu, right?
So, for example, over here,
if I do CT ETC OS release.
I am on Ubuntu 244.
That is the most recent
long term support version.
It's the most recent thing
that's pretty stable.
If I look over on
the Docker hub,
I can see that they
have 2410, right?
So these are actually
based on dates, right?
So this is the October release.
I guess it's not even October
yet, but it's out there.
And it's not going to be a
stable or long term supported,
but it's the most recent thing.
Maybe I might want
that in my container.
So we're going to
see how we can use
2410 and just get a container
that is running that.
All right. So what
I can do is I can
say, Docker pull Ubuntu.
And I'll say 22,
I'm sorry, 2410.
And I'm going to pull that down,
and that was trying to fast.
And then if I want to see
what I have available,
I can say, Dor images, right?
I can see all the
different images.
I should have kind of
clean this up before.
But I can see, sure enough,
here is Ubuntu, and
it's 2410, right?
And there's some
kind of image ID
associated with it, right?
So then I could grow and I
could run that if I want to.
If I want to, I can give
these things different names.
So I can do something like
I could say Docker tag,
and I could say old
name and new name.
And when I do this, then it
will have two names, right?
So I could say Ubuntu 2410,
and I could say, I could
say my Ubuntu, right?
And then if I say Docker
image images after that.
So images should
be in your list.
I see here is my Ubuntu.
Here was the one I pulled down.
Even though I had they have
different tags on them,
they have the same image ID.
So we have differ
name the same thing.
I want to know what is actually
different or the same.
I'm going to look
at that image ID
instead of the
actual name of it.
Alright, let's try
running this thing.
I could do Docker Run ubuntu,
24.10, or if I just
do it like this,
then it will look for
the latest version.
And I think I actually have
a latest version up here.
But that's another reason
we might tag things.
I might tag it as
ubuntu latest, right?
I might indicate, what
is the latest ubuntu
that I actually
want to go and run?
And then if I can just say
Docker Run Ubuntu,
and nothing happens.
Well, nothing happens
that I can see.
I created a container. It
looked for some input.
There was none, I
exited again, right?
So what if I want
to run something
inside of that container,
I can put a command over here.
Any kind of shell command
is fair name here,
so I could do echo hello,
and then it will
run hello inside
of a container, the
container exits.
The main thing to see
right now is that this is,
like, super fast compared to
creating a virtual machine.
It's impressive, both in
terms of pulling it
and running things.
All right, what if I want to
do something more interesting?
What if I want to
do like a doc or
run, and I want a shell.
So then Bash is the name
of a shell. I do that.
That starts a container,
starts running bash,
the bash says,
there's nothing from
standard input.
I'm going to exit right away.
What I might want to do is
I might want to say IT.
I want to have an interactive
terminal so I can
start typing to bash. I do that.
And now I am inside
of a container,
and I have a shell
environment there.
And this is pretty cool.
Be if I like, look at
my home directory,
my home directory is
root, look over here.
IM root. When you're in a
container, you're always root.
There's no more pseudo when
you're inside of a container.
You can do whatever you want.
That's your sandbox
to play around with,
have fun and just be free,
right? I can do that.
If I look at ETC, OS release.
I can see that even
though the Ubuntu,
I'm going to call
that the host, right?
That's outside of the container.
On the host, I'm 24 oh
four, inside I'm 2410.
Okay, I'm going to do
something kind of crazy.
Okay, if you're following along,
make sure make sure you're
in the container.
Don't do it otherwise.
I am going to do remove
recursive force.
L et's delete everything,
right? I run that.
I'm trying to try to delete
everything it possibly can.
Alright. And now I'm
gonna run the LS command.
I remember if people
remember the LS command.
What is this t to show
up when I run LS?
Just shout it out. I
heard people say nothing.
It's even worse than that.
I deleted the LS command.
There's like, This is the most
worthless environment now.
Everything is completely broken.
There's nothing I can do here.
Thank goodness. It's
in a container.
Let's get out of
here. I'm going to
do Control D. I'm out.
LS works again. I'm
back to my host.
How many of you have ever felt
like that you can kind
of learn something
by playing around,
but you're afraid to play around
because you might
break something?
Has anybody ever felt that way?
I felt that way a lot.
Containers solve that problem.
You can get in a container,
you can mess around,
break things. That
doesn't matter.
You mess it up,
create a new one.
It's such a great learning
tool from that perspective.
All right, cool. Any questions
people have so far about
this very broken container or
the tools I've been running
so far? Yeah, right here.
Oh, that's a good question.
Is the container still there?
It's an exited state,
so it's still there,
and there's ways I
could rebuy it or kind
of poke around and it state
and then I'll show that.
But yeah, so it's
pretty much gone,
yeah, there's some other
cleanup that we'll look at.
Yeah, other questions
people have.
Yeah, right here.
Exit machine Yeah,
if you reboot your machine
or stuff like that,
it's still there.
Y. I another handle.
Oh, yeah, that's
a great question.
So when I did ubuntu
like that, how did
it know which one?
So if I look at the images,
I had tagged one of
these as the latest,
and so it does that
one by default.
And so that was
one of the reasons
I ran this command because
I wanted to spec maybe I
have a few different ubuntu.
I want to say which one
is like the latest one
that I would actually use.
And then if I do that, then
I don't have to specify.
So it looks for a
latest by default.
Yeah, lots of good questions.
Fantastic. Alright. Cool.
Let's run some other stuff.
I'm going to do docker run well,
actually, I've
already pulled this,
but I'm going to pull Alpine
3.15. And then
it's already here.
If I look at that, you actually
see a lot of different
docker images that
are based on Alpine because
when you're trying to
build a container image,
you're just trying to
do one thing well,
and you don't need
all the stuff you
get like in a full ubuntu.
So I can see that Alpine is like
a tenth the size of
a ubuntu, right?
So you'll see a lot of
things starting on that.
If I do a docker run, Alpine.
It's so stripped down that I
don't even have
bash inside of it.
I just have to have kind of,
like this just generic shell,
but I can do that, and there's
things I can run inside of here.
Another thing I want to show
you is that if I do this,
I don't already have 316
of Alpine on my machine,
but it'll actually
pull it for me,
which is fast because it's
small, then it'll run it.
So I can actually pull the
whole image and run it in,
you know, maybe just
like a second or two.
L et me it out of here. Let me
show you a common
issue people run into.
So I'm going to have a
typo, pretty obvious.
I'm going to have Alpine
typo. I run that.
And what it's trying
to do is since it can
pull automatically
it first sees like,
Oh, do I have it local,
and answer is no.
So then it goes to
the Docker hub,
and it says, Well, it's
not on Docker Hub.
And then it's wondering, Oh,
is this the name of some image
on your private
corporate network,
corporate registry?
And it says, maybe you have
to log into something.
So I've seen that
this error message
has thrown off a
lot of students.
When you get this,
it doesn't mean
you actually have to
log into anything.
It just means that that
image wasn't there.
So maybe you had a typo
or I think more often,
like in your projects,
you're supposed to, like,
build images for your homework,
and oftentimes people
just didn't, like,
build it, they forgot to
build it, and that's why.
So just know that all this
means is that it's missing,
it doesn't mean that
you have to log
into something. Alright, cool.
Let's Can somebody remind
me what does PS do?
Yeah, right here. It
lists all the processes.
Excellent. And so a lot of
the Docker commands are
kind of similar to
the shell commands.
So when I look at Docker,
they have all these
different subcommands.
One of them is Docker PS,
which lists all the
running processes,
and right now there are
no running processes.
If I do A, that means
I also want to see the
ones that have exited,
and I see wi there's actually
a bunch of them that
are not cleaned up,
these are all using space,
and I think that actually people
commonly run out of space on
their VMs during this course,
and Docker is a big reason
because all of these
are taking up space.
You have to go through and clean
that stuff up from now and then.
Yeah, right here. A means all.
So that means I don't want
just running containers,
but I want exited
containers, too, right?
So all the things I've done
so far have been kind of
accumulate all these
exited containers.
So one way we can delete this,
I can say, remove,
and I could grab I could grab,
for example, the
ID of it, right?
So I could grab
the container ID,
and I could remove that.
Another option is that
I could grab the name.
So the way they
give these things
names is they have a
list of famous people.
They have a list of adjectives.
They randomly pair them,
and they give it a name.
So it's maybe a little
bit more human friendly,
so I could remove
determined Wesco.
And I could go
through one by one,
and I might try to paste a
bunch of different IDs here.
But I want a faster
way to do that.
So what's a faster way?
Well, I can say Docer PS and A.
And what I might
do is I might say,
I want quiet output.
So Q means quiet.
And what I'd like to do
is I'd like to take this,
and I'd like to somehow feed it
into to RM to
remove all of them.
Now, if DocR RM was taking
input from standard input,
then I would use a pipe, right?
If that's how they built DCR RM,
I would like to
pipe this to that.
But DCR RM does not
take standard input.
What it takes instead
is arguments,
but there's still a
way to chain together
two shell commands so
that we can either
feed the output of one
program into standard N
or we can feed the output of
that first program
into arguments.
The way we feed into arguments
is we use back tech.
Let me say Ba tech B tech,
and I'm going to take
this command up here,
and I feed that in, and so
it'll run this command first.
I'll get all those IDs,
and then it'll
remove all of them.
And now when I do that
and I run PSA again.
I've kind of cleaned
everything up,
so you can drove through,
clean things up and
reclaim some space.
Oh, right, fantastic.
So other things you might do
is you might say Docker system.
There's a few different
commands under there.
You might remember DF
from before, right,
DF shows you how
much disk is used,
and I often run it
kind of like human
readable on the
current directory.
So this tells me I
have 24 gigabytes,
and I'm using like 4.7 of it.
Right? So again, right, a lot of
the Docker commands
mirror these.
So I can say Docker system, DF,
and I can see kind of
how much space I'm using for
images or things like that.
The other one I'll often
use is Docker system Pune.
And that will try to
just delete, like,
a lot of this extra stuff
as it's able to, right?
So the semester
you often kind of,
like, keep an eye
on your dis space,
you know, delete
some big data sets,
do Docker system, Prone
every once in a while.
Then you'll be fine, like,
whenever you're law on space.
All right. Cool. Any
questions people have so far?
Here. Maximum space Dera
So how can I
check the maximum space
docker has available?
So we don't have
space that's, like,
kind of segmented
off for Docker,
so it can use all the space
of my system for storage.
And so I just have
to keep an eye on it
and clean it up when I
basically run out of that.
So I might totally have
created a bunch of
stuff with Docker,
and then I'm separately
trying to download a file,
and I'll say no
space for the file.
Then I'll go look at Docker as
trying to the culprit,
even though it doesn't.
No while I was using Docker.
Do that make sense? Yeah,
other questions people have?
Yeah, right here. Yeah.
Yeah. So you're saying,
like, if we have
files inside of a container,
can they be on the
host computer?
If I kind of, like, exit
it, but I didn't delete it.
Yeah, there is a place they are,
which is a little bit hidden.
We'll eventually learn about
something called a volume mount,
which kind of is
for that scenario,
and then they'll be in a place
where you would expect it to be.
So we'll eventually have
lectures about storage,
and we'll see how to
do volume mounts.
Yep. Yeah, lots of
good questions today.
Fantastic. Okay, so
what I want to talk
now about is debugging things.
And kind of, like, we might
often have a bunch of
different containers running.
We have to check
up on them. And so
I want to show an
example of something
I might be running for
a long time, right?
So I'm may say a
Docer run Ubuntu.
And I actually want to put,
like, a few different
commands here,
but the trick is that I
can only run one command.
And so when I want to
run multiple things,
but I only have one
command, I'm like,
Ha ha, my one command
will be a shell.
And it will take an argument
which is a string with
multiple commands.
Right? So I can only
give it one command,
which is a shell,
but I can kind of sneak
multiple commands in.
And I'm I do this.
I'm going to echo before. I am
going to sleep for 3 seconds,
and I'm going to echo after.
That's the command I'm to
run inside of a container,
so before sleep, After
done. Okay, great.
So if I was doing this for
something that takes
a long time to run,
this would be a
very boring example
N. We'd all sit
here for 5 minutes.
The way I want to run
something like this is,
I want to run it
as detached mode.
So I'm going to say
D, detached mode
is to be in the background.
Great. It's asynchronous now.
I don't have to
have anything here.
But you also see that I don't
have any kind of output, right?
This is the way you're going
to run most containers.
This semester because
you're going to have like
little clusters of
containers working together.
And of course, you could only be
looking at like one
container at the time.
Usually have a bunch of
containers in detached mode.
They're going to have
a bunch of output,
and you will not
see it by default.
That's like when
somebody comes to help,
that's like one of the
first things I want to see.
They're like, Oh, my
server is not running.
I'm like, Well,
what did it print?
Did it print an
error or whatever?
It's not trying to just
jump to the screen to you.
You have to go down and
try to dig in and find it.
So when I do Docker PS,
I see it's running.
And what I can do is I
can say docker logs,
Elastic Austin, and I see
that it says before, right?
So we did before, sleeping,
eventually, it'll say after.
Depending on the
program, I might be
printing a bunch of
more things right now.
And if I want to,
remember how we
had tail fallow tail dash off.
I can do logs follow as well.
I'll see everything
printed so far,
and then it'll wait as there's
more output, I'll see it.
Right?
I might have a bunch of
different containers
running and as I have
troubleshooting I might
tail this one for a while,
ta out tail that
one for a while,
figure out what's rowing on.
Right?
If you aren't using these
and seeing what's going on,
then it's like there's no way
you're going to troubleshoot
anything, right?
That's just like the basic
you have to do that.
Remember this, if you're
always googling this,
you're going to be slow.
This is the kind
of thing you just
want to get fastness
environment,
and there's just a bunch
of stuff to remember.
It's not interesting, but
you'll save time if you just,
you know, brute force
remember a lot of this stuff.
Alright I may he Ctrl C
to cancel out of that.
Other things I might want to
do to troubleshoot this thing.
Sometimes I like
to jump inside of
a container and start
running some commands.
And so there's a couple
of things we can do.
When I do Docker Run,
I'd say an image name,
and I create a container
from that image,
related to that, is I
can say Docker Exec.
And then here what I
have is a container.
And the idea of Exec is
that I'm not trying to
create a new container.
I'm going to add
a second command
in an existing container, right?
So the name of my container
is Elastic Austin.
And I want to get a bash
prompt inside of it,
and I need to have an
interactive terminal.
So I'm going to
run those things.
And now I'm inside
of this environment.
And if I say PS, maybe PS,
A X, it's kind of cool.
I can see that here was that
command that was running.
With some server, I could
check other things like what
ports is it using where I see
examples of that eventually.
I can kind of poke around in
this environment and
see what's going on.
It's also very interesting
that this has process ID one.
You don't see that too often
on your host operating
system, right?
I mean, the numbers
keep cycling through.
So you're pacing
big process IDs.
But when we start
a new container,
things start numbering from one.
And then I can kind
of see that there.
All right. So if I
wanted to, I could say,
for example, I could
kill a process ID six,
and then let me then
it actually exit out
of the container,
be the whole thing
finish finished running.
So this is another reason
why it's more secure
because I could have a bunch
of different containers.
Well, let's say I don't have
containers, and I have like,
an evil, malicious program,
and it tries to kill
another process.
It can use whatever you know,
any program can try to do kills,
and it can use whatever
process ID it wants, right?
Now, imagine I have a bunch
of different containers,
and they each have their
own process ID name space.
Maybe they each have
their own process ID process
with a process ID sex.
If I'm in this container
and I say kill sex,
I only have a way of
referring to containers
in my name space.
There's no way for me to kill
a container or somebody
else's sandbox, right?
So kind of this will make us
a little bit more secure.
Alright. Fantastic. Let me
just run that thing again.
And I want to show you
some other commands.
So we already saw Doctor PS.
I might also say Docer Stats.
Some of these things are
kind of like memory hogs,
and so we might see
that the containers
are using too much memory.
That's something you might
keep an eye on it if
you're having trouble
running things.
I'm going to hit
control C out of that.
What else might I do?
I have Docker PS.
If I wanted to, I could chill
this container so I could do
a kill blissful angle bar.
And then it's not
running anymore.
It's still there, right?
I could have to
go remove it too,
but I can chill
containers if I want,
and then restart them as needed.
Those are my best
troubleshooting techniques.
Any questions about those
about how to troubleshoot
these container environments?
Yeah, right here.
Oh, you're saying, like, can I
execute inside of this one?
There's a way, but I cannot
just do this, right?
If I just do I have
to restart it.
So there's a way to, kind of,
like resuscitate a
killed container
before it gets removed.
I think it's like
started or something.
I don't do it too
often, honestly,
but there is a way to revie it,
and then I can
start executing it.
I might do that if my container
crashed and I want to
kind of do a post mortem
and figure out what
went wrong with it.
Yeah, right here.
Kill container.
Yeah. So I wouldn't
kill an image,
but I would delete
an image, right?
And so Docker Oh, no.
This is the hopefully that
comes back in a momentarily.
I would do Docker RM
to remove a container,
and I would do Docker RM I
to remove an image. Yep.
And all that stuff should
just be in your
notes because you'll
have to remember and use it
frequently this semester.
Yeah, great question. The
other questions people have.
Right. Cool. So let
me we're getting a
little short on time.
Well, I want to talk
briefly about Docker files.
And so I'm going to make
a new directory for this.
I'm gonna call it Lecture two.
And basically what I do it,
I want to make a little
environment where I can
run a Python program
that uses Pandas.
And so I'm going to
create a Docker file.
And in a Docker file,
we have different directives.
And the first directive
we have is we have from.
I want to start from
a different image.
And so I'm going to start
from Ubuntu, 24.10.
And then the idea down here
is that I can run stuff.
And I'm just trying to go to
my lecture snippets because
I forget what I'm
supposed to type.
If I'm over here and
I go on to resources,
and I go to lecture snippets,
you can see these things,
and that can help you
follow along, too.
So the main thing
I want to do is
I want to do this
app, get Install.
And maybe first, I'm just
going to install
the on ZIP program,
and then maybe later I'll coment
this and install
some other things.
When I'm doing an
applicant install,
it's checking the repositories,
and I have to kind of
refresh my view of
what software is available
in those repositories.
So I'm going to also grab
this command right here.
Alright, so I'll update,
I'll refresh that view.
Then I'm going to
install some stuff,
and then I should be good to go.
You all, I think have
used App before.
App and AppCt are
pretty similar.
I mean, App is trying
to design for a human.
And if they have a nicer
syntax or things like that,
they just like update App,
whatever is nicest for a human.
AppG ideas it's for a strip,
and so they never change
anything because they
don't want to break your code
or your strips, basically.
So I'll normally use like App
when I'm in the shell myself.
And if I make it a Docker file
or something I'll use apk,
but not a super important
distinction for us.
Alright. So I have
these three lines.
And what I can do now is
I can say Docker build.
I have to tell at a directory
where that docker file is.
That's a current directory,
and then I have to give it
a name. I may call it demo.
So I'm going to run that thing,
and it's staring to do
the app to get update.
It is staring to do the
app to get install.
And then eventually
it finishes running.
And at that point, I could do
a docker run of my demo image,
and I could do a bash thing,
and then I guess the
big feature is that I
have the on ZIP
program inside of it.
Right? So I can do
that. Let's head
up to the Docker file again,
and I want to install
some more things
now like these two, right?
So I'm going to come
back here. I'm going
to show you a couple
of problems, right?
Issues that you're
going to run into.
I'm going to build
it again. All right.
And so the first thing
I want you to see is
that it does caching on
a line by line basis.
So what does that mean?
That means that I've
already done this app to
get update thing before.
And so whatever state that
drove the system to
it remember that,
and it just skips
that step this time,
that makes things faster.
And then this was only
line that changed.
Looking at everything before
then the Docker file.
It could just kind of skip.
And here's where it's actually
executing something new.
So what went wrong
with this one,
I come down here and I was
saying it was asking me,
like, do you want to
actually install that?
And of course, I do or I
wouldn't have written that.
But it's expected that
a human can type yes,
but a docker file
cannot type, yes.
So one thing I'm going to
change here is I'm going to
say y so that it
will not prompt me.
Right? If things are
above a certain size,
I get that prompt, I
just want to say yes.
That's one improvement
we should do.
The other thing is is that
This caching in general,
it usually makes things faster,
but it's actually a little
bit of a problem here,
right because the
software available
in these APT repositories
is always changing,
and I need to have kind
of a fresh view of it.
And so if I run this and
then I wait, say, like,
a few days, and then I run this
on here, it won't work, right?
Because the last time I kind of
viewed what software
is available,
it might have changed where
things are, things like that.
And so I have to run
these close together.
When I look in the door file,
they're close together,
but the problem I can run
into is that maybe it's like,
Oh, you ran this two weeks ago.
I don't have to do it again.
That's usually true, except
when I need it kind of fresh.
And so what people
will actually do,
since this cash happens
on the line by line basis
is they will combine this
into a single one liner.
Right to break that thing prom.
So you kind of see
these ugly lines.
There's a good reason for it,
why people are doing that.
One way that they kind of might
make it at least
look a little bit
nicer is that you
can put backslashes in
and then break it up.
It still counts as one line as
far as far as Docker
is concerned.
Right? So I'm going to do
this. I can build it again.
And then that was way too fast.
There's no way that that's Oh,
because I did in the morning.
That's why it tahed
that version.
And then I could run it,
and I should have Oh.
Let me just run this, and then I
should have Python
three installed.
The last thing I want
to talk about, I'll
wrap up because I know
I only have 1 minute
left is that before I
try to add any kind of
install to the docker file,
I kind of usually have
some stuff there,
and I'll test it out here
in this interactive environment.
So for example, if I do a
PEP three install Pandas.
Let's try that. I'm actually
going to get an error.
And what they're
trying to say is like,
Oh, you should use Python
virtual environments,
and I'm like, actually, I
don't really want to because I
have docker virtual
environments.
And it's saying that, so
you shouldn't install it
like that, and it says,
if you want to do something
scary and you trust yourself,
then do this, right?
And so I'm like, Okay,
well, I will do that.
And so I'll kind
of test this and
make sure I can do
the install here.
And then I think I'll just
got this a little bit wrong.
I'll kind of do that install
here and make sure it works.
And only after that, after
I get it working here,
then I go back to
my docker file,
and I will add that
down here, right?
That's how you can
kind of troubleshoot
these things and have it
interact and do things working.
And then I could build that.
And that'll take a while,
so we'll kind of wrap up.
Anyway, hopefully that helps
you debug your docker files,
debug your containers, and just
get very comfortable
in this environment.
Bs d be the whole semester.
Feel free to come up
and chat if you have
any questions and have a
good evening, everybody.