About Spark SQL, and I have
a few more examples there
that I want to talk about.
In particular, I want to look at
how Joy works in Sparks equal.
And then I spend most of
the day on a topic that
I'm pretty excited about,
which is how Spark
works internally,
and how can we get better
performance out of it.
So first, let me head back here
to the slides we had last time.
We've already talked about
grouping data together.
And Joy is maybe
similar in some ways.
I so to look at some
concrete examples
of how a joy might be de.
And so in this example,
what I'm imagining
is there's some kind
of music festival and
different bands play
on different days
and different trauma
different day.
So it's a three day festival.
And what I want to do is I
want to figure out first,
who saw which bad, right?
That's really, a many
Mya relationship.
Some bads played
on multiple days,
and some jests arrived
at multiple days.
So it's a many M d relationship.
And I can do that with
ergoid like this up here.
Enteroid, visits dot da
equals performances dot da.
There's different
tides of joids.
That's what we call it equidid,
right because we're say,
Well, it's actually equal.
That'll probably most of
the joids we look
at this semester.
So when we do that, it's
actually somewhat similar to
a group pipe is we have to
bring related data together.
Even though we have
two different tables,
we want to bring all the
Tuesday rows together.
We want to bring all the Monday
rows together, so
on and so forth.
We have to bring
that data related data
in the same place,
even though the related data
is coming from two
different tables, right?
So instead of the grouping
picture we've seen before,
it might look like this, right?
We get different fragments of
each table that are brought
together in the same place.
And then I can try to
mix and match, right?
So I can see down at the bottom.
I guess A came on Monday
and bad X played on Monday,
so we can say that A saw X.
When we look at the top one,
We see that there's two
guests and two bads,
and so we're actually
have four rows
because we want to have
every combination.
And the one in the
middle on Wednesday,
while there's some
people who came,
but nobody was playing that day,
so then we'll have no rows.
So the output looks like
something like this.
We're just outputting for
every combination between
these when we have a
match on the day, right?
So we could then ask the
question, who saw, what,
maybe we use that for
targeted marketing or
something like that,
maybe were trying to sell
the merchandise afterwards.
You might also want to know
when guests K but did not
actually see any performance.
And so instead of
doing it interoy,
we could do a left join, right?
The results between
these are very similar.
But when you have a left joi
and the table on
the left is visits,
that means that every
visit row should be
outputed one at least once,
even if it doesn't
pair with anything.
And so because a ta
pair with anything,
then the bad is just
going to be dull, right?
These people who
came on Wednesday
did not see any bad at all.
You can imagine having that as
an intermediate output and
doing further processing on it?
You could group by
guess, for example.
You could count where
it's not at all,
then you could say, well,
when is the Cut zero?
You could ultimately get a list
of people who showed
up at some point,
but didn't see anything
at all, right?
So we'll often do
either inter join
or left join depending
on our needs,
and we might be using
that in combination
with other things like
group by and having.
Do we have any general
questions about joins before
I have some concrete
examples? Yeah, right here.
Excellent. So the right oid
would be the flip of it.
So if we wanted to see,
is there some bad that
played like literally
nobody came to see them?
I'd be kind of sad, right?
Then we could do a
right oid, right?
They were to make sure
that each bad gets
emitted at least one
even if nobody saw it.
Yep, Exactly. Yeah, A
questions people have.
Right. Cool. So ahead over here.
I may do some demos,
and I'm in the same
notebook as last time.
And as you'll recall,
we were analyzing data
from the San Francisco
Fire Department.
We ended last time
doing some stuff with
windowing functions
and I'm sorry,
with partitioning and
windowing functions.
Let's do some things
with joins now.
And so I want to
have a table that
I that I can join calls again.
So remember, if I say
spark dot table and
I look at my calls,
It has all of these things.
It may add another
table of holidays.
And what I could do is I could
joy basically the call
date to holidays,
and I can see, Okay, this
event happened on this day.
For example, on 4 July.
There's lots of fireworks
and that's terrible in
San Francisco because it's
super dry, and there's fires.
And so we can see,
for example, right?
A there more fire
department talls on 4 July?
So we actually have a data set
of all these different holidays,
and it is a this holiday
is dot CSV file.
And these are like,
specific dates for holidays.
And so, for example, New Years
is normally on January 1,
but this is actually the
day people get off, right?
So maybe if it was on a
weekend for whatever reason,
maybe independent day or
New Year's was
celebrated on January 2.
So anyway, we actually have to
join a separate table of all of
these holidays to make
everything work out fine.
And so I've already taken
that file and I have
uploaded it to HDFS.
And if I come to my
snippets from last time,
I have a bit of
code here that will
create a temporary
view for me with it.
I'm just going to
come to do that now
before I go much farther.
I'm ready to do a crate or
Replace a temporary view based
on that CS V file, right?
I'm go to do that. And that's
a relatively simple
table, right?
So if I come down here, I
could then look at the holidays,
and I can see, well,
just has a date.
I'm just going to use strings
for dates in this example.
That's probably not
the best thing to do,
but I don't want to
get caught up in
those details and the name
of the holiday in question.
Great. So I have two tables,
and I might want to join them
together to see which calls
happen on which holidays.
So my first question is,
can we associate
calls with holidays?
And the answer is, yes, we can.
The way we do it will
be interjoi, right?
So select star Fb calls,
and then I can
interjoid, holidays.
And when I do that, I have
to have some kind of filter
here to specify which row
matches with which row.
It might be obvious to a
uma look at the Schiba,
but we have to be very explicit
to the SQL engine, right?
So I can say calls T date.
Equals holidays
dot eight, right?
So I could do that.
That would give
me another data frame, right?
I can see at the end
of this data frame,
I have columns from
both the calls table and
from the holidays table.
If I do something like two pad
this, I may have
run out of memory,
so I'm not trying
to do that, but
I could do like a limit of five,
and then I could see a few
of these So that will run,
and then I will be able to see,
like this call event
happened on Memorial Day.
I could joy it across those.
Great. So I could do that.
What if I wanted
to, for example,
output all the calls,
even if it was not on a holiday?
How would I modify this?
Any volunteers? Right now,
when I look at the
data set out here,
it's much smaller
than the original
data set because I'm only out
putting rows that happened
on a specific holiday.
What if I want all
the rows, and maybe
sometimes there's a holiday?
Maybe sometimes it says
nothing. Yeah, right here.
Left join Excellent. If I do
a left joint then
calls us to the left,
then I'll get every single call,
even if a tappy
pair with anything.
Sometimes the holiday
will be dull.
That'll be fin and desirable.
Alright, so I may do the
same thing down here, right?
And I'll do the same,
but with data frame API,
just be I think it's useful to
see multiple ways to
do the same thing.
And so in this case,
I'm just try to get
my tables out first.
So I may have calls is try
to equal spark table hoops.
Table of calls. Great.
So I have my calls out here.
And that I also get
my holidays will
be sparked dot
table of holidays.
Maybe I'll just take
a quick look at that.
Great, I have both of those.
And so what I could
do is I could say
calls Joid on holidays,
right? That's the base form.
So the base relatively simple,
but I have to give a
little more information.
I have to tell it, for example,
what kind of join to do.
And so I could say
that, I could say how
equals d. That's
actually optional.
I don't say how
editor is assumed,
but in this case,
I'm to do an Editor.
And then I have to say d equals.
I have to have some
kind of way of
capturing an
expression that says,
these two rows match
or they don't match.
And that's a little bit
funny how they do that.
You might remember
that before we
imported Tol at expression.
And so What I could actually
do is I could use column
to refer to different
columns of these things.
And so I could create a
column object like this,
or what I could also do
is what I have calls.
I could say a column, right?
I can say somebody
a call date, right?
That's an example of a column.
I could also say holidays,
and I could say date,
that would be an
example of a column.
And I can actually do
comparisons on these, right?
So I can say when they're
equal to each other,
that I get this other column,
which would basically
be describe me like
when they're the same or
when they're different,
right? So I may have that.
And down here, I can say
that for my odd
expression, right?
When the call date
lines up with the date,
that I want to match it up.
All right, so I could do that.
And if I actually
want to see it.
Well, first of if we'd see they
got the same scheme as before.
If I actually want to see it,
then maybe I'll try to
split this up a little bit,
cause I might be getting
a little bit long, right?
So I might say, you know,
give me five rows,
and then two pads.
I have put all this
in parentheses,
so it accepts the fact that
it's multiple lines, right?
But I could do that.
It'll be exactly the
same results as before.
I could do it either
with the data frame API
or the Spark SQL API.
Any questions about
either of those examples?
Yeah, right here.
Oh, yeah, that's a
really good question.
You're saying, could we do
a ware statement?
Instead of an odd.
I think the idea is,
right? Base in both cases,
they're doing filters, right?
I guess there's a
lot of cases where
we filter things in sequel.
We have ware filters things,
odd filters things,
having filters things.
For whatever reason,
they have kind
of set it up so that you have to
use different claws in
each case, right?
So I could not use.
W would do is it would
actually filter out by
rows before it even
performed the joint.
But you're right. They're all
filters that they just had
forced us to use different words
in different places. Yeah, full.
Oh, are you saying
I think maybe if
I understand what you're
drawing, and correct
me if I'm wrong.
But maybe what you're
saying is that we
could first do what's
called a cross join,
where every row on the
first table matches with
every row on the
second table that
after that we do aware.
You're saying that that
would have the same result,
but it would be slower, is
that what you're saying?
Yeah. Yeah. Well, would the
performance be different?
Maybe it all depends
on what optimizations
the SQL engine does.
And we'll actually see later
like relearn big query,
and big query, you
write it that way.
L you're doing every
combination that
there's like a ware clause
afterwards to filter it out,
which is strange, but
it's optimized, right?
So it would be fast, right?
I think it's kind of
like it's easy to
look at the choice
of the language,
the SQL language,
and then try to
make assumptions
about performance.
But it's essentially
fairly D couple, right?
People have done
a lot of work to
take kind of queries
that maybe they look
slow on their face,
but what actually
runs is not directly
corresponding to what
is typed, right?
So you're right that they're
logically equivalent.
And maybe also in
terms of performance,
they might be
equivalent as well,
depending on the optimizations.
Yeah, Yeah, kind of a path.
We can revisit that
with big query, too.
Yeah, other thoughts or
questions people have.
Right. Cool.
So I have that. You know,
I think the next
natural question is,
how Betty, how Betty
calls were there on
each holiday, right?
And I can just try to naturally
build on top of this
pipeline I have up here.
And I just try to copy this.
And after I've done this,
well, what do I have?
Let me just take a
peek at it here.
I have this holiday here,
and so I want to group by that.
So I could say dot
group by holiday.
All right. Then I
could say dot Cut,
I could account
for each of them.
Remember that, in this case,
since Cut is being happen
together with group,
it's a transformation.
It's not an action
that's actually
triggering any work yet, right?
Just a transformation.
Because I might want
to do other things.
I want to do order by. You kind
of see a sty fy People say,
be consistent with
your programming,
but people become
wealthy programming
and still not be consistent.
Spark is used so broadly.
But anyway, I do this or
say sort by the cot
I could do that.
Then at the very end, I
could say convert to Pads,
and then I could see A people
calling the Fire
Department a lot.
Oh, I have a limit
up here, right?
Sequel would let me do that.
Mabe sequels actually save
Aby from myself, right?
Let's do it properly
with all the data now.
I don't have to limit
Atha because there's
not that many different
distinct holidays.
And sure uh like
independence day is.
The fire department
is a little bit
maybe busier than they
are for a typical
holiday. All right.
Cool. Any question about
that example where
we're combining droid
with a group by? All right.
So for my last question,
is I want to say what percent of
all calls occurred
on a holiday, right?
And so I come back here,
and I be copy this pipeline from
before. I'll paste it down here.
And I'm back up a
little bit, right?
So I've joined these
things together.
And in this case, right,
if I want to get a
percentage, right?
I need to have some
kind of numerator
and denominator, right?
The Nuerintor is
the holiday calls,
and the denominator
is all the calls.
And so right now I already
have a little trouble,
right because If I
have an inter oid,
I feel row it down to
just the holiday calls.
I really want all the calls.
And so this would be a great
case where I do left, right?
So at least after I do my joid,
I still have all the calls,
and I can still get
subcuts from them,
I want to remember
all the calls,
not just the ones that holidays.
Right? So I have that.
And then what I want to do is I
want to do some kind
of aggregate on it.
I'm be to do a group.
Pe I'm trying to get a
bunch of aggregates.
I just want to get one single
simple number that I
can walk away with.
And so we have an
aggregate here.
And remember that sometimes
I have simple aggregates, right?
There's just like a
function already there.
This, when I have a more
complicated aggregate,
I have to put some
kind of expression
here to do the math, right?
And so when I try
to have this ratio,
I guess the numerator
is going to be
some kind of count of something,
and the denominator will
be some kind of
count as something.
And then I'm going to express
that ratio as a percentage.
And then maybe I'll just say
like Alias perc Alright,
so, help me out here.
For the deminator, I want
to count every single call.
So what kind of count do I do
want to do if I want to
do every single call?
What should I type
here? Yeah, right here.
Yep, I want to do all rows.
Absolutely. So what is
the symbol to say,
do all the rows?
Yeah, right here. S
Excellent, right?
I want to count
every single row.
And here, I only
want to count the ones
that are holidays.
So remember that
sometimes this would
be dull and sometimes
it would not be dull.
What should I type
here? Yeah, go ahead.
Holiday. Excellent. Right. Yeah,
this one will count
all the rows,
and this one will only count
the ones where the
holiday is audiol.
Let's run it and
see what we get.
EXPR is out to fight.
I could have sort.
I had that earlier.
Anyway, no problem.
I could say from pi spar
dot squel functions,
Import, column, and expression.
Great. Let's see if we can
get an answer on this.
And that running?
Alright, so 1.5% of
all calls happen on
holidays? I don't know.
I can try to figure out
how many holidays
there are the year,
but it doesn't
seem like holidays
are especially bad for
the fire Department.
Yeah, right. Equal to.
When you do a count of a column,
what it's doing is it's counting
the ones that are
not equal at all.
Yep. That's why some people
will put that there.
Some will put a start, a pity
on what they're
trying to achieve.
Yeah, thanks for asking.
Other questions people have.
Yeah, right here. Oh, yeah,
you're saying, Okay, so
you wanted to see, like,
what percentage of them
are Memorial Day, right?
I guess there's different
ways I could do it.
Like I I think one
way I could do it
is probably have to have
some kind of sub query.
I guess, like for the holidays,
maybe what I would
do is I would have
a fil rout holidays to get
memorial days might be
one way to do it, right?
All the rest would be the same.
But yeah, there's probably
other ways to do it, too.
It'll probably involve
some kind of nesting.
Yeah, great question.
Other questions
people have. Alright, cool.
So I think that's everything I
wanted to show about Doids.
And so now we're a head over to
This lecture where we learned
a little bit more about how
Spark works in Turtle and
how to get good
performance out of it.
And some of here, I
think it is a little
bit redundant with things
I've shown before,
but I just feel like it'll make
more sense now that
we've had hands
on experience with Spark,
so bear with me, if
you've seen some of this
before when we were first
starting with RDDs.
So I have a few
objectives. We want
to become more sophisticated
users of cash.
We can select
different cash levels,
and we want to have some
guideus for how to do that.
Well, we've been having just
simple partitioning so far.
There's somebody else
called Hash partition,
which to bring
together related data.
We want to see
water cases where we
would want to do that.
Spark has all these
optimizations
related to grouping
by and aggregates.
So I want you to walk away with
knowing what those are and how
to take advantage of them.
And then finally, when we're
joining data together,
there's actually different
algorithms for doing
that in a distributed
environment.
And Spark will try to
choose the best one,
but it might not
choose the best one.
And so there's ways
you can override it.
I want you to know
what both of these are
the kind of have an intuition
about when they're good.
So maybe you might override
what Spark does by default.
All right. So there's five
big areas of performance.
I'm just trying to give
some ideas in each of
them about how we can
get better performance.
The first one is related
to Schema forts,
which we've seen before.
I just want to show it again.
So we're doing everything
with performance in one lecture.
Remember that we
could pull our data
from either a CSV
file or a PK file.
And if we're doing a CSV file,
everything in a CSV is a string.
And so if we want types,
we'd have to do some kind of
schema forts or some other
way specify the types.
So I just have some
times here, right?
If I do this data frame load
of a CSV and I say
in first Schema,
that took me 17 tasks
and 33 seconds.
For this San Francisco data.
There's three options down here
where I wouldn't have
to do Skim Ed prits,
and two of them are with CSVs.
One is that I could say,
I could just not include
schema in first schema,
it'd be really fast.
They'll just have
to read a header,
and it'll make
everything be a string.
That probably isn't that useful,
but at least it's fast, right?
The other thing I could do
is I could say dot schema.
I could put a
string here where I
manually specify the
type of each string.
For a big table
like San Francisco,
Fire Department vets,
that would be pretty
annoying, right?
I don't want to have to
type 20 things there.
But if I do that, that's
actually extremely fast
because SMRT doesn't even
have to look at my files, right?
It already knows
that the schemas
without reading
absolutely nothing.
The best, one of most cases
is be reading a Park file.
In that case, Spark does have
to read it to figure out
what those types are,
but it just reads the header.
It does have to read
the whole thing. And so
at 0.2 seconds and one task.
It can have that
schema information.
Alright, so avoid Schema
efts whenever possible,
and use Park files,
whenever possible.
Alright, let's talk
about collecting data.
This is also something we've
seen a little bit before,
but I want to look at
it in more detail.
Now though we understand
how Spark jobs run. So
Excuse me. Here I have
a data frame that's referring to
some kind of part
K file at HDFS.
And I have two different
lines on here.
Results equal data frame that
where some filter
that I could collect,
or I could do the same thing,
and I could say two pads.
Collect in two pads. You know,
maybe the data comes back
to be a different format.
But from the perspective
of what actually runs,
those are extremely similar.
In both cases, they're
bringing all those results
into memory on the
client machine, right?
So I want to show what actually
happens in one of these cases.
I'll just say two pands.
In this case, I have
a computer down here
at the bottom that
where my application is
running, and I have some ab.
Right now there's
nothing in the ab.
My cluster has two worker
machines. Right here.
Each of the worker
machines has two CPUs,
and they each have some ab.
Nothing is in the
rab there, either.
Now, when I say data frame
equals that big file dot load,
then what that means
is that a data frame
is defined with a
bunch of partitions,
and each of those partitions are
referring to a piece
of that park file.
But they're just pointing to it.
There's nothing in memory
at this point. Okay?
That's a setup. So what will
happen if I actually want to
collect the data
or do two Pandas?
Well, it's I have
to run some tasks to do
the filtering, right?
Remember that a task
runs on one CPU,
and it runs on one
partition of data.
When it's running
on a pit of data,
it brings the entire
partition of data,
the entire partition of data
into RAB at the same time.
I have eight partitions of
the Part file and four CPUs,
so it can only bring
four at a time.
It brings in four partitions
of the Parte data into Rab,
like so, and it runs a task
out of CPU to filter that data.
Those tasks are going to
produce output data,
which is smaller, right?
I'm filtering down with a ware.
I'm going to assume that the
put data is small enough.
I should fit on one machine
in memory just fine.
And so these tasks are going
to be sending their data
back to application over here.
I'll be loaded in memory.
Maybe that's like
half the data for
a data frame a pada data frame.
Alright. Now, it's
going to have to
load those other four partitions
in after the first
four tasks were done.
Those will be do the same
thing. They felt there down.
They said a small
subset of the data,
and that ends up in
memory on my computer,
and everything worked fine.
And this is frankly kind of cool
because my original data, right?
That's in that large park file.
It doesn't fit in memory
any single computer.
It doesn't even fit in
the cumulative ab across all
the computers on my cluster.
Yet I can still do
operations on the results.
So if the results are
small, it's fine to have
those results in memory
in one place at one time.
So that's all cool.
That's straight.
Those are the mechanics of how
we would run
something like that.
Anybody have any questions about
the mechanics there? All right.
Yeah, right here. Results.
How big the perdition
worst since Oh,
yeah, how would the
partitions works.
It's the Park A file
is column oriented.
Well, I could certainly have
I guess here I haven't like,
shown anything about it, right?
So I guess maybe I'm
just assuming that we're
having some operation that
touches all the columns, right?
But in practice, right,
these partitions
might be referring
to just specific columns.
And the great thing is is
that where are these
tasks coming from?
They're coming from somebody
who wrote some Spark SQL.
And so the Spark SQL optimizer
is going to be able
to figure out,
for these tasks
that are running.
Which columns do we
actually need, right?
So that case, maybe,
we might only be
accessing half of
the large park file or
something like that.
So I haven't shown it, but yeah,
that's a great detail
to keep in wide.
So it makes sense? Yeah,
thanks for asking.
Yeah other questions
people have.
All right. Cool. So let's
say somebody that's bad.
So this would be bad if I
did filter it down, right?
If I don't have a were
clause, what would happen?
So it would first load
the two partitions into
memory on each of the two
machines like before.
Those would start
sending their data
to my application computer.
That can only fit two of these
big partitions at a time.
So I'd d two of them, and
then I would crash
right very early out.
Only two tasks would
be able to finish.
And maybe maybe I
don't put by crash,
maybe I hold VM byte freeze of,
but nothing good
will come of this.
Crash right here. By
the applications.
By application by Crash or
sometimes the whole VM, g.
Yep. And one of the things
that I like to do is like,
when I'm using
docker containers.
I can set a memory limit
on a docker container.
And so I'll kind of
see like, Oh, like,
I have 4 gigabytes of
ram on my machine,
and I'm running
these containers,
and I'll kind of set memory
limits on each container,
and I'll make sure that
some of those limits is
less than my machine
because if they are,
and my containers are trying
to use too much memory,
I'll kill the processes
of those containers.
And that's annoying,
but it's a lot less
annoying than having my
whole VM freeze up, right?
So so you can
depend on whether you set
memory limits on
your containers,
you can get different
symptoms when this happens.
Yeah, thanks for asking.
Yeah, there are
questions people have.
Yeah, right here.
That's a really
interesting question.
Could you tell them that, hey,
if you're about to
go over a memory,
don't actually do that?
Yeah, well, it doesn't work that
way. Could it work that way?
Maybe. I think that's teres
interesting question.
It's definitely trickier
that it kind of seems at
face value because well,
we learned about AP, right?
We learned about
MAP that you could
say, I have this large file,
and that I have some region of
virtual memory that
corresponds to that file,
and when I first
read that memory,
that it actually brings
the data, right?
And so at a given
point of time, right?
I probably have a bunch of
different processes
running on my computer?
The mapped all this big stuff,
and it's probably okay
because they aren't actually
accessing So it's a
little hard to know,
like, Oh, am I gonna
be using too much
memory if I do this,
it depends on what everybody
else is doing, right?
So it's definitely tricky,
but I think it's an
interesting idea.
Could you fail more gracefully
when we run out a memory?
There's probably some
things you could do,
but it's not trivial.
Yeah, and they
don't do it, right?
Yeah. Interesting thought.
Yeah, other other thoughts or
questions people have. Alright.
So the takeaway there, right,
is that be very
careful when you're
collecting data, right?
Make sure that if it's fine
to work with huge datasets,
but if you want to collect it in
one place on one machine,
make sure it gets
small before you
pull it all together?
Yeah, right here.
Yeah, yeah, absolutely. To
the five by patients in
this Excellent point, right?
The partition HDFS. They
have some other sizes,
they're partitioning
in these blocks.
There's no reason
that that would have
to be the same as
it is in Spark.
Yes, I think the
question is, maybe it.
Will Spark make any
decisions regarding
partition size or
boundaries based
on how HDFS partitions things?
And I'm not aware that they
take that into a factor,
but I also don't know
the negative that they
don't use that in some way.
What I observed is
that it kind of
seems like it's mostly
based on the file size
rather than the HDFS
boundaries, but I'm not sure.
Right?
It's possible that they could
take that into account.
But they also I mean,
you when you're
reading the data,
you could choose like the
petition count, right?
So it certainly doesn't
have to be the same.
I don't know if they
try to make it the
same for any kind of
performance reason.
But I may say in general,
it's probably not the same.
But maybe maybe it is.
Yeah, interesting ought.
Yeah, other thoughts
or ideas people have.
All right, cool. Let's
talk about caching.
So I have that same picture now,
but now it's a little
bit more complicated.
We aren't going to worry
too much about the client.
I'm not showing that
anymore, but I'm
showing some more
detail up above.
Each of these machines
has Rab as before.
And they also have some hard
drives or SSDs attached,
and there's a local file
system on top of that.
The local file system probably
has more capacity than Rab has,
maybe a lot more. So
I have that here.
I also am doing this. I'm saying
a data frame two
equals data frame.
And this by data frame two is
just like transformations
on the data frame.
There's no work being done.
I'm not collecting
anything like before.
But what I'm imagining is
that the user wants to do
a bunch of calculations
on top of data frame two.
And the default behavior
is that every time
I want to do some
calculations over DF two,
it will rescan all the data
for DF and shake it down again.
That's why I'm expensive,
right because I
only want to touch a
small subset of the data.
I've repeatedly
scanned this big data.
So this is a perfect
case for caching, right?
I want to maybe keep DF
two in memory, right?
Normally a data frame,
it based on RDD,
and normally doesn't have
bites of data and memory,
right, that are just
persistent there.
But in some cases,
I might want to do
that for performance,
even though it's not
strictly necessary.
So how do you do that? Well, I
can say data frame
two dot per ces.
And after that, the first
time that I use the data
frame two for something,
it'll keep bytes of
that data somewhere.
And then when I access
again, it'll be faster.
And when I do that, I can put
a different storage
level options, right?
Because there's actually
different places I could
keep this cached data.
And there's actually
lots of options,
and I want you to remember
six of them this semester.
But if you remember
three, you'll
be good because they
come in pairs, right?
So I have three here
that talk about,
and then there's
three other ones
that closely
correspond to these.
Right? So you can
trouble ag and you
can specify one of
these, if you want.
The first one is memory Oly.
And that's actually the default.
If I say dataframe.ca,
it's just a short head for
data frame dot persist,
storage level memory Oly.
And when I do that,
if I'm cash ADF two,
you see those eight
partitions up there.
They're just going
to be in Ab, right?
Even when the job is
done, they'll stay there.
So that's the kind of most
taming one people use.
Now, I want you remember
how Spark was built.
They wrote Spark and Scala,
and Scala compiles to
JVM Bite code, right?
The Java Virtual Machine.
It's all this scala analysis
stuff that's happening.
Well, the analysis is happening
on Java types, right?
Like, you know, Java
alist or whatever types
they have, right?
And Java is notorious
for kind of memory blow.
For example, you know, they
have like primitives too.
So imagine like
that E primitive,
but they also have
an editor object.
An editor object would have
four bytes of data
for the number,
but objects need this
extra stuff in Java.
They need to have some kind of
reference to the type
is baked into it,
or they need to have a reference
cap for garbage collection.
And so they have a 16
byte header in Java,
even for some like
a simple piece
of data that's like four bytes.
So right there, we have
something that's like
four to five times bigger
than it needs to be.
I don't even know how they
made strings so terrible,
but this is from the
documentation in Spark.
Apparently, if you
have a java string,
there's like 40
bytes of overhead.
I don't know if
that's like toting
stuff or lake or whatever.
They use a UTF eight
UTF 16 toting,
which means that every character
is always going to be two bytes.
And so, if I have a
ten character string,
it might be that
it's actually taking
60 bytes of data. So
all this is horrible.
Things kind of blown up
in all these awful ways.
And, you know, memory is scarce.
So when we're ca, we might
actually worry that I'm
keeping this bloated
data in my rab.
That leads us to
this other option,
which is memory only serialized.
SCR is shorter serialized.
You've seen
serialization before.
We might have some like a
Python list or something,
we serialize it to
protocol buffers.
Protocol buffers have a very
compact byte level
representation for that data.
So they aren't using
protocol buffers here,
but they have some kind of
other serialization happening.
And so even though we have
all these bloated java types,
we could serialize them into
this compact format, right?
I just want to flip
back and forth, right?
When I did the regular
caching, it looks like this.
I have all these big
partitions cached and rab.
That's all that java blot.
But when I do every serialized,
that they would be
much smaller, right?
I could save quite
a bit of memory,
maybe four or five
times less memory.
That'll sound straight, but
there's a disadvantage.
The Scalco that's
doing analysis is
expecting to work on Java types,
and the serialized data
is not Java types, right?
So it cannot directly operate
on that serialized data.
So if I actually wanted
to use the data by cache,
I have to reverse it.
I have to deserialize it back
to the bigger Java types so
the analysis could actually
run. What does that mean?
If I serialize that
I save memory,
but I'm going to have to spend
more compute
resources serializing
and deserializing
each type, right?
Any questions about the
difference between those two?
Right. Cool. You know,
it might also be
that my cache data
just doesn't fit in
RAM on the machines.
But I might have enough data
on my local storage, right?
You probably have all
done enough of P four to
realize that HDFS is
kind of slow, right?
It's very scalable,
but it's slow.
A local file system
will be much faster,
especially if it's on like a
SSD or something like that.
And so it might make sense
to write my cache data
to local desk rather
than having it at
its original place.
By any means, right, I would
have to filter out again,
like I would otherwise, right,
if I'm going from DF to DF
two. So I could say disc.
In this case, it's actually
still serialized, right?
So Going back, memory
is not serialized.
Memory serialized is,
of course, serialized.
Disco is also serialized.
It's just a different place.
Why do they serialize it?
Well, you know, we probably
have lots of disc capacity,
so that probably doesn't
matter too much.
So that we're trying
to save space.
But what does matter is
that it's slow to write to
disc and read from disc.
And so if I can crutch it down,
then I have less data transfer.
So even though I have
to do extra compute,
that probably is
going to be a lot
faster than doing
extra disco, right?
So that will always be
serialized. All right.
Any question about
those three options?
Yeah, right here. If you try
to catch it to level doesn't,
does it go level down ore here?
What does it do if
you try to cache
it to a level, it
doesn't fit it?
I don't think I've
personally tried
it, but I read somewhere once.
This is like say maybe
I read wrong or not a
super reliable source?
I read that, if you
try to cache it
there's not enough room,
it just doesn't do it.
I mean, it'll still
run otherwise,
I'll just pull the data.
So it's like a best effort
is my understanding,
but I haven't tested, so I can't
promise that. That's
a good question.
Yeah, other questions
about these three levels.
So each of them well,
that's paired with it.
I have just a regular
version, I underscore two.
And what that means is that
when I cache this data,
I'll actually have two
copies of the same thing.
Can anybody think about why that
might be useful in this context?
What I want the same data
cached twice at two different
places. Right here.
Yeah, if what computer is down,
I can have an other copy.
That's definitely true.
That's like the main reason
people replicate things.
Now, I think here it's a
little less critical
than other cases.
In other cases where
we have our primary
data if you lose it,
like, it's just scrawn, right?
If we lose some
data in the cache,
we can row back and recompute
it from original
sources in this case.
But what if that took
like an hour, right?
Like, I don't want
to have to re run
something for an
hour just because,
you know, one machine
went down, right?
So definitely, it will help
us recover faster if
a machine goes down.
Do you think of any other
reasons why I might want to
have two copies of
it? Yeah, go ahead.
Is that may be more efficient by
using Yeah, there are
performance reasons.
You're say, I could use
maybe both computers for it.
It's a little bit tricky
because I'd have to
somehow split my partitions,
but maybe, right?
Split, I could do
something like that.
Or the other thing is
that at any given time,
there's all these different
smart jobs running, right?
They're all using resources,
and some computers might be
busier than others, right?
Maybe some are
doing like a lot of
work and some are kind of idle.
If we have the same data
in two different places,
we can choose where we
do our computation.
We can choose machine
that's less busy.
That helps us load balance.
We can try to put the work
more evenly across
all the machine.
That's called load
balancing, right?
So it helps us with
load balancing,
which is very useful.
Alright, cool. And
the downside, right.
So both of those things are
important performance aspect.
The downside is we have to
use twice as much space, right?
So trade offs, what do you care
about most? Alright, cool.
Yeah. So what we go ahead, we do
a top hat debo and top hat.
We'll do top hat, and then
we'll do a debo. My apologies.
So I just want you to pick
between two cache levels,
Memory and memory serialized.
About 30 seconds left.
Alright, so people
are saying memorial
serialized, which is correct.
We don't have much memory,
so it's a good thing we're
crunching it down to les da.
It does mean whatever
we acts and we have
to do some computation
to de serialize it.
Fortunately, we have lots of
compute resources for that.
Alright, cool. So head
over here to my notebook.
And I may do a load
balancing example.
Right? I'm going to do example,
load ballots and caching.
And so for this example,
I may get some data from
calls and I may cache it.
And what I may imagine is that,
let me just see. What
do I have before?
I have my spart table of calls.
And kind of caching might make
sense for any case where
it's sreaking down, right?
Like maybe like aware, like
I've been talking about.
I'm just try to do a sample
to keep it simple for this one.
And I'm may say I want
1% of my data, right?
And this will be my
data frame, right?
I could do that.
And if I want to,
I can say that I want
to cash it, right?
So I can cash it
like that. Now, I
think this had something
like six partitions.
That's probably too many
if I'm on having 1% data.
And so I will say, let's
repartition down
to one partition.
I get one partition, that's
a small set of data.
Let's just keep it in memory,
so I can keep operating
on it without
having to re sample each time.
F I do that, that's
all fight it well.
Maybe like the first time I run
this, it'll kind of
be a little slow.
There's like these six tasks.
It has to sample it down
to get that partition.
But, after it happens once,
it should actually
be pretty fast.
So I'll run at that time.
We can see it's visibly
very slow. All right.
And then after that
I'm just run it again,
and then we'll see that,
after once, it's
really fast, right?
I just have that small bit
of data, I one partition.
I can add stuff quickly.
All right, so that's
cool. Now, what
I want to do is I want
to think about how this affects
the load balance because I
only have one partition,
and I only have one
replica of that partition.
I have two workers, but it
can only be on one of them.
So that means that
if I ever want
to operate on this quickly,
I have to do all the jobs
on the same machine.
And so if I actually come
to local hosts for 40,
And I go to executors,
what I see is that I
have these different
executors running tasks, right?
Like, this executor
has done 33 tasks.
So this one has done 36.
Relatively balanced so far.
If I keep doing
operations on the sample,
that's going to
become in balanced.
There's going to be
one executor doing
all the work because
it has the data cache.
And so this thing here, right?
I can have a goo here.
They also have a rest API
built on top of this
on this port for 40.
And so I have some
lecture snippets for
that that access that rest API.
And so I will just
copy this here.
So we can see that in practice.
And so, this is documentation.
What this is here is
it will let me view
all these different spark
applications that are
currently running,
basically sessions.
In this case, I only
have one session,
and so I could just, you know,
pull it out of that list.
And if I watch, I could
get the ID of that,
and I could store that
as some kind of app ID.
Right? So so great.
So like this spark
session I have,
they gave me this app ID that I
can refer to what I'm doing.
And that's useful
because I can make
other rest calls to
learn about the executors
belonging to that application.
So, for example, Let
me come down here.
I am going to say,
tell me about all the executors
for that app ID. I'm
paste that here.
And I want to plug
this app ID down here,
so I'm to make this
a format string.
Cool. And I have this list
of executors down here.
And I have different
information about them.
I think I have total tasks,
which is cool, and I have
an ID, which is also cool.
And so I'm just trying
a loop over this.
I'm going to say four
executor in this.
And I'm going to do
list comprehension,
which is basically just throwing
a loop inside of a list.
I could say executor ID,
or I could say executor total
tasks. I could do that.
I have to put parentheses around
these two things,
like like a tuple.
And I could do that same
information, right?
Like one executor
has had 36 tasks.
The other one has had 33.
All right, cool. So
what I want to show
now is that if I keep doing
this count thing
a bunch of times,
Then it's going to be a ballast.
I don't know which
executor has it,
but whoever does has
to do all the work.
So I may say, let's
do this like,
you know, fry it
range like 30 times.
And maybe I'll just print
off what that cout is,
and let's just do
it all on one line,
so it doesn't take
too much space.
I may do, I mean to say,
like, Ed, that's fine.
Whatever. I'll just
say end to now.
I just want my notebook to
be a little bit shorter.
I'll do that a bunch of times.
And excuse me, after it's done,
I may check out my
executor couts.
What we're going to see
is that, sure enough,
this one had to do all the work
because it's the one
that had a cash.
This would be an
example where if
I had had replication, too,
I could have had
better load balance
between my two machines.
Any questions about cash
of your load balance?
Here. The main solution Yeah,
if I have two, that
they could choose.
So I have one partition. I could
have two replicas of
that partition, right?
So instead of say cash up here,
the solution would be to say,
and I'll just leave
it as a comb.
It would be to say, DF you
know, there's all that stuff.
And then at the very
end, I would say
repartition, one as before.
And then I would say persist
instead of cash,
that I could say,
like storage level,
I could say like
Mbary 02, right? To replicas.
Of the one partition.
I could have done
that instead, right?
This is just one replica
of the one partition.
Yeah, yeah, great point
of clarification.
Yeah. Other questions
people have. Alright, cool.
I'm going to head back
here to the slides.
And we're going to talk a
little bit about how we
do grouping and aggregation.
And so this is the
logical picture, right?
And the logical picture, I
have lots of different groups.
I mean, I didn't draw
here, but I mean,
I could theoretically have,
like millions of groups.
And if I want to
do an aggregate,
I have to bring all the
rows for the same you know,
value together in
the same place,
so I can aggregate,
say like the Y column.
I want to sum up the y
column for all the As.
I bring all the As
to the same place.
That's what happens
at the logical level.
But these logical groups
here don't correspond perfectly
with Spark partitions.
So let's actually
see what happened if
I'm running this on
Spark partitions.
I have my original
data over here, right?
And all of this data if its
process is going to
be on some machines.
I have two machines.
Maybe the first one
has two partitions.
Other one has two partitions.
And I can see how
my original data
just arbitrarily split up there.
I still have to bring
all the As together,
all the Bs together
if I want to do it.
But if there's like
1 million different
values in the x column,
I definitely don't want 1
million Spark partitions.
If I have 1 million
spark partitions,
I have 1 million tasks,
and it will take forever.
I want to have a
fewer number of them.
And so what we will do
is a little bit more
flexible, right?
All the As will go to
the same partition,
and so on and so forth,
but it's fine to
have a partition
with different x
values in it, right?
I have a partition
down here that has
both a C and a D value in it.
So that's what we'll
do. And so first,
we're going to shuffle
all the data around to
get related data in
the same partition.
Even though unrelated data
might be also in
the same partition,
and then I can do aggregates
for each of these, right?
Some of these, if there's
just one unique value in it,
I'll have one row out.
This other sparked partition
at the bottom, right?
There is two unique
values. I'll get two rosa.
The most important
thing is I don't
split as across
different partition.
I can never split anything.
This also might mean that
the partitions might
not be nicely,
evenly sized like
they were originally.
Be maybe two thirds of my
data set is As, too bad.
I have a giant partition
with all A. Alright.
So how will I process this now?
At the very end, right,
all these transformations
at the very end,
I have some action where I could
actually get some results back.
Maybe that's a file
written somewhere,
a panos data frame.
So we've seen three different
kinds of things, right?
I have an action. That's
one type of operation.
Then I have two kinds
of transformations.
Remember, everything is an
action or transformation.
We talked before how
transformations come in two types.
Wide means that this time
that many to many
between partitions.
Narrow means it's one to one.
And so that's important
to keep in mind
because when I have the
wide transformation,
at least some of
these things are
transfers between
different machines.
That's network io.
That's expensive.
We also see there's
two different kinds
of partitions here.
In the first case, I have
normal partitioning,
which just kind of
arbitrarily broken up.
We're talking about why this
is called hash partitioning.
But in the second case,
we have hash partitioning
where we make sure that
all the same keys end
up in the same place.
Alright, cool. So
I'll break there.
We're going to come back next
time to talk about
how we can make
this picture faster
than it is now.
Have a fantastic weekend.