I hope you all had
a great weekend.
And so we're wrapping
up the content that
will happen before the mid term.
We have a mid term on Wednesday.
Hopefully, that's on
everybody's radar.
I've sent some announcements.
I've been talking
about it for a while,
but does anybody have any
last logistical questions
about the mid term on Wednesday?
What's that? Yeah,
everybody gets
18.5 by 11 edge sheet
of paper that you can
handwrite it on it.
You could print
spping out. Yeah, you
could put whatever
you want on the Pap,
but I saw other
questions over here.
Same thing. Yeah.
So start working on
your note sheet if
you have it already,
A. That's pretty helpful.
Cool. So one other quick
update is that I had had
a quiz on Huda as well it just
doesn't make sense to have a
term a quiz on the same day.
So I just pulled that
off shortly ago.
Cool. So we've been
learning about storage,
and we've seen how we can
store data and files directly.
We might want to put
it at a a format
like Park instead of CSP
depending on what we're doing.
But we aren't always
directly using files.
Sometimes we're putting
our data at a database,
which in turn stores
its data in the files.
There's lots of different
inds of databases,
so we want to talk about
how different ones
might be optimized for
different use cases,
how we might move data
between databases.
And then in the upcoming
lectures after the mid term,
is one where it really
gets interested.
We look at a lot of different
distributed systems
that have some very
clever approaches
to dealing with large data.
And to appreciate that,
I want to look at kind
of a traditional,
normal run of
the mill database and
that will be by squal.
So we spent a little bit
of time looking at by SQL.
Maybe some of you have even
used SQL databases before,
but I want to make sure
everybody has this point of
comparison like this is kind
of a traditional database.
So when we see something
a little bit unusual,
we can appreciate
that this database
is doing something a little
bit out of the Made stream.
Alright, os ever ahead over
here to where we were last time.
So last time we had ended by
doing some demos with Park.
And now we talk about databases.
So what do databases do?
Well, they store a collection
of different tables.
Instead of a park file
that has one table.
A database might have a bunch of
different tables that
I'm showing here.
Itty to fight a schema
for each of these.
Schema is just a fatsy word
for what are my column
names of the types on them?
So, for example, over here,
I might say that, you know,
amount is an rate is afloat,
right where we have
types for all of those.
Databases will often make heavy
use of what we call keys.
Keys could be numbers
or something else.
But these can help us
relate our tables together.
So, for example, when I
look at the first load,
this load table down here,
I see the state ID is two,
and I could look that up in
the upper table up there and
see, Oh, that's Alaska, right?
We can do a special
operation called
the oid to basically
resolve those state IDs
to actual state names.
We're go would be
talking a lot more about
Joys and how to do
them efficiently.
So in addition to storing
all this data for us and
all this information,
databases usually give
us a way to do queries.
Queries could be just
questions about the data.
So I could say, for example,
what is the name of the state
with WI as an abbreviation?
That's a query. It's a question.
Maybe a little bit strangely,
we also use the
word query to refer
to changes to our data.
So, for example, let's
say that Puerto Rico
became a state,
we would have to
modify this table.
We could do a query that
would ask the database to
insert Puerto Rico into
the state's table, right?
So we can make these changes.
Now, These queries I
put here are just in
a natural language,
but they're often in some
kind of query language,
almost in some ways,
similar to a
programming language.
And by far, it's not
the only one out there,
but by far, the most
common one is SQL.
We pronounce that SQL.
And in SQL, can let us ask
questions about the data
using select statement,
so we can select specific data
from our tables to
answer questions.
Or we can also have SQL
queries that modify the data,
they might insert, update,
delete, so on, so
on and so forth.
So we learning a little
bit about SQL today,
and develop a contrast.
Where we learned
about Cassandra.
Casandra has a slightly
different query language
called CQL, instead of SQL.
And so I want to
have this basline of
comparison for where we look
at these different systems.
Now, one of the
things that's really
interesting about SQL is that
it's good for both transaction
processing and
analytics process.
We talked a little bit
about that last time.
When we're doing
transaction processing,
we might be inserting some rows,
looking up rows,
things like that.
When we're doing analytics,
we're trying to answer usually
questions about all
the data in a column.
So we would be
looking at more SQL,
but I just have some example
SQL statements here.
So I can select the average
interest rate from the loans.
That would be an
analytics operation.
I probably look at
that whole column,
or maybe I have
something that it's like
a database backing,
some application that's
actually letting
people apply for loads
and things like that.
In that case, maybe I might
look up a specific load where
an idea is something or I
might insert some rosen.
That'd be transaction
processing.
So it's kind of cool that we
have one language that works
quite well for both
Adalytics processing
and transaction processing.
Now, just because the language
works well for both does not
mean that databases are
going to be good at both.
Any particular database will
probably be good at
one or the other,
but at least the language is
a unified language that
works well in both cases.
Alright, so let's talk a little
about database architecture.
What is architecture in
the context of systems?
When you build systems, usually
there's lots of
different parts to it.
So Architecture is the
big picture of view
where we see how these different
parts that are act
with each other.
Architecture doesn't
really think about
internally in detail how
these different parts work.
And so, you know, I just grabbed
a random database book and
looked at the architecture
picture here,
which I'm showing And
there's different components
that are interacting.
And what's cool about this
is that we've learned
about a bunch of different
resources so far.
Storage memory
network and compute,
and all these things are in
play in databases, right?
Databases have to interact
with all these resources.
So, for example, there might be
an access methods portion
of the database that
actually stores the data in
files or on disk in subway,
and then provides
access to it, right?
So we have to think
about storage there.
They have a buffer manager,
which provides some type of
caching, maybe an LRU ca,
maybe somebody else, but
it's going to be doing
a lot of the memory
stuff that we
talked about in
the caching there.
Oftentimes, we'll
have a database on
one location and a
client somewhere else.
And so they're communicating
over the network.
When you're playing a database,
you're probably thinking
about ports and
all that stuff we've been
thinking about with.
Networking. And then finally,
to answer any
question about data,
you probably have to do some
type of computation over it.
So all these different resources
that we've been talking
about come to play.
Databases and really
any distributed
serious distributed
system we might look at.
Alright, so we have
those databases,
and we could choose to give
our data in one of those
databases and say,
store my data for
me, or we could
choose to directly put
our data in some files.
And one of the things I want
you to walk away with is
a sense of the trade offs
between those so you
can pack, right?
If you have some data,
or you put it in
a database or put in
a file somewhere.
And I think the Spark book here,
loading Spark that
we're going to
be reading more or later,
has a really nice
comparison between these.
When I have a database
that's directly creating
the files for me,
what they can choose to do is co
design the database layout
and the query edge, right?
They can try to make choices.
If my query engine wants to
have some p of optimization,
maybe I can store my data in
a slightly different format
to make that faster.
Right? If you build
two systems together,
they often interact and
behave faster than if they
were designed separately.
So that's one advantage of that.
One of the disadvantages of
store all your data
to database is that
doing queries on our data is not
the only thing we want to do.
Right? There's this
whole ecosystem
of all kinds of different tools,
maybe there's machine
learning tools, whatever,
and we want to use
those tools to take
advantage of this
data as well, right?
So if I put all my
data in the database
and then I want to trade a
machine learning model on it,
I probably have to do
a query that will dump
out all the data somewhere else.
So that would be a lot slower
than directly access the data.
So the other way people
might do things is
you might store your data
directly in park files,
and you could build
some kind of query
engine on top of that.
It wouldn't be as
slightly integrated.
I'd probably be slower.
But then if I do some machine
learning thing or
something like that,
I could directly access
that data there.
Alright, cool. So we see there's
different ways we might
want to start data.
Sometimes you might want to
get the best of both worlds.
So so may be talking
about that as well.
In particular, if
we have some data,
we often will want to do
a mix of both analytics.
Maybe I want to select the
average value on a column,
and transactions kind of
on this row by row basis.
Even though SQL works
both great for both,
any given database
tends to optimize
for either one or the
other of these use cases.
There are special names for
these different categories.
Of databases, right?
Dates are OLTP and OLAP,
and that T and A are the
most interesting letters of
these acronyms because that's
transaction and analytics,
P is processing and
OL BDs online, right?
So people will say, OLTP
database, OLAP database. Right?
You're really looking for
that third letter to
figure out what it's
actually doing in
transaction or analytics.
That's important,
right? Because if
you're doing a lot
of analytics and you
throw all your data at a
transaction processing database.
For example, today, we're
going to be learning
about b equal.
If you throw all your
data on bequal databases,
then you're doing
this analytics,
that's not going to give you
the best possible performance.
You'd want to put it
in something that's
actually good at analytics.
And how will these
databases optimize for it?
Well, we saw last time that
when you have a storage format,
we often have these tables.
Tables are two dimensional,
but when you store your
data on desk, right?
It's all one dimensional, right?
I could start data
at offset one,
two, three, four, right?
It's very one dimensional disk,
even though I have this
two dimensional thing.
And so I have to decide.
What is consecutive disk?
Do I put rows consecutive?
That'd be a row oriented
format or Columns consecutive.
I'd be a colobated
format, right?
So databases, right? They be
deciding down here,
what they do?
If it's an OLTP database,
they probably have some
ro oriented format.
If it's an AP database,
they probably have some kind
of colobiated format, right?
You have to choose the
right database for
the right job. All right.
Now, here's a very
common situation.
Let's say you're some
kind of big company,
and I grabbed this example
straight from this book,
which is excellent, by the way.
You probably actually
have lots of
different databases going on
for different applications.
So for example, maybe I
have an E commerce website,
and that I can take orders on,
and I will have some kind of
OLTP database for that, right?
If somebody places an order,
that's probably inserting
some rows in the database,
representing that order, right?
So I might do that.
You know, I might have
some warehouse to keep
stock of things, right?
So maybe I have a
separate database
related to a separate
app inventory.
Maybe that has different users.
Maybe I have some kind of
special geographic
database that keeps track
of where my vehicles are and
plans routes for them
and things like that,
that would have different users.
Right? If you're a
large corporation
or any kind of large entity,
you have lots of
different databases for
different purposes and for
different applications, right?
And that all works great until
the data analyst comes along.
The data analyst probably
wants to do things, like, see,
I don't know, when people are
ordering things together,
can they be delivered
together or
kind of asked more complicated
questions like that?
A lot of those questions,
one would really spa
the data across different
kinds of databases, right?
And two, It's not great
for them to use those OLTP
databases because they're not
designed for somebody to come
along and do these
queries over every call.
Right? Sobody comes along
who does that query,
and all of a sudden the database
is really slow for doing
the transaction processing
because it's doing
this giant operation
that's not good for that.
And so what we'll typically
do these organizations do is
they'll actually have
multiple copies of
their data in different
places, right?
They'll have
all these different OLTP
databases somewhere.
And then they'll
have what they call
a data warehouse somewhere else.
And the data warehouse
is an OAP database.
And what they're going to do is
they're going to be
constantly pulling
new data from each of
the OLTP databases,
changing the format, and dumping
it into that App database.
And once they have
it there, then
a business analyst can come
along and do queries
efficiently on data
across different places,
and they're going to have
their calibre human format,
but everything will
be fantastic, right?
So there's some
people who are using
these OLAP databases.
There's another kind of job
that I think a lot of
us might don't get,
kind of a data engineering
job where we have to worry
about the data from
point A to point B.
And so what that person
might do is they might
be writing different kinds
of transformation code
that pulled out the
change data from
these different
OLTP databases and
load it into this giant
data warehouse for us.
And of course, there's always
a new data B generated.
So maybe this happens on some
schedule or maybe you have
some more clever thing
that's happening
continuously, right?
But there's all these
data engineering jobs
where people have to
get the data into
this data warehouse so somebody
can actually start doing
analytics and answering
questions about the data, right?
Any questions about this picture
that is so very important to
us and what organizations
do at their data?
Yeah, right here.
Slide. Oh, the photos
out of the slides.
That's kind of strange.
Oh, I export the Rog?
Okay. I'll just
export this quick.
Maybe I exported to
the Rog directory.
Well, it's there.
Yeah. Hopefully at a
few seconds that sake.
Otherwise, I'll just have
to do it after a lecture.
Yeah. All other
questions people have.
All right. Cool. So
that was a big picture.
Let's start looking at
an example of an OLTP
database in more detail.
And see the different
kinds of things
that it does, in particular,
we'll be looking at
the BEQ database,
which is widely used.
I have a few goals today.
I want you to be able
to go and create
a BEQL database and
specify Skibas with
different types and
different keys
relating to the data.
We're going to introduce this
new idea of transaction.
I'm using transaction here.
In a slightly different
way that I've been
using it, you know,
just minutes ago, where
I learned about what
this other media of
transaction is and how
we can use it to group
together updates.
And then finally, I wanted
to be able to go and write
queries that answer
questions about the data.
We do those queries on Mic
eQL for the sake of example.
But a lot of the queries
I'm doing would actually
be faster if they were
on an AP database.
Alright, so first,
let's talk about how
we can create a design tables.
And when you're creating tables,
there's this data
modeling question.
Data modeling says that if
we have some information,
some data, how do we actually
represent it somewhere?
Data modeling is
something that can
happen at a high
level or a low level.
We've actually seen the
low level a little bit.
Right if I have some data,
let's have some numbers, right?
And I want to send
them over. A network.
How would I represent that? I
could use protocol buffers,
which would represent
it one way.
And I do very blith tolling.
You can imagine I could
put my data an arrow,
and I could send that
over the network as well.
There's different
ways I could take
the same data and represented.
They have different
trade offs, right?
I could represent my data as
some text based
JSON file, right?
That's a low level low level
data modeling question.
Usually, when people are
talking about data modeling,
they're more often talk
about the high level,
which is if I have
some kind of database
that has different
information about things,
people or events or whatever,
how can I represent
these different things as
rows at a table, right?
So, for example, one
way I could do it
is if there are people
ordering books, right?
I could have a table orders
and I could put for each order,
I could put the
information about there.
Le who ordered it the
book and stuff like that.
But there's different
ways I could represent
that same information instead
of just having this one table.
So, for example, another option,
Is that I could say,
I want to avoid the
duplication here, right?
I have Dade County in
Wisconsin, a lot of places.
What I could do is I could have
a separate table of
counties, right?
And each county
could have an ID,
and I have the county
name and the state name.
And then what I would
do is my table orders,
instead of having
those two columns,
I would just have a
county ID that refers
from the first table
to the second table.
Right? The vocabulary I
would use for that is
I would say in the
table counties,
I have a primary key called ID
that it uniquely
identifies each county.
And in my table orders,
I have a foreign key that
refers to that primary key
it's like a reference
or a pointer.
There's
whatever programing language
you're familiar with.
There's some analogy there,
right where we have variables
referring to some data, right?
Now, If you go take
a data base course,
there's some theory around this,
and you'll learn that theory.
I'm t you do a lot of detail.
But one of the
words I want you to
walk away with is normalize.
What I'll say is that
the second version is
more normalized, right?
When I squeeze the
duplication out of
my data, it's more normalized.
They have kind of
der definitions
of different levels
of normalization.
We don't need to know that at
this level of this course.
But if I showed
you both of these,
I'd expect you to
identify the second,
what is the database layout
that's more normalized.
So, this idea of
normalization, right?
I have different layouts,
I have to choose.
And you can see I can
even normalize more.
Right? Maybe I have
table counties is
referring to separate
state things.
I have lots of
different choices.
There's some trade offs
here. What is that?
We can avoid
inconsistencies, right?
Like, for whatever
reason, let's say,
the name of county or a
state changed, right?
I just if it's very normalized,
I can change that in one place,
basically, it looks as if it's
changed everywhere, right?
Whereas the kind of
the de normalized case
where I was like,
copying the county
name in every place.
If I change that, then I
all of a sudden have to go
update a lot of
different things, right?
So we can avoid inconsistencies.
Change of the real world might
lead to fewer change
of the database.
That's often faster. I often
save some space, right?
I repeating those
strikes all the time.
So normalization has
a lot of benefits
and most people
encourage norbalization.
But there's cases where you
actually don't want
normalized data, right?
So Oftentimes, queries are slow,
right instead of having
all my data in one place.
Well, I have to
access this table,
then the database agent
also has to go figure
out the corresponding rows
in some other table, right?
It might also not be good from
the perspective of
historical data.
So, for example,
here, you can see,
let's say I bought a couple of
books under the
name Tyler Harder.
Then after I got married,
I changed my name to
Tyler Carraza Harder.
And at some point,
I changed my name,
and When I'm looking
over the old data,
what do I want to see?
Do I want to see my current
name on old orders?
Or do I want to see my name
at the time on those orders?
Right? For a lot of things,
like let's say I want to,
you know, let's have
invoices, right?
I should be able to
produce an invoice
based on a query of my data.
And it would be kind of
strange if I produced
that invoice,
and I brought a query a
in later the invoice.
Hey, so for historical reasons,
you might not want to
normalize your data.
So there's different
trade offs here, right?
Oftentimes, we
were talking about
how we have some OLTP databases.
Often those databases will
be highly normalized, right?
Because you want to keep
your data consistent.
But then in the OApp database,
in your data warehouse,
they might denormalize it
because there you care
more about speed,
and you are so worried
about keeping your data
consistent because that's a
downstream database, right?
If somehow things get messed up,
I could delete that
App database and
regenerate it from the data
by OLTP databases, right?
So how we normalize our things.
Well, it might depend on which
database you're working on
and what your goals
are, right? All right.
Any questions about
normalization or how that
fits in with different
kinds of databases?
All right. Cool. So we're
going to talk about
transactions now.
And transactions has two
different definitions.
I'm just going to recall
the definition I've
been using so far.
That is really in contrast
to analytics, right?
Adalytic is computation
over columns.
Transaction is
really row by row.
That's one met of
transactions, right?
It means access pattern.
There's a second met also
used in the context
of databases,
and it refers to
what guarantees does
the database give me
if I'm trying to make
multiple changes
at the same time.
And excuse me, a
traditional database
will typically give us what we
call acid properties
or acid transactions.
That stands for ACID, atomicity,
consistency, isolation,
and durability, right?
So traditional databases give
us all these strong guarantees.
And it's important to
think about what those are
because when we
see all databases,
they might say, Oh, this
is a no SQL database.
What does that
mean? L O means no,
but also means not only.
So no SQL means
not only SQL now.
Istad of a very broad term.
Usually when people say, Oh,
I made this kind of non
traditional, no SQL database,
usually they're
weakening the gartes
here at some point, right?
So maybe you want them
to tell you, right?
Okay, here's the
database we use.
They might say,
Oh, it's not acid.
It's just ACI.
There's no durability or
something like that, right?
You want to know what
exactly they're diving.
Right? It's very
important to think about
these different terms. So we
Figure out, Okay,
it's not just no SQL,
but what is special
about this database?
They're probably
sacrificing some of
these things in order to
have some other property.
Maybe it's more scalable
or it's faster.
Right? We might give up some of
these guarantees to
get some other things.
Alright, so what exactly are
these guarantees giving us?
These guarantees
are helping us do
multiple updates a lot
like we did with Locking.
When we did locking, we
would have to identify
these prinal sections where
maybe I'm trying to
do a bank transfer,
and I want to make
sure that everything
happens or nothing happens.
And Database people use
these words in similar,
but slightly different
ways than people use
when they're talking
about about locks, right?
So when we were
talking about locks,
we use the term atomicity.
Atomicity, that means that if
I'm making these two changes,
I want both or nothing, right?
I database bs, that idea of
atomicity actually gets
split into two concepts.
What is atomicity, and
what is isolation, right?
So database bs, atomicity means
that if I'm making
a bunch of changes,
and then for some reason,
it fails at the end.
I see I cannot make all
these changes successfully.
It should roll it back, right?
So atomicity database terms
means it's all or nothing,
but it doesn't really
guarantee that
other threads can't see
partial progress of
the middle, right?
So atomicity and database
terms is a little bit
weaker than adamicity,
when we were talking
about locks.
But atomicity and Database terms
is not the only concept we have.
We also have isolation, right?
So if I'm talking about
locks, I say it's atopic,
and then I start talking
about databases,
and I want equivalent
properties,
what that mean is that it's both
atomic and isolated, right?
So sight be all in the end
and isolated to mean that
somebody will not see
my partial progress in
the middle of that,
right? All right.
So we already see Atibcy before.
Now we're kind of
breaking that into
two smaller concepts,
which is database atibity
and database isolation.
We talked about
consistency before.
Which means the same
thing here, right?
Usually, there's some
rules about what type
of data makes sets, right?
And those rules are called
in variates, right?
That really depends on the
context what those bed.
But consistency for a
database means that
those in variates are
not broken, right?
So, for example, let me give
you think about like that.
Those earlier tables,
right when I had
table orders has a county ID,
referring to the county tables,
it would be inconsistent if
there was no such county
with that county ID, right?
If I'm referring to some
county ID and there's
no county with that ID that
doesn't make sense, right?
So that would be an example
of an invariant, right?
Every four and G refers to
a primary KE somewhere.
Databases can help enforce that.
And then finally, databases
guarantee of durability.
And what that means is
that all this stuff that
normally works also works if
my database crashes subtly.
If there's a power loss or
something like that, You know,
if my computer crashes
at a bad time,
I shouldn't see partial
updates, right?
So normal databases have
traditional databases are ready
to guarantee all these things.
No traditional, no SQL
databases may or may not
give us all of these things.
Do you have any questions
about any of these terms?
I realize the concepts
are confusing in
and of themselves,
and that it's even
more confusing
because different communities,
systems people or database
people use these terms slightly
differently even the
database community
transactions can mean
different things.
There's a lot of confusion
here. Does everybody have
any questions to get
all this straight?
A, right. Cool. Let's talk
a little bit about queries.
So when I write a SQL query,
it has this general structure.
I say something I
want to select.
And I'm going to say
up there specifically,
maybe something about columns or
what kind of analysis I want
to do on those columns and
I'll say f to indicate
a specific table or maybe
there's other things that
I can select from as well,
but let's just
imagine it's a table.
And then there's a bunch of
optional stuff after that.
Joy where group by Having
order by and limit.
And these will all transform
the data in some way, right?
So these are kind
of all clauses that
you should just throw
memorize and remember.
And the The structure
here of these queries is
a little bit misleading.
People have actually built
all their query languages
because this is misleading.
It throws off people
who are due to SQL.
Because, for the most
part, you can think of
these things happening
in some order.
But the select statement is
a little bit fuddy, right?
Some of the things
that are happening
with select kind of happened in
the middle of all the
data transformation.
So the picture that I
found is really helpful
to understand SQL
queries is right here.
What I imagine is that I
have some starting data.
And it flows through
all these different
transformations to
get some final result data.
And when you're
writing a SQL query,
any kind of sequL query you
write will correspond to
some variant on this
picture, right?
This one is kind of
like doing everything.
Usually, you might do two
or three different kinds
of transformations to get
your final adds, right?
You might have a
complicated query
that does all the things.
So let's just go through.
Oftentimes, I start
with multiple tables,
and so one of the things I
could do is I could join.
If I joined together, then
I'm ready get
basically something
that looks like a new table with
some columns from A and
some columns from B,
I might be doing that based
on this four and G to
primary K relationship
or something else.
A wear statement filters out
which rows I have, right?
So maybe two of these rows after
the wear are no longer there.
Excuse me. A group Pi pulls
together related data, right?
In this case, I see I have
four different groups of data.
A aggregate often works in
traduction with a group pi.
For each group, which
might have a few rows,
I might want to
just have one row
that summarizes
them in some way.
May be like average or sub or
cow or something like that.
That would be an
aggregate. I often do
these aggregates after
I do a group pi.
So I have all these
things out here.
After I have basically one
row summarizing each group,
I may not be interested
in all the groups.
And so I can have a
having statement that
eliminates some of
these summaries, right?
So having and we are actually
very similar, right?
Both of them are filtered down,
but the where would happen
before group by aggregate.
Having would happen after.
After I do that, I might want to
figure out these
different groups
I have what order I want them.
I could do it order
by statement.
And then finally, I might
want to say that I only
want to have the first two
results or something like that,
that would be a limit, right?
So when you write a query,
I want you to try to imagine
a picture like this,
maybe a sipiler picture if
you have a simpler query,
kind of imagine step by step,
all these
transformations that are
happening to your data.
That's make you better at
writing these sequel queries.
You have any questions
about this picture?
Yeah, right here.
That's an excellent question.
Tables have to be the same size
when you join them. They
don't have to, right?
So, for example, earlier,
I showed that I had a table
of all the counties, right?
And let's say I have
a successful business
that I might have like,
millions of orders, right,
and more and more orders.
Even though I've gave more
and more orders over time,
there are not new
counties being created,
right? That's relatively fixed.
Right? So it might be
that for each county,
there might be
something like hundreds
of different orders, right?
So in this case, I
might want to join
this giant table with a
smaller table of counties.
Does that make sense?
Yeah. Excellent question.
Yeah, all the questions
people have. All right.
Cool. Some to head over here.
I'm going to do some depos.
And you know, under resources
and lecture sipets,
we're very heavy
lecture sippe saves.
There's lot of
stuff I want to do.
Different questions, Suff I
don't want to do
is so much typing,
right as we won't
ever hit through
this. So there's a few things.
There's an environment
here that you have to
set up with some
Python packages.
And so on my computer, I'm
just going to do that.
Now, I already installed
all this stuff.
So I'm going to activate
my virtual environment.
And then after I have that,
then you would
install these things.
And then I have a Docker
run statement here,
which will be a copy and paste,
and we're going to
take a look at this.
So there's a lot of things here.
So the most supportt thing
is at the end, I
have the image dame.
So there's a Docker Hub,
there's an image called M SQL,
and if I run it for
the first time,
it would pull it for me,
I already have it pulled
so it'll be faster.
I may run in the background.
That's the detached mode.
I may say I can only
have 1 gigabyte of
memory used for this conator.
Inside of the Cttor,
the bic equal database
is at to be a server,
and it'll be listed
on port 3306.
And I may say that Port
33 o6b virtual machine
should forward to
3306 inside of there.
And that way, I could basically
run quote out of the side of
the Cttor and access
this the database.
What else do I have?
E stands for
environment variable,
and I'm telling the
database that M equal,
I wanted to create a
database called CS 544.
It's totally possible to have
one database server that has
different databases
edit that it adages.
This one is just to
have this server.
Database server, we'll
have one database,
which is CS 544.
And then I'm to put
a password on it,
which is ABC, terrible
password, I know,
but you can't access
my database because it's
list of the odd local host,
plus I have a firewall, right?
So even though it's
terrible password,
nobody will be able
to get access to
this database unless they're
already on my machine,
and at that point,
I'm kind of out
of bluck anyway. Right?
I'm to go and I run that
database. It start up.
And that's all fighted well.
And then what I might
want to do is I might
want to jump inside of it
so I can run some queries.
I may say Doc Exact IT.
T let me do Doctor PS
and find the name of it.
And say a copy of
my container name,
and I want to get a
bash session inside.
I'm inside of the
container where
my MicQal database is running.
I could run the bicquL command
here to be able to
interact with it.
And when I do that,
I want to say what database
I'm connecting to.
So CS 544, and
I want to tell it to
ask me for a password,
which is ABC, and great.
So I have a client now inside of
the container where my
database server is running,
and I could do things like say,
like, show tables, which
they may be done, right?
I don't have any
tables traded yet,
but I have an
environment where I can
jump in and start
running queries.
Alright, so what
I'm gonna do now is
I'm going to head
back over here.
SSH Do Window.
Alright. And let me just
clean that up a little bit.
I'm go into F 24
Lecture 15. Here I am.
And I'm going to activate
that environment again.
And what I'm go to do now
is I may start Jupiter.
So Jupiter lab is
going to be running
outside of my container, right?
I'm to say Python
three, Jupiter lab.
And I don't want it to
start a browser for me.
Somebody say no browser
because it doesn't make
sense to have a browser
by virtual machine.
I want to be able
to see it anyway.
So I'd be to run that thing.
And then the idea
is, I made sure
we can write SQL code inside of
Jupiter lab that's to
access data inside
of that database.
And so I see here
that I have a URL.
I can copy, right to open
this up. May come over here.
And this will not
work for BB this
is local host on my laptop.
And so what I have
to do now is I
have to set up an SSH tunnel.
And I may do local host 8888,
my laptop going to the
same the virtual machine,
right? So I may do that.
Great. So I have a lot of
things set up. I'm
ready to roll.
I have a database there.
I have all my prep
work from last slight.
I'm a to make a
new notebook now.
I'm ready to roll write
my databases there,
I should be able to start query
it from PADs, right?
That's my goal.
All right. And so what I will
do is I will come back to
these lecture snippets.
And there's this tool
called SQL Alchemy,
and where use SQL Alka to
connect to the b squal database.
And SQL Alchemy is
pretty flexible.
It lets us have different
connection strings
that will specify what
type of database.
This is actually great because I
can write a bunch of code,
and assume doing any kind
of unusual kind of
quarter case equal stuff.
Maybe if I switch database,
I can just switch this
string here, right?
So from SQL Alchemy, I'm
creating this database engine.
It's my SQL. The
password is ABC.
It's my database servers
on this support,
and this is my database, right?
I can get a connection to
that database that's inside
of the container. Okay, cool.
How would I use that?
Well, I can say connection,
execute. Execute like that.
Then I can try to put
some straight here.
I let's say I want to see
somebody show tables.
I could do that. And I run in
trouble because they
might want to put
different things here.
I could have some kind
of more structured
description of a query.
In this case, I
want to just give
it some texts, so
I could do that.
I try to give me
some results back.
In this case, it's something
I could loop over.
I might just convert to a list,
and there's no tables.
No surprise. I haven't
created any tables yet.
But this is how I could write
some Python code that runs SQL
queries on my my SQL
database inside of a contor.
I can get all these
pieces working
together. Alright, cool.
So what I'm go to do now is
I'm going to look at
this description of
a table and see if I can write
a SQL query to create
that table for me.
Right? So I have a multi
lie straight here.
I often do that, so
the SQL statement
is just out of line by itself.
And I have the general
structure to create
table something and then
something in parentheses,
and then I have a
description up here
of the table I want
to create, right?
So I want the table
name to be users.
I'm put users as a
table name here.
And then the columns I want
to have are ID name and FOD.
So I'm put that here, right?
So I'm set up now
where I can have
a three column table
in my database.
And when I do that, I
actually have to put types.
Remember that types are
part of the Schema.
And so I have to
put the type name
after each field, right?
Somebody say that
ID is an integer,
Nab will be a string,
and pod will also be
a string. Okay, cool.
So far so good. I have some
other requirements here.
Dab is required.
And so the way I will
do that is I will say,
I will say, No
null on it, right?
So I could say, after this,
I could say dull.
All right. Cool. I
get ahead of myself.
I think I kind of did right?
I think that Oh, well,
it's not important. We
do it in either order.
And the thing it
says that is that
ID should uniquely
identify the row.
The way I'll do that is
I will say primary key,
Oh, there are my notes.
Sorry. I just trying to get
a little lost of my notes.
I can say primary
key over here that
I say what column that is.
And so I just don't want to
throw people off, right?
There's still three
columns here.
And this is just adding
of extra information.
I'm saying that that ID
should be by primary key.
So I read that. And I read
a little bit of trouble.
I have an error.
Check the syntax
So I have issue here. All right.
Where did I go wrong?
Let's take a look at this.
You still need to use
like a single syntax side
listening es and
all when you're Oh,
no, you need to use the
semicol I actually don't,
so it won't hurt.
But let me just try to check.
Yeah. If other people
have other ideas,
feel free to shout it out,
right? So let me just check.
I I create table users ID.
Name. Oh, I'm sorry.
I think that instead of
straight the use tax,
s right? Okay, cool.
So I was able to
create that table.
Now, if I came back and
I said show tables,
I can actually see there's
a user's table there.
All right.
Cool. Any questions so far?
I've done a lot of stuff.
I've created this database
create a table there.
I want to make sure
about lose anybody.
Any questions so far. All right.
Cool. So that was
our first table.
What we want to do
now is I want to
have another table
that relates to it.
Somebody imagine
that were a bake.
And each of these users has
some number of bank accounts.
You might have like a
checking savings account.
It's not unusual to have
multiple accounts, right?
And somebody copy this out here,
and I want to have
another case now
where I am going to
have an account,
right each user can have
some bank accounts.
I'll call this accounts.
And what will we have here?
We have to say what user
ID is. We'll be a Editor.
That's going to refer
to this up here,
because I want to know the name
out of the account.
What else will I have?
I'm going to have a name
for the bank account.
And I say that can not be all.
I have a phone. Let me see.
I make my examples again.
I have an amount in the
bank account, right?
That will be an it,
and that will not
be ll, as well, right?
Okay, so the user has a name,
bank accounts have a name.
Bank accounts are
associated with users.
Bank accounts have
some number of
dollars in them. So I have that.
And then the other
part that I need to
add is I need to indicate
that this user ID down
here is actually referring
to this up here.
And then the
database is going to
help me to make
sure that I don't,
for example, have accounts that
nobody owes. Yeah,
question right here.
Whatever you're saying that
with the prior table is,
does it have to go an like right
after like the Yeah,
I'm not sure, actually, if it
cares about the orders.
Maybe I'll just try it.
Maybe I'll call this
like my test table.
You're saying, like, let me
do something like this,
just for convenience?
Yeah, looks like
that's allowed, too.
I was I normally
see it at the end.
Apparently, that's just
must just be convention.
They must allow you to
do other ways as well.
Yeah, great question. Yeah
the questions people have.
All right, C. So what I
want to do out here is I
want this user ID to
refer to the ID up here.
And so I could do that
using something called a
four and T. And so I'm going to
say four and G. And
then I have to say
what the key data is.
So it's user ID down here.
And then I have to say
what it references, right?
So straight a references.
And I cant ID because I
might have other tables.
I have to say users ID.
The ers users table,
there's this ID Club, and I
want to reference that.
I'll create that.
Now I should have two tables
up here. So that's looking good.
I guess I have that
test table, too,
which is all flighted well.
Okay. Let's insert
some data in here,
and I show you how
these primary and
four keys come into
play by having some
examples that will break.
And we'll think about why each
of them break in d, right?
So to come out here.
And I'm going to say,
first, I'm going
to insert in two.
And what we can say is table,
and what we do it here
is we say the columns,
and then we say values,
and then over here, we
have the values, right?
So I'm going to say,
I want to insert into
the ID column and the
name column up above.
What will I do? I want
to insert the values.
I'll say one and
Tyler. All right.
Cool. So I'm ready to do that.
And I run into some
sort of issue here.
These exceptions are
always pretty bad, right?
That at the very it it will
actually say something.
So you have an error
in your syntax.
Inserted into I ever say
by table day Baby Dot.
All right. Inserted into table
that I have to say
the table day, right?
So I'm a user.
That I have another issue.
If somebody just sees it,
feel free to shout out,
otherwise, we'll get there.
Inserted the table users
ID da, but the values.
But Oh, it's just Oh, I see.
You're saying I don't
say table. I just
say it start two users.
Alright. Oh, cool. Thank
you. Alright, great.
So we have a user there.
Excellent. Thank you
for catching that.
Let's say I try to
do it again, right?
If I run the same thing again,
I'll going an error because I
have a duplicate entry
for that, right?
So my primary key is
helping me vd issues.
I I had another user
with the same ID,
maybe somehow I might
think that they have
my bank account or have
access to it, right?
So maybe I'll just make
a note here, right?
Primary key Privet
duplicates. Okay?
That's cool. Let's see
what else we can do.
Let's create some bak accounts.
So those are users. Let's create
some bank accounts out here.
So insert into accounts.
These have to have some user ID
associated with them
and then some name.
As I'm say this
is bak account A.
And then what I can do
is I can actually put
multiple values
in here if I want
if I want to insert
multiple rows.
So I'm going to say B,
and I'll say two here.
So User one has bak account A.
User two has bak account
B. I try to prevent
that as well.
Let's see what it
says down here.
Oh, amount doesn't
have a default value.
Okay, so I have to have
it amount as well.
So let me see. So let me
put some values in here.
I'll say the first
account has $10.
Second account has $100.
Okay, so more errors.
To does not match.
Okay.
I'm trying to get show
like the error that I
actually care about.
I'm show you like every
other possible error.
Alright. Let's hopefully,
this is the error I wanted to
actually talk about. All right.
I cannot do it because
there's this contrait.
I have this four
and F K is a four,
it is reference to users.
I do not have a user two.
So try to help make sure
our database is consistent.
There's these variates.
If I have a four and
referencing something,
it's actually a reference
something. Yeah, right here.
What's that? Right. Yeah,
this could be in a
different order,
that it could match
it over here.
Which raises the
question, why do I
even have to specify these?
Well, I could have some values
that are optional, right?
Then I could say, I want to
specify it or I don't
want to specify it.
All right, I actually
want to insert this.
I'm going to do what, right?
And then I could insert that.
I should have some
good things there.
Now, let's say I want to
come along and I want
to delete my user.
I'm going to say delete from
users where ID equals one.
Let's try that. Get
another error down here,
which is, again, it's enforcing
that same constraint.
Right?
If I have bake accounts
referring to this user,
I better not delete that user,
I would have these
orphan bake accounts
that are not associated
with anything, right?
So this would break
consistency as well.
So these primary for Kezer
prevent us from making
a lot of kind of
common mistakes or kind of
ending up with bad
data in a lot of ways.
Alright, so this is
all fighted well.
So I could do things like now,
I could say, for example,
let's say I want to do I
may be looking at
more queries soon,
but one of the basic
queries you could do is
you could say select everything.
From some table, right? I
can say, from accounts,
for example, that maybe
I want to convert that
to a less, right?
More problems, e.
There we go. Alright.
Great. So I can go
and select that.
That's all fight,
well, let me show you
something that is a
little bit confusing.
I'm gonna come back over here,
and I'm gonna run that
where was I? Here I was.
I'm inside of my container.
I have the same
session over here.
I'm gonna run that
exact same query
that just gave me some results.
I'm run it, and I have to
put us in my call here.
And somehow I'm not seeing
any results there, right?
Why is that? Well, databases
give us these transactional
guarantees, right?
Like, the one that's in play
here is in isolation, right?
Isolation means that if I'm
making a bunch of changes,
Other transactions
or other users
shouldn't see those changes
until I'm all done.
They should either
see all or nothing.
That's the eye or
isolation and acid, right?
I can see it over here
because I'm the one
making the changes.
What I really have to do at
the very end here
is I have to say,
I want to commit
all these changes.
And that means I'm done
with all my changes,
and they're all going
to become visible.
At the same time to other users,
right now, they
can actually go in
and see all these things, right?
Sometimes when you're
interacting with the database,
it'll basically
say, each statement
is its own transactional.
It'll automatically
do it for you.
But if you're trying to do
more complicated things
where you want to
enforce things like say,
like, I'm doing a baking rat,
where I don't want any
account to go negative.
If you're doing stuff like that,
then you're a be writing
transactions and thinking about
transactions all the
time. All right.
Cool. Any questions so far?
L et's talk about
how we could get
a bunch of data
into our database.
So I mean, one way
is we going to
do a bunch of insert sits.
There are some
other ways as well.
So I'm just ready to
come back here and show
you this picture
of demos, right?
So in buy had,
I created a users and
a bank accounts table,
I use that for some examples.
I'm also going to have some
tables related to loads,
which will actually have
some serious data in them,
and I'm show how we can
upload all of that.
So come over here, and I have
some starter code
again for this.
And this is show you
how we can insert
a small table into
the database, right?
So let me just, Let me
grab this here first.
Alright. So I'm importing Pad.
Pads is reading
these CSV files from
the Internet that are
related to different loads.
So, for example,
I could have load
ID one means that the load
was actually created,
or there's different
ys of rejected.
And so what I could
do if I paste this d,
I'm using a pad statement
called two SQL.
When I do that, I can
say, well, what is
the table name I want to create?
What is the database
connection I can use?
I've been using a database
connection the whole time.
If there's already a table
there with that name,
do I want to replace
it? Yes, I do.
And Index means,
do I want to have
a column corresponding to
this? And I do not, right?
ID is really what is doing that?
I'm ready to do that,
and that actually
taken in pairs, right?
I guess in triples, right?
I read a table and
convert it to SQL.
I can have pads to
all these Cs forbi
then commit at the very
end. I'm ready to do that.
Let's tb over here.
I'm say show tables.
And I see it created
all these forbs.
So I can say select
star from actions,
and I can see that I was able to
automatically do this, right?
So you might be doing stuff like
this where you write
a little bit of code,
pulls data from one source,
dubs it into another
place, so you do
analysis it. Yeah,
question right here.
How do decide what
the. So in this case,
there's no primary key.
Right. There's no primary key.
Yep. I could, figure
out and pad this like,
how do I specify it, right?
Or there's ways to update
a table and add it later.
But at least for now,
there's no primary key.
Alright, well, so
we'll break there.
Drick on the mid term,
and we'll do more by
SQL after the mid term.
Have a great day.