About big query, and
we're to wrap it up.
That'll be about half a day.
And then we're a
little bit ahead.
So we'll also get to
start talking about how
we deploy things in the cloud.
I'm looking ahead
at the schedule.
You can see that we have pretty
much the worst exam time.
It's like the first
day at 7:45 A.M.
I'm just as sad about
that as you are.
I don't have any choice in it.
But anyway, we'll
get through it.
On that Wednesday, I'm to have
a lecture dedicated to review.
Best to be a student
driven section, right?
I'm a pet thing for that.
I'll be here. I'll put
off some old exams.
You could ask questions really
about anything that
might be on the exam.
You could, asked about
old exam questions,
specific topics, whatever
you think will help you?
Maybe old quizzes. And then we
might do a little bit of
that on Monday as well,
right if we finish early.
And so maybe come
with some questions.
If people have any questions,
we'll just have maybe
a shorter lecture
on Monday. I think
that would be fine.
It's really up to
you all. I think
that's the main
logistical stuff.
I just posted a bunch
more Aki flash cards.
I realize I forgot to post
them for a couple of days,
but those are all
posted through the end
of the semester now.
Do people have any
logistical questions
here at the end?
Yeah, right here.
By get set. Just one note sheet.
Yep. So evict some more
things, unfortunately.
Yep. Location. Yeah, I mean,
I guess I'll just like
do it as soon as I can.
They give me a few different
locations and it's
my job to divide you
up and tell you.
So, it's known.
It's just on me to tell you
before that actual day.
It's kind of over, like,
kind of like Charter Street
near the Math belly.
They give us a few
buildings there,
so it'll be in
that general area.
Yeah, other questions
people? Oh right.
Fantastic. So I'm going head
over here to the slides,
and we wrapped up last
time by finishing
machine learning.
And now I want to talk
about how we can do
cross management.
That's going to be the
last topic for Big query.
And If you're Google,
what you do is you
buy a bunch of
machines and those
machines have CPUs,
and they have RAM.
And rather than thinking
about as each
individual machine,
they kind of take a broader
picture of like, Okay,
I have a zone with a bunch of
CPUs and RAM in it, right?
And what's running
on those machines?
Well, the Dremel
query engine, right?
And Dremel is going to
use a lot of CPU and
memory to answer
questions about the data.
The data lives in ploss,
which remember resembles HDFS,
but is better and
more scalable, right?
So that's the setup
we're working with.
And so there's three
different types of
resources that we
could look at here.
We have the Compute
bebery resource.
We have Closs storage,
we have Clous IO.
And they actually have
different billing models
you can use with Big Query.
You could have a
capacity billing model
where you basically
reserve resources.
And when you do
that, then you get
compute and memory
and closa storage.
Those are things you pay for.
Upfront, but then any kind
of closus IO would be free.
On demand billing is what
we've been doing,
and in that case,
computer memory is free,
but we pay for Closss
storage and Closss IO.
And this is kind of a common
pattern in billing models.
They might have different modes
that kind of fit
different needs.
And they don't want to make
every billing model so
complicated, right?
Any kind of system. There's
so many different kinds
of resources you might be using.
What they'll often do is they'll
charge you for a subset of that,
and then something
else will be free.
And I'm putting free in quotes
because whatever
they charge you for,
they probably marked it up to
compensate for something
else else being free.
Okay, so you can pick
your billing model
and try and choose what you're
paying for based on that.
Now, they want to
take a little bit of
a simpler picture since they
are running when
they run dribble,
it needs to use both
compute and memory.
And so rather than trate
each give a machine,
you kind of squint at it, and
they break it up into
what we call a slot.
So a slot is about one half of
a CPU core and 1
gigabyte of RAM, right?
So a slot is the unit in
which we're going to
be allocating stuff.
And this is approximate because,
you know, as they
add new servers,
they might have different CPU
memory ratios or, you know,
if they were giving you
like a half a core and
then they get a new
server with faster CPUs,
maybe it's like 45% of a core.
It's kind of approximate, right?
But they have all these slots,
and that's what they're
going to either sell or use.
Okay, so there's
2 billion models.
Remember, the first one
is the capacity pricing,
and that's where we pay
for computed memory.
So in that case, what you are
renting are slots, right?
You pay to reserve slots,
and it's about last time I
checked about $0.96 per day,
a little less than $1 per
day to rent a slot. And
it's reserved, right?
So that means whether or
not you're actually
using it for anything,
you pay that flat rate.
Now, when you reserve it,
you aren't really
reserving it in
a specific location
because with big query,
I have all this colossus data,
and it could be in different
places around the world,
and when they're
running the query,
they want to run it
near where the data is,
and I might be using
some queries that are
near some data or other queries
that are near other data,
or I could be doing a query that
is maybe joining tables in
two different places, right?
And so anyway, I've
reserved these slots,
but then they'll
decide when I need it,
where it actually runs and
they'll kind of put it
close to the data to the extent
that they're able to, right?
I've reserved these
slots somewhere, right?
Now, I want to think about
the cost of these things, right?
So an e two medium is kind
of close to $1 a day, right?
E two medium is what we use for
the second half of the semester.
Now an E two medium has
twice as much CPU as
a slot and it has four times
as much memory, right?
Okay. So what we're seeing
here is that Big query,
we're paying a lot
more for computed
memory than we would with VMs.
And that goes back to that
point I made earlier about
infrastructure as a service
versus platform as a service.
Infrastructure as a service,
you have to install stuff
and manage it yourself,
and that tends to be
cheaper as a result.
You have to be more
skilled to use it,
and there's more
competition because
it kind of looks the
same across clouds.
Whenever you have a
platform as a service,
like, you know, big query,
They're going to market
up perhaps substantially,
right? That's what
we're seeing here.
To be fair, right? There's also
giving us free class
SIO in the mix,
but I'm guessing that
that would be less
valuable than these compute
resources. Alright, cool.
So we're looking at
this, and right now we
have customer one
on the top left,
and they have four
slots reserved up here.
They're using two
of them right now.
This other one, I guess, has
some slots across a couple
of different zones,
and they're also using
a subset of them.
Okay. And so when I
look at this picture,
I see that there's excess
capacity for two reasons.
One, maybe nobody
paid to reserve it.
Or two, maybe
somebody reserved it,
but they're not using it
at the moment, right?
Maybe the data scientists
are at home sleeping, right?
And there's nothing running
on big query, right?
And so the second billing model,
the on demand model is
where they basically try to
sell this excess capacity
in some way, right?
So for this second
billing model,
the on demand model, what
they'll do is they'll
charge you a little
bit differently.
They're going to
charge you for ClosIO.
And after the free tier is done,
that might be something
like, $6 per tapyte.
Okay. Well, what's
cool is that all these
slots that they use to
execute on that data,
they actually just give that
to you for free, right?
Sometimes it was like leftover
from Billing bottle one.
So they'll just tribute to you.
And that's actually
very powerful.
I'll kind of how much resources
you get varies by
the time of day,
but for a single query,
they'll give you up to 2000
slots. A slot is half a core.
So they're giving you
potentially 1,000
cores for free if you're
running at the right time.
Now, This capacity that
they're giving you for
the on demand model
is perhaps leftover from
the reserved model,
the capacity model.
And so if somebody who reserved
that only want to
start using it,
and they were letting
somebody else run their job,
they need to interrupt the
on demand job so they can
give those resources to whoever
actually reserved that.
And so what we'll say
is that these tasks
that run on these
slots are preemptable.
Preemptable means that
I can start running it,
and then I am capable
of interrupting
it before it finishes
running, right?
That's the main case,
right? I'm going to
preempt a slot if somebody
actually reserve it.
I'll take it away
from somebody who's
just kind of getting
the spare capacity.
The other situation is
that maybe I have lots of
spare capacity and somebody's
like using all of it,
and then somebody else runs
a second on demand job.
They'll want to try to
share those slots fairly,
so they might preempt some of
those slots and hand
them over, right?
So really the on demand one,
sometimes it's great, but
it's really a best
effort, right?
Sometimes it's fast,
sometimes it's slow.
It really depends on what's
happening at the moment.
Now, when it preempted,
it's really similar to as if
it crashed and restarted.
And so all the stuff
we talked about before
with item potents and retry
applies again, right?
Because if you get
preempted, then you
retry again later, right?
And so we want to make sure
that if I'm running
a big query job,
I'm not getting
duplicate output rows.
And unfortunately, they give
you exactly one semantics.
And that's because these
big query tasks are
atomic and also item potent.
So to compare this,
there's trade offs here, right?
And if you are using Big
query and a company,
you should be able to
kind of think about
the needs of the company and
make a recommendation here.
One is that capacity billing is
going to have very
predictable costs, right?
You just pay a flat
rate per month.
Very predictable
performance, too, right?
If you need to do something,
you get that compute
whenever you need it.
You have what you call the
first right of refusal.
That means I reserve the thing.
If I want it, I can use it.
I only goes to somebody
else if I refuse it.
You can get discounts
for that mode, right?
You kind of You're
a very predictable customer
because you're always
paid the same thing.
And if you agree to
do that for say,
like a year or multiple years,
give you a reduced
rate for it, right?
Now, there's some downsides
to capacity billing, right?
We pay when you are using
nothing, so that's not dread.
And it's hard to say, you know,
use 1,000 cores for a
short period of time.
Alright, so Ooma is
kind of the flip of it.
It's what we might call a
server less billing model
or a pay as you go,
a billing model or maybe a
pay for use billing model,
different terms people use.
And basically when you're
using nothing, then
you pay nothing,
which is fantastic
because for a lot of us,
most of the time, we're
not using it, right?
We use it, occasionally when I'm
saying in my computer,
working question right here.
Yeah. Oh, yeah.
So is it a problem if
the task is preempted?
It's a problem that
it'll take longer for
my self to run because it'll,
you know, eventually, right?
So imagine like I have,
like 100 tasks running,
and then they steal 50 away.
Well, I still will finish
those 50 and those 50 slots that
eventually my other
50 tasks that
got interrupted, we'll
get a chance to run.
So it's a performance problem,
but it's not a
correctness problem.
Yeah, thanks for asking.
Yeah other questions
people have. Yeah.
Free
Yeah,
A Bad slots are free.
And so pay as you go,
what are you pay for,
you're paid for
closss, Io, right?
And this is the second
what Oda Bad Billy is what
we all have been doing.
And so like what I
write a query, right?
I'm paying nothing until
I rated the what I rated.
I can see how many bites
I got billed for, right?
So I just try to pay at
the gradularity of
each query, right?
On demand is not fixed.
The terminology sometimes
flips in my head, too,
but the capacity billing
is where you have
this fixed cost.
And A Daad is that when
Ida did I pay for it?
Demand I don't pay for it.
Yeah. Like Ada Bad
feels like you would
have higher priority,
but Ada Bad is actually
lower priority. Pay for the.
That is. You pay by
the Terabyte, right?
And so with A D Bad Billy,
they have a free tier, right?
That's I made a
distinction here,
like between casi
Billy and Adama Billy.
That's a little bit
orthogonal to like
the free tier versus
paid tier tier.
Yeah, thanks for clarifying.
Add billing. It's cool.
Sometimes you get
a 100 s for free.
You have to be very
careful, though,
because it's totally possible
to write a query that
runs kind of fast and
maybe blows a $100, right?
We don't want to do
that. And so what I'm
talking about now is some
different strategies with
Adoma billing to avoid
that horrible situation,
right? What is that?
You could set limits or
quotas per day to say,
like, how many bytes
of IO will I do?
You know, the cost is directly
proportional to the byte,
so I can kind of indirectly
max out my daily cost.
They have this
cool configuration
you can do called a dry Rd.
If I have a query
and I pass a dry Rd,
it won't actually do anything,
it won't actually
build me anything,
but it'll estimate how
much it would cost
to do that query.
And the estimate I get is an
upper upper bound, right?
Oftentimes upper bound estimate
is exactly what it is,
trying to for simpler queries.
We're talking about
some optimizations
later that the dry Rd
has trouble estimating.
So there's some
cases where there's
a kind of a weird optimization.
The Dry Run doesn't know about
it, but when you run it,
it actually will be
cheaper than the estimate.
Given the estimates
aren't perfect,
another thing you could do is
when you start running it,
you just say, well, how
much am I willing to
pay to do this query?
You put a maximum on it for
that one individual query,
and they'll start running it.
They'll do the task,
and they see if
the kind of total cost
ticks up past that.
They'll just kill your job,
and they won't charge
you for anything.
Even though they did some
compute for a while.
Finally, they have these it's
almost like a view over,
kind of a metadata view over
all the queries I'm doing,
and I can see for
all these different
jobs I've submitted,
how much they are all costing.
So I have an organization,
I can draw and see,
who's racking up the big bills.
All right. Well, I'm going to
do a quick demo
for all of these.
So for the first one,
I'll just d row to
the Google Cloud
Cosle over here,
we'll actually see
that they have,
They have 17,000 different
quota limits I could do,
different kinds of services.
And even if it's
somebody a big query,
I could go and say
for specific regions,
I have different limits, right?
So kind of a complicated system.
You know, a common
taste where I've had to
adjust that is when
you're launching VMs,
usually, providers will
say you can launch
like three VMs or five VMs
or something like that.
And then if you want
to do a lot more,
well, they want to make
sure you're actually
going to pay, right?
So they don't want to just
be like casually do that.
You have to request,
like, can I increase it?
And then based on your
history with them,
they may or may not let
you launch more VMs,
right You know,
just an individual,
maybe they'll say,
Okay, you can do
ted or whatever be you asked.
You know, if you're
a big company who's been
paying the millions,
I'm sure they'll just
like trust you to do
whatever you you
want to do, right?
Okay. So we're just trying
to do this for big query.
And so I spent some time
before looking for it.
I'm just to search
for it query, usage.
Per day, and then I see that
I get this setting here.
And right now it's 1 terabyte,
and if I want to, I
can edit that, right?
So edit that quota.
And remember that like
1 terabyte might trust
me something like $6.
Let's say that I really
only want to pay
like $3 a day because I'm cheap,
right or worried about it.
So maybe I'll say, Hey,
let's max it out at
half a terabyte,
that'll be about $3 a day.
I can submit that, confirm,
and you know, if I
try to increase it,
they may or may
not let me do it.
But if I'm decreasing it,
you know, There's a lot
of good reason that
they would reject it.
Okay, great. So I did that
and now last time I say here.
Maybe some of you will do
that while you're working
on the project, if you like.
Alright, I'm a head over
here to my notebook,
where we've been
working last time.
And let me just do a
dry run of the query.
I'd to go back to last time.
And we have this
Counties data set.
Somb say where are the
counties somewhere here.
Let me just grab Grab
this query here.
I'm just tacking this stuff onto
the machine learning notebook,
so there's not
too many different
notebooks floating around.
Normally, we do a
big query like this,
but this convenience thing
doesn't let me
specify options like,
you know, do it as a dry
rod or stuff like that.
And so I may instead do this as
a big query like
this. All right.
And then I have to say job
fig equals something, right?
And so up here, I
may specify a K Fig,
which will be a big
query query Job Fig.
You saw last time
how we could put
caching options in
there, for example.
Here, one of the
options I could do
is whether or not it's
a dry run, right?
I'm go to create this Fig thing
and pass it in down here.
And you know what? First, let's
just select
everything from this,
right? I'm select everything.
From that. And this will return
to query objects for me.
Normally, I actually have
to get results back from
it before it'll tell me how much
it costs because it's a dry run.
It's not getting any results,
and I can just check
down here, right?
I'm going to say
Total bytes build.
And that will be zero
because I'm doing a dry run.
If I look at total
bytes processed,
It didn't actually
process anything,
but now this is an
estimate, right?
This is an upper bound
estimate on how much it is.
And so what is that?
I guess I'll divide
by 1024 squared, right?
So it's like an megabytes.
Let me just like print
that off as a string,
right so we can
easily see All right.
And maybe I'll just say
like megabytes here.
Alright, so that's
like 182 megabytes.
That's cool. What if I
try to limit it, right?
So instead of having all
the rows, I want like ten?
Well, it turns out
that that's the same
because it's a column
oriented format.
And so they aren't really
charging the less if
I touch fewer rows.
They're only charging the s
if I touch fewer columns, right?
So I could do that. Let me
try to look at some of
these other things.
I can check, for example,
like the county name.
Maybe I'll get every
single county name.
That's pretty cheap
because there's
not a lot of information
in there, right?
That's a relatively
small data set.
If I get the name of every
county in the United States,
The one that really gets me is
the county geometry
because there's where I
have the polygons that
specify all the borders,
and I can really see
that that's almost all
of my costs,
selecting everything.
You're selecting that
one is very similar.
And so what you want to
do is instead of being
somebody who just optimizes
stuff when it's slow,
you can play around with
this and you can
try to figure out,
well, which columns
are expensive.
If you're like filtering it
down before you select it,
you might copy that filtered
down data somewhere else,
so you don't have
such big big columns.
Yeah, question right here.
Select not select You mean,
like, a star minus something?
I'm not sure. I don't
know if there's any
SQL experts here.
I mean, is there
a way to do like
star minus something?
You are here?
My understanding
is that you don't
get billed for any dry run.
And I personally don't know
any way to do like
star minus something.
Yeah, other questions
people have. All right.
Cool. So that's one of
the things I can do.
You know, the other
thing I can do, right?
So again, this is
an upper bound.
So I might just want to try it,
but specify a limit that's
a little bit smaller.
And so I'm going to
copy this down here.
And in this case,
instead of doing a dry
run, what I will say is,
I have maximum bytes build,
and that will be 100
megabytes, right?
So 100 megabytes. And
then when I run this,
it won't actually do
anything at first.
I'm getting what's that?
Maximum good catch.
Max pretty horribly, actually.
Thanks. So I'm
trying to say none.
Q is none because it
doesn't set down until I
actually run the query.
It's not a dry run anymore, so I
actually have to get
the data somewhere.
I'm say data frame equals.
You know, I'm just trying
to put a limit here, right,
so that when I
eventually run it,
it's not going to
give me too much.
This is a geodata frame
right because it has
that column of
boundaries, right?
I'm say Q two Geodata frame.
Let me run that thing and I
get an internal server error,
which is good because
that error says
that this costs more than
you're willing to pay, right?
So that will not run.
What happens if I try
running it down here?
And this time, I'm going
to say, What did I do?
Did I actually not copy
that well? Let me copy it.
I think I pasted the
wrong thing. All right.
I think before it was something
like like it was like 180
megabytes, something.
So let's try 200.
In theory, this should
actually run now.
And so it's running for real.
And I see the estimate
before it was
actually quite accurate
is a simple query, right?
More complicated cases,
it might be an upper
bound. All right, cool.
Any questions about that
upper bound idea or
the maximum price
idea? All right.
Fantastic. So, what I want to
do now is I want to try to
figure out who is running
up my big big query costs.
And so I can do a
big query here.
And what I'm going to do is
I'm may select a star from,
and then there's a
special table they
create for me. It's my project.
And then within there, I
have to say which region.
And usually a region
is something like
US Central or US
West or whatever.
But in big query, you
can have it's almost
like a pseudo region that
encompass a bunch of them.
When I say a region, US,
it's like they decide where
it actually runs within the US.
So anyway, I want to see kind of
across the US where it goes.
And then there's information.
Schema jobs by by project,
to be able to just do
like a limit of ten.
And that will show
me like these ten
most recent jobs ore.
I can sometimes
I'm loading data,
sometimes I'm doing queries.
I can see, like,
Oh, that Tyler guy
keeps running up the big costs.
I'd better talk to
him. And so lots
of stuff here that I could do.
What I may do is I may
have sort it by a field,
which is a I guess
I can't see it yet,
but I'll just use
it from my notes.
You could figure it
out by digging around.
I may order by
total total bytes,
build, descending.
I'm with the most expensive
one first, right?
So do that. Then what I'll
do is I'll put that
in a data frame.
So My run that thing, and
then And then I have
that data frame.
And if I want to, I can say,
give me give me
the first row because
that's the one that's
most expensive.
I can see who did it if
I want to go talk to them
about what they're doing.
I can see lots of stuff in here,
like the total Bytes
build, I can see.
I can also see what Query
was actually done, right?
And so I'm going to print
some of those things off.
I'm going to print the
total bytes build.
And let's do megabytes.
Megabytes. Let me convert
that to Python float.
All right, you know,
about 300 megabytes
was my most expensive query.
And then I finally
want to see, well,
what was that query
actually doing, right?
So what was the expensive query?
And let me print it off
because it's a string.
I was selecting every single
road in the United States.
So that's surprisingly
that's a big data set,
it would be bigger than
the county boundaries
because there's more roads than
there are our edges
around counties.
Cool. So Those are
all my strategies for kind of
understanding how
you're being built.
Any questions about any
of that? All right, cool.
So let's talk about some
more advanced optimizations
that can reduce
the costs, right?
Costs get big when I
select a whole column and
that column is large or even
when I select a
part of the column.
And so what we might
sometimes want to do is
we might want to break
up a bigger table
into smaller tables or chunks
of tables that are
relatively independent.
One strategy for that
is called partitioning.
If I'm doing partitioning,
I choose a column,
and then every unique value in
that column goes to its own
separate little chunk, right?
So maybe I have May
1 data over here,
May 2 data over here.
I have all these
little partitions.
When I do a query,
there's different queries
I could do obviously.
And if I have a ware statement,
I could filter on
different things.
If I have a ware statement that
necessarily limits me
down to one chunk.
Like if I say where
the date equals May 1,
then they will automatically
only access those chunks.
They'll touch less data,
and they'll bill me less.
You can imagine that's a
little bit complicated?
I mean, I could say, what if
it's like May 1 or May 2,
or if I say, is it May 1,
and B is straighter
than three, right?
But they will do their best
to try to figure out that, hey,
they only have to
look at some of these
instead of looking at
all of them, right?
So when they do that, that's
going to save IO cost.
If I only have to touch
a subset of them,
and they'll save me money.
Now, it's a little
bit limited, right,
because I didn't really
do it for certain types,
like, you know, states.
I don't think it works
for strings, for example.
And it only really
works well if there's
a substantial amount of
data per partition, right?
If I just have a few rows
here and a few rows there,
then if I do a query over a
lot of these different dates,
it'll generate a
lot of random IO,
and it'll be a slow
expensive operation.
All right. Alternative
partitioning is called clustering.
When we do clustering, we
specify one or more
cluster columns,
what we're going to do is
sesort the data, right?
When I say semisot,
what it means is that
we'll have these chunks,
and each chunk will have a
mutually exclusive range.
So this chunk is first, it
contains one to one on B,
this chunk is xs four to ten.
This chunk is exits ten to ten.
Within here, it's
totally fine at
seven tums be fo
four or vice versa.
It's not sorted within a chunk.
It is sorted across chunk.
And clustering is
more flexible, right.
It works for all kinds of data.
They're trying to decide
how to chunk these things.
And so, in contrast to
partitioning, right?
If I search for exactly one day,
I know I'm not having
anything else here.
With clustering, maybe
different values
might end up in
the same chunk and I'll
end up paying more.
So it's a little bit
hard to reason about.
They might reshuffle
the data over time,
so the costs might
change over time.
This is something that
the dry run is trying
to have trouble
estimating, right?
But in general, it'll
be cheaper if we
can somehow look at a subset
of chunks instead
of all of them.
All right. Now, We've
mostly talked about
reading data for queries,
but big query can also
let you insert new rows.
And if I'm inserting
a bunch of rows with
different B values,
one of the problems in
this picture is that
I'll have to insert,
a row over in this truck
or roll over that truck.
I may have to do a
bunch of random writes.
Random writes are terrible.
They're bad for
hard drives because
hard drives actually have
to seek to these
different places.
They're also bad
for SSDs because
SSDs are broken to
these big blocks.
That have to be erased
altogether, right?
So if I'm kind of doing
all these small rights,
then it'll trigger eventually
garbage collection of the SSD,
the SSD will start having
slower performance, right?
So they don't want to
have random rights,
even though they have
the data clustered.
And so what they'll do is if I
have a bunch of new
data coming in,
rather than splitting it up
across all these chunks,
they will just write it all into
one place sequentially, right?
And that area is called
clustered data, right?
So having some amount
of clustered data means
that rights will be faster,
But now I have a problem.
Whenever I have a query, I can
look at it and I can figure out
which cluster chunks it rows to,
but any rows I'm interested
in could also be here, right?
So every single query
has to look at all of
the n cluster data
every single time.
Okay, so now we
have a trade off.
How big can we let the
unclustered data be?
If we let it be bigger,
our writes will be faster,
but it'll be slower to do
queries. If it's smaller.
Well, then our queries will
be cheap because we don't
ever have that data that's
part of every query,
but writes will be
more expensive?
I'm constantly pulling rows
of the unclustered area and
inserting them mostly randomly
to different places, right?
That's just like something
you'll see again
in systems, right? That
there's a trade off.
You can either optimize for
making reads fast
or writes fast.
Here, they just set some kind of
threshold on how much
can be unclustered.
And so they're trying to go
for a more balanced read
versus write approach.
Any question about
partitioning or clustering?
Yeah, right here. And the
strategy only works if
the clause would
include. Exactly.
Yep.
Yeah, it only helps if
we're kind of filtering
on Colm B. F other cases,
I'll end up having to
pay the whole price.
And that's part of this
cost estimation here.
You can't just look at the table
and say, Oh I'm going
to optimize it.
You have to say, Oh,
here's the table,
and here are the
queries I'm doing.
And here are the
expensive queries.
And if I cluster on this thing,
I can make this query
cheaper, right?
You can imagine that somebody
could be assigned as
a task to do, right?
Go figure out how to
make these things
cheaper and it's a
tricky job, right?
Yeah, good question.
Yeah there are
questions people have.
All right. Well, I just
wanted to do a couple
more demos over here.
Let's actually look at
that Roads data that we
saw that popping up
that was so expensive.
Somebody come over
here to the tonsil,
and big query is way
down here. Excuse me.
And I may search for
what is it called?
It is called Go Go US Roads.
And I'm may to look
at everything.
And I'm going to come
look at this over here.
And basically, they have
a bunch of different data
tables within this dataset.
I think these are broken
down by FIPS code, right?
I think that, you know,
like Wisconsin is state
55 for a FIPS code,
so we could look at
Wisconsin roads if we want.
What I'm going to do
now is I'm actually
look at all the roads,
which is in US National Roads.
Down here. I'm me
take a peek at this,
kind of a bigger dataset
than we've been
working with, right?
So it's like, you
know, 9 gigabytes.
And I see a couple of things.
What is that they partition
it by day? Okay, that's cool.
And then they also have
clustering enabled.
And rather than
clustering a one column,
they clustered on a few
different ones, right?
So you can imagine for each row,
I could have a tuple where
it's like, state name,
FIPS code, route, full name,
and then I would sort
based on those, right?
So, kind of first I'd sort
by state and so on and so forth.
And so what this
means is that if
I'm filtering to say Wisconsin,
then it'll be cheaper, right?
Because I don't have to look at
every cluster chunk, right?
It might not be as
cheap as partitioning,
though because I don't
know what the boundaries
are of these chunks.
Maybe if I search for Wisconsin,
it might be in a
chunk that also has
like Wyoming and Washington,
right I might end up
paying a little bit more.
Right? It's a little bit hard
to say how much I'll pay.
But I'll probably pay less
than I would otherwise.
What if I a filter data based
on a state's FIPS code?
Well, there's a one to
one correspondence
between state name
and States FIPS code?
So if I do State's FIPS
code, it will figure out,
while this chunk has
this range of FIPS code,
codes, which will be small,
that'll be fast too.
What if I want to get
a specific route type?
So, for example, you
know, they have, like,
made highways, they have,
like, service roads, whatever.
What if I want a
specific type of
road in Wisconsin? That
would be fast as well.
It's cluster on that, so
I can kind of get it to
one chunk or relatively
fewer chunks
of the cluster data.
That'd be fast.
What if I want all
of the service roads
across the whole country?
That would be slow. It's
part of the cluster key.
But since I sort
first on State Name,
and then later on
Route type, you know,
I'll be a little
bit of this chuck,
maybe like the Alabama
chuck over here,
and so on and
so I kind of like get little
pieces of each chuck.
I'll touch all the
chucks, and I'll have to
pay the full price, right?
So Route type, I can
only create for that
efficiently if I do it in
combination with a state name.
Right?
So you want to be able to
think about these
and then try to
reason about what will be
fast or what will be cheap.
Alright. Cool. L et
me head over here.
And I want to do a query
with a dry run of this.
So where was my dry
run from earlier?
I think it was Here's a dry run.
Let's do this one. And so
maybe what I will do is I'm
going to just say
select everything from.
Let me just check what
this thing is called.
There is its name.
Let's select everything
from that table.
It's a dry run. I just want to
see how how expensive it is.
Alright, so that's about 9
gigabytes of data, right?
So kind of bit more expensive,
but but not horrible, right?
What if I filter down and I say,
maybe where the state FIPS
code equals 55, right?
Still 9 gigabytes, right?
That should be faster and
cheaper because it's clustered,
but the dry run is bad
at estimating that.
It doesn't reason well
about clustering.
So this is the case I'm
actually go ahead and run it,
and so no dry run.
And So no job can figure either.
When I actually run this thing,
I won't be able to do
it until I have to
be I want to have total
bytes process until
I actually run it?
It's say query two
GO data frame,
and I'm going to put
that in DF like that.
These are lines,
right? Lines are
geographic data.
Let's run that thing.
It's going to take
a while, right?
It's kind of a bigger
query to be done.
But what I should expect is
that the total bytes process
is going to be less than
the estimate because we
have that cluster of the data.
Any question about
clustering while
that's running? Yeah, here.
Cinder to the cluster Yeah.
Yeah, can I explain the ordering
of it? Yeah, absolutely.
I think if you
specify a cluster,
you could imagine that you
could do a total sort
the data, right?
And when data is lots
of things are faster,
you can do like a binary
search and try to find some
quickly or you can
try to quickly
find a range of values, right?
Here it's like se sorted, right?
So the data Like,
each chunk is the chunks
can be sorted relative
to each other,
but with that a chunk,
it's not sorted.
So like what we could do.
It's kind of analogous to
that binary search, but
I can see like, Oh,
I have to touch these chunks,
but then it can't be
find rated off that,
I touch like half
a chunk, right?
So that sort order
will determine
what I can look up
things quickly for.
If I try to look up something
that it's not sorted by,
well, then I have to scat
all the data to find everything.
I can't have any
strategy to just
narrow it on the data
I'm interested in.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, good question.
Now, this was zero because
of a cash by results.
And so I should actually bring
back the job could
figure after all,
because I want to actually
see how much that cost.
And in this case,
I'm going to say,
I'm going to say something like
that was a good time
actually for me to come
back here and remember
what it was last time.
Or do I have the caching stuff?
I'm going to say
let's not do any
caching because I
actually want to
know how much this thing cost.
Alright, I pass that in here.
Job fig equals fig.
Let's run it. All right.
Any other questions while
I brought it again?
Sorry that I goofed that.
Yeah. We, what's that?
Oh, where was it cached?
So I did this query,
like, for example,
in the morning lecture and then
Google is caching it for me.
And so they know
it's the same query,
the same input data.
And so rather than
redoing classes,
I, they're just ever be
the same data set back.
Yeah, quest questions
people have?
Um, then what am I do for fun?
I guess it's not super
related to big query,
but it would just be
nice to see, well,
we see that it's quite
a bit less, right?
So the dry run
overestimated the cost.
This would be an example
where you might want to use
those MAX bytes sil if
you're kind worried
about it because
we can't trust the estimate.
Okay, let's just for fun just
plot this to see what it
looks like in Wisconsin.
There's the lines for
rows are too thick,
so they'll just look
like a big blue mass.
So I'm going to say
transparency equals
0.05 and You know,
Wisconsin is kind
of a rural state,
but we still have
built a lot of roads,
such as there's basically
roads everywhere, right?
If we draw the roads,
look exactly like Wisconsin,
right it's just filled
in. And there we go.
There's all the
roads in Wisconsin.
Of course, you can see,
in metro areas, there's
more roads, right?
But there you have
it. Alright, cool.
Any questions about Big
query before we move on?
All right. May I save that.
Let's head over to
these slides, right?
So but a big query,
and let's talk about
Cloud deployment.
So this is my last lecture.
I'm going to split it
between today and Monday.
And what I want to talk
about is how we can run
things in the Cloud.
We've learned a lot of
techniques for deployment
this semester.
We've kind of
comfortable with Linux.
We've learned how to
build Docker images.
We can run a Docker
image of the container,
we can do that with compose.
I want to talk a little bit
about how we can expand
those skills into the Cloud.
Right? A lot of those
things are going to use
similar or related tooling.
Now, to really explain
that stuff well,
We have to understand a
little bit more about
Docker and containers
and images.
Right? Let me explain how
those things work and
then talk about how that
relates to some other tools.
Let's talk about
containers first.
And if I want to really give
a good history of containers,
I have to do a little bit
of review of a couple of
operating system principles that
we saw earlier in the semester.
First, if I have a program
and I run it, it's a process.
The process is the
running program,
and every process has what
is called a virtual
address space.
I see here there's two processes
with virtual address spaces.
That's where I would
store any data,
like code or variables
or anything, right?
That virtual adder space is
broken up into four t by chunks.
Some of those are not valid,
and then other pages mapped
actual physical memory, right?
That's virtual memory.
And this actually
provides a form of
safety called isolation.
The first process
cannot mess with
other process because it
doesn't have anything
pointing to its data, right?
I can only change
virtual memory.
I can only change physical
memory that I have
virtual memory
associated with it.
So for example, if I
want to somehow mess
up the data in
page at Index one,
that will only hurt my process.
I cannot hurt the memory
for other process.
That's isolation.
They can't see each other.
In another idea from
operating systems.
We have CPU schedulers.
What do CPU schedulers do.
While they look at all
the threads across
all the programs running all
the proceeds on the system,
at any given time, they decide
which CPUs are running
which threads.
They run it by having
an instruction pointer
and then the CPU
advances the instruction
pointer as the code runs.
We don't have to wait until
that process is done.
And any time the
operating system
can context switch
to different threat.
We can say, Okay,
you're done running,
and we start running a
different one, right?
This is another form
of safety, right?
What we are doing
is by taking turns,
is we don't let a single process
dominate the whole
system, right?
We can preempt it. We can
give those resources
to somebody else.
Right? It's another form
of isolation, right?
And so let's talk
about this idea of
isolation a little bit
more broadly, right?
We have a few concerns
related to programs
interfering with each other.
Sometimes people
straight up write
malicious programs that
are trying to do damage.
We want to be able to run
those on the same machines as
our other programs without
having harm. We want
to isolate them.
You know, when somebody
writes a buggy program,
that's almost as bad as
a malicious program,
because if you have
a buggy program
and you feed it the right input,
you might be able to get it
to do something bad, right?
Fans refers to hey,
is there one program that's
getting 99% of the CPU.
The other one has 1%.
So when I look at
all these things,
I see that there's two
different ways for
programs to interfere
with each other.
We could directly interfere,
and that means that like this
process modifies your data
or maybe it spies on
you and extracts secrets
that shouldn't see.
And then there's
more indirectly,
where maybe I'm just making
the performance bad for
that other process.
Tying this in to the virtual
memory and virtual scheduler,
we see that these tools
are providing different
kinds of isolation.
The virtual memory
provides, what I
may call namespace isolation.
The namespace refers
to what things
I can name like
addresses and memory.
And if I can't name
somebody else's data,
I can't see it or
change it, right?
Virtual memory is an example
namespace isolation.
Schedulers are an example
of performance isolation.
I limit the impact
that one process
can have on other processes.
These are old ideas.
They've been in, you know,
operating system from
the beginning of time.
But unfortunately, CPU
and memory are not
the only resources we
have. They're not
the only resources.
We have DI, we have network IO.
We have kind of more abstract
sounding resources like
process IDs or you know, maybe,
like the time that
my system thinks it is
is a resource, right?
If I have one container,
and I want to
let that container
change the time,
will that appear as a time
change in other containers?
Lots and lots of resources.
And the goal over
time in Lenox has
been to add namespace isolation,
performance isolation for
more and more resources,
right? That's an ongoing effort.
And so we have two
broad categories.
For the performance isolation,
we have C groups,
and that's short
for control groups,
and it's like for CPU memory
and lots of other stuff, right?
There's a bunch of
them there now.
And for namespace isolation,
we have abstraction called
a name space, right?
And maybe that's network or
there's a mount name space.
Remember that for file systems,
they get mounted, so that's
a storage related one.
Time, lots of different
name spaces, right?
And if you wanted to, you
could run two
different processes,
and you could configure like
the ten things I have here.
You could configure other stuff
that I'm not even talking
about because it's
kind of beyond
the scope I want to get into.
That'd be very complicated.
But if you're very careful,
you could more or less
protect two processes
from each other,
but it'd be very
complicated, be very hard.
That's where Docker comes in.
Docker said, we're going to
automatically configure like
these dozen or so Linux
features for you and where
to make it really easy.
You say, like, Docker
run, and we're
going to start some processes
that are using all this stuff.
And the combination
of all this stuff,
we're going to call that
a container, right?
So what is a container?
Well, it's basically the usage
of all these different
Linux features,
and it roughly is trying to
isolate them from each other.
A container is not
a single concept,
and a container is not something
that's like
implemented in Docker.
It's really something
that Docker is stitching
together from these features
that are directly
in Linux, right?
But Docker became
very popular in
part because this solves
an important problem.
It makes it relatively
easy, right?
Now, one thing I want you to
think about is that given
a container is really a
combination of a lot
of different things,
there's different ways
you could combine
that and you could
maybe build containers
differently or you could even
build other things that are
not quite like containers.
You could invent
new abstractions.
And so, yeah, se right here.
Is there a space isolation
from its isolation within
a single container?
Is there you mean like
within a single container,
can you protect processes from
each other within a
single container?
Docker doesn't do that, but
these Linux abstractions
are inherently
hierarchical, right?
So for example, you
could have C groups
within C groups within C groups.
So Docker doesn't do it for you,
but if you wanted to have
containers and containers,
you could go build a new system
based on what Linux
gives to you, right?
But I don't think there's
tools that make that easy to do.
Yeah, good question, though.
So let me look at
something that uses
these features a little
bit differently.
And that thing is
called C Kubernetes.
C Kubernetes can run
containers as well.
We often abbreviate like this,
k8s because there's
eight letters
between the K and the S. I'm
going to contrast Docker on
the top with C
Kubernetes down below.
So on the top, we have Docker,
we just have containers
that have processes
inside of them,
and each container
is basically using
all the name spaces and
all the C groups, right?
And we can isolate them.
Now, with Kubernetes, what they
do is they have containers
that are similar,
and they have most
of the name spaces
and most of the C groups.
But one thing that they do
differently is they
sometimes want to
have different containers
that share networking.
So additionally the containers,
Kubernetes define
something called a Pod.
A Pod has the same
network namespace,
and then within there,
I have different processes
that are in different containers
that try to share
things more closely.
So you can invent
new abstractions
giving these building blocks
that Linux gives to us.
Why if you're Kubernetes,
would you want to do
something like that?
Often, you want to aploly
multiple applications that
work together in some way.
So for example, let's say
have some kind of
web application.
I built it in Flast or Jango,
or whatever it is people use,
I could have that
in one container,
and in the other container,
maybe I have a MEQL
database that has
all the data for my
application, right?
I want them to be able to see
all the same ports of each
other and communicate easily.
So I have them in the same pod.
They have the same
network name space.
They're going to have
to be on the same
machine because of that.
But Other than that,
they can still have all
their stuff be independent.
And really important is
that mount name space
because if they have
different mount name spaces,
they have different files.
So these applications
are working together,
but maybe the last application
has Ubuntu 20 404,
and maybe my SQL has
some version of the Debian
Linux distribution,
like, I don't know, bookworm
or whatever, right?
They can both have the act
set of files they want.
And that might be really
helpful if they have,
maybe contradictory
dependency requirements.
Maybe one needs a specific
version of something,
and the other one needs a
different version, right?
So they're closely coupled,
and they communicate over this
single network interface
that's shared between them,
but otherwise they're
decoupled, right?
So, you can see that
you can mix and match
these things in new ways.
Yeah, question right.
They will communicate
over virtual neck, right?
So when we create a new pod,
there will be like
a new nick for it.
Normally, when I create
like a new container,
it gives it a virtual Nick that
has an IP address that's
on a virtual network.
So they're communicating
over the network,
but that doesn't mean
that traffic is actually
going over anything
physical, right?
Because it's the same machine.
A virtual neck could allow
you to share data between
them very efficiently, right?
You would never have
packet drops, for example,
because it's actually on
the same machine, right?
You'll code it as if it's
going over the Internet,
but it actually will be
faster and more reliable.
T. Yeah.
Yeah. For the application
of developer,
it feels as if it was
running somewhere else.
Yep. Yep. Yeah, good
question. Other
questions people have.
Oh, right. Co Bernie
is more broadly is
something that we would
refer to as a container
orchestrator.
There's actually a really
nice article here.
People are interested
in this topic.
But beyond just like launching
individual containers,
often we want to have kind of
like sets of containers
that are working together.
Maybe like they're each
having a HDFS data no.
Maybe I have different kinds
of containers that cooperate.
A container orchestrator is
going to help you with that.
And by far, the most popular
container orchestrator
is Kubernetes, right?
So that's the big
one out there that
people should learn if
they want to go learn one.
Now, there's other ones, right?
Like doctor Compose.
You might think of that as
a container orchestrator.
Some people might nit pick it,
and they say that to
be an orchestrator,
you have to have
multiple machines and
be able to schedule across them.
But, you know, it's kind
of sort of a orchestrator.
And even though
it's complicated,
there's a steep learning curve
that you will experience
this semester,
it's still on the simpler end
of all these orchestrators.
So that's why I chose
it for the course.
Doctor Swarm is like
doctor Compose,
but it's a little bit
more complicated.
Feel similar, but
you can actually
run containers across
different machines.
And then nomad is one out there
that's just trying
to be more complete,
but also simpler than
Tubers because Cubers.
Like, I'm not that
great at Tubernettes,
and everybody who is says
it's a big pain, right?
So most popular but
also very complicated
and difficult to use.
Am I doing on time here?
I think I will end there,
and I will start talking
about images next time.
So I have a fantastic weekend,
and we'll wrap up on Monday and
then bring me some review
questions if you have them.