Talking about
Sandra replication.
That probably won quite
take us to the end
of lecture today.
So I also brought
some old exams.
Maybe we'll look
at a few questions
there, time permitting.
I just want to remember.
Well, actually,
before I do that one
more announcement.
As I've been saying, we
have a mid term on Monday,
I sent out some details again.
These are basically
the same as last time,
so I just wanted to
have it fresh for
everybody and a
Canvas announcement.
One thing that a few
people have asked is
whether you get one
note sheet or two,
and the answer is just one.
So you'll probably want to
find the most
important things on
your old note sheet and
then write that over
on your new one.
But, do people have any
logistical questions about
the exam before we
take it on Monday?
There here.
The final be one? Yep, the
final vs will be one note sheet.
Always one note sheet.
Always cumulative.
Yeah, right here.
Yeah, I don't know.
Maybe something like a
third or maybe a quarter
from the last one.
I don't have an exact account
off the top of my
head, but yeah,
I want to put some more emphasis
on the new stuff. Yeah.
Any other logistical questions
people have? Alright. Cool.
So I head over here
to the slides.
And I just want to
remember where we were.
So what we've been talking about
is how we have this ring.
We have a token ring, right?
And the token ring can tell us,
if I have a given row of data,
what machines should it be on.
So we often the easiest term.
I need to walk the ring.
Right?
And walking the ring isn't
the only thing we have to do,
but it's one of these
main pieces, right?
And when we were first learning
about just partitioning,
we would have
replication of one.
And it was simple.
We just walked the ring to
the right until you hit a node.
The ly tricky case was that
sometimes you would
wrap around, right?
It's ring ins of
a lie because if you fall
off the bigges number,
you just wrap around to
the smallest number.
So we learned about that with
just simple partitioning.
When we added a replication into
that, we just modified it.
You would still
walk to the right.
But if you need two replicas,
you would walk until
you find two Vendes,
or if you need three,
then you would
walk until you
have three Vendes.
The only tricky
thing there is that
sometimes we would skip Vendes,
if maybe it was two Vendes on
the same computer or maybe
two computers of the same brack.
There are certain cases
where we would skip.
But in general,
the same strategy,
we walk to the right
to find some machines.
And so that's all fded well.
Another piece on there is that
if we have a row of data,
it has some kind of
partition key with it.
And we would hash
that to get a token.
And that's where we start
walking in the ring.
Okay, great.
So we do all that. We find
some number of machines.
And what we're
talking about now is,
how do we actually
use those machines
if we're trying to
read or write data?
And that happens
with quorums, right?
So it's try to be okay.
Sometimes if a machine is down
or maybe permanently dead,
if there are enough
machines up, we
can still maybe read
and write our data.
If too many machines are down,
then we won't be able to.
And we have some
choices there to make
about how many machines
is good enough.
Now, in general, when
you write some data,
you want to have subsets
that your data is safe.
And that means that even
if something bad happens,
like a hard drive dying or maybe
a whole computer dying or
maybe multiple computer dying?
You want to have subsets
that your data is be ok,
even if these bad things happen.
And the technical word for
our data being safe
when something
bad happens is committed.
And there's lots of
different definitions
of committed because,
well, you could think
about different
bad things that
could happen, right?
Is the whole data center
destroyed or just one machine?
So depending on what
you're worried about,
you'll have different
definitions of committed.
And then I want to
think about how that
will play into when we're
reading or writing data.
If you're trying to read
data from a database,
you're doing some query, and
if you get results back,
you know it was okay, right?
If you're trying to write
the database, generally,
there's no results coming back,
but we still want to
have some sense, like,
did that work or did
it maybe fail, right?
And so where I
have this definition of an
act or acknowledgement.
And acknowledgement, is
something that you get
set back when there's
a right that says,
Hey, that worked, right?
If I get an acknowledgment,
I know my data is
committed for some
definition of committed.
And just like we have multiple
definitions of committed,
depending on what bad
things we're worried about,
there's maybe definitions
of acts, right?
And so in WhatsApp, for example,
right when I'm
sending a message,
there's different
levels of acts.
And I think it's actually
cool that they expose
this de technical detail about
the system to just
the average user.
All right. And so
even with these,
you can imagine other
definitions of C, right?
Like we get the double
gray check mark if
it makes it onto one of the
receiver's devices, right?
You can imagine a
stronger definition that
maybe it has to ladd all
their devices, right?
I want to get that ac
necessarily as soon.
But when it does, I
would feel even more
confident about it
reaching the person.
Now, I want to think about
what it means, right?
So if I send my message and
I get an AC and whats app,
that means they
definitely got it.
If I sent a message to somebody,
I don't get any acknowledgement.
Does that mean they did
not get the message?
What does it mean if I don't
get an ACP? Yeah right.
X, it might mean
that the act failed,
or maybe they never
got my message, right?
So there's two scenarios here
that look very different
to the receiving side,
but to the sender, they're
very different, right?
So maybe my message
number got through,
or maybe my message got
through and the act back.
And be the scenario where
if I get an ac, great,
my data is committed,
I I don't get an ac,
it may or may not be committed,
right? That's what
we're working with.
Alright, so with that in mind,
let's talk more specifically
about Cassandra.
And if I have a client that
wants to write some data,
the first thing that we'll do is
we'll look at the partition kee.
I may say that five
is the partition key,
and we need to figure out,
well, which computers are
own rows of that
partition, right?
The client does not
have a token map,
so the client cannot
walk the rig.
It needs another computer
involved that can walk the rig.
What computer could do that?
Well, any worker in the cluster
has a copy of the token rig,
and they can help us with that.
So we'll just choose some
worker in the cluster.
Maybe it's random, maybe
it's not random, it
doesn't really matter.
But whatever worker we choose in
the cluster is a coordinator.
So I have a coordinator here,
and the coordinator
will walk the rig for
the token corresponding to
partition five, and
I'll say, Okay,
there are these
three computers that
have a copy of that or
should have a copy of it,
and we're going to
call those nodes one,
two and three, because we
have triple replication.
I'm just going to
abbreviate that RF
replication factor
equals equals three.
So the coordinator knows,
And now what's
happened is that we
send that rode to
the coordinator,
and the coordinator is to try to
send that data to
each individual node.
And at each individual node,
if they can do that
right, they're going to
send acknowledgement
back to the coordinator.
I can see node one.
What was it before?
I had A here, we're
changing A to
B. Node says, Hey,
that worked for me.
Node two says that
worked for me.
Let's say that just
kind of at a bad time.
Node three is rebooting.
So Node three is not send an
acknowledgment back. Okay?
So now the question here,
which is very similar
to the question
we had with WhatsApp is,
should the coordinator send
an acknowledgment
back to the client?
Right? If the coordinator
sends that to the client,
that means client, you're
right was successful.
Is this successful enough to
justify an
acknowledgement, right?
And the answer is that you
as a programmer get to
decide how many
successful rights
is enough to consider
the whole thing success.
And that's another
variable called
W. And so if we
say W equals two,
we'll say, Okay,
that was a success.
If application factor is three,
we will always absolutely
always try to write the three,
but maybe we'll say two is
good enough if W equals two.
There's two things like how
many do I try to write two?
That's RF, and then how many
is good enough and that's W.
This case, if I say W equals
two, great, it's good enough.
Now, I want to contrast this
with HDFS a little bit.
When we write data at HDFS,
we end up writing, say,
three replicas or whatever.
And when we read
back, we just read
one copy back because at HDFS,
all the partitions
have the same value.
Here, with Cassandra, we
were able to say that that
write was successful,
even though we didn't update
all the machines properly.
And so one of the
applications here is
that when I try to
read my data back,
I can't just look at one
copy like we do with HDFS.
I have to try to see, are
there kind of different
versions out there, right?
Because if I read
from the wrong w,
that I would get some
old data, I would
get A instead of B.
So what we're going
to do is we read from
multiple nodes before we
try to set data
back to the client.
And how many we try to
read from is configurable.
Were they say R
equals two in this case, it
could be different things.
And in that case,
we will try to read
from two to make sure we
have a better chance of finding
the latest possible data.
You could set r equal
to three, and say, Hey,
I want to read from
all of them and
really make sure I'm
getting the latest data.
If you just want to be
fast and you aren't
worried about getting
the laates data,
maybe s set R equal to one.
All right?
Now, the common case is
that we're getting
identical data
back from all the nodes, right?
So for example, maybe
node one and node,
two send me the same data,
that's a little bit
wasteful that they're both
sending me identical
data back, right?
I need to be able to tet
if they disagree
with each other,
but in the comments,
they're going to agree.
And so there's an
optimization on that,
and what will happen
is that each of the
nodes individually,
will look at the row, and one
of them will be in charge
of sending the data back,
and the other one will
just send a check sum.
So a check sum is
just a hash function
where collisions are very rare.
And if the coordinator has
a check sum of the data
and it has actual data,
well, then it can
compute what the
check sum could be and
it could compare it.
And it could see Okay,
even though node one and
node two didn't send
me full data, they
agree with each other.
Okay. So it can detect
if there's a problem.
It can detect if they disagree.
If they do disagree,
then it can draw
back and read full
copies of the data.
All right, so is it
making sense so far,
how we can detect if
there's disagreement?
Yeah, question right here.
Scenario with the coordinator
also check some on
the data send see if
they're the same.
Yeah, so the coordinator
needs to see if
the data is identical across
node one and node two.
So the coordinator will compute
a check sum of the data,
that it gets back from node two.
And then if the check
sums are the same,
it's very unlikely the
data is different.
H.
Oh, how does the creator
determine which
two to read from?
It could be random or maybe
they have some cleverness
baked into it.
But for now, let's
just say it's random,
what we want, if one of
them is responding slowly,
it might try to read it
from a different one.
So just kind of like random
performance things
might affect which one.
So we can't have
any guarantee about which
ones it'll read from.
It could be a good question ug.
Yeah, other questions
people have. Yep.
That's a great question.
So the coordinator
try to write to Node three,
it rebooting, does it try again?
Let's for now say no, like,
a let's say that
it's just stale.
They do have some things that
will run in the background where
they eventually try to
fix up differences.
Generally, that would
happen actually be
between these nodes talking
to each other and
sorting out because,
you know, soon the IO
operations be over,
the coordinator will
be out of the picture,
but these replicas might
sync up with each other.
But, that kind of happens
later on any kind of time frame.
And so what we're
re talking about is
without considering that
that gets fixed up,
how can we still make a system
that behaves in a
reasonable way?
So yes, eventually,
they try to fix it up,
but for now, let's pretend
that it doesn't
try to fix it up.
It's just old data, it's
old data indefinitely.
Yeah, great question, though.
Yeah, right here.
Is it very dangerous to
get sale data sometimes?
Yeah, let's hold that
for a little bit,
cause I want to talk
about what happens.
So we might get
sale data, right?
And if R is larger,
I'm less likely
to get sale data.
So we talk about like, Well,
how can I make sure that
if I wrote some data,
I read it back again later?
That's what that we
want to talk about.
The other thing that I'm
real talk about, you know,
at the end of the
lecture is that,
Okay, if I got back, like,
fresh data, se data,
how do I figure out,
this is the proper version,
and this is the old
version, right?
Yeah, so great questions, but
we'll hold them for a bit.
Yeah, right here.
Yeah, I think that's
a similar question,
if there's a disagreement
between them,
if we get different
versions, how
do we know which is
the correct one?
And that's like there's
some even more nuance
to that questions.
We save it. We'll
come back to it.
That's a great question, though.
All right, so we can choose,
right when we're writing,
how many successes does
it need to have to
say it's good enough.
And we're reading, we say how
many we try to read from,
and we also get to choose
a replication factor.
So what I want you all to
walk away with is to be
a sophisticated user in
choosing these three numbers.
And there's different ways
you can do it. I'll
talk more about that.
But there's one very common
approach people have.
And that's what they do
is they choose RW and RF,
such that R plus W
is greater than RF.
Why is that? Well, here I have
replication factor three.
And if I have W equals
two and R equals two,
then I'm guaranteed that if I
write the subset and
read from subset,
there's going to be some
overlap between them.
What I'm really
trying to guarantee,
right is if I write some data,
and the system says,
y, that was committed,
and I read it later.
I'm not trying to
get a surprise where
my data is missing, right?
If R plus W is equal
to RF or it's smaller,
then that would happen
all the time, right?
I might write something
and it says, Hey,
it's good, and I read
it, like, where is it?
That would be an anomaly, and we
want to avoid those anomalies.
Right? So, you know,
You can't just
remember the formula,
but also you should
think about why that is
a formula that
makes sets, right?
So I want to talk about some
different ways people might
tune these three variables
and what the trade offs
would be in each case.
And so you know, RF
isn't necessarily three,
I may imagine for all
these cases, it is three.
Let's say that you make W equal
to three and r equals to one.
What that will mean is that
reads are highly available.
Would I say that the system
is available for something,
I mean that you
could do that thing,
even if there are a lot of
problems going on, right?
So if I have three
copies of my data,
and I only need to read
one copy to call it Dred,
that means I can have
any two machines
down astray to work fine.
Okay? So, uh W equals three,
R equals one, reads are going
to be highly available,
writes will not be
highly available.
If there's three copies,
and I have to be
able to write to all
of them to acknowledge
it is committed,
that means if any
one machine is down,
I just won't be able to
write data for a while.
So kind of as you try to
satisfy that formula,
R plus W is greater than
RF, you can try to choose.
Is it more report that I
always want to be
able to write data,
or I always want to
be able to read data.
You can make some choices there.
The other factor with this
is that I W is three,
that makes my data
durable, right?
Durable means that if there's
like permanent failures,
right, I'm not going to
lose my data, right?
So if I say that
it's not successful
until it's on three machines,
even if these machines
die permanently,
as long as I have one
that survived, it's good.
Okay, so the flip of that is we
could say that I want rights
to be highly available,
even if maybe reads or not.
So I could say W equals
one, R equals three.
In that case, as long as
any of these three
machines are up,
I can write data just fine,
but if any one of
them goes down,
then I won't be able to
read my data back, right?
And that's actually what
you're able to do P six.
So on P six, I imagine
you have this server,
and there are all these weather
stations setting a data.
And if the weather station tries
to write the data
and it doesn't work,
I'm imagining that the
weather station doesn't
have some kind of
buffer to store it,
so the weather report
would just be lost, right?
So you to have a server that's
very welcoming to writes.
Even if sub machines are down,
it should take
rights whatever it.
The server also can give
you some weather stats,
and they say, well,
to satisfy that formula.
R plus W is greater than RF.
We they say that R equals three.
So, you know, sometimes if
there's a machine down,
you might not be able
to get statistics like,
what is the highest
temperature ever.
Eventually, you will when
the machines come back.
The main thing is
that this server
should be there to be
recording these things, right?
So that would be an
example where writes
are highly available,
even if reads are not.
You know, a very common thing
is people have a
balanced approach.
They'll say W and
R both equals two,
then we can lose any one machine
and everything
still works, right?
If you want to live dangerously,
you could say W equals
one and R equals one.
Now, it's not totally
insane because even
though W equals one,
we're going to try to write
to all three replicas.
All that means is that if for
some reason the
machines are down,
we'll still call it dro if we
can write to at
least one of them.
If some machines are down,
it might mean that
I write some data,
get an acknowledgment, and then
I can't read it later, right?
So there are some anomalies
that could happen here.
But this system is
going to be fast,
and it's going to be
highly available.
Can anybody think of an
application where that make
sense? Let me put it this way.
Like a baking application,
this would not
make sense, right?
Baking application has
to do the right thing.
Is there an application
where I might just care
about speed and availability
even if it's wrong sometimes?
Yeah, right here. Is that?
Maybe kind of
messages, I kind of
depends on the nature of the
messages. Yeah, I out here.
Yeah, maybe some kind of
real time streaming video.
Are there other kind
of real time things
where we just want it
available all the time,
and it's okay if
it's not perfect?
Yeah, right here.
The weather Yeah, Well,
maybe a weather app. I
guess it depends, right?
Is it like recording
weather things?
In that case, you
want to make sure
the records actually
get recorded.
Yeah, I guess there's different
applications out there.
Some applications peel
higher stakesthan other.
I think about something
that's very low stakes,
I imagine like a
computer game, right?
Like, with a computer game,
it's low stakes, right?
People are playing
it to have fun.
And it's probably more
annoying if it just says,
Hey, the game is not
available right now.
Even if there's some weird
quirks or anomalies,
I'd want to keep playing
the game, right?
So I imagine like
computer games, right?
You might have one
way to tune that and
then you might
imagine like bake.
You'd have a very different
way to tune that.
So, anyway, you
should be able to
think through this and
ibt your application,
choose some settings that
make sense. Alright, cool.
S a head over here
to the worksheet.
Great. I have this
token g from B four.
And I assume now that I have R
equals two W equals two
and RF equals three.
I assume the token of
a row being read it as
negative three, right?
So we're writing right here.
And I want to know
to which nodes,
will the coordinator
attempt to write the data.
Okay? And so this
is the keyword.
What is it attempting
to write to?
And does anybody
want to help me out?
Which of these numbers is
relevant to this question?
Yeah, right here. W at RF.
So yes, and does anybody
want to elaborate W one matters
even more? Yeah right here.
The replication factor is
what I really care about.
So the W tells
me how many I have to write
to for it to be good tou,
but RF tells me how many I'm
re to attempt to write to.
So I may start here
at negative three,
and I may walk right
until I hit three node.
So I hit a no there,
it a do there, hit a do there.
And so we're ready
to try to write at
one n two and N three.
Right? If I write to two
of the, we'll say it's
good enough but I bet at
least try to write
to both of those.
All three of those. Oh, right.
Cool. Let's head down here.
And I want to look at a scenario
We're basically doing that.
It's the same row,
but a lot of bad things
are happening, right?
So first, node one is down,
and then I try to write a row.
That's right to work because as
long as I can write to
two, that's good enough.
Alright, Node one comes back
and node three crashes.
Then I try to read a row.
Okay, well, that's good enough,
too because R equals two,
there's two nodes up.
All right, so I want to see
which nodes perform reads.
So at the time I was reading,
node three was down, right?
So what will this
mean? This is node one
and node two are the ones
that I'd read to read from.
I has to read from two of them.
Which nodes perform rights?
Well, when I was writing,
node one was down.
So I guess, in that
case, I'm doing
node two and node three.
All right?
Is the data that was
written read back later?
So I read from these two,
I wrote to these two.
And so I can see
there's overlap,
right? I wrote some data.
I got an acknowledgement,
I read later.
I ready to get that data back,
at least as one of the
copies of the data.
Alright. And then this
last one out here.
So I have in this case,
W equals three RF equals four.
Maybe people can up
some number of figures.
What should R equal
in this case,
if I want to make sure that
that I read my rights.
Everybody can up some
number of figures.
I'm seeing some two is also
some three. So the
answer is two.
Let's think about this, right?
So I have four replicas.
And when I write to it,
I'd bet to write to
three of them, right?
I'd be to say we equals three.
And when I read back,
if R was one,
then that's not good enough.
I might read from the bad one.
I have to make sure that R at
two to guarantee some overlap.
These are how we work
with read write or.
Any questions about
those examples?
Yeah, here. Three and
four. Two, three and four.
Yeah, I could make
bigger if I wanted to.
I don't know if there
would be a benefit
to making it bigger, right?
Because I'm guaranteed that
it's big enough
that I'm going to
see what has been
recently rented,
but it won't stop me from
making it bigger if I want to.
Yeah, good question. I saw
the hand up right over here.
Even Yeah.
Oh, yeah. How did I do that?
So I guess maybe 11 kind
of builds off Ted, right?
So in this case,
I started at negative three.
And then I my replication
factor is three.
So I just walked the reg until I
got three. Boom, boom, boom.
That, that makes sense?
Oh, yeah, exactly, right?
So, the first thing we do,
Fredy Gvd row is we
figure out the Tkid,
and then we see, Okay, these are
the set of workers that
are going to be involved.
And so those are RF workers.
And then R and W are both
subsets of those.
That makes sense?
Yeah, great question.
Yeah. Yeah, right here.
Mm hmm.
Yeah.
Well, I think you're
thinking about
the right thing because you're I
think what you're thinking
about now is like, Hey,
if I have R equals two, I
have one good and one bad,
and you're saying, would it be
nice if we could have
more, we could vote?
Voting is one a. Well there's
another idea that they
used to resolve this.
And so having be
dreaded off for us.
There are some
ideas behind that,
but we'll talk about
that more detail.
All right. Yeah, right
back here. Yeah.
The answer is yes,
because we wrote and
read to the same bod.
The answer is yes. We'll read
back the data that
was readed. Yeah.
Thanks for clarifying.
Yeah. Follow up.
Like you have another
question, but
Yeah. I see what you're saying.
Is the data that was re
read back? Yes, it is.
In addition, some bad
data was read back.
It reads back the good
data plus some bad data.
That's the next thing what
we talk about, right?
What we're talking about, I have
a mix of good data and bad
data. How do I deal with that?
Right?
So you see all these things
built on top of it, right?
First we walk the rig,
then we do read write quorums.
And then the final piece
that we still need
to talk about is how
do we resolve conflicts?
Yeah, right here.
Yeah. Houses are not going to.
Let's talk about I think
everybody is on the right track.
Everybody sees the problem
that we have, right?
So the next thing is
conflict resolution.
And this is actually
going to be kind
of similar when you're
working a ditch.
Sometimes you have different
versions of the same code,
and you have to
resolve conflict.
So first, let me show you
kind of a really nasty
conflict because we've been
talking about kind of
oversimplify things.
We'd say, Oh, there's
a good version,
there's a bad version.
What we really see is that,
sometimes you have
different versions,
and neither one is they
each have something that's good
about them that's not good
about the other version.
There's not always a
strictly best version,
just like it did, right?
You can branch out
and you can say,
well, you wrote some code,
I wrote some code, the best
is probably some combination.
Okay, so for all these things,
when you think about it,
you want to think about,
really perverse cases.
L, what's the
nastiest combination
of failures and recoveries
that could lead to
something weird,
and then think about
how you handle those.
So, in this case,
I have these rows out here.
And the partition for
or the primary for
each of them is five.
And I see that there's
one cell, which is A.
I want to change A to
B and each of them.
And just at the wrong time,
This machine is rebooting.
So I change A to B in these two,
but there's some sale
data on known three.
Alright, now we're ready to
try to change X to Y, right?
So let me look at this.
I want to change x to y.
And just what I'm doing that,
well, there's a different
machine rebooting.
Okay? So on the
machines that are up,
I will change x to y,
but now I may have a
sale value over here.
So A is stale and x is sale.
And now let's say
we're ready to read.
And just what we want to
read, known is rebooting.
Okay. So now we got ourselves
in a bad situation because,
you know, we get two versions of
the data, neither of
which is perfect.
Both of them have something
old about it, right?
And so some systems,
a lot of distribution
systems will be very
careful to make sure you don't
get into this situation.
To make sure that your different
replicas are consistent.
Maybe they're not all the
same state at the same time,
but there's a clear liteage,
like, this is the
history for this object.
Cassandra is an example of
an eventually consistent system
where the state can diverge.
There's not really
one best thing.
Eventually, we
want to get things
consistent body has the
same version of the data,
but it's okay for it to
temporarily diverge.
Other systems that are
eventually consistent,
what they're often
trying to do is they're
trying to optimize to
be highly available.
Even if things are failing, they
want reads and writes to work,
and the sacrifices that you
get yourself into this mass,
right? How do we deal with that?
There's a couple of approaches.
One is that the coordinator that
gets these two could
just send the both
back to the client.
The client is like, Oh,
let me read that value.
And the coordinator is like,
Oops, I have two values.
You figure it out, right?
That's harder as
a program, right?
Maybe some of you have written
a Trode does like SQL queries,
like you just hit
your results back.
It would be harder to
write that code if you got
two different results back and
like, we'll figure it out.
In some cases, it
makes a lot of sense.
Like, for example, remember that
this idea was pioneered
in the dynamo paper,
which they were using at Amazon.
And at Amazon they're always
thinking about
shopping carts, right?
If I have an application,
that's try to you a shop cart,
and I'm like, Oh,
here's actually
two versions of
the shopping cart.
They have different
things in them.
I mean,
there's some reasonable
things you could do, right?
You could take like
the union of all this
stuff in them and say,
well, this is your new
shopping cart, right?
But a lot of applications is
not clear how to do that.
And so the other
thing you could do
is that The coordinator
could try to automatically
combine them into
a newest best row,
right? We could do that.
So if you're using Dabo,
DDBo actually lets
programmers choose,
which approach, just
do the best you
can automatically or make
the application do it.
Cassandra only uses
a simpler approach,
which is, let's try to merge
these the best we can.
And it doesn't do perfect,
but it's the best effort system.
And so the way that Cassandra
does that is for every value,
it's going to record a
type statap in it, right?
When was this value changed?
And what we could
do then, right?
Is that when we get
both these back,
we can merge it to
get the best of both.
So is A or B better?
I guess B has a bigger type sep
than A. So we put B there?
Is X or Y better?
Y has a bigger type sep,
or we put the y there.
So we're send that back, right?
You know, it's okay.
It's tight of reasonable.
There's things I
don't like about it.
When we have a
distributed system
and we have a bunch of clocks,
they're never perfectly
in sync, right?
And so we might make
a role that's not actually
the latest, right?
We could get something
that's not quite right.
That just happens
sometimes Sandra.
It doesn't always give
you the right answer.
What else might happen?
We've talked about how
there's different rules
that apply to your data.
For example, like a bake
account to negative.
Humans know what
those rules are,
and it's possible that
the combination of
B and Y doesn't
make sets, right?
Maybe for some application,
there's certain states that
Casadra might give you that just
to a human, they
don't make sets.
Well, that's too bad.
That's just what
Cesara does, right?
There's some cases where that
might not work. All right.
So this conflict
resolution policy
that Casser has is called LW.
That's last rider wins,
and it happens on
a per cell basis.
Yeah, gosh right here.
As very resource intensive.
Cob? Is it very
resource intensive?
Yeah, that's probably
my intition, as well.
Does it become a problem?
Well, I mean, it's
definitely an overhead,
how much of an overhead?
That's a little
hard to say, right?
I would be interesting to try
to do some measurements and
see if you turn that off,
how much faster is it?
I bet I bet it's noticeable.
Yeah, s right here. Oh, that's
a really good question.
So why not just always
use the time stops,
instead of using the check subs.
Well, I've been focusing on,
like these weird
scenarios, right?
It's kind of a little bit
like constructed, right?
Oh, this fails, and that
fails. That happens sometimes.
But let's remember
that the normal case
is that all my machines are up,
and they're probably
up for days, right?
The vast majority of the time,
all the copies of the data
are going to be
identical, right?
And so I don't want to know
sometimes I have to do
the slow thing and carefully
construct a new row,
but I don't want to
do that every time.
I want to make the
common chase fast,
and I want to make
the the kind of,
like, bad case, do something
semi reasonable, right?
So that's why we wouldn't
use Type saps every time.
As faster as send one copy
of the data. Yeah,
good question.
So the other thing here, which I
don't really quite show is
that we wouldn't like
these nodes to eventually
sake up with each other.
So the coordinator when it's
sending that row
back to the client,
the coordinator is well
aware that there's a
problem with the system.
And so at that point in
the time, the coordinator,
in addition to sending
this row back,
we'll try to write
that row on top
of nodes two and three so that
we are to this weird
state forever.
You know, that's
eventually consistent.
Eventually, want all the
rows to be the same,
even if we temporarily
allow them to diverge,
when machines are dying.
All right. So I
may to do a couple of quick
demos because I want to
save a little time
for Exa review, too.
Let me just head over here
and I'm going to SSH Ed.
And All right, I'm going
to look at my containers.
I have three containers here.
I'm going to do a
doc, a docker Eat IT,
and I'm going to jump into.
It doesn't really
matter which one.
One of the things I want to
show you is the node tool,
which we've seen before, but
you'll understand it
in more detail now.
I can say node tool rig.
When I've been drawing
the rigs on paper,
like all the numbers
are kind of small,
I go from like negative
eight to seven.
Here, It's way too big,
but I'll kind of spread
that out a little bit.
Here what I see
is that there are
only three different
IPs in my cluster
because there's
three actual nodes,
but each of these appear many
times because they each
have multiple Venodes.
The token numbers assigned to
each Vende are shown over here.
So we can see the tokens
for the V nodes start
from very small,
and they go to very large.
There's like 16 for each node,
so there's like 48 tokens here.
And so If you had
the token for a row,
you could go through here
and you could see, like, Oh,
maybe it equals this, so that
would draw on this V node,
or if it was between these two,
it would also go on this V node.
Right? So you can work through.
Sometimes I've had
people do that in P
six but I guess we're being
a little bit nicer
this semester.
Then you don't have
to write prod that
walks the rig automatically.
But I go to the very
end, I see this number.
And so if there are
any rows that are to
the right of that they have
a bigger token number,
those are the wrapping range.
And so just remember
some digits from this.
It's like 919, something.
I see that's up here as well.
And so this V node is
a little bit special.
It handles any tokens
that are less than this,
and it also handles
nodes that are the wrapping
rags that are big than this.
That's why they're showing
that number twice.
Cool. So I can go through.
I can inspect a real token ring,
which is slightly more
complicatedthan what
we've been looking at,
but it's still not crazy, right?
The other thing I want to
show is if I have SQL SH
and I connect to Demo DB one.
Let me just use baking
like last time,
and I'm going to select
star from loans.
And I see there's a
bunch of loads here.
One of the things that
I want to show you
is This bake ID
determines by partition,
and if I want to, I can
get a token for it, right?
What is the token of bake ID?
Right? So this is
my partition key.
And so I can say
for a given row,
what the token is, and I can
actually take this number,
and if I wanted to,
I could walk the rig,
and I could say, k,
this row of data has this token,
and I can tell you what V node
or multiple V nodes is
straight B. I can use that.
I can walk the rig.
I won't because
I don't like looking
at that many digits,
but it's the same concept as
what we've been doing
on the worksheets.
Another thing I want to show you
is when I come back here,
I can look at the right
time for fields like state.
I'm sorry, so that's
not Wisconsin.
I could Maybe let me
just take a look at
the state and that for each
of these state fields,
I can see what the
right time was for it.
What was it last readed?
And if I wanted to,
I could do something
like I could update loads,
and I could set state
I'll just change
like the case of it,
where and I have
to specify the whole
primary key to changes.
So the bake ID is 544,
and the about is 400
and the load ID.
Loan ID would be.
I'd change you this
one right here.
Sutray copy paste this.
So I could update that thing,
and then if I tub
selected again,
then I can see that it updated
the right time sap for it.
So I could go through it.
I can actually inspect,
like when this field.
Let change. Other applications
might have some value
for that as well.
One thing I cannot do is I
cannot get the right type
for something that is the
partition key, right?
Because if I have a different
primary key, by definition,
it's a different row, so I never
update values of
the primary key.
I just create different rows.
So it does't keep track of
the time staap for that.
It just keeps track of
the time staps for
the normal fields.
All right. C, that's
my Cassandra demo.
Any question about
the Cassandra demo?
All right. Cool. So
let's head over here
back to the worksheets,
or not the worksheets,
but the exams.
And so you know,
like I've said, we're going
from two exams to three exams.
And so that means if you're
looking for practice questions,
the old final exams are
the best place to go.
And I have two of them.
And just to save you
all a little bit
of doubt about what
questions are relevant.
I went through it. I just
marked some of them.
So this might be something
that you might want
to write down if you're
trying to study from these.
So this is the final
exam from Fall 2023.
And there's some
of these questions
that are relevant based
on what we've covered.
So questions one, two, five.
813 202-20-6208.
And that's all,
right? So those are
questions that I'll spend
some time looking at
some of them now,
but those are questions
that you could look
at from this final.
Let's take a look
at the Spring 2023.
So for this final exam
from Spring 2023,
questions, two, three,
four, five are relevant.
Question 11 is relevant.
What else do we
have here? 21 22.
And that's all.
Right? So you have
at least some questions you
could use to practice for this.
I also want to talk
a little bit about the
systems we've covered.
So for this part of the
course, we're spending
almost like a week or so on
different major systems.
So the first major big
data system was HDFS.
Then we looked at Spark.
And now we've just
completed Cassandra.
And so when I write the exam,
I want to make sure I have
at least several questions
about each of those major
systems on there, right?
So you're going to have to
go and review each of those.
One of the ways I might think
about it to kind of make
sure you understand what
you need to know
for each of them
is like let's say
I'm looking at HDFS.
You could ask yourself,
where does HDFS store data?
Right? Like how is
it partitioned?
How is it replicated? You should
be able to have very
clear in your mind.
If I write HDFS
data, what happened?
Was talking to the dat node,
it's writing to the data node?
The data node it's
like piplighting it.
By trying to read data
with HF is what happens?
And I want to go through it.
L for each of these systems,
think about how is
the data actually moving
at each of those?
Right? I think that
would be helpful.
Then there's some minor systems?
Like we learned
map reduce HBase.
I didn't actually show
any programming depos,
but you know, a question or
two might be fair there.
Anything else we
covered is fair.
You know, there's may be
some questions from
the first part.
So at the very
least, I make sure
you understand what
you did on the exam.
O, well, both what you got
right and what you got wrong.
Do we have any, like,
general questions before
we start looking through
some specific ones here?
There, right. Pd H
base. Yep. Yeah.
And so, I want to
look at the history.
I'm like, Oh, here's Map reduce.
I talked a little
bit a bit about it.
And then we talked
a lot about Spark
and Spark is more common.
Same thing, like, we
looked at H base.
You know, Cassada
is more popular.
So we spent a bunch
of time at Csara,
but I want people to
understand the history a bit,
too. Yeah. Alright, cool.
So I'm just ready to go through
these and talk about them,
and pop up ahead at a time,
to ask about anything you want
to for ping for the exam.
So let's take a look here.
All right, so I have
an HDFS cluster with
a single name node,
and that name node is
becoming a bottleneck.
And so this cluster has
a small number of files,
but each file is
extremely large.
I'm wondering what we can
do to help the name node.
Now, the name node has
a data structure at it.
Can anybody describe
what the data structure
is that it has internally?
Yeah, go ahead. Petition file.
Then the name note Yeah,
The Nab node has something
where there's like a key,
which might be a
block within a file,
and then the value would be
the locations of it, right?
So that's called the block map.
So the Nabe has this
block map that maps.
Okay. Here's a partition.
Here's where it's located.
And what I'm worrying about
the Nab nod, I'm wondering,
like, are we doing too
many look ups on
that data structure?
Is the data structure too big?
And so what about, like,
adding more data nodes?
It might change the contents
of that data structure,
but we be using it just as
much, I'll be just as big.
What's did it happen if I
increase the block size?
What will that do for the M
data structure? Right here?
Excellent, right? If I
have a larger block size
it reduces the number
of blocks in total.
So the size of my block map
will be like half
of what it was.
And if there's these
clients reading,
if a client is reading
like the whole file,
the client won't have to pull
as much data from the
da node as well, right?
So this is the answer here.
It treats the block size
See what make the problem
worse for the same reason.
Splitting big files
into bite small files.
That would be worse,
too, because the name
has to remember all
the names for these.
I have maybe a bunch of
files that fit in a
signal block, right?
So that would be
the answer here.
All right, I'll just
keep moving along,
but if anybody has any
follow up questions,
please just pop up a
had at eight time.
Alright.
So looking at Cassandra,
so we have W equals eight
and RF equals nine.
And what should I choose for R
if I want to make sure that
readers see successful rights.
Maybe people can hold up
some number of fingers.
I'm seeing some twos,
so that's straight.
I'm glad everybody try to
freshen people's mind.
You know, if it was one,
that's not good enough because
maybe I write to these ad,
and then maybe the one is
the other replica that
hasn't seen the data.
So, so two is to make sure that
at least one of the ones
is from one of the
ones that we wrote to.
All right. Cool.
So I bet like out here now.
So I bet imagine that in
my cluster, I have Spark.
And I don't really have as
much Rab as I would like,
but I have a lot of
computational power
in terms of CPU cores.
Okay? And so I want
to cache some data.
And so of these four,
does anybody want
to make a case for
which caching level will be most
appropriate in my situation?
To be very clear. I don't care
about load balances
or fault tolerance.
I really just try asking
in terms of Rab and CPU.
What should I pay?
Yeah, right here.
Because you want
to serialize it,
so it doesn't take up much ab.
And you don't care
about fuller, so.
Excellent, right? So first
of if you're saying, I
don't care about Toler,
so there's no real point in
having two copies
of the same thing,
so I agree that quickly
knocks out these.
If I'm scarce on ab, I
don't want to have two
copies of it, right?
Between these, remember
that memory ly,
has a memory, but it's
in the Java types.
The JVM types are
pretty bloated, right?
There's a lot of overhead there.
And so if we serialize it,
it's a compact format, almost
like protocol buffers
or something like that.
When it's in that format,
it takes much less memory,
but I can't directly
do computation on it.
That means I may have to do
some extra instructions,
some extra compute to
deserialize it immediately
before I access it, right?
So this is to take the
least amount of memory,
but I will have to use
some extra computational
resources.
Oh. Alright. Maybe people
will remember this from P four.
So when you were doing CP
to copy a file into HDFS,
and what granularity
were you specifying
the replication
factor of one or two?
Yeah, right here. Per
file, Excellent, right?
So for the CP,
there was a flag we could
pass it and say what that is.
So each file could have a
different replication factor.
All right.
Lo Cassandra questioned
about the Token rig,
and we have replicas for it.
And what technique do
we use with updating
the multiple replicas
of a token rig, right?
So this is not rows
of data, right?
These are not the actual rows.
This is that token
Map data structure
that every single machine has.
So Any volunteers,
what do we use?
Yeah, right, over here.
What's that? Quorums.
So Cassada does use quorums.
That's a little bit
of a trick question,
because it uses the quorums
for the rows, right?
So if I have a row, maybe
there's like three
replicas of that row,
and I might think
about, you know,
read and write quorums
on those three.
So A. Excellent, right?
So for this one, we
have that token rag.
Maybe there's 100 copies of
the token rags on every machine.
And the way I update those
100 is that I update
a few of them,
and they start
gossiping with each
other until it's globally know.
Upright.
All right. What about
this one for 17?
A single spark task typically
runs on how many cores,
it operates on how many
partitions? Any volunteers?
There here.
One core one partition.
Excellent, right?
That's really important
because you can
choose how to partition
your data, right?
You have a lot of small
partitions or a few pig ones.
Given each task is
running out of partition.
That's to influence
how many tasks I have?
Given each task runs on one CPU,
that will determine
how many CPUs
I can use at the
same time, right?
So, so remember
that is to help you
tune that better when you
repartition your data.
Alright. So down here,
we have another sada question.
And somebody assume
two times replication.
And I want to know which
nodes are responsible
for token negative five.
So I kind of drew this out here
just as a convenience for you.
And then what you'll usually do.
If you see somebody like
this is, you'll draw
these things on top of here
so you can answer the question.
Right? So I can
see that node one
has Ten negative six, right?
So node one is here. Node two
has negative five and seven.
So Node two. Node three
has four and negative
two. All right.
Cool. And so I need to
walk the rig starting
at a row with Token
negative five, right?
So where is that?
So it's right here.
We get the exact match,
which is node two, and
we walk until we hit
two replicas. So I
walk to the right.
I may hit node two
and node three.
I walk to the rig,
and now I know that
these are replicas.
Que right here.
Exactly, right?
So if you hit node two, then
you hit node two again,
then you would skep right?
Because of the same
failure domain.
Yep.
Excellent. Yep. Yeah, there
are questions about that one.
Those are the two complicated
things you do when
you walk the rig.
Sometimes you sk,
sometimes you wrap.
Alright. All right.
So I tip to insert
insert a row into Csdra.
And the primary music is
already in the table.
Anybody remember what happens?
Here.
Yeah, it just gets
updated, right?
Because insert they
call it insert,
but really what it
is is an upsert.
It updates or inserts,
depending on whether
there's already there.
Alright. Cool.
Maybe everybody can nod
their head, yes or no.
Does the planet algorithm
sometimes collect all the rows
corresponding to
a single node of
a decision tree on
a single machine?
Does it do that sometimes?
I see a couple of people
say yes, which is true.
The main thing about
the planet algorithm
is that it's a hybrid
approach, right?
Some nodes in the tree
have very few rows,
and we can bring them
all together, right?
And as the tree grows down,
we have fewer and
fewer rows per node.
So eventually, that's how
we're going to end out.
I might also have some nodes
that have too many rows
to bring together.
And in that case, we need
to find a good split point.
By a split point, I need a
question, which is like,
is X greater than five or
is x greater than 100?
In that case, we just are
competing stats in place.
To try to find a good split pie.
And basically a type.
I'm are to put the answer
on here that I'll end up.
What is the primary reason
HDF has to us pipeline right?
Because we don't want one pet,
having to send the same data
to a bunch different machines.
That would be an
unnecessary amount
of work on a single machine,
better to split up
that work work.
All right. Thanks
for an extra minute.
Feel free to come up
and chat if folks have
any questions, have
a great weekend.