Semester where we're learning
about different
kinds of resources.
I have a little bit
to wrap up from
last time when we were
looking at Locks.
And then we're will
be moving into
our fourth and final
resource, which is storage.
And after that pretty soon
we'll be into a lot of
interesting things.
We're starting looking at
different distributed
systems that
can actually hold
quite a bit of data.
So let me actually
head back here.
Actually, before I do
that, let me just remind
you that we have a bid term
in one week. I try to check.
Does everybody have any
logistical questions about
the upcoming mid term?
Yeah, right over here.
So this Friday.
It will be anything before this.
Monday is fair game as well,
and I know that's not a lot of
turnaround time to perhaps.
I'll probably keep the
questions about that
Monday maybe a little
simpler than the rest.
I've tried having
another cutoff,
and then people just like,
don't come to that
lecture there like,
why should study for the mid
term instead. So it's there.
You'll maybe do better on
the mid term if you show
up for that October 7 lecture.
Yeah, other questions people
have about the mid term.
Fantastic. You'll
be like here in
class, show up as usual.
Cool. So I am going to
head back and look at some of
the things that we were
wrapping up last time.
So we learned about
blocks in general.
And I want to talk
about a couple of
advanced topics that people
should keep in mind.
And part of my goal here is that
sometimes people will have
maybe, like a clever idea,
and that it might
backfire on them because,
you know, there's some
of these advanced topics
that make you have to use
locks in a certain way.
And if you less you understand
them at a very deep level,
right, you cannot kind of have
some sort of clever
pattern, right?
You have to use locks in
a very conventional way.
So I just want to show a
couple of those things.
The first is about this
infamous lock called
the global interpreter
lock that is a Python.
First of may just show what the
global interpreter
Lock does to us,
and then I'll talk
about why it's there,
maybe the future of the lock.
But Here I have a machine
with six different CPU cores.
And at any given time,
one of these CPU cores
can be running a thread.
Here I just have
a single process.
So I see right now there's four
different threads
that are running.
One of these threads in
the Python code is
waiting for a file,
right? So it's blocked.
And I have another one here
that is actually blocked
on this thing called the
Global Interpreter Lock.
So the rule with the
global interpreter lock is
that only whenever any thread
is running Python code,
it has to hold that lock,
and that prevents other threads
from running Python
rode at the same time.
Right? So when I have
this thread here,
I cannot be running
this other thread that's in
Python rode at the same time.
Maybe somebody wrote
some library and
C or something that
doesn't use a global
interpreter lock,
and they can be running
a bunch of things.
That's one of the
reasons why people get
good performance where
you use something like
um Pi or somebod
else built in C,
instead of using
pure Python Trode.
But I can only run one
of these at a time.
That does mean that locks or
threads are less useful in
Python than other
languages, right?
In most languages, you
have a bunch of threads,
and they can all use CPU
cores at the same time,
and that helps you
utilize the CPU.
In this case, the main benefit
I'm getting from threads
running Pre Python rod is that I
could have one thread
that's blocked on IO,
while another one is
using CPU, right?
So if I just have
Pre Python road,
none of these extra libraries,
it's very you can't really
be using more than one
CPU core at a time.
Alright, let's just run
through this a little bit.
So it's running for a while.
When I stop running that w,
then both of these
become runable.
And maybe it starts
running this one,
W it starts running
this one, that thread
would acquire the global
interpreter lock.
And the first thread
would be blocked, right?
We can't run it right now
because it has to
wait until it has
a chart to have that
lock and run a good.
Maybe the IO finished
over here on this one.
So this thread that was waiting
for IO, stud with that.
Now we'll have to wait for
the global interpreter
lock as well.
Maybe when this one blocks,
because maybe it's doing
some sort of network I owe,
then we could start
actually running that
one again, right?
So we can see that that global
interpreter lock is
preventing us from
running as many threads as we
might be able to otherwise.
So why do they have this?
There's different reasons.
Probably the most supported
reason is that we have to do
some bookkeeping to figure
out what a piece of data
is no longer needed.
That bookkeeping is called
garbage collection, right?
So garbage collection,
we'll see, like, Oh,
maybe I have this
list that nobody's
using anymore in this program,
maybe I can free it up.
And let me just
show you an example
where I have two threads,
and they each have a
piece of code, right?
So I say x equals some
list that x equals no.
Y equals actually the same list
that the first thread
is looking at,
and then y equals ud.
And so at different
points in time,
kind of depending
on inner leavings,
I might have two variables
referring to that list
or one variable or no variables.
And of course, when
there's no variables
referring to some
data structure,
there's no other way
to get access to
that data structure.
We call it garbage, right?
That's memory that is not
helping our program in any
way, we could free it up.
So this point in
time, let's imagine
that I have both x and y set,
and I haven't set
either to ud yet.
So this case, I have the
both point to that list.
Python is ready to do some extra
bookkeeping to keep track of
how many references are
referring to that list
object on the heap.
And so as this runs
as y equals ud,
then that reference
cut would go to wood.
And then if it eventually goes
to zero, we would free it up.
Okay? So reference
counting is the only way
they do garbage
collection in Python,
but it's a big part of
what they're doing.
And one of the applications
of this is that if I
have multiple threads,
they need to modify
these same editors.
And one of the things we saw
last time is that if I have
two threads and I have
an editor that's just
like counting up,
I actually have to have
locking to get that
right because even a simple x
plus equals wo is
multiple instructions
and we could have
a context switch at
a bad type, right?
So how are we going
to do this here?
Well, we're tostly having
variables referring to objects.
So one thing is that we
could have lots of fine
grain locking in the
Python interpreter, right?
We the starbage collection,
stuff it could be acquiring
and releasing locks.
And that would actually
be quite slow, right?
It would probably make just a
regular single threaded
program slower?
If you have a single
threaded program and
it's constantly
locking and unlocking,
it's unnecessary and
slower than it would be.
What else might we
do? Maybe there's
other more clever approaches.
We could just say, let's run
one threaded type.
That's what Python does.
And so there's different
trade offs here.
And one of the
reasons that we've
had the global
interpreter lock for
a long time is there's been
pushback when people
want to remove it.
Well, that might make multi
threaded programs faster,
but single threaded
programs slower.
That's a trade off a lot of
people have not wanted
to make, right?
So we've had the
global interpreter
lock until now, right?
Now, what is the future of it?
Literally, this
week on October 1,
Python 3.13 is released.
And this is the first
made Python version where
they have a mode where you can
run without the global
interpreter lock.
And so there's actually
different versions you sell.
You can say one to
download Python with
the interpreter lock or
without the interpreter lock.
Which one is better for
you? While it depends?
How heavily you
are using threads?
Water lower might
be faster for you.
But they make a
note here, right?
This is experimental. There
are probably some bugs in it.
If you're using the
version without
the global interpreter lock,
single thread performance
is right take a had.
So this is something that
You know, for a long time,
it was not even an option to run
without the global
interpreter lock.
Now it's trying to
becoming an option,
but you're still going to have
to think about it because
there's gonna be some
performance trade offs.
Who knows?
Maybe somebody will fix
that and we have the best
of both worlds someday.
But I wouldn't bet on it.
The global Interpreter lock is
probably something you
have to think about if
you want to write
high performance
Python road and the log run.
What questions people have
about the global
Interpreter lock
or kind of the reason
why it's there.
Alright, so that was
one of the advanced
topics I wanted to talk about.
The other one is really related
to how CPUs work and how that
makes threads and locks
more complicated.
What I've been talking about
threads of locks so far.
The kind of problem that
we have been talking about
a lot is to text switches
at a bad time, right?
To text switches at
a bad time or one of the
reasons we use locks.
But it's actually
not the only reason.
I I don't want to spend a
lot of time on these topics,
but I just want people to not
get clever and think, like, Oh,
if I find another way to deal
with context switches
at a bad time,
I can avoid locks, right?
There is, whole areas of
research where people
build lock free data structures,
but you don't just have to
worry about context switches.
You have to worry about a
couple of other things.
So I just want these
other things to be on
your radar so you
don't try to write
something clever that is
missing some important details.
So, let me show you some
code that has two threads,
and it has no locks.
And based on everything
we've learned so far,
it would seem like it
would be correct code,
but it's actually not.
There's a bug here.
So let's see when I was
first sing about threads,
I wrote code like this
because I thought,
Oh, this is simpler than
thinking about locks.
But this is actually buggy.
What are we doing
here? So we have
a task that's to be
a thread, right?
So I'm say thread
target equals task.
And that task, its job is to
square x and put the
value in the y variable.
And then I can see down
here in the Bad thread,
we're putting off
that y variable.
And so the goal is that
we don't want to put
off the y variable until
the computation is done.
We want to wait until it
actually calculates it,
and then put it out later.
And so, you know,
the correct way
to do that would be
with a droid operation.
What does this person
try to do here?
Well, they created
a ready variable,
not lock, just a ready variable.
And after they set y
equal to the value,
then they say ready equals true.
And what does the
made thread do?
It just keeps looping
until ready is
true and then it
prints off y, right?
So if I only had to worry
about inter leaving and
context switches at bad time,
this would be correct code.
It's actually not correct code.
And the reason why
is that CPUs do
something called out of
order execution, right?
W I wrote this code here,
Y equals sing, ready equals,
I wrote in that order.
But sometimes it might be
faster for the CPU to say,
ready equals true first and
y equals something first.
And when the CPU is
trying to figure out,
can I reorder these
instructions?
It's only looking
at the code here.
It's not thinking
about other threads.
If I'm only looking at the code
here inside of this function,
well, yeah, it doesn't really
matter the order of these.
The order really matters
depending on what other
threads are doing,
but the CPU is not aware of
those at the moment, right?
So the CPU might reorder these.
Why might it do that?
Well, We've already seen
that one of the reasons that
CPUs get slow is because
they have to load
some memory from RAM.
And when they do that, they
do some load instruction.
And, you know, we were going
along with this fast clock,
like, you know, billions
of ticks per second.
And all of a sudden, we
have to wait for 200 ticks
to get a piece of
memory from RAM.
We have to load that
to the register.
And so sometimes
the CPU might say,
Oh, like, this instruction,
I'm stuck on it for a while.
Maybe I can work on some
other things, right?
Maybe there's other
values that are already,
like in a cache
or in a register.
So CPU might do
things out of order
if it's kind of waiting
a long time on a specific
instruction, right?
So stuff like this can happen.
And the CPU is just
looking at that local code
to figure out whether that's
a reasonable thing to do.
Do people have any
questions about
out of order execution?
And, of course, why is
this a problem for us?
Because if ready equals true,
before we compute the value,
then this loop out
here by it sp and it
might pret y before we
actually get a value and Y?
Yeah, question right
here. Yeah, you're right.
By should be a global variable.
Maybe I'll just make
a note of that.
So maybe I'll take
something like global.
Why? Good catch. Yeah.
Thanks for catching
that. Yeah Myb
I should actually
the previous slide,
too, so it's not confusing.
Y, those are both
global variables.
Whatever I you and pick
a bunch of these slides.
Yeah another question over here.
What will the CPU do?
What? Order. What does
it know not to reorder
the execution.
So Locks can do multiple things.
One of the things they
can do is make sure that
two pieces of cod any
at the same time.
They also do something that
I'm not trying to
get into a lot,
but they have something
called a memory barrier.
And Aby barrier
says that basically
all these changes to
memory before the locking
happened have to basically be
visible elsewhere before
after the lock, right?
So if I'm kind of like releasing
a lock and somebody
else acquires it,
it's try to make sure that kind
of all the changes
I had with the lock
are going to be visible
afterwards, right?
So it's not just about
running at the same time,
I try to make sure
all these changes
actually appear to other people
in that order. Do
that make sense?
Yeah, excellent question.
Yeah. Other questions
people have.
Alright, so that's
like, one weird thing
that CPUs do that we
have to worry about.
Locks just take care
of that, right?
So if you're trying to do
something clever
that's lock free,
you really have
to understand how
the CPU works in
quite a bit of tail.
You have to understand in more
detail than, I understand.
I could just row and
make a lock free
data structure very readily.
I'd have to really understand
in more detail what's drawing.
These are just some broad things
that you might have
to worry about.
Let's look at another case here.
We learned that we have these
different caches, right?
And You know, an L
one cash is just for
a single core on a CPU on a
single core on a processor.
It's totally
possible I also have
multiple processor chips plugged
into my motherboard
and in that case,
each of them would have their
own L three cash, right?
So cashes, right are not
shared across all
cores in general.
Some are shared to
a greater extent
and some to a less extent,
but cashes are not
shared universally.
So I can imagine a case like
this where in Poor one,
maybe the L one cash
has these values in it,
and maybe the L one cash for
CR two has se old values.
The cash hasn't been
updated yet, right?
Because we just just
now made these changes
in the L one cash.
And what could happen is
as the cash becomes fresh,
we are really don't
have really guarantees
on which value will become
fresh first, right?
So maybe ready gets fresh first,
and we sell a sale value for y.
And I might put off
that sale value.
Again, if we do locking history,
to make sure that the
right thing happens
with respect to cashing, right?
So What I really want
you to do, right?
Is don't get too clever with
this locking stuff that can
really come back and bite you
with all these strange things.
What you should do is you
should see, like, well,
what state am I accessing
for multiple threads?
And I should identify
those critical sections of
code that are accessing that
and just, put a lock around it.
Don't get clever
and avoid locks.
These locks solve
many problems for us.
And are leaving is the one
problem we looked a lot at.
There's other problems
they solve as well.
So, do people have any questions
about these kind of
more advanced topics?
All right. Fantastic. So I
already give a bunch of advice,
and we're a little bit be hid,
subtraight a head over here,
but feel free to review
that advice for kind
of using lock as well.
Let's talk about file systems.
So file systems to
do a lot of things.
One of the things they
could do is they could
manage the bytes of
data on a block device.
A block device might be like
a hard disk drive or an SSD.
And so one of the things we
want to do is if we were
to thinking about files,
we also have to think about what
are the performance
characteristics
of different devices
that we might be using.
Why do you be able to describe
different types of
file systems? Right?
There's lots of different tins
of file system out there.
At any given time, you're using
at least a few different types,
and not necessarily
thinking about it.
And then finally, we've seen
these commands before Mo and DF.
I want to look at those a
little bit more carefully
now that we actually will
understand what a
file system is.
Okay, so let's start
at the low level,
which is block devices.
And what is a block device?
Well, maybe it makes sense
to contrast it with memory.
With memory, what I
say is that memory is
byte addressable, right?
So Memory has a bunch of bits,
and those bits are chucked
together in bytes.
So eight bits is a byte.
Each byte of memory has
its own unique adress?
Yeah, question right here.
Slide. Oh, are the
slides out of the site?
Maybe I forgot to post the
I could just do that quick
if that's helpful to
people. Let me just see.
Maybe if some people like
to take notes on it or
something like that.
You know, I may have
to exploore stuff.
So by apologies, I'll try to
have it posted online later.
I'll be sure it comes
it's posted afterwards.
So memory is bite addressable.
Whereas blocks, block device.
What they are we do is
break up all these bits
into blocks that are
relatively large.
Maybe like 512 bytes,
half a kilobyte or maybe a
couple of kilobytes, right?
And I may have a block address
for each of these
different blocks.
That'll be the granularity
that I communicate back and
forth with that block device.
So that's going to make some big
impacts on our performance.
So let's imagine that I had
this file stored
on a block device.
It's a CSV file,
and I've highlighted
different colors regions
of 512 bytes, right?
So the first few rows of the
file are that first block,
kind of splits in the middle.
I have some more rows
of the second block,
and so on and so forth, right?
And if I'm writing a program,
I might be looping over, say,
like, one line at a time,
but when we're actually
accessing data on the disk,
it's to be doing these
bigger 512 byte transfers.
So there's a couple of things
that the operating system
is going to do to help
make that faster.
What is that long term?
It might cash these things?
We already learned
about the page cache.
About how that works with MAP,
and can also use that
if we're just like
doing regular reads to a file.
And so in that case, the
page cast lease linux
is four kilobyte blocks,
so that would be sorry,
four kilobyte pages,
that would be
like eight blocks from,
say, a hard drive or
something like that.
And it will just
keep that. So if I'm
reading the same
file multiple times,
maybe I don't have to do
disco on multiple times.
Even if I'm making
one pass though,
we can use memory to help.
So Pytho and lix and other
layers of the stack.
What they'll do is if I access
just like one line of data.
They're going to pull
in a whole block of
data or maybe multiple
blocks of data,
and they're going
to keep that in
a piece of memory
because they're
assuming I'm may be
looping over and
I'm going to ask for
the next slide soon.
That's called buffering, right?
So when I'm to try
to keep data around
blog terminas.
I using. That's caching.
Buffering is when I'm doing
these transfers that I want to
transfer data to the bigger
chucks for performance reasons,
but the application of
a higher level needs
smaller chucks.
I might buffer those
bigger chucks and memory.
So it's ready when
it's needed, right?
So when I'm actually
these files,
both caching and buffering
might be in play.
And you can usually see
that if you look at H top,
usually there'll be
some amount of memory
that's just like actually memory
that processes are using.
There's may be some
page cache memory.
And then there's
usually another color
there that indicates
memory for buffers.
That's usually not a
lot of memory, right,
because it's kind of temporary
for having these
bigger chunks of data.
So that will show up if you
go and run a tool like H top.
Okay, so where does this
matter for performance?
I want to imagine that I
have this big CSV file.
It's not quite a CSV file.
It's like a kind of a cab format
where I have some spaces
between each column.
And I'm just trying
to imagine that
I don't care about all the data.
I just want to access all
of the weather
station IDs, right?
So this is a data set
of weather stations.
And there's a couple
of ways I could do it.
Of the simple way on
the left hand side
would be I just open the file,
and I read it one
line at a time,
so I'm pulling it whole lines,
and then I could just slice
out the first 11 characters,
which is the station and put
that in the list, right?
So this program on the left,
could give me all
the station IDs.
I wrote that program. I
rad it on some data set.
That took 66
milliseconds to run.
And at first glance,
it seems kind of
wasteful, right?
Because I only care
about that little bit
of data at the
beginning of each line,
but it's actually reading
the whole lines first,
and kind of trimming it down.
Okay. So that was not great.
So then I tried to write
an optimized version.
The optimized version.
I put that in quotes
because it actually
ended up being slower.
And when we know about
how the display works,
we can understand
why the optimization
was actually bad, right?
It actually made things worse.
So this more complicated
optimized version on the right,
I said that I only ever want
to read the station ID.
I don't want to read
any other data.
So I did a few things.
When I opened the file,
I said, don't buffer it.
I don't want you to read
it all this extra data.
I just want to access these
small bits of station ID.
And then what I did is
I figured out how
long each line was.
I was like 86 characters.
And then I would compute
it offset by that.
I would have an offset,
and I would 86
characters at a time.
So I could draw a
different offset of
the file that was always
the start of aide.
And that's the SIC operation.
The SIC operation means that I'm
ready to read at a specific
offset of the file, right?
I kind of jump into the
beginning of each slide.
In this case, I just read,
I say, dot read instead of
reading the whole thing.
I would just read
11 bytes, right?
So I'm kind of very
carefully saying,
I my Python program,
only ever give me the Sasha IDs.
Don't give me a whole line
because I don't need
the whole line.
And that's actually
slower, right?
Be because I disabled
buffer at the lower level,
we're still communicating with
the disc get the
granularity of 512 bytes,
no matter what I try to do
otherwise in my Python
program, right?
So my Python program,
it's not very helpful to try to
read small pieces of
data that are subset.
Of block, right?
That's ABD faster just
reading the whole blocks.
And I'll actually get
worse performance,
right if I try to disable
buffering, right?
So it's very similar to what we
saw with cash
liides with memory.
When we're kind of
accessing cash lids,
we want to have programs
that are accessing
whole cash lids of data.
If we just access a little
bit of each cash liide,
where I have worse
performance and
if we're accessing
the whole thing.
So people have questions
about the difference
between these two approaches.
Yeah, question right over here.
Explain what? Oh,
like, the buffering.
I basically disabled buffering.
So normally, Python will
do some buffering for me,
and it'll try to when I
read a little bit of data.
I'll actually read a whole bunch
of data and save it in memory.
So when I do some more reads,
it's just ready for me.
And so I'm saying the
optimized version,
I try to say, I only want to
read the data I
need, nothing more.
And that's why I
disabled buffering
because buffering would
read extra stuff.
Now, disabling buffering
did actually help
because when I'm ultimately
doing disci at a lower level,
it still has to bring
in these whole blocks
at a time anyway, right?
So disabling
buffering could only
hurt me in this case.
That makes sense?
Yeah, right here. Fo.
Yeah, I think if buffer was d,
we ought to have
identical performance.
I don't know if I tried it.
I guess I kind of did
it like a year ago,
but we could try it too.
I mean, that'd be
kind of fun, but
my expectations that
the performance
would be identical
if we had buffer od.
Yeah, great question. Yeah,
all questions people have.
Alright. C. So we have different
types of block devices,
and that was one thing
in common, right?
We want to have be transferring
at least the size of these
blocks for the block device,
but also they have very
different characteristics
as well in other regards.
I'll be look at too.
I look at the hard
disk drive and
also the solid state disk.
And the hard drive actually
has these moving parts.
It has these platters
that are magnetized,
depending on the state
of the magnetism.
It could either be a zero or
a one and a specific point.
This is just spitting
around quite rapidly.
And What we have over here at
the top is is a read right head.
And so that arb will just
move the head back and
forth across the platter.
And wherever it is, it can
read the bite of data at
that position, right?
So if I want to either
read or write some data,
there's a few things
that will happen.
It has to manually move
that head somewhere,
and has to wait
until the platter
spends so the data is
underneath the head,
and then it'll finally actually
start transferring
the data, right?
And those first two
parts that I'm talking
about are going to be what
takes most of the time.
And that's true unless I'm
transferring a lot of data,
say, like the order
of a few megabytes.
If I'm transferring a
few megabytes that I
care about that step three,
but if it's smaller, then step
one and two will
tend to dominate.
Okay? So the way
we'll interact with this
is that internally,
we have all these bytes
in different places,
and what the hard
drive will do is
we'll a side block
locations out here.
Of course, this will be packed
much more tightly
than I'm drawing,
but you can see
block location zero,
one, two, so on and so forth.
And what they try to do
is they try to make sure
that consecutive numbers are
actually next to
each other on disk.
Be when you're programming,
right, let's say,
like you were building
a file system or
something like that,
you don't can't
really quite look
inside of the hard drive
and know the layout.
But what they're trying to
guarantee you is that if
you access blocks
with similar numbers,
If you do a bunch
of those in a row,
then we should have a
pretty fast access pattern,
where we spend most of the time
transferring data instead of
the fixed overhead of
one and two, right?
So that's what's
happening in totally.
And so for the
external perspective,
when we're reading or
writing to a hard drive,
we want to access consecutive
block locations, right?
So we call that a
sequential pattern.
So if I read like 5678,
that would be fast because I
don't have these
fixed overheads.
If I have a do access
pattern where I read,
you know, block two, nine,
five, one, then
that would be a lot
slower because I have to
pay these fixed overheads.
All right.
Just some other interesting
things that people do.
You can imagine that,
you know, rotationally,
it's rotating some
number of degrees
or radians per second.
And on the outside track,
there's more space so they
can pack more bytes in.
And so one of the applications
is on the outside track,
The bites are going
underneath the red head at
a faster rate than on
the inside track, right?
If the physics of that
that makes sense.
And so data on the outside
track would actually
be faster, right?
Kind of different location on
the disc will be either
be faster or shorter.
Some people just
decide that, you know,
hard drives have
a ton of capacity
and kind of the performance
of actually accessing is
what really is painful.
Some people just say,
like, I don't want to
even use the inside track.
That would be called
short stroking. They say,
I'm going to keep all my data
on those outside tracks.
The way they'll normally
do that is I'll start
numbering from blocks
zero around the outside,
so you could just
say I want to use
like the first half
of the blocks,
and then you would have
better performance that if
you were using
that inside track.
Of course, the disadvantage,
you have less space available.
Yeah. Questions right here.
Era Yeah.
Like, you're saying, like,
would it make sense so you
put the operating system
of the outside track
or the inside track?
Yeah. Like, I think generally,
you want to put data that is
kind of accessed a lot on
the outside track
with the caveat that
fits access so often destroy
me a Rab anyway, right?
So you want to put data on
the outside track
that's like pretty
hot, but not the hottest data.
So you can imagine like that
becomes like a whole problem
that you could spend a long
time thinking about, like,
Well, I have all this data,
all these files, and, you
know, where should
I put it, right?
That's something that
people think about, right?
And it's a complicated
space to work in, right?
Yeah, it's definitely
interesting though.
Yeah, other questions or
comments people have.
Alright. Cool. So
those are hard drives.
They have some performance
characteristics.
Solid state discs.
The solid state means that
there's no moving parts.
There's different technologies
like the main one that is
basically used universally
is something called flash.
And with flash, instead
of it being magnetized,
it's either like
charged or not charged.
And so since there's
no moving parts,
right, it's going to
be faster, right?
Be you're of sending
electrical signals instead of
waiting for something to
actually physically move.
And it's also
inherently parallel.
So when I'm look
at a hard drive,
there's like one head
that moves around.
It could be one place at a
time with an SSD, often times,
like we could be
reading bytes from
different portions of the
SSD simultaneously, right?
So already, you
can try to imagine
why we would have a lot
better performance with this.
But it still has some
weird internal details
that impact performance.
To understand these, I have to
use these word block and page.
And I've used both of
those words before.
I've been using block
in this lecture
to refer to the granularity
of the data transfer
between the block
device and software.
And I've used page before
as type of the unit
of caching of memory in
the operating system.
And these words are also used to
talk about how an SSD
works internally,
and they just have absolutely
completely different
meanings in this context.
So my apologies, I didn't
choose the terminology.
I just want to be clear that
when I'm on this slide,
I'm using these words
completely differently.
Okay? So a page is
the unit in which we can either
read or write some data.
Okay? And so I've drawn down
here a small page of data.
And one of the
tricks is or one of
the annoying things is that when
I have a page of data writed,
I cannot rewrite it
with something else,
because that page is
part of something
bigger called a block, right?
And if I want to, I can
erase a whole block,
but I can't just erase
a portion of it.
Has anybody ever played with
an echa sketch?
That's this toy here?
Yeah. So actually a sketch
there are lots of fu,
you could draw on it in
fired detail, right?
But if I want to erase
something, it's cores straight.
I have to shake the whole thing.
So in this case, the fired thing
that's happening
are these pages,
but the erase is cores straight.
That's the whole thing.
So you should really
imagine at SSD,
like, a big array
of these sketches.
I can try to write in the pages,
but then if I want to
change the value at a page,
Well, now I have
a problem, right?
And so that's going to
impact the performance.
I'll kind of make us
think about how we
actually want to
use this device.
So I want to imagine that I've
already ridded all the
pages of the block here,
and so ABCD, and now I want
to replace B with x, right?
So I have two options.
One is that I could
erase the whole thing.
And then I could write x there.
But if I have to do
that, then I'd have to
save ACD and memory and
write those a second
time as well, right?
So I try to write
one page one page,
but then I'm like,
I had to erase
this whole thing. That
took a long time.
I had to write all the pages.
That would be kind of bad.
Right? It would be slow.
So the other thing
that people will more
often do is instead
of writing x there,
they'll say, Let's just write
X somewhere else, right?
So they'll say, Hey,
let's write X over here.
And even though B is garbage,
we're trying to
replace B with x,
we'll just like leave
it there because
it's too expensive to erase it.
If I erase that then I have
to have all this collateral,
I don't want to say
damage, but I have to have
this collateral cost, right?
All right. So, What
about here, right?
So if I do that, that I need to
do some extra book
keeping, right?
So SSDs will usually have
something about of Rb,
and they'll keep track of,
like, well, you know,
instead of the data actually
being where it was
originally here,
in this other place,
they have to have
some mapping that
when you're using it,
and I write to a page specific
location that I read it,
maybe it's different
places internally.
I don't want to think about
that. I just want to get back
the same data that I
wrote to it before.
So that's one thing
that they have to do.
The other thing is
that Eventually,
right, if you're
already out of space,
they'll have to reclaim that.
And what they might do
is they might wait.
In this case, procrastation
is good because right now,
B is garbage, but if I wait,
maybe C and D might
become garbage as well.
Maybe if a lot of that data
that block is garbage,
that it's not so wasteful to
erase the whole thing
and rewrite it, right?
So we kind of want to
procrastate it and hope of
that when we have
to do the work.
We could do a lot of
that at the same time.
So in terms of the strategy
for somebody who's actually
using these things,
what you want to do is
you uh to avoided this
circumstance, right?
B this is slow it kind
of creates this waste.
If you want to use
the SSD effectively,
you uh to write, like,
big files sequentially.
You're to write a little bit of
data here and a little there,
the natural cause
these override.
They'll kind of get
this bad performance
out of your SSD. All right.
Well, I guess I
should just pause
there by question about it.
It's a little bit strange,
right? But that's
how the performance
will play out.
Yeah, right here. Block s
and then like dated
that you Okay.
Yeah, you're saying
that we could
move ACD somewhere else as well,
then just try of
reclaim this block.
Yeah, and they're going to do
something like that, right?
Because once they have to
add this extra
bookkeeping to keep track
of that a given piece
of data could be in
different places,
then would I have to
eventually erase this?
I mean, I could we
use the same block,
or I could be use
a different block
and kind it doesn't
matter if I have
some sort of mapping
structure that
keeps track of where
it actually is, right?
So you'll usually just
try have like some pool,
like these blocks are
ready for writing,
and then of all
the other blocks,
the SST is try to keep
track of how dirty
they are, right?
L, there are some blocks that
might have mostly current data,
and some of mostly garbage.
And we need to free up some
space you want to do
the ones that are
mostly garbage first or you
know, there's other policies.
I don't want to get
too deep into it,
but there's other strategies
you might chose to
figure out, well,
when I clean something
up, there's a bunch of
blocks that have a mix
of garbage and data.
Which one should I clean up to
get the best performance
of the long run?
But yeah, definitely everything
is fluid at this point, right?
If we keep track of
where the data is,
it doesn't have to be
in the same place.
Yeah, Excellent point. Yeah,
other comets or questions.
Cool. So I want to compare
the performance
characteristics between these.
There's different
metrics when I'm
comparing storage resource.
I can think about the capacity.
A latency is how
long it might take
to transfer just like
one small piece of data.
Iops is related to that,
so that's IO
operations per second.
So the IO operations
are read or right.
And when it's ask me how
many I could do per second,
that will depend on the latency,
but it will also
depend on how many
I could do in parallel.
So these reads or
writes are generally
considered to be small.
And then throughput
would just be
how many bytes I could
transfer per second?
And that probably
depends on by workload
by doing kind of a sequential
pattern or added pattern.
I just put Oh, let me go back.
I put over here, relative
to S hard drives, well,
what I say about SSDs,
and this is a little
bit, you know,
handwavy, about
quantifying things
here because both devices
are always changing.
So in terms of capacity,
like how many bytes
we just store,
SSDs are much worse
per dollar, right?
You have to pay a lot more
for SSDs per byte of storage.
In terms of latency,
SSDs are much better because
there's no moving parts.
If I just want to read
one little block of data,
I can get it back very quickly.
If I'm talking about
rad i ops per second,
I'm randomly reading little
pieces of data all
over the place,
Estes are fantastic about
that because there's low
lats no movie parts.
I can do a bunch of those
things in parallel,
right? What about throughput?
So, let's say I'm
just sequentially
accessing a bunch of data.
Hard disk drives are actually
pretty good at that, right?
Le once you get the
head in position
and you start
transferring bytes,
it could be pretty fast, right?
So SSDs are probably
a little bit faster,
but that might be in
the same ballpark.
I mean, it all depends on
how high SSD you have.
But hard disks are pretty
good at throughput transfer.
O, you'll say, SSDs are
a little bit better.
What about if I have
measuring my throughput
bytes per second,
and I'm either randomly
writing data or
randomly reading data?
SSDs are going to be
better in either case,
but for the random write taste,
I have to worry about
that block thing,
the block clean up.
How important does that?
It might depend, right?
If I'm just like
cost like writing to
my SSD randomly all the time,
eventually, I may run out
of blocks to write to it.
It's going to be constantly
garbage collecting them,
and that would be Trosty, right?
One of the nice things
about the SSDs is
that I could have a burst of
a bunch of random writes,
and that if I don't
write to it for a while,
then it could try in
the background to clean
things up so that when
I have another sudden burst
of a bunch of rights
would be okay, right?
So if we're doing a
bunch of random rights,
we have to worry
about that with SSDs.
You can see, in terms
of performance,
with the hard drive,
there's a bunch of things
you have to worry about
to get good performance.
With SSDs, the one thing
you really have to worry
about is am I randomly
writing data a lot
of different places?
If you are, then you might have
a problem, but in general,
SSDs, a lot of patterns,
it straight be pretty fast at.
Have you got any
questions about that from
Parison? Yeah,
question right here.
Yeah. So you just proposed idea,
which is cell just say that.
So, maybe the application
itself is doing a bunch
of random rights.
But when we write
applications, right?
No probably none of us
have had to actually worry
about this where we're like,
say, I'm writing
to this block on
my SSD or that block on my SSD.
We are doing that.
What we're really
doing is we're writing
to maybe a database or you
do a file system, like that.
That's to ultimately manage
those blocks for us.
And so it's totally
possible that
an application have
some random rights,
and some layer of software
could convert those
random rights.
Into something sequential that's
better for the device, right?
So you can imagine this from
the perspective of like,
Well, I'm trying to
write an application
that's SSD friendly.
It's also possible
that you could have
a SSD friendly database that
makes the application
not need to
worry about it.
Excellent point, right?
So we have to make things
sequential to get a performance.
That doesn't mean that
every person writing
every application has to
necessarily worry about it.
If they're building on top of
somebody else that
worries about it
for you. Yeah, great point.
Other points or
questions people have.
Alright, cool. So that's the
hardware we're dealing with.
I just want to show
some quick other things
that might happen here.
One of the things
we might do is if I
have a big hard
drive or a big SSD,
I could partition it
in different parts.
And kind of logically,
each of those will appear
like it's a wed device,
even though there's
only one real device.
Onlytx, if I go under Slash Dv,
I can like L S files,
and I can see these
different partitions.
So SDA and SDB would be
referring to two different
actual hard drives or SSDs.
And then all these other
things like SDA one,
SDB one, SDA 14.
Those are referring to
partitions of that, right?
So often we'll have
kind of a big device,
and we'll carve it
it a smaller chucks.
That's called partitioning.
The opposite of
partitioning is that we
might actually have a bunch
of different devices,
and we want to make it look like
one giant device with
a lot of capacity.
And the technology that
does that is called raid.
And so raid ss for
a redundant array of
an expensive disks.
Who knows? Maybe
they are expensive.
But the idea is that we have
a bunch of different disks,
and a raid controller
can make it appear.
Like it's one big desk, right?
And why is it redundant?
Well, it's not always
redundant actually, right?
So maybe it's not always
red it's always expensive.
But sometimes what we
might want to worry about
is if I have all of these SSDs,
and one of them
eventually fails,
I don't want to
necessarily lose data.
So sometimes a raid
controller might
heat multiple copies of data
in different places or have
other forms of redundancy so
that we feel like we
have this giant device,
and if one of the
actual devices fails,
we don't lose any data, right?
We can have a bunch of cheap,
bad desks that we
could appear like
one big, reliable desk, right?
That's rain. Have you
know any question about
either partitioning or raid?
Yeah, right here.
Possible. For SSD.
S three Oh, you're
say say you have three
HDDs, and three SSDs.
And you have a rad controller
that manages both of them.
So I'm not aware
of, like in theory,
you could do anything, right?
Like the implementations
that I have seen,
they do well when the
devices are similar.
They have similar
performance properties
and stuff like that.
They generally aren't
going to realize, like,
Oh, like, this one's fast
or this one's slower.
Let's take advantage
of that, right?
So generally, they'd
use raid to kind of
have a bunch of similar devices
appear like one big device.
Now, you could totally
have a computer that has
both fast SSDs and
slow hard drisks.
Then generally at a higher
level, maybe in software,
you might write
like a database or
some application that's smart
about using both of those.
But what generally happen
at the raid level?
Rd is usually kind of simpler.
Making uniform things appear,
like, one bigger thing.
Yeah, its excellent ought thoug,
right you could imagine
building a different
kind of raid.
That's smart about it, right?
Yeah, Other questions or ideas.
All right. Cool.
So we've seen lots
of different ways we
have block devices.
You have an SST, you can
have a hard disk drive.
You can have some
combination of those.
You can have some fraction
of one with partitioning.
Once we have a block device,
then we need to have some
way of managing it, right?
Imagine how annoying would be
if you want to save some data,
and you have to say, like,
I want to write my data.
And blocks like three,
six and seven, or you
have to figure out
which blocks are free.
You'd have to break it up.
And so writing data
directly in blocks is
something that's difficult and
we wouldn't want to do it often.
And what's easier is
just writing a file.
When I just write a file,
it's like whatever
size I want to be.
And that data ultimately
ends up in different blocks,
but I don't really
think about it, right?
So why is it
so why do we have that
convenienal to write a file?
Well, there's a piece of
software called a file system.
The file system lets us write
these files of any size we want.
And it figures out here
are some free blocks,
and it splits up our data
across these different blocks.
And so what we want to
do if we want to write
applications that are kind
of using storage well,
we have to understand
a bit about how
the actual hardware works,
and we have to understand
a little bit about what
the file system might be
doing on top of that.
The world all user is abstract.
The file system is
abstracting storage.
If I write a file,
I'm also writing
block individual blocks, but
I'm not thinking about that.
That's headed from
me. Abstraction hides
ugly details that I
don't want to have
to think about all the time.
There's lots of different
file systems out there,
and the most common or kind of
basic one is what I call
a local file system.
But I have a local file system.
I have some code that's
maybe read or write a file,
and that is to figure
out on my behalf,
which blocks to actually read
or write to achieve that.
Here's six different
kinds of file systems.
I'm just going to
go through one by
one that I want you
to remember, right?
So I have that local file
system on the top left.
When we're using docker,
And I create a new container.
It has a new file
system with new files.
Now, fortunately,
I don't have to
buy a new hard drive every
time I start a new container.
That would be awful, right?
And so the file system that
I'm giving to that container,
what it's actually doing is
it's saving its data at
a different file system,
probably some local file system.
So there's some
file systems like
overlay FS is the one
that Docker uses,
where I store files in there,
that it takes some of
those files and it stores
at a different local
file system, right?
So we might often have
file systems on top of
file systems on top
of block devices.
Right? Sometimes people want
to read and write files,
but they wanted to
be really fast,
and they want it
to be temporary.
And so even though they like
to think in terms of files,
they want it to be in memory.
And so we have
memory file systems.
The big one is called TPS.
Kind of makes sense,
right? You have
temporary files there
because when you reboot,
all those files are broad,
but it's really fast for
we're using that, right?
So a TPS instead of using a
block device might use Rab.
Oftentimes, the operating
system wants to give us
different information
about processes
or things like that.
And you can imagine different
APIs they could build.
But why build something new
when everybody can just
learn how to use files.
And so there's things called
pseudo file systems, right?
In a pseudo file system,
what it might do is it It
might look like I have a file
for every process
that's running.
When I read that file, I can
see that the data that file
would tell me like
how much memory
that process is using, right?
Like that information about how
much memory a process using,
it's not stored in a disk
anyware in real file.
It's just a pseudo file system.
The main one that we need to
know is called the Proc FS.
That's a process file system.
There's no real files there,
but it looks like
there are files,
and when I read them, I
can learn about my system.
How many people have ever
gone out to the CS lab and saved
some files and then draw on
to a different machine and
saw those files are still
there? Has anybody
ever done that?
A few of you, that essks
to something called a
network file system, right?
So one network file
system is called NFS,
the one of the CS
lab is called AFS,
that's a different type
of network file system.
And the idea here is that we
have some type of server.
And on that server,
there is maybe a
local file system,
storing data on some desk.
And then on top of
that, what we have is
a network file system
server, right?
And it's there.
And what that's trying
to do is it's try to
let other people on other
machines see those files.
So if I have some code running
on a separate machine,
It's going to be using
an NFS file system
that is there locally,
and that NFS file system
is going to be doing
remote procedure calls
to that NFS server.
So if I read a file over here,
I send the request
over the server,
get the data there,
and then send it back.
That's great because it feels
like I'm just reading files,
even though those files
are not on my computer.
I could jump to
a different computer and
have the same set off,
and I could see those same files
that I created elsewhere.
So we need to have
network file system.
As well, right? And then
where are we headed?
After the mid term,
one of the things we're
going to be spending
a lot of time on is
distributed systems.
And particularly we want
to see what happens
if I have a distributed
file system.
And the w where we learned
is the Dup file system.
In that case, the Du
file system is going to
have maybe like hundreds
or thousands of machines.
I's star to be storing
data across those.
But it's just started to
feel like a file system,
that's where we have
some big files.
Of course if you have
hundreds of machines,
these files can be quite large.
Do people have any
questions about
these different kinds
of file systems
or the different purposes
of file systems?
All right. So I want to look a
little bit more closely at
the local file system, because
that's often the base.
Right?
At of these other file systems
are based on top of it.
And somebody I
imagine in this case,
I have two kilobyte blocks,
and I have a few here.
And so the question is, how does
the local file system
use different blocks?
There's actually lots of
different ways you could do it,
a lot of different strategies.
I'm just trying to show
an example of one
way you might do
it to kind of give you a general
idea of what they might do.
First off, they want
to have some notion of
file that is really the
stake from any name,
what we actually see
is there's ways to
have multiple names
for the same file.
And so the technical
term is ode, right?
And so an ode can refer
to some number of bytes.
You just think of an iod as
somebody that's
giving me file data,
but not a file name.
And so what we can do is we
can put some ides in a block.
I imagine that's 1 kilobyte.
And what it'll do is it'll
have basically pointers
to different blocks.
So I guess this ode zero
has blocks two and four,
and it'll have some metadata.
It might tell me that
that file is only 3
kilobytes, right?
So I'm not really using
all of my second block.
Right? In this case,
that files fragmented,
it's not contiguous at disk.
Sometimes you write
an application
that's like read
data sequentially,
but takes the file system,
and it actually ends
up random, right?
Which is not great.
What about directories?
Well, directories are really
kind of special files,
and so I've shown
one here, right?
So I've added 01,
and that just has blocks three.
And I have some data inside
of that special file.
And what is that data inside
of a special directory file?
Well, it'll be a
bunch of file names
referring to IO numbers, right?
So file dot text is
referring to 00 over here.
F 00, I can get the data
inside of that file, right?
Things like these extenches
don't mean anything.
It's just for kind of
human documentation.
And there's no reason
I couldn't have
the same O number in
different directories, right?
That same IO would
have different
names in different places.
Each file system
has a root factory.
So I might say that iO.
One is the root factory
from which I can find
everything else.
And would I have a new
desk, I have to format it.
I have to create all these
initial stata structure.
I have to create some ios create
an empty root drator,
all those things.
That's called formatting, right?
So if you get a
new empty device,
you're going to have to format
it before you can use it.
Alright, fantastic.
We'll there and
feel free to come up and chat
if you have any questions.