Rapping up one of
the major resources
of the semester,
which is networking.
After that, we're going to spend
about three lectures
on memory resources,
and then we're going to
do computed storage.
And so I just have a
few things to wrap
up from last time just
a few slides there.
And then we're able to
spend most of the time
today talking about
how we can use memory,
and in particular, how
we can create caches.
So I'm going to head over
here to where we were last time.
So last time we learned
about how we could
spit up these Doctor
compose clusters.
And you can imagine
doing something similar,
where instead of having
all the containers
on the same machine,
you have them on
different machines.
And once you start to do that,
where you have
different pieces of
your application running
a different machines,
and you have a large data set
that doesn't fit on
a single machine,
you have to think, how can
I break up my dataset?
How can I make sure that
I don't lose pieces of
my data set even if
some machines die?
And that leads us to
partitioning and replication.
So I'm imagining this large data
set with a lot of machines,
and I'm realizing I need to
be on HDMI. Okay, great.
And so when we break it up,
that's called
partitioning, right?
And when we have
multiple copies of
the same piece for
reliability, that's
called replication.
Often, you might
use partitioning or
replication or very often,
both in combination.
These are ideas that we we
see repeatedly this semester.
I just want to have a light
introduction early on,
because it makes sense after
the networking content that
we would take a look at that.
So, let's imagine that I'm
building an application
to help instructors.
I love applications
like that, by the way.
And this application is going to
let you search for
a student's name,
and it will tell you
their student ID.
Very simple, right? And let's
imagine that the dataset is
huge for whatever reason.
And it's so big that we cannot
store it and serve it
up on a single machine.
So let's say we
have two machines.
It's really kind of like the
simplest possible cluster,
of course, you can imagine
something analogous to this.
Maybe it's like Facebook IDs,
and you have like 1,000
machines. Who knows, right?
But here we're look
at a simple scenario.
And so with the data set,
I want to find different ways
that we could split it up.
O is that we could just
try to cut it 50 50,
first half on the first machine,
second half on the
second machine,
that that balances the data
nicely across different places.
But the disadvantages is that
when I am using an
application built on this,
I'm ready to put it a name,
and we have to figure
out which machine
or multiple machines
do we have to check?
To find the student ID.
And if we don't know anything
about kind of the range
of values in here,
what will happen is that
we actually have to
send the request
to both machines,
you know, let's say,
like it's R of.
We can ask the first
machine, do you have R of?
Second machine do you have RF,
and then combine the answers.
That's not efficient.
Kind of defeats the purpose
of partitioning this
in the first place.
Some cases is okay,
but many use cases, it's not.
The other thing you could do is
you could do range partitioning.
Maybe we look at these
names alphabetically,
and maybe there's 26
letters of the alphabet.
So let's say A to grows on
the first machine and n to z,
the last 13 letters grows
on the second machine.
There's advantages and
disadvantages of that.
The good thing about it is
that if I have somebody's name,
I could immediately figure out
what machine there
has that range.
I can figure out which one
machine I should talk to.
You can see that sometimes
it tends to lead to end ballots.
In this case, just
maybe coincidentally,
or I don't know if there's
something more
interesting about it,
but most of the names
ended up on that on
that first cluster rather
than the second cluster.
So that's not great. You can
imagine trying to more
carefully find a split,
maybe I look at a histogram
or something like that.
That might work well initially.
If there's totally new
students getting added,
maybe the distribution
changes, right?
So it's just kind of tricky
to keep that ballots.
So there's good things about
it and bad things about it.
A third thing that we could
do is hash partitioning.
You're actually do
some hash partitioning
on the project that's going
to be coming out shortly.
And hash partitioning
depends on a hash function.
Some of you might have seen
hash flexions if
you're coming from
the CS track, 200300400.
For those of you from 22320,
maybe you haven't seen
hash functions before.
But the idea of a hash
function is pretty simple.
It's a function that
can take any value,
string dictionary,
whatever, doesn't matter.
It can take anything, and
it returns back a number to you.
Okay? And then there's
some other properties
that they usually
have that are kind of nice.
What, well, this
is a requirement.
If I feed the same value
in more than one time,
it has to be deterministic.
The same value in gives
me the same number back.
Okay? The other thing is that it
should be kind of a
seemingly almost like
arbitrary pattern.
So if I put in A,
I'm going to get some number.
And then if I put in
B, it should just be
a completely different number
if they're doing a good job
with the hash function.
Okay, so how are we going to use
hash flexions for partitioning?
Well, here I have my
name and my student ID,
and I will choose
one of these to be
what I call my partitioning key.
And I may say the name
is the partitioning key,
and I may compute
the hash over that.
And I'm going basically get
Numbers corresponding
to each person's name.
And then what I could do is
I could put all the eV ones,
let's say, computer one and
all the odd ones
on Computer two.
That's not perfectly balanced,
but it'll tend to be a
little bit more balanced
than the case I saw
earlier where I was trying
to do the ranges, right?
Because there's not like weird
patterns in terms of, you know,
a lot of people's names use
letters from the first
half of the alphabet.
Right? So that's the common
thing people will do.
If I have somebody's name, then
which machine do I talk to,
well, I'll take the
hash of their name.
And I'll see is that
number even or odd?
And I'll talk to that
appro appropriate machine.
If I wanted to get
everybody's name like
at a given range of values,
so this wouldn't work.
That I have to go back to
the range partitioning.
But this works for you,
a large variety of cases
if what you're going
to do on the project.
So the project we're going
to be releasing soon,
what you'll do is
you'll actually have
two datasets for the two
different partitions.
And you're going to
start a simple doctor
composed cluster where you have
two containers and
each container
is going to be responsible
for one of these datasets.
And then inside of
the containers you
have these two little
servers running, each,
which is serving up
one of these datasets,
and clients can ask
questions about it.
And so some of the work will
just be kind of like getting
these two GRP servers up and
running and having the beat
responsible short some data.
And then in your client,
you have to say what I'm
calling a method and
my colleague that server
water server too.
The client will have
to do a little bit
of work beforehand to figure
out where we should w
looking for the data.
Alright. So just a little
bit of vocabulary here.
So partition is this
general concept
that the T Bible use.
There's a lot of
analogies for it,
maybe used in different domains.
So this data Itsive
applications book,
which is excellent, by the way.
They list a bunch
of them, right?
Sometimes it's called a hard or
a region or a tablet or vetoed.
Whatever, you know, we
will learn the concept and
adapt whatever vocabulary
different systems use.
But I want you to see the
general concept up front.
Have people have any
questions about partitioning.
Right here. Yeah, Uh huh.
Yeah. So if we wanted to subs
go from an ID to a name,
sometimes from a name to an ID.
Yeah, I think what we
would often do is we might
have like two copies of
the same data, right?
Would be one way to do it.
Or Another thing
you could do is you
could have what we
might call an index in this
case is just two columns,
but me usually there
might be a long row.
And so we could have the
rows started someway,
and there could be
an ID for each row.
And in different places,
we could have different
lookup techniques,
maybe I'll look up from
this column or that column.
But anytime I want to support
more types of lookups,
I have to use a little
bit extra information.
That makes sense. Yeah,
it's an excellent question.
It's the right way to
be thinking about this.
We're going to see more
examples like that.
Yeah, other questions
people have. All right.
Let's talk about replication.
This actually, I just pulled
it off of a slide
that we're going
to revisit later
this semester when
we learned about the
udu file system.
Don't worry about what the Hadu
file system is for right now.
What we're just going
to worry about is
that it has files,
and those files are both
partitioned like we saw,
and they're also
replicated, right?
There's going to be multiple
copies of the data.
So here I have two files.
File F one contains ABCD.
And File two is a
little bit longer.
It's EFGH IJ KL.
And I may imagine that
a partition is just
four characters.
It's absurdly short, but just
for the sake of the demo,
let's say that it is.
And so the File one
has one partition.
I may call that F 1.1,
and File two has two partitions,
F 1.1 and F 1.2.
And for different files,
I might have different
replication factors.
If I'm more worried
about losing my data,
I would have more replication,
and I want to more machines.
Let say this first file
has triple replication,
and the second one has
two times replication.
So the ABCD, I
guess there's three machines
as a triple replication,
kind of has to be
on all of them.
And then what about F 2.1?
Let's say that's on the
first two machines,
F 2.2, t's say it's on the
the second two machines.
Right? So AC systems
that do replication,
Some AC systems that
do partitioning,
often, you'll see the vies
in combination like this.
Yeah, question right. Yeah,
that's an excellent question.
How do I figure out
which machines get,
which parts of the file?
It's something we'll talk
about extensively, right?
You can imagine lots of
different scenarios.
I'll just quick throw out
a few things you
might factor in.
What I might factor in that?
Some of these machines
might be in the same brac,
and so I don't want to have
all my replicas
of the same rack.
I want the machines
to kind of have even
amounts of data, right?
So I don't run out of hard
drive space on one of them.
Even if they all have
the same amount of data,
some data might be more
popular than others.
So I don't want some
specific machine
to get overloaded with requests.
So you can start thinking about
all those things and
try to figure out
how to lay it out, right?
You know, you can You
know, it's a deep area.
How do we figure out where
to put these replicas?
Is a big problem, right?
What will revisit?
Yeah, other questions
people have.
Alright. Cool. Great. We're
done with networking.
We're going to move into
our new topic, which is
Memory resources, with
memory resources,
you look at this
idea of caching.
You know, this course is
specifically about big datasets,
and memory tends to be kind
of small compared to like
an SSD or hard drive.
So often, for a lot of
these big data sets,
it will not fit in Rab, right?
Our dataset will
be disc somewhere.
And so the question is,
well, how do we use Rab?
The answer is that
maybe certain subsets
of our data is
access more often.
We can't put everything in ab,
but let's choose
something to put there,
and let's make that
decision carefully, right?
That's the question of caching.
When can we put a
copy of our data?
Is something that's faster and
smaller because we
can't always do that,
so we kind of have to be a
little bit smart about it.
Alright. So there's a few things
I want you to be
able to describe
at the end of this lecture.
The first is you
have to be able to
describe about cash hierarchy.
We try to talking
about it like, Oh,
there's like Rab
and there's SST.
There's actually many
different levels of cash
growing from small and
fast, a big and slow.
And we could have a kind of
cash between any two
of these layers.
And here you have to kind of
talk about how that looks like
in actual real hardware and
in a realistic scenario.
Second, one of the
things I want you to be
able to do is trace
through access pattern.
So if I'm running a program
and that program is like
reading different files,
I can write down, like, Oh,
read file one, then
read file two,
then read file one again.
That's an access pattern.
And for an access pattern,
there might be some
cashing going on.
That caching might be driven
by a policy automatically.
There's a couple of
policies that will
led like LR U and FIFO.
What I want you to
do is I want you to,
like, look at an access pattern.
Like this is what a program is
doing and say, here's the cache,
and kind of how we're
managing the cache,
and then kind of trace
through step by step and say,
We found this value
in the cache.
We did it by this
value in the cache.
Overall, this was the
total performance.
Is this something
I would want to be
able to do on pencil
and paper and actually,
that's why I have
the worksheet today.
And calculating the cash
performance metrics
just naturally follows
that tracing aspect.
Okay, so what is the problem
we're trying to solve here?
The problem is at
at C. L at at C is
any amount of time that
you wait for slipping.
And so if we want to
understand ate at C and how
it often shows up in
programs that are ready,
we have to understand a
little bit about hardware.
So I have a simple picture here.
Over here, I have a CPU.
I've been stowing match
like one core, one ship.
So I have the CPU.
And the CPU actually has lots
of different things in it,
and I'm sowing, like, two things
that are important
to us right now.
O is that it has a clock. Right?
And that clock is
ticking very fast.
A lot of CPUs you buy.
It will, like rate the
performance or the clock speed
in terms of Gigahertz,
Giga billions.
So that clock is actually
ticking billions
of times a second.
And as that clock is ticking,
it's doing instructions, right?
Maybe it's adding
numbers or kind
of evaluating
whether an expression is
true or things like that.
It's definitely not
the case that we have
one instruction for
one clock tick.
I mean, there's some
instructions that
might take a bunch
of clock techs.
The flip side, sometimes
it's possible to get
multiple instructions
through with
a single top clock tick,
but kind of a accrue
approximation would be
fair to say this CPU can do,
over 1 billion simple
things every second, right?
CPU is running very fast.
Now, as I say these
calculations,
it does these
calculations on values.
And you all are used to like
variables in your program.
A CPU has something a lot like
a variable called a register.
Register is really like a
variable that's like built
into hardware and is
super fast, right?
And so you can't give
them banams or here
I just them like register
12 and three, right?
Call that R one or two or
three? They have other names.
It really depends on the CPU.
There won't be a lot of them,
maybe like half a dozen,
maybe a dozen,
something like that,
kind of a small order,
but we can put values in there,
and we can operate on very fast.
So, for example, Maybe
as this clock is ticking,
we could do a calculation.
We could say the
R three register
should equal R one plus R two.
That would happen very quickly,
maybe in one clock cycle.
That's the happy
part of the story.
Of course, even for
a small data set.
We're looking at big data sets,
but even for a small data set,
it won't fit in this
handful of registers.
I have a bunch of values
over there in RAB.
And so Rab can have
lots of values,
but there's no computation
built into RAB.
There's not something
in RAM that can
add to numbers or do any
other sort of calculation.
And so what that
means is that if I
want to add these
two numbers in Rab,
I have to get them over
where the CPU can see them.
And what that will involve
is a few instructure.
I have to do a loaded
structure that will
bring these values
into the registers,
another calc another operation
that will add them together.
And then a third
one that's going to
store them back up to Rab.
And the way that all works,
I kind of draw this
weird lie here.
That's called a memory bus.
The CPU and Rab are communicating
over this memory bus.
And so what happens
when we do a load?
Well? It has to
bring that value from
rab into this register,
and that might take
something like,
let's say, 60 nato seconds.
That seems kind of fast,
but that might be say,
like 200 cycles on
the CPU, right?
So we were kind of
chugging along.
We were maybe like
doing one thing every
cycle more or less.
And all of a sudden we have
to wait for 200 flock techs.
So that's painfully slow,
right? You will
feel that, right?
I, you won't feel
if it happens once,
but if your program
is doing this a
lot versus doing this not a lot,
Your program could be 100 times
faster or slower than
it would be, right?
This is something we very
much have to worry about.
What can we do while
we're waiting?
Well, there's kind of
limited options, right?
It's kind of a lot longer
than a normal operation,
but it's not long
enough to switch and
run a different program, right?
That would take even longer than
the 200 nato seconds or
the 60 nato seconds.
So it's a little
bit wasted, right?
So the 60 data seconds,
that's an example of lacy.
Latency is measuring any
amount of time like that.
Another measure of
performance is throughput.
That's a rate, how many bytes
can be transferred per second.
And so I can also think about
performance between these two,
not just in terms of latency,
but the throughput, right.
Depending on how many
values I can load at
the same time might affect
my performance too,
not just how much time it takes
to do an individual value.
Alright, so how do we
solve this problem or
at least, make it not as bad?
We add, you can
almost think of it
as a bit of memory
on the CPU itself,
part of that chip, right?
That's called a cache.
And obviously, the whole
ab will not fit there,
otherwise we wouldn't
even need ab,
but we can keep the hot data
that we're accessing
often there.
Maybe some small
subset of the data,
we can put it there, then we can
access it more quickly, right?
Now, it turns out that,
like, how big is this cache?
Often, as we have to
make things bigger,
they necessarily get slower.
So you can imagine
that I don't know,
I have a few papers here.
Maybe I have like a bunch
of different books or
things that I might
have different
kinds of information, right?
You know, I could
put these books
and papers or whatever
on this desk,
and I could switch between
them quickly and read them all.
You know, I I had
like 1 million books,
it might fill the
stage or even more,
maybe it might fill
the whole room,
and to just buy the physical
necessity of it, right?
If I want to have
some place to like,
spread out, you know,
1 million papers or books,
I would take me longer to travel
to each one that if I have
something small, right?
So it's just like we
see this fundamental
trade off, right?
You could be small and
fast or big and slow,
and we're look at more of that.
There's a lot of
different places
you could be on that spectrum.
Okay, so if we have this cache,
then we can think about
performance in a
few different ways.
We think about kind of
total throughput of the
application. Right?
There's throughput from
main memory to the CPU.
But if a lot of the
data is in the cache,
then if we look at
how many bytes the
program is accessing,
we might get better
throughput than that
bandwidth between
CPU and memory.
We could look at some kind of
typical latency in terms of
maybe like average or median.
And then sometimes people will
measure what we call
tail latency, right?
So there's like a
statistical distribution.
Of the latencies.
And so tailed CVs
were looking at kind of a
high percentile, right?
If I took all the
different latencies
of b different operations,
maybe I look at the
99th percentile.
So one of the slowest
ones or 99.9,
and I can measure that.
So when I add the cache,
right, performance gets better,
but there's one statistic
out here that's going to be
hard to fix with a cache.
Anybody have any thoughts on
which of these is going to
be hardest to solve
using a cache?
Yeah, right here.
Was the rough put
be hard to solve with the cash?
I think the cash will
actually help with the
throughput, right?
Because let's say that before,
I had to access all
the values from rab.
Let's say I can transfer
like a gigabyte per second.
Right? Well, then my
applications performance
was a gigabyte per second.
If now I have a cache
and half of my values,
I pull from the cache,
and then half I can pull memory,
then all of a sudden I can it 2
gigabytes/second.
Yeah, I had I p here.
The tail. Why is the
tail hard to fix?
Faster. Mm hmm.
Yeah, it makes some
things faster,
but the slow saves
will still be slow
because the only way to
make everything fast is
that if all the
data fit in cash at
that point is it
even really a cash?
Right? If we have a cash,
you know, presumably,
there's going to be some
data that's not in the cash,
and that will show up as
the slowest accesses.
So that's a hard
problem to deal with.
And we'll talk more about
Hill to see other lectures.
Alright, let's talk about
the cash hierarchy now.
Here's a nice picture I
borrowed from that book,
where we're comparing
that faster
and smaller to
bigger and slower.
So I mean, at the very
top of the hierarchy,
we have CPU registers.
That's super fast.
We might have a
Kind of cash their
different size.
L1l2.
There's some other distinctions
between them I one and
two that might be
per core on a CPU.
Then I might have some like
at L three cash that might be
shared across all the
cores on a processor.
As we go down, you
can see some example
sizes down here,
like at L one cash.
Maybe that's like 64 kilobytes,
l21 megabyte, 77 megabytes.
This is just one particular CPU,
but I want you get an idea
of the order of magnitude.
It's like we have many gigabytes
of data in a CPU cash, right?
It's small. We have to use
that resource carefully.
And then, of course, once
you get out of the CPU,
out of the gray
area, then we have
made memory, which was slower.
Now, main memory
certainly is not
the biggest slowest thing
you can imagine, right?
There's other things that could
store bytes, so for example,
but SST or hard
drive would be even
bigger than main memory,
and quite a bit slower, right?
So I could keep data there.
And even beyond that,
you could imagine like
in the cloud, right?
There's these services I guess
it's technically finite,
but for all practical purposes,
there's like infinite
capacity in the cloud,
and it's pretty slow to access,
right? I have to kind
of go over the network.
I fetch some data and
send it back to me.
So maybe I put cloud
storage at the bottom of
this hierarchy or maybe
a network in general.
And so when we're
talking about thing,
it could really be
happening between
any two layers in
this picture, right?
So it cuts up. That shows
up and get it again.
And you should have kind of
imagined this like pyramid,
tah hierarchy and kind
of remember some of
the key layers here.
So, those numbers I just showed
were from reading a spec, right?
For that hardware. But you
can also run some experiments
and figure it out empirically.
So here's another nice
experiment they did in the book.
And I apologize, the fat
is a little bit small.
But what they did is they wrote
this little benchmark program.
And what the program
would do is it would
generate datasets
of different sizes.
And the size of the data set
is on the x axis, right?
So I guess it goes it'll
be like 1 kilobyte up
to 10,000 kilobytes like
10 megabytes, and beyond.
And then when they
have that dataset,
what they'll do is they'll
kind of loop over it, right?
And they'll loop
over it many times.
And if the dataset is small
enough to fit at a particular
level of the cache,
Well, then you'll get the
performance of that cash level?
If it's a little bit
too big for that,
then it'll be at a
different cash level
and you'll get a
different performance.
And so as they're
looping for it,
they show how long it takes
to do a memory access, right?
So in the good case, we're
talking about, you know,
1-2 nato seconds to access,
and then in the bad case,
I guess what is that
100 nato seconds,
so even worse to that,
something like 100-200 nato
seconds in the worst case.
So I'm just wondering if anybody
could help me
interpret this strap.
Does anybody want to venture
a guess about how big
the L three cache is
and what the latency is
for accessing data,
L three cache?
Yeah, right here.
Yeah, I guess this
is the threshold,
the 10,000 kill bytes
or 10 megabytes.
So I guess what is
the last level?
I guess what is the
last level that
we might have here at
the picture up above.
It is what? Under nanoseconds.
So I think your logic is right.
I think we have it off by one.
Like this last level
is going to be
some in made beary, right?
So you described to be like
the performance of
accessing bad beary,
and that's up here.
And then right before
the L three cache.
I think this is I'd say that
the size is about 10 megabytes,
and the axis is,
I guess a I don't know.
It's hard to read out a log
scale, maybe let's say,
18 nato seconds
or something like
that for accessing the L three.
So you distinctly
see that, right?
If you're down here,
right, I mean,
you're 100 times
faster than pier.
So this makes a huge deal,
like, what cash level
our dataset fits at.
So, do people have
any question about
the cash hierarchy or
that reason right here?
Yeah, why is it smoother
up here and kind of
more sharp down here?
It's a little hard to see, but
you can actually see they put
little bubbles out here for
the places where they
rat and experimented.
The light is interpolated
between different
data set sizes.
And so the way it looks to be
is where it's kind
of steep here.
It looks like that
they didn't run
anything in between, right?
And here, we can see there's
a bunch of points at it.
So maybe the other ones might
be a little curved, too.
It's hard to tell.
I'm speculating.
But especially when
you have a log scale,
I don't know if I don't know if
they chose their points on
a log scale as well, right?
So if you do that,
then maybe as you get
farther to the right,
you might see more detail
of the curve rather than
the interpolated light,
speculating a little bit,
as I to do the experiment,
but it's a good
thing to point out.
Yeah, other questions or
comments people have
about the experiment.
All right. Yeah, right here.
Why does it flat?
Yeah. Yeah. Why does
it flat it out?
So here my L three is
let's say 10 megabytes,
what is this one over here?
I guess in between there
would be like 1 megabyte.
So somewhere I guess
this drop off is less
than 1 megabyte.
Let's say I have a five
megabyte data set.
It fits entirely in my L three,
but it definitely does
not fit at the L two ca.
If I have an eight
baked by dataset,
all fits of the L three cash,
nothing fits in the
L two cash, right?
That's why it's pretty flat.
Now, I mean,
maybe the question that
you're asking is, like,
why don't we see that
at least some of
the data is even though,
like the Data set is
mostly in L three,
why don't we see that some
of it is in L two, right?
Li You might expect to be
maybe not perfectly flat.
And it really depends, right?
B I guess when we look
at the cash policies,
we'll see there might
be cases where I
keep scanning over
the whole data that
never It doesn't know
what data to keep in
the smaller cash,
and it might not do a
good job of using it.
You can totally imagine that if
it doesn't fit L two Cash,
it might still use
some L two cash
and get some
performance out of it,
but this CPU does not
seem to be doing that.
It'll make more sense
when we do the worksheet.
You're thinking about it
the right way, though.
Yeah, other questions
people have. All right.
W. The way to think
about caching is that
you're trading off two
different resources.
Usually, the two
different types of
resources or are different
ways of story pypes.
So I would just look
at some examples
of Caching shows up
everywhere, by the way.
Let's just see a few examples.
Normally, I have
a bunch of files
on a hard drive or a SSD.
And when I read those,
my operating system
caches those in memory.
So there's a res
source trade off here.
The operating system
is using more memory.
And there's a cost to
that. I could have used
that memory for something
else. It's using more memory.
But then it's avoiding having
to do storage reads, right?
I can only read data so
fast from my device.
So I'm trading off between
two scarce resources.
And try to be good
at this space,
you have to start to gain
some intuition about
when you want to trade off one
resource for $1 resources,
you have to think about
what resources are
available to you and try to
make a good decision
to that space.
What about this? When my
browser visits a web page,
it fetches it over the Internet,
and that's inherently slow.
It'll often store on
my local hard drive,
and then I visit
the web page again,
and it actually doesn't
do any network yo.
Sees like, Oh, this web page
here is already stored.
What am I avoiding?
I'm avoiding network yo.
And what am I spending?
While I'm spending
some storage space,
and then also some
reads to that storage.
I'm trading off two resources.
This third one is like a
good optimization trick
that I bet you all will
use at some point,
is a good one to remember.
You often end up with
like your programming,
you have a function that takes
a long time to execute,
and your function,
let's say, also happens to have
the behavior that if you
give it the same input,
it gives you the same output.
Let's say you also have to call
this function many times
for whatever reason.
How can you deal with this?
You can solve it with cache.
Your cash can remember
previous results.
So I just have a little
code stip over here that
Python I have by cash,
which is a Python dictionary.
Python dictionaries have
keys in values, right?
So the values are going to
be the thing I'm caching.
Like these cash entries will be
the things that G of X
returned previously.
And then the key
will be the x value.
I'll use that key to
look up an entry.
In general, when you're
building a cache,
you have to have
some type of key on
it to look up a specific value.
So I have this
cash here, and I'm
trying to make the G
of x flection faster.
So what I'll do is I'll
write an F of x fleion,
that's a wrapper
around of G of X.
That F of x calls G of X.
And what F of x will do is
that it will check if we've
seen that x value before.
Is that x value in the cache?
If it's not, then we'll
have to call G of X,
it'll be very slow,
but we'll save
that in our Python
cache dictionary.
And then when we
get down to here,
we're going to return whatever
is in the cache, right?
So at this point, it's
definitely there,
if it wasn't, we put it there.
So the first time I call f of x
with a new X value,
it'll be slow.
I call it again
it'll be very fast.
And from the perspective of
somebody like writing code
that uses this function,
it doesn't feel any
different to them.
So it's kind of a very
natural optimization to slip
into a lot of programs if you
identify a slow
flection somewhere.
So what are we using? We're
using more memory space?
What are we saving? We're
saving compute time.
Alright. Most of the things
I've been talking about might
be thought of as
mechanisms, right?
Like how do we
actually do something?
But then there's a
question, like, well,
what should we do or
what decisions can we
make given these
general strategies.
And that's a question of policy.
So we're talking
about policy now.
So we have a cache, but what
data should draw the cash?
I clearly cannot put everything.
There's a few different
ways. What is
that we can decide manually?
And you're going to
be doing this when we
look at Spark later
this semester.
So Spark is one of the most
important systems will learn.
Spark is a little bit like Pads.
Some of you might know pads from
320 or elsewhere or not,
don't worry if not.
But Pads gives you data frames.
Data frames are basically
like tables of data.
And data frames with
pads are usually,
basically almost
always in memory.
Spark also has data frames
when it's designed for
large datasets
that do not fit in
memory in general, right?
Now, it might happen
that you have
a small Spark data frame
that you're accessing
a lot of times.
And so you would like
it to be in memory,
even though that's not
the usual behavior.
In this case, you could say a
smart data frame about cash.
It'll be a memory
after you use it,
and then you can
use it for a bunch
of things, and when
you're all done,
you can say persist, you're
done using it, right?
And, is this squid or bad?
You might wish that it
happens automatically,
but there's some nice
things about Manuel, too.
The nice thing about Manuel
is only I know my
own mind, right?
Only I know what plots in
the death somebody do next.
And so you have that knowledge
of what I'm about to do,
I can make a caching
decision, right?
So if you get dredit cash,
you kind of understand
how it works,
and you get intuition about
what you should cache.
Then analysis that might
be very slow, you
could save some time.
If you kind of selectively
cah things that
you're using a lot
of that fitted
memory. Excuse me.
Alright, let's look
at another example.
So a web browser.
A web browser visits
some server that has a
co that has a website.
So let's say that's like
the course website.
And it's a page back.
Most browsers will
then write that page
to a file somewhere on my SSD.
And that's may be called
the browser cache.
If I visit that same page again,
there's a good chat
and we'll pull it from
the browser cache instead of
going back to the web server.
I vocabulary here. The
first time I did it
where I had to actually go
out and do the slow thing,
that's called a cash mess.
My data was out of the cache.
The second time it was in the
cache, as we call it a hit.
So I might often ask you,
like for Devi scenario,
how many hits are there?
How many messes are there,
right? Alright, so I have that.
Now, let's say a day
pass that I visit again,
even though that data
might still be in my SSD,
there's a good chance
that we'll go out to
the course website server
again and fetch it.
And that is because maybe
the schedule change or
something like that.
Maybe the data in the cache
might be stale.
We have to check.
So we have to send a
request over here.
Maybe the request just
says, give me the website.
There might be other
ways to be a little
bit smarter about it
and kind of asked,
when was the last time this page
changed before we actually
asked for the whole page,
but data can become sale,
and so you know,
SSD is so large that we don't
worry too much about space.
We're really just worried about
freshness in this type of case.
So the policy could just be
that when we fetch something,
we put some expiration
of data on it,
and we stop using it after
that expiration date.
We might do that if
we just have a lot of
excess capacity to store stuff.
The final one that
we're going to spend
a bunch of time on are
automatic policies where we have
very limited cash space, right?
And for these policies,
there's two parts of them.
What do we have to figure out?
When do we bring
something into the cash,
and when do we remove
something from the cash?
The bringing something into
the cache is the easier part,
and I'm to talk about
it for like 1 minute,
and then we'll talk
for quite a lot
about how we evict or remove
things from the cache.
The usual behavior
for most caches
is that when you access
a piece of data,
if you have a cache, it'll put
into the cache after
you access it.
That's what generally happens.
Now, I mean, there's some
weird scenarios like maybe
the person writing the program
knows that after
I read this file,
I will definitely never
read it again, right?
Like maybe I'm trying
to think of an example.
Maybe this program
is reading a file,
encrypting it and writing
the encrypted data
somewhere else,
and then deleting the
add encrypted data.
It would be weird to cache
the original file because
it's about to be deleted.
And only the program knows
that. So there's like flags.
Like for example, Lyx, if
you're reading a file,
you can say, operate system,
please don't cache
this because I know,
for a fact, I won't need
it in the future, right?
So there's ways you can do that.
But the general behavior
kind of except for
these weird exceptions
that when you
touch something, you
bring in the cache.
Alright, I've done
talking about that half.
Let's talk about
this other half.
If I break something into the
cache and the cash is full,
I have to bup
something else out.
I have to choose an entry to be
the evictim that
gets evicted, right?
One way is I can randomly
choose a victim.
And there's actually
some important scenarios
where that's actually like
a good decision, right?
It seems stupid, but it
can actually outperform
the so called smarter
policies in some situations.
Here are a couple of other
ones that are commonly used.
One is first and first out,
and the other one is
least recently used.
The idea here is that
with first and first out
is that I look at all the
entries in the cache,
and I know when they
were added to the cash,
and whoever has been
in the cash logs,
well it's that entries
turned to be removed, right?
LRU maybe is a little bit
more clever because
LRU will say.
It doesn't really matter
how long you've
been in the cash.
What really matters is,
when was the last time
somebody used this piece
of data that case
that would draw.
So they both have
subsets of, like,
older and newer data,
but they defined it a
little bit bit differently.
All right. Let's head over
and we'll do the worksheet.
And let me grab this. All right.
And hopefully you
have this if you
have a tablet that's site.
Otherwise you could just try to
write it out on paper as well.
What I will do with these
is a couple of things.
Usually, I draw out a
big box for my cache.
I'll usually label
it, like, what is
the policy and how much
space does it have?
I usually try to keep
trees ordered here,
so the more important
fresher data is on
the right hand side.
I rese it up here?
And the older stuff I might want
to evict is on the
left hand side.
You can imagine drawing
it differently.
And then I have a workload.
Over here, a workload
describes the series of
accesses I did, right?
So if a program
reads file one, and
then it reads file two,
and then it reads file
one again, and so on,
what I'm describing is the
workload of that program.
So I have a workload,
I have a cash.
And a common problem I might
give you is I might say,
tell me which ones will be
cash hits and which one
will be cash misses.
So let's do it.
So I'll put an X if it's a mess,
check if it's a hit.
So the first one always is
a mess because while
there's nothing here.
Okay, so I miss.
And then I add one to the
cache. Alright, Good.
Now I do two. To
also is not here,
so that's another mess.
And I add two to
the cache up here.
Now I have one,
and one is there.
Fantastic. I have a cash hit.
And I don't have to bring
anything in because
it's already there.
Now I have three,
which is a cash mess.
And if I want to bring
three in here, I have
to make room, right?
Because the cash can
only have two values,
and I already have two values.
So I have to choose a victim,
and my victim is one.
One was the first
number in the cash,
so one will be the
first number out.
First in, first out, FIFO.
So I may say goodbye one.
Hello. Three. Alright.
And that was actually
very unfortunate because
my very next one
that I do is another one, right?
So I have a mess because the
one's not there anymore.
And I have to bring one back in.
Of these two, two was
the first one in.
So it'll be the first one
out. And then one is back.
And so I had one.
One out of five was a hit.
So my hit rate is 1/5
equals 0.2. Hit rate.
So you can imagine so many
things I could ask you.
I could ask you,
after this thing,
what is the contents
of the cash?
I could ask you how
many hits are there?
I could ask you what
is the hit rate.
So much fun we could
have with this kind
of problem, right? All right.
Any questions about how to
solve that kind of problem?
All right. Let's do another one.
This is a similar problem.
We have a cache of size two
again. Here's the big
difference, right?
Before we were doing FIFO,
and we're using LRU.
We can have like the same space,
but we're going to use it
a little bit differently.
And then what about this
workload over here?
This is actually the
same workload as above.
But it has different
names, right?
So instead of 121, it's ABA.
I'm just try to show
you that, you know,
the cash entries
could have any kind
of description or key on them.
Alright. So let's do the
same workload as before,
but with an LRU and a
slightly different labeling.
Okay, so the first
one is always ass,
of course. So I have A.
Then I have B, which
is also a mess.
And now I have A,
which is a hit.
And this is the point
where we do something
different than FIFO.
FFO and LRU are very similar.
When you have a mess,
these two are the same.
But when you have a hit,
they do something a
little bit different.
At this point, we
use something that was
already in the ca A,
and we're like, Oh, well,
I recently used that.
A is important to me now.
And so we'll actually move A.
Over here, right? So when
we have a hit on an LRU,
you will change the
order priority of
these things. FIFO
doesn't do that.
FIFO doesn't do anything
smart when there's a hit.
Only when there's a mess,
right? Alright, so we do that.
And now we have C C is a mess,
and so we're going
to bump out B.
You can see that
this is a case where
FIFO would have ended
up evicting something
differently because
previously they
put those letters a little
bit differently, right?
So I'm going to bring
in C. And then finally,
we have A again, and A is a hit.
And then I'll just move
A over to this side.
And so now I have
2/5 hits equals 0.4.
You can see for the
same cash size,
different policies might be
better or worse than other ones.
Do people have any
questions about
FIFO or LRU. You got a
question right here?
Yeah, I, I spent a lot of,
we can look at We will
look at code soon,
but I was just thinking,
how can I do it on
pencil and paper?
I write with pens, and I
don't like erasing stuff.
So that's just how I
reorder things, right?
But I mean, Yeah,
somehow restructure it said,
like, this is higher
priority. Now.
You can imagine it like a list,
and maybe I just swap some
values around in the list.
There's lots of different
ways you could represent it.
But we have to have
some sense of, like,
which entries are kind
of higher priority
and which ones are
lower priority.
That make sense? Yeah,
thank you for asking.
Yeah other questions
people have.
Okay, so we have, like 7
minutes left. 6 minutes left.
And so for this one,
we're actually I might
make it into a top
at question where I
spend 5 minutes on it.
The question is might be,
what is the hip rate?
And so you'll work
through this on your own.
And then upload it to Canvas.
I'm not to Canvas. You'll
upload the top pat.
I'll leave this on here in case
people don't have
their worksheet,
and then I'll just
open up the top hat
on my computer. So do it.
You have 5 minutes,
then put on top pad.
And you can actually
if you want, you can
leave after you do the
top hat because we
won't have time to do
something, something else.
Yeah, there's a
question here. No.
Okay. Alright. Yeah, go ahead
and get started on that.
And I'll kind of, like, since
I'm not showing top
pat on my streen,
I'll be kind of shout
out when you have, like,
2 minutes left or
something like that,
but you'll have 5
minutes to do it.
Alright. Well, the
top pat is open,
just do it on your
worksheet and then
put it there when you're done.
Yeah, so you do it like
the zero point something.
I would be my preference.
T 2 minutes left to
submit the topic.
1 minute left, everybody.
All right, 10 seconds left.
So if you haven't
put something in,
just throw something in on top.
And we're kind of out of time,
so I'll just like
do this on Monday.
We'll kind of work through it
and talk about the answer.
Have a great weekend, everybody.