On Monday about ACA reliability.
We'll do a couple
of top hats soon to
review that material if people
chance ask some questions.
Then we're going to be
looking at Spark again.
Spark actually could integrate
pretty closely with KAFKA.
What we've seen so far
is that we can write
KCA producers and consumers
directly in Python code.
It turns out that Spark can also
act as a Python
producer, consumer.
And in a lot of ways,
it'll feel similar to
what we've seen before.
So what we've done before
with Spark is that
we can read data frames from,
say, Park files in HDFS.
Instead of getting our data
frame from a Park file,
in this case, we're going to
get it from a Kafka stream.
And that'll be
interesting because
Kafka Streams are always
getting new messages.
And so we're essentially
going to have
a Kaka stream data frame that
keeps growing over time.
That'll be called a
streaming data frame.
So today, I'm going
to do a few things.
I'm going to start with
some programming examples.
I'll just see how
it works hands.
And then after that, we'll
actually dig in and understand
internally how it works
and the general concepts.
So first ahead over here and do
a top hat about CFC reliability.
So RF is replication factor,
and it's actually about whether
a given piece of
data is committed.
30 seconds left.
Alright, so most
people are saying,
yes, it's committed, but
that's actually not quite.
This data is not committed.
Okay. So let me do a little
bit of review on this.
It seems like this is a point
that is confusing
a lot of people.
We learned about how
replication works
for Cassandra and also ACA.
And they're very different
strategies, right?
So with Cassandra,
we would say, Okay,
these are the three replicas or
how many give piece of data,
and all the replicas
were equal, right?
You would have some
forum, and you have to
write to some number of them,
but it could be any
particular ones, right?
And the thing that was nice
about that it was
highly available.
Any given worker could go down,
it doesn't matter, and we
could still write to the system.
The disadvantage was that
was eventually
consistent, right?
Given that we could just
write to any of them
we want and still call it drud,
we could have cases
where different workers
have different
versions of a row,
maybe none of which is like
the correct or most
current version.
And then we'd have to
see things like, well,
how do we resolve
conflicts, right?
So trade off there,
Cassandra, right?
V available, but we would have
divergent history, right?
ACA is trying something a
little bit different, right?
In the case of ACA,
they're imagining this is
like the center of your company
where all your data lives,
and whatever it
goes through KACA
is populating downstream
data sources,
it's not okay to have that
kind of wishy washy data.
We really need to, you know,
know exactly what
the messages are.
They can't change. Everybody has
to agree about the
order of the messages.
And because of that,
Taka uses leader follower
replication, right?
All the rights are going
through a single leader,
and that leader is going
to be the authority on
what that message
is and what order
the messages are are in, right?
So we don't have all that hand
weavines that we
get with Cassandra.
Now, Kafka is not going to be as
available because if
that leader dies,
it takes a while to
recognize that it's
dead and elect a
different leader.
Cassandra, there's
no kind of downtime,
whereas there might
be some downtime for
Kafka. All right, great.
So we have that leader,
and it's getting
all these messages,
and the followers are pulling
those messages down
to themselves, right?
And ideally,
all four of them are going
to have all the messages,
but of course, that's not true,
and there's some lag, right?
Now, some of the replicas might
be in sync or not in
sync at any given time.
And I'm wondering if anybody can
remind me what does it mean
for them to be in sync?
Is that a hand off right
here? Yeah, right here.
Does it have to be I guess.
I'm I'm looking at a replica,
and I want to say, is
this replica and sync?
Yeah, it's fetched
the latest message
from the leader in a
reasonable time frame.
And you can kind
of configure that.
There's a little bit
of flexibility there.
When a follower goes
the leader says, give
me some messages.
There's a limit, how, how
big of a batch we want
to send it on, right?
So it's possible I
give me some messages,
and it may or may not
be fetching all the
way to the end, right?
Right? If I kind of
am falling behind,
then I might not
fetch to the end.
And so what it's looking for
is, did we fetch to the end?
And when was the last
time we did that, right?
That's some measure of
how fresh it is, right?
And you can set the threshold,
but if it did that within
some time frame, we'll say,
Okay, this follower is
sink it's keeping
up reasonably well.
That's another kind of
interesting thing about
Kafka because from the
outside perspective,
when I'm looking at a node,
And it's not responding to me.
It's really hard for me to
tell if it's just running
slow or it's behind or
it's actually down.
And at some level, it doesn't
really matter, right?
And so it's just like, Well,
it's either in sync or not.
Okay, so that's fine.
I can identify that.
And the leader knows
which ones are in sync
and which ones are not.
And it uses that
information about who's in
sync and who's not for
a couple of purposes.
One is, if we don't have
enough followers
that are in sync,
I mean, we can't keep up, right?
We don't want to keep taking
more and more messages
that the followers
can't keep up with.
So at some point, we're
going to tell producers,
hey, back off, don't send
me as many messages.
Okay? And that's where men
sinc comes into play, right?
If we don't have
enough inc followers,
we'll tell the producers
stop sending us messages
for a while until they catch up.
That's what Men sinc does.
It really has to do
with availability
and also durability.
Okay. So if we're okay with,
too, And our data is on two.
Why can we not say this
data is committed?
Why is the leader not okay
with that? Here's why.
The leader is well aware,
it could die at any moment and
be replaced with a follower.
And if the leader wants
to say that this
message is committed,
any follower that can replace
the leader better also
have that message, right?
Because if the leader dies
and a follower takes over
that doesn't have that
message, that message is gone.
Because that new follower,
which becomes a leader
is the authority, right?
And so that's why
we have this rule.
Data is not committed until
it's on all sync followers.
Because any no that's in
sync could become
the next leader.
Right? Our data is not safe
until every candidate for
leader agrees about what
that message is, right?
And that's why we have
different thresholds.
The mite Isc is whether or not
we're telling
producers to back off.
In terms of whether it's
committed, it's like,
well is it on every
insinc replica.
So do people have
have any questions
about pica replication?
Yeah, right here. Mm hmm.
So you're saying that o.
So you're saying the state in
the system changes, right?
So this moment in time, it's
not committed, and
then what happens?
Right.
Mm hmm. Yeah. Okay, great.
So there's a few things
that could happen, right?
One. So in this state,
one is that the
sync replica that
doesn't have the message
could grab the message,
and then we'll say,
now it's committed.
That's one thing
that could happen.
The other thing is that we've
classified this worker as
in sync because it relatively
recently was keeping up,
and it's possible
that it recently had
a problem and it's start
to be not in sync soon.
So the other possibilities
that this Esache replica
could way too long
and that we could
reclassify it as not Esache.
And at that point,
we could say it's
committed because it's
two because there are
only two Ed psyche.
Does that make sense?
How do we decide if
it's committed or not?
Yeah. So the leader
is the one that will
decide if it's committed
because when it is committed,
we communicate that back with
an acknowledgment to
the producer, right?
And the leader is the one
that's that acknowledgment back.
And so it turns out
that the leader knows
who is in sake because it knows
when these other followers
are fetching messages.
Not only that, like In
addition to knowing
which ones are sake,
the leader needs to
communicate that elsewhere.
Because if the leader dies,
then there's a separate
election system
that needs to chose one
that's sake, right?
So that leader is writing
to a separate system.
Could be somebody called
Zookeeper which we
won't get into,
could be somebody
called Craft, right?
There's some external system
that's highly reliable.
We'll just assume that's there.
And that leader knows who's in
sake and to try to
communicate it there, right?
So the leader will
decide who's sake.
Do that makes sens?
The one that is lagging
is not in sync,
and for it to become
insync again,
that means we have to fetch
the very last message.
Therefore, it will also have
this message that
we're worried about.
I saw some other adds up, too,
so I want to make sure I get
some time for
everybody right here.
These What is the
purpose of s replicas?
You could imagine they
could have built the
system without that,
and we would still have
the same guarantees
around committed.
What would happen
that case is that
producers will just keep
sending us messages,
and we won't be
acknowledging them because
the Nyc replicas are never
really catching up, right?
So what would happen if we
didn't have men sync replicas?
Eventually, all the
followers would
be out of sync if
they can't keep up.
And then because we don't
have any men, we'll just say,
well, there's the leader
whose Ny by definition.
Therefore, it's
committed on the leader.
But then we would have gotten
ourselves in a bad case because
there's no candidate
to take over
if the leader dies, right?
I mean, I guess our
data is more durable
if we have a higher
men in sync, right?
Because if we don't
have any men in sync,
and we just have everything
else is the same,
then and the producers are
sending messages too fast,
then eventually every faller
will be considered not in sync,
and so only the leader
will be in sync.
That's a bad situation
because If the leader dies,
there's no follower who
can take over, right?
Because nobody's in sync, right?
And so it would be
better if we're
following behind to
tell the producers,
I can't accept these
messages right
now because we don't have
enough followers keeping up.
Assuming these
followers are not dead,
they're just trying to
like running behind.
Then if we stop taking
new messages for a while,
they will get a chance
to actually catch up,
and then we'll be able
to maintain some number
of replicas that could
take over as the leader.
Yeah, hopefully
that makes sense.
Yeah, lots of great questions.
People have other questions.
Right. Cool. So it's
a very different system,
right than Cassandra.
It's interesting to
compare them. All right.
One other one I
want to do is about
this word called item potents.
And so I just kind
of a fun question
about house sitting, right?
When people give you directions,
the kind of operation
they're asking you to do
may or may not be item potent.
15 seconds left.
All right, so people are saying
empty the cat's litter
box, which is true, right?
So if you empty the
cat's litter box,
the state of it is that
it's empty or clean.
And if you repeat those steps
again in an already
clean litter box,
well, then it will
still be clean.
What about the other ones?
Somebody said some
people are saying
decrease the b two
degrees, right?
So if my Friend tells me
that I decrease it by two,
and they tell me, again,
I decrease it by two.
The outcome is different
than if I had done
it once, right?
The state of the temperature
in the house will
be different if I do that one
time or many times, right?
That's what you want
to ask yourself,
what is the ending state?
And will the ending
state be different
depending on whether I do
it one time or many times?
Any questions about that
one? I see that one through
some people the dog would
be very happy here,
if it's just cheap
until you get an act,
the dog keeps getting
more food. Alright, cool.
So a little bit review
from last time.
One other thing I want
to talk about briefly is
that some people have been
having issues with their VM.
There's some directions on
here about how to troubleshoot
like if it's VPN, who to ask.
I think some people have
been a little bit
stuck on this one.
So I just want to show
what this means, right?
So if your VM is non responsive,
you might have to reboot it.
And on my laptop right now,
if I go and I say,
like, you know,
shut down or restart,
what the file system will do is
the file system is going to
have some data in memory.
I try to write that
out to desk before
it reboots. So I
don't lose anything.
Now, If my computer,
for whatever reason,
is like hung up, it might not
be able to write that out,
and I just will not be
able to rebot normally.
In that case of what I do, I
just hit the power button.
Same thing with your VM. If
your VM's not responsive,
you probably have to
do the equivalent
of just like a hard reset,
then rather a clean
reboot, right?
So when we do the reboot,
right, we wanted
the reset option.
And so if you go to
the Proxmx thing,
which I linked to, you know,
I can see my VM here.
And by the way, I can't
see yours, right?
So people are going to have to
do this on their own a bit.
I can you know, look at
your computer, but I
can't do it for you.
I'm going to click on
this. If I right click,
they don't actually
show the reset option.
They hide it a little bit.
But if I double click on it,
then I can go ahead
and I can do a reset,
and that should work even if
it's kind of in some
weird hung state.
Alright, C. You know,
just show me your laptop if that
somehow is not working.
I'd be curious.
Alright, so let's jump
into the new stuff.
Um, I have somewhat of a
similar set up as last time,
right, I have my
Kafka client here.
I'm going to make a stream or
a topic called animals JSN.
Very similar last time.
Last time we used
protocol buffers,
and there's nothing wrong
with that except with Spark.
It's very hard to parse
protocol buffers unless you
pay databricks for their
non open source version.
And so I'm just
going to use JSN for
our formats of protocol
buffers for this one.
And I have an anti producer
down here like before.
The beach is a random
letter like ABCDE.
I'm choosing a random animal
every second I do this.
And so here I just
have to send it off.
And I'm going to do that now.
I'm going to say,
producer that send,
and I'll say the
topic is going to be
animal animals J SN.
All right. And then the key
will equal something and
the value will equal
something as well. All right.
Well, for the key,
it's going to be based
on the beach again,
but it has to be bytes.
So I will just convert that
to UTF eight like last time.
And for the value,
I'm going to take a dictionary
with all the information into
it and convert it
to bytes, right?
So All the information
is the beach and also
the animal in question.
And so what I'm going to do
is I'm going to dump it.
Dump it to a string,
right, JSN dump.
And then I'm going to convert
that to bytes, right?
So UTF eight like B four.
And then I can just pass
those values in
here. Alright, cool.
And so I'm going
to kick this off
as a thread running
in the background.
And I don't really
punt anything.
So I'm just going to assume it's
working unless I get some error,
if I'm missing data later,
then I'll come back and
look at it more closely.
Anyway, I'm generating JSN data.
It's also nice to see
an example of how
you could have JSN dictionaries.
Be your message format, right?
Alright, that thing is
running in the background.
Now, if we were doing
things the old way, right?
My previous examples, I would go
right like a Python consumer,
I would pull things
off, and maybe I'd
try to count by beach
or count by animal.
What I may do now is I'm may use
Spark as my consumer, right?
And if you want to do that,
then you have to add this
Jars packages thing here.
Remember that all this
spark stuff is based
on the JVM with the JVM.
You can have code resources
that are in these ars,
as like Java archive or
something like that.
Anyway, I'm going
to do that and it's
going to automatically
download it from
something called Ma Maven
is kind of like the
PEP repository.
Anyway, I'm going to get a
spark session where I can use
libraries that let me access
CP data, right? So I've
already done that.
All that stuff happens.
And then we're were
to do down here is
we're to do a spark dot read.
And what I want to do is I
want to read from
that Kafka stream.
So we've seen before
we could say something
like Park and then I don't know,
some more stuff and
load it back in.
I might put a path there.
That's how we would
do it before.
Now our format
that we're pulling
from is actually
going to be Kafka.
And there's going to
be no path, right?
Because they're not files.
They're just Kafka streams.
Instead, I can put
some options in
here to specify how I'm
going to find that thing.
This a little bit long.
So I'm going to just
break it up a bit,
and We'll just space that out.
Now, remember that
I could easily have
a bunch of different Kafka
clusters in my company.
And so one of the things
we have to do is we
have to say, which 1:00
A.M. I interested in.
And the way I do that is I say
Kafka dot bootstrap servers.
And then I have to
specify what it is.
And this is really analogous
to like how producers or
consumers normally work.
Like up here, we'd say bootstrap
servers equal a broker,
and my broker is in
the same container.
It's on Local Host 90 92.
And I'll just come down
here and I'm going to say,
Okay, well, this is
the Kafka cluster.
And then down here, I
can do a subscribe.
Just like any consumer would,
you can subscribe to topics,
and I'm going to
subscribe to animals.
Jason, And so I'm going
to get that whole thing,
and let me just make
a little bit more
room here. All right.
Great. And I'm going to put
that in something called DF.
And when I look at DF,
what I'm may see is that it
doesn't matter what
stream I chose from,
I always has the same things.
It has the key of the message.
It has the value of the message.
And get anything out of here,
the real work will
be, can I take this,
which is bytes and extract it,
so I get a few different
columns there.
Another thing that
we're going to see,
is that if I look at the count,
Of this. I go to run some jobs,
and we'll tell me how many,
I guess there's 181
messages there so far.
If I run it again instead
of 181, it will be 187.
Right? So every time I run
it, I can just, you know,
get a snapshot of
that Kafka stream,
which is growing forever
and ever, right?
Alright, so I have all of that
there. That's fine and well.
If I want to say,
I'm going to say
data frame do limit.
I'll just do it like the first
five and convert them to Pandas.
And so I'm going to
see it down here,
these values, they kind of look
like like lists of integers.
They're not. That's the way
they show you bytes, right?
A byte could be a number 0-255.
And so I see while there's a
bunch of numbers like that.
These are bytes. My job is
to extract it back so I can
actually see what animal
and what beach is
involved, right?
And so a lot of the
stuff that we do, right?
A lot of this processing
is based on functions
under Pi Spark SQL functions.
And I'm a important column
that we've seen before EXPR.
My do another one, which
is going to help us,
which is from JSN.
And so I have this data frame,
and I'm going to try to
parse some stuff out
of there, right?
So I could select, for
example, a couple of columns,
I could select out the key,
and I could select
out the value, right?
That's what I'm most
interested in here.
I could hit those two things.
And if I want to,
I could cast it.
Cast means I'm
changing the type,
and I could do it to a string.
Very fortunately, for me,
by default, it assumes
a UTF eight encoding, if
I go bytes to string.
And in fact, I don't think
there's even a way
to override it.
So a good thing I use
a UTF eight encoding.
And so I can do all that.
Great. And let's
take a look at that.
Maybe let me just do the limit
five again in two Panda so
we can see where we're at.
All right. I can see I'm
already making progress.
I can see, well, this
was a row of data that
came from from where.
Like, way back here, right?
I got this beach and animal.
I wrote it to a message.
That was the value,
which was bytes in the message.
And now I can already see,
and in the Spark side,
I can get that back.
I can get a string
representing that Jason.
Now, it's not everything I want.
I would like to somehow extract
individual things like this and
make them individual columns,
because I actually want
to do analysis over it.
And so what I'm going
to do next is I
will say, check on this here.
I will say from J SN,
on this one, and that will
convert it to these strucks.
And when I do that, I have
to specify some schema,
because I need to say, well,
what types am I
expecting in this thing,
what are the column
names, right?
And so the schema
is just a string,
and some say schema up here.
And what it should
do is it should
specify the names of
the field, right?
I'm going to say Bach
and creature, right?
And I also have to
put the types for it.
The type names come afterwards.
And so in this case,
these are both strings.
I'm to say string, string.
And then I'm going to
pass this in here.
Let's try that. And what
we actually see is I have
a little issue, right?
I'm getting the beach name,
but I don't have creature
because if you look
back here where we
were writing it
before, I called
an animal, right?
So I had a typo, right?
And that's to emphasize
that how we actually
parse this out.
Now, you can imagine that these
different producers over
a different time, right?
It's just running indefinitely,
and people change that code.
They might add stuff
to these dictionaries
or remove it over time, right?
And so what happens if
the schema has
something extra here?
It just fills it in with
the none because maybe it
thinks that I'm supposed to
have a column with that name,
and older messages
didn't have it.
On the flip side, right,
if there is something like,
if it has animal, right in
the actual dictionary and
I don't have animal up
here, just drops it, right?
So it's going to
work regardless why,
I'm not going to get any error,
but it might mismatch, right?
So you have missing data, you'd
want to go back and
double check that.
Right? I'm may say
that as animal.
And now I'm making some
real progress, right?
I can actually see it
looks like a tuple here.
It's actually a structure. It
has names on those fields.
But I can see I'm
making progress, right?
What I may do is I may
give this a new name,
which is just going to be value.
And then the reason why
is that down here I
can select a couple
of things, right?
I can select down
here, both the key.
And then instead of value,
I may say value dot star.
And then all the
entries inside of
those struts are going to
become their own own column.
I'm going to do that. And now I
say I've actually made a
lot of progress, right?
I can d from that
JSN dictionary,
and I actually can
get some columns,
and I could analyze it.
If I wanted to, I can start
counting the beaches or
start counting the
animals. All right, cool.
Any questions so far
about all of that kind of
consumer parsing stuff? Right.
Cool. So when I look at
this thing, this DF.
You know, actually,
what I may do is
I may call this animals.
I may put it in there, and
then I'll just
take a look at it.
Animals, Dot limit, two pandas.
When I look at animals,
it's a data frame, but I
can say, is it streaming?
And the answer is false, right?
They have a special
case for that.
Right now what I'm doing is it's
a Kafka stream, and it's
constantly growing,
but I read it at a single
point in time and I get
a static data frame,
that's not changing.
What I want to do is
have a new kind of
data frame that grows
with the Kafka stream.
Alright? And soba
come back here,
and I am going to get my
code that was reading DF.
And it's actually a relatively
simple change, right?
So to get a streaming DF,
change read to read stream.
So I'm just going to put
read stream down here.
Alright. And then at this point,
DF is going to be a streaming.
Data frame. And if I get
animals like this back here,
I'm going to be the
same thing back here.
Let's get these animals,
and animals is also going
to be streaming, right?
If I have a streaming data frame
and I do some
transformations on,
I get a new streaming
data frame.
Okay. And there's may be
different things that we
can do with a
streaming data frame
in a regular data frame.
So, for example, I want to
say how many rows are there.
Like I did before, I
can't do that, right?
When I come down
here and I look,
it says, I need to
do something elses,
right stream thing.
It doesn't make sense, right,
because This is a data frame
that's by definition
constantly growing.
How can I possibly say
what the count of it is?
Right? That's constantly
changing, right?
Okay, so how do we
actually use these things?
The format will be kind of
like this. Where do I say?
Where I go from
source, a data source,
where I do some transformations,
and then we have some sync
where the data ends, right?
And so what we're doing is we're
constantly moving
data from point A to
point B with some transformations
in the middle, right?
And so how do we specify
the data source
of the data sync?
Well, we're going to do
something like this,
where I say spar
dot read Stream.
And then there's going to be
some transformations
in the middle,
possibly or maybe not, right?
And then at the end, where I say
write stream to
someplace else, right?
And so what this will
do is we can say,
this is where the
data is coming from.
This is where the
data is ding to,
and these are all the things
I'm doing in between, right?
Okay. So how could we
actually build some kind
of application based
on this, right?
So say to do build,
build a shark alert
app, for swimmers.
They know not to go
to those beaches.
And I'm trying to say taking
this stream right from Taka.
And then the sync
where the day is ready to
do is just be the screen.
The screen will pop up messages
whenever there's a
shark that's been seen.
They'll tell me where
they've been seen.
And how ma I do this?
All this stuff here like
the Spark Red Stream and
transformations If you look
back here, I've
already done that.
I have the read
stream right here.
That's the source of my data.
I already have some
transformations based on it.
And so if I look at,
like this part here,
I already have that,
and it's called animals, right?
I've given animals as the
name of half my pipeline.
Now, I want to do some
additional transformations
on it before I
send it somewhere,
and I'm going to say dot filter,
and I'm going to say where
the animal is a is a shark.
I do that thing, and
I get a data frame,
I can see a schema on it.
But to really complete it, I
have to do a right stream.
So I'm do that right Stream.
And maybe this is another one
of those ones where I
want to break it up.
Some to say right Stream,
And for this one,
I go to have to say
you the format, right?
I mean, I could do
like CPA, again,
I could be writing
the Sarka art out to,
like, a special topic, and
people could subscribe to it.
In this case, I just want to
send it straight to the
consul, which is my screen.
I just want to see it, right?
Alright. So I'm gonna do that.
And what else, right?
It'll kind of match these things
up and do a few at a time,
right as I have the
messages coming in.
And so I can say what
trigger will do it.
And I'm going to say
processing time.
Equals 5 seconds.
So about every 5
seconds is going to be
giving me some shark alert.
Hopefully, that's enough time
to get out of the water.
Then finally, I have to say
what output mode Do I want,
right? And I'm may say, a pen.
A pen means that I'm writing
to the end of something
and I never go back and
make earlier changes.
So for example, if I have a
new shark that's been seen,
I'm going to pen
some new output,
and that would not make me,
go back and change any of
my previous outputs, right?
A new shark does not make me
change what I said about
previous animals, right?
I'll just have that be
added to the stream,
right? So do that.
And when I do all of this,
I get the data
stream writer thing,
and if I really wanted to start,
then I have to say, start.
And start is going
to return an object,
which is called a streaming
A streaming query, right?
All right. So I'm going
to do that, right?
I did a bunch of this had
that red stream inside if
I did some pre processing,
more pre processing, now I
write stream and it's drawing
somewhere else, right?
So Data is going to
be coming off that
Poka stream onto my stream,
right? I have some batches here.
No sharks, thankfully.
Okay, there's a shark.
Well, lots of sharks all at
the same time and a bunch of
different beaches, right?
Not a good day for swimming.
And that's just ting to keep
running forever, right?
I would be kind of weird
to do this on NOPA, right?
People probably
normally do this like
an adopt Pi file that's
running somewhere,
but I'm just doing it here
for the sake of of example.
All right. So I'm going
to pause there and see.
Do people have any questions
about this streaming job?
Here. Where does this start?
I'm assuming that
before this there
were so many sharks in the Wh,
yeah, that's a really
excellent question, right?
Be You assumption is right,
that there are a lot of
sharks before I even got
to this far in the code.
And by default, it
just starts at the end
of the topic. I will
do an example soon.
How can I guess last
time we saw we could
call S two beginning,
I think it was called.
And they have
something analogous to
that probably a wrap
around that I show.
Yeah, Excellent point. Yeah, all
the points people
have are questions.
Right. Cool. So that
thing's running.
I probably want to stop
running it at some point.
And so I can say
streaming query dot stop,
we'll stop running the thing.
Let me just run it
again. Let me show
you another way I can do it,
right? So that's running.
Because sometimes you forget to
save it in a variable, right?
And so the other ways you
can say spark dot streams.
And then I can say
specifically the active ones.
That'll give me a list.
I can get the first item,
and I can say stop.
So I can d row and I can stop
whatever I want to stop,
or if I have a variable, I
think that's preferable.
All right, so that
was one app, right?
We built a shark alert app.
All right. Any other questions
about the Shark alert app?
Yeah, right here. Oh, what
are some other formats?
Yeah, that's an excellent
question, right?
So I could be like
a FCA producer,
right where I consume
from one stream
and then write alert
to another one.
I could write it to Park
files and HDFS, right?
So maybe I'm just
trying to build
up some dataset for
people to analyze.
It could be, maybe like
a my SQL data base
or it could be
like I don't know.
I could write it to like
a socket somewhere.
It's actually very plug. You can
put a lot of different
things there.
Yeah, great question. Yeah.
It looks like
there's a follow up.
Yeah. Oh, you're saying
that if I said it to like if
I had like a shorter time,
like, would it still
be able to keep up or
Oh, yeah. And in this case,
I'm getting a bunch
of messages at once.
So in this case, I had three
messages at once, right?
Absolutely. Yep.
It's time waiting.
I mean, what we see is that
for each of these batch,
is actually running a
different spark job,
and it's like, Well,
it wants to do it quickly enough
so we quickly know about
the sharks, right?
But also, it's like
trying to batch
up enough, so it's efficient.
Yeah, a great question.
Yeah, other questions people
have. All right. C.
So for the next app,
we're going to say,
let's build an
animal counter app.
And that's a little
bit this is the case
where we have an
advantage of using
Spark over just Pre Python code.
Right? When I come back here,
to where I was
writing this stuff,
I chose my key to be the beach.
And remember that when I do a
send message with that key,
it will hash partition on that.
And so what the animal producer
right now is it's
bringing together
related data when I have two
rows with the same beach.
That means if I have one animal
that's seen in
different beaches,
that data will be split across
different topics, right?
And if I was just writing like
a Python consumer, right?
I wouldn't be very easy to
count the animals in one place.
I could get two
different sub counts
and two different consumers.
Now, Spark is great at
hash partitioning and bring
related data together.
So it doesn't share
what Kafka does.
It's try to do that hash
partitioning as an extra step,
bring together related data,
and then tell me how many
animals there are of each type,
right? So we have animals.
And we can, if we want to,
we can group them, right?
We can group them by the
animal type. All right.
Then I can say, let's
count them, right?
So I have that count
there. And then
I can do all the
stuff I did before.
Let me just copy it because
I don't want to type it all.
I can do all the right
stream stuff to try
to get it onto the
stream, right? All right.
And I may have a streaming
query like before,
streaming query will
be all the stuff.
Run to a little issue now
and this give me an
opportunity to talk
about the output
mode. All right?
So let's see what
it says down here.
A Penn output mode is not
supported when there's a
streaming aggregation.
So exception with water marks.
We'll talk about watermarks.
But in general, I cannot
do the pen type when I'm
having a group by
or another kind of
aggregate. Why is that?
Well, remember that a pend
means I get some new data
and I write something out
without changing
previously what I put out.
Something I filter that's fine.
In this case, let's say I
told you there's ten sharks,
and now I see another shark.
I can't go back and
change it to 11, right?
And so in that case, I
cannot use that output mode.
There's some other output
modes. One is complete.
And that means that every
time we see some new animals,
we're going to dump out a count
of every animal
we've seen so far.
Let's do that. So I'm
going to run that thing.
And there's 200 tasks
running right now.
What did I infer based
on the fact that
there's 200 tasks?
It's running another
patch, another 200.
Yeah, right here. When
it's trying to do what?
Yeah, we saw that for y,
we saw for group, we
do hash partitioning,
and then sometimes we
end up with 200, right?
And the reason right
is that we have to bring
related data together, right?
So you do like a
hash on the key,
and then moy the
partition count.
And any kind of partition count
would be logically valid,
but it may be faster or slower.
And by default, they do 200,
and that's usually too many,
but it's been okay before
because they would
co small partitions
together, right?
They can't do that
with Spark streaming
because how can you say
it's a small partition?
It's not like we
have one fixed data
that we look at and
see how big it is.
It's like, Well, I
do the partitioning.
I have to decide,
and I have to keep doing
that indefinitely, right?
I don't know what
the future holds.
And so it has a bad default,
which is 200, and there's not
a good way for them to
automatically fix it, right?
And so that's one of the
things I want to fix.
The other thing I
want to fix here
is what was coming on earlier,
I want to start counting from
the very beginning, right?
So I'm come down here and
I'm going to stop this job.
I'm going to say,
streaming query dot stop.
And whatever, I'll
get some error.
It's fine. I interrupted it.
It's fine to get an error.
Okay, so What I'm
going to do first
is I am going to go way back
here to where I made my session,
and I actually have
to configure this.
Unfortunately, the number of
shuffle partitions is fixed
for every single spart job.
I have to set it
globally, right?
So I will do that.
I will say, I will say spark
dot squle do partitions.
And I'm just going to have
ten Because I only
have like one machine.
I don't have a lot
of resources, I
makes sense to have
a lot of partitions.
Alright, I'm to do that. And I
probably have to restart
all of this, actually.
Fortunately, I'm to do that.
Probably need to restart,
I need to restart my broker.
Or my producer.
I'm going to
recreate that thing.
I'm probably download
all that stuff again.
Great. Let me just
head down here.
I'm not t to rerun everything.
I'm not going to do
the shark stuff again.
But down here,
I'm actually getting my
streaming data frame.
I'm going to do all
of this. Then I
think I'm good down
here where I can
actually start
running this again.
All right. So we're gonna run
it. And instead of seeing
200 tasks of two partitions,
you saw it was like ten.
And now we're trying
to do it like so fast,
maybe we might even not see
it all the time, right?
It's kind of warmed up a bit.
Great. So it's running a lot
faster because I chose a
better partition count.
That's one takeaway, right?
I'm going to do that.
And then the other comment
was that when we
read this thing,
we should seek back
to the beginning.
And so when I come back here,
there's an option for that,
and I can say dot Option
and starting offsets.
I want to do the
earliest, right?
A little bit differ than
the sk to beginning,
but it's the same thing.
It's probably a wrapper
around that, honestly.
I'm just going to run
through this again,
and let's skip the sharks and
trump down to this app.
I'm going to do that.
Now, the first job is
actually probably big,
because there was
a lot of data, I
had to count up
all these things.
But now it's caught up.
Things are running fast.
I get a few animals at a time.
There was one shark
between this batch and
the last batch. All right, cool.
The last thing I want to show is
that maybe actually
should be running this
again is that we have
this console on 40 40,
and as this is running,
I guess there's a bunch
of jobs down here.
We have, like 11 completed
jobs, 12 completed jobs.
Every single batch of data runs
as a new, there's one active.
Now it's 113 jobs.
Every new batch is its
own Spark job, right?
If you keep doing
this, it runs forever,
and you have lots
and lots of jobs,
and that's just how it works.
Right. Cool. Any questions about
the programming demos
before we dive into
some concepts and
actually understand how
Spark streaming works internally.
Questions about that.
All right. Cool.
So let's head over
here to the slides for Friday.
We're going to kind
of an early start
on it, which is nice.
And I have a few things
that I want you to
walk away with.
One is that remember with Spark.
Everything is built
on these RDDs,
Resilient distributed data sets,
and the same thing
with Spark Stream.
I want to understand how
I have a Spark Stream,
how it gets broken down
into micro batches
and each micro batch
runs as an RDD.
Okay? We've already
seen that there's
this kind of finicky setting
about the outputs it a pen?
Is it complete? Something else?
I want do you understand
what that is in
more detail and how to pick
it for a given situation.
It turns out the vast
majority of the things
that you can do with
regular Spark SQL,
you can do with
streaming Sparks equal.
But there's a few
things like pivots
or certain types of joins
that are not supported.
And I want you to get
some intuition about why those
things aren't supported,
so you can kind of anticipate
when certain features
will be there or not.
And then finally,
there's a bunch
of optimizations I
want you to know.
We already saw one
of them, which
was dealing with the number
of shuffle partition configures.
But there's some other
stuff like how you might
cache when you have
certain s of joins,
or there's this thing called
a watermark that you need
to be aware of. All right.
So those are a few
goals for you today.
Let me start with distributing
this idea of a D stream.
A DStream and a Spark Stream
mean exactly the same thing.
The early literature when they
first introduced
streaming to Spark,
they published a paper where
they called it DStream.
So sometimes you'll see
that. Sometimes people just
more informally
say Spark Streams.
All right. So D streams
are based on RDDs,
and so I want to
remember how RDDs work.
Here's some data where
I have a list of rows,
and I want to filter
it down to the A's,
and then I want to double the
value in the second column.
And I can see how
I have that data,
I do a bunch of transformations
on it, and in the end,
I collect it, and I get a
list of tuples again, right?
That's like classic RDD stuff.
That's where we started
our exploration of Spark.
Now, I want you to think about
what happens if I do that,
and then there's some more data.
A naive way to do it is
that whenever there's
some new data,
I just rerun the
entire job, right?
That would not be great because
every time I do it I start
to be a little bit slower,
there's more data, and
I'd be repeating a
lot of work, right?
So I could do that. It wouldn't
be a good thing to do.
It'd be slow, right?
All right. What could we
do that would be better?
Well, when I have
these two rounds,
I could actually
have them be part of
the same graph, right?
I could say that
Hey, let's cache.
Those results in memory.
And then I'm going
to have a new RDD,
that's going to combine the
old state with some new stuff.
I'm going to get
some new results.
Right? That's the main
idea they have when they
introduced streaming to Spark.
Okay? So what did that
end up looking like?
I mean, on top of those RDDs,
we usually have data frames,
which are a bunch of rows.
And instead of having a
fixed sized data frame,
this table is continuously
growing, right?
And rather than to
treat it one row at a time,
that would be kind of slow.
What we do is we're going to
break it into many batches.
I could say, well,
here's a many batch,
here's a many batch.
And I can choose different
time thresholds.
Depending on how I choose that,
I could have you know
more smaller batches
or fewer bigger ones, right?
So I have this constantly
growing data frame
that's growing
down into batches,
and I want to do
processing on each of
these batches to produce
more output, right?
And so what I may do
is I may have a chain
of RDDs coming off
of each batch.
And And in a lot of these cases,
the final output will
depend on previous results.
So I might, I don't always,
but I might have kind of
a vertical chain
here, too, right?
And that's what a D
stream is, right?
It's like a chain of all
these RDDs that build on each
other and it keeps growing
indefinitely, right? So
we have all of those.
Those are what a D stream or
a spark stream is. All right.
Now, sometimes I have what
is called a stateless D stream.
And that means that each of
these batches can be handled
independently, right?
This batch does not depend on
the previous batch, right?
That would be stateless.
This one state Pub
as it does depend.
All right. So when they're
independent, that's stateless,
showing to a quick
tophat to make sure that
people understand what it
means for it to be stateless.
Bizet has a lot of implications
for performance. All right.
Let me just head over here,
just a moment, please.
All right. All right.
So I have a query here,
and I'm wondering
if it is stateless or not.
About 3 seconds left.
So most people are saying, yes,
it's stateless,
which is correct.
Let's think about how we
could reason through that.
Let's say that first
off, I have my stream.
Sometime table. It's
constantly growing.
I can see based on
the select line
it has x and y columns.
I've got a bunch
of rows coming in
and I've been putting
a bunch of output.
Now I have a new row, which
is x equals f equals three.
The question is, when
I get four plus three,
can I put some result without
looking back at history,
and answer is, yes, I can.
I can add four plus
three, and I can tell you
seven without caring about
what the history was.
If I need to look back at
the history to
produce a new output,
then it's stateful,
but this is stateless.
All right. Any question
about statelessness?
Yeah. W. Oh, how
could it be stateful.
For example, if instead of
doing a sum over each row,
if I had a sum over each column,
then I would have a rolling
count and if I got a new row,
I could give you a new total,
but I would have to remember
what it was previously.
That makes sense? Yeah.
Yeah. Thanks for
asking for an example.
The other questions people have?
All right. Cool.
Heading back here.
So, we have
all these d streams building
on top of each other,
and of course, the whole
goal is we want our data
to end up in some
other system, right?
That's called the
sink over here.
And we already saw we can do
the Red stream for the source,
the right stream for the sink.
And so we have all
of these RDDs in
the middle that are
maybe usually depending
on each other,
and they're helping me move
data one batch at a time.
From source to sink and
doing some transformations
in between.
On both sides, it's
high pluggable.
I mean, we could be
pulling data from Kafka,
or HTS files,
Cassandra, anything.
Same thing on the
sink side, right?
Maybe I'm pulling data
off a Kaka stream,
and I'm writing a bunch of
different Park files
every time I get,
like, a big batch
of data, right?
So it's an excellent
system for moving data
from point A to
point B. Oh, right.
And I think I have
1 minute left.
I don't want to start
talking about this slide
because it'll take
more than a minute.
So tell you it.
We'll end there. And come up
if you have any questions.
I'm happy to chat, and
we'll dig deeper next time.