The exam results for most
of you unless there
was some issue,
if it was ten with Penn stuff,
there's a few weeks
up to start out or I
still need to get back
the copies from the
testing evaluation,
c, that might affect
a few people.
But hopefully, most people
have their exams back,
double check it and make
sure it's actually there.
And I'm going to
be working to get
the last few exams out
out soon for everybody.
If you go into resources,
you could see your
exam what ass.
That shows you the answers you
put down and also the
answers that were expected.
There are eight different
versions of the exam,
so you can see which
version you took.
And then just check
that Canvas message.
I pushed all of the PDFs for
the eight versions
to our git lab repo,
so you can draw and kind
of learn from that.
And it's always nice
to spit a little
time after exam to learn
from the mistakes.
So I mean, it's cumulative,
so that's kind of the most
maybe immediate concern,
right preparing for other exams.
But I think you spent
all this time doing the
exam, prepping for it.
There's an opportunity to
learn a little bit more.
Whenever you got
something wrong,
there's something else that you
could kind of refine your
understanding of the material.
So I'd encourage you to throw
and spend a little
bit more time on it.
So where are we in the semester?
So we are doing
some HDS practice.
I want to do a little
bit more of that today.
Make sure you start with
some top hats so that we can
just review some of the
things we're seeing with
HDFS. We'll wrap that up.
And then we'll start
talking about Map reduce,
which is a system that runs on
top of a distributed
file system like HTFS,
and you can use it to
analyze large data sets.
And then we're going to
be moving into Spark,
which is the thing that
we'll cover for a week,
and a lot of people are using it
now instead of a map reduce.
Alright, cool. So I'll head over
here and do the top hat first.
So this is a conceptual question
about a client that's
writing to HDFS,
and I just want to
know how much data
does the client send
over the network.
If we're writing to a file that
has four times replication.
About 30 seconds left.
Alright, so people are
a little bit split
between 5 megabytes
and 20 megabytes.
And the answer is actually
5 megabytes. Why is that?
Well, this client has to get
this identical 5 megabytes
of data on four different
data nodes, right?
And you could imagine
they could have built it,
so it actually sends that
same data to each of them.
That'd be a little bit waste.
Instead, there is
an optimization.
I remember the name of the
optimization, right here.
Pipeline rights. And the idea,
rather than having this client
kind of fan out and
do all the work.
The client sends it to
the first data node.
The first data notes
the second data node,
second data note, sends
it to the third data
node, and so on.
So nobody has this big workload.
And we can write the data
faster than we would otherwise.
Especially depending on
where the client is,
the client might
be in a different
maybe data center even, right?
We might not have as much
bandwidth there, right?
So we want to make sure
that that kind of link from
the client to the first
data node is not over used.
All right, do it
have any questions
about that one?
Yeah, right here.
Does that change doesn't change
the fact that you're still
writing it four times.
But it's how much data does
the clients over the network.
Absolutely. So if I was asking
how much data was the disk,
then the answer would
be 20 megabytes.
If I asked how much data the
clients is over the network,
there would be 5 megabytes.
Does that make sense?
Right. Yeah. So sometimes
I might ask about network IO,
sometimes I might
ask about disk IO,
Is much data is read from disks.
I just want you to understand
how the read paths work
and then be able to answer
these questions in that context.
Have other questions
about this one?
Alright, cool. So I'm going
to do another one as well.
That's kind of a
more hands on one.
And in this case, right,
we spun up our HDFS
cluster before.
And so, oh, let's
just there we go.
It started. Okay, fantastic.
Yeah, I'm just wondering
which type of node do we have
to format before we first,
you know, launch a client
and start using it.
About 10 seconds left.
So the name note
only is correct,
the data notes don't
require you to do that.
And I have to remember
those things as you're
setting up for Project four,
right because you have
to get a name node
and some data nodes deployed,
and you have to figure out what
the steps are for each of those.
Of course, you don't
review the video and
I set all this stuff up.
Alright, great. So
we'll head back to
this notebook where
we were last time.
And I just want you
to remember my setup.
If I come back here
and I say, Doctor PS.
You see I have two
containers running.
There's one for HDFS.
And in that one, I manually
started both a name
node and a data node,
and I showed the
commands for that.
And you're project you're going
to be doing it a
little bit different.
You have the name node
running in one container.
You'll have a couple of data
nodes running in
different containers,
but in this example,
I ran them together.
And then I have a separate
notebook where I'm sorry,
I have a separate container
where my notebook is running,
and it can refer to this one.
And when I had started
this up before,
I said that the host name
for the HDFS container was Mine.
And so I've been using
Main in a lot of cases.
So I've been talking to
the name node so far,
and the name node really
is a server on two
different ports.
One port is 9,000.
There are RPC calls that
happen over port 9,000.
So all of these
different things like
these different
command line tools
are using 9,000 to
use those RPC calls.
We can also use it with HTDP,
and there's a Rs API for
communicating with it,
and that's where we
were in last time.
And so for HTP,
thenam node is actually
listed in a different port,
which is 8987 oh.
And a lot of these
well, I guess,
all these different things
are documented in this file,
and we're only using
a few of them.
Let me just throw up to the top.
Right? There's all these
different things you could do.
And they all have
similar form, right?
The form is that we maybe
say what file or directory
we're operating on.
And then a question mark
and we have some
arguments over here,
and we say what
operation we're doing.
So so far, we are doing
an open operation,
and we can have these
other arguments that
are separated by these
ampersands, right?
So I'm opening a file for
reading at this offset
and this length.
And when I did this, right,
I'm sending this open
request to a name node.
And I did it with url.
And I said dash I so I
can see the headers.
And I actually see that
it's kind of a little bit
unusual because I have
one set of headers,
and then a second set of
headers before I
actually get the data.
So can anybody let me know or
remind me what's going on here?
Why is Carl?
Why is Carl actually doing
two different HDDP
requests? Yeah, right here.
So a node redirect data data.
Excellent, right? So when I
go to the name node first,
the name node should never
send data anywhere, right?
B I have this giant cluster with
lots of data. I only
have one name node.
That's the bottleneck,
so it should
only send metadata, never data.
And so it's redirecting.
It's redirecting assist
location down here,
which is the data node and
the L. You're also
correct follows it.
And so we first got
a temporary redirect
from the name node.
And then after that we got
an actual proper response
from the data node
that we redirected to,
and then we were able to get
the data back. Okay,
so we can do that.
We also saw that
instead of using curl.
Often rest documentation,
they give curl examples,
but we can do very
similar things
with the request module
in Python. I'm bring
that down here.
We saw that we can
say, no redirect.
And in that case, it
will not follow it.
Right? I'll just get actually
Json back to strike
me the location.
And so I can see
the location where
the name node is telling
me I could go get
that piece of data.
And in this case, if I
run this many times,
I would get the same
output many times.
On your project, when you
have multiple data nodes,
this might actually change if I
kept rerunning these
couple pieces of code.
Any thoughts about why it might
change if I keep
rerunning these couple
lines of code here?
Go ahead. Yeah, when
you're saying semi sing a
semi other data node, right?
So the name node sometimes
sends me the one data Node.
Sometimes it sends me the other
one B there's
replication, right?
They have the same data, right?
And, maybe it's based on
whether busy or maybe
it doesn't randomly.
Who knows what load
balancing policy they have?
But there's multiple
places thena could
send me and it is choosing one.
Okay? So that's what happens
when we read a file.
And sometimes they'll do that
for part of the project.
For another part of the project,
you actually have to tell
me where the data is on
different data nodes.
And so we have to
have a separate call.
We want to ask the name node.
Tell me all of the
locations where it is,
instead of just a
single location.
And so if I come back to the
documentation over here,
that is called a get
file block locations.
And so I can tell them and
I can see an example here.
It's pretty
straightforward, actually.
There's no really extra
arguments or anything like that.
I just say they get
file block locations.
And I'm just going
to do that briefly
because you're going
to have to do it
on the project as well.
And some say, instead of all
this. What will I pass in?
I'll say it file,
block locations.
And then I can get r dot JSN,
kind of a strange format.
I guess they have
a dictionary here,
and I can see the keys
in the dictionary.
It only has one key,
which is block locations.
All right. And then there's
only one key in that one.
There's a dictionary in
side of a dictionary.
That one has block locations.
I don't really know who
designed this or the
rationale for it.
But that's fine.
We can just see what we
have and pull things out.
And at this point, I
get a list, right?
So I could say for
block and this and I could
print off each block.
And in this case,
there's only one block,
but what I can see here
is for each block,
we how large is it.
And I can see more
importantly the host.
This is telling me what data
nodes there are. I'm
going to make a not here.
Hosts tells you which
data nodes Ha it.
So you use this maybe
in a couple of cases.
One case, I just want you
to be able to tell me,
where is the data
for a specific file,
including both replicas.
In another case, you might
use it because I want you to
tell me after you manually
kill a data node,
which data was lost.
And so if you ran
something like this,
you might see that there's
some blocks of data
that don't have any data
that data was lost.
There's no more replicas of it.
And so you can use this
to kind of understand how
the replication and fall
tolerance are working
in the system.
Can you any questions
about either of these two,
the open and the file
block locations?
All right. Well, I'm just going
to show one more quickly,
and that is list status.
And List status could let me
see all of the things that
are in a directory, right?
And so in this case,
I'm going to put
a path here that's a directory.
Let me just put this down here,
so I'm may say the
data directory,
and I may say list
status. All right.
And then let me just throw
back and look at the JSN again.
That's why I always
use these restings.
I just look at the
JSI and I figure out,
you know, what keys
are available to me.
And then I dig in.
I get those. I get those keys.
And what do I have
here? And now I
see I have another
dictionary, right?
So I check what keys
are available here.
The are only really
one again, right?
I'm going to say file status.
All right, fine. And then
here I actually see
have a list, right?
So this is a list of
all the files, right?
So I can go through and I
can see the names, right?
I have like a licensed dot TXT,
and I have a v two dot TXT.
So all these things that
you might do in the command
like listing files,
opening files,
or listing directories, you can
do as well via
this web HDFS API.
Oh, right. So I
want to show you a third
way to access the data.
So we've seen the
command line tools.
We've seen Web HDFS.
And then the third way is
that we can use Pi Ro,
which we've used before for
a couple of things, right?
We've used it to learn
about cash friendly layout.
We've learned about
how we can use it to
map data from disc.
And so let's tub down here.
I may say, let's do Pi arrow.
And in most case, if
you're writing a code,
this is probably going
to be an easier way
to read your files instead of
using that web HDFS API.
And so when I'm down here,
I'm going to import Pi arrow as
PA. And there's
some other things
in there that I'm going to need.
So it has different
file systems, right?
So file systems.
And based on that,
I can say, Pi arrow to file
system, Hadu file system.
And I might have different
Hadoop clusters, right?
So I have to specify
which one, right?
I have to say the name note,
in particular is how
I really identify
the cluster B is the name node
noes where all the
data nodes are.
And so I have one
that was at the Main.
I have a name node
there on port 9,000,
and I can basically get a
Hadoop file system like that.
And then what I can do is I can
open files in the
Hadoop file system
in much the same
way I would open
files on my regular file system.
So any one of the calls
that we've seen before
is open input file.
Right? And I can do this and say
specifically it's from
this file system.
And so I can say something like
slash data V two at TX.
So I can open that.
I'm going to open
it as F, right?
And maybe penology pass, so
I can take a look at it.
When I understand these APIs,
there's a couple of
things I might do.
I might look at
the type of F or I
might look at the method
resolution order.
So one of the things
that that would help
me do is I could see,
not only, like, what type is it,
but what other things
is inherited from,
I guess that's not
telling me so much here,
but just trying to a
general thing to do.
And then the final thing
I might do to try to
understand what I can
do is I might say Dur,
and that will list all of
the things that I can
call on this, right?
I can do things like
reading at certain bytes.
I see there's some things
here like read line.
Let me just try to
read line quickly.
So I'm going to say F read line.
And they're going to
say it's on support.
So even though they're
trying to this kind of
generic standard API for
interacting with these files,
They didn't implement
the API completely.
And so let's say I actually want
to use this and read the file.
I'm going to have to have some
other wrappers around it.
And so some of these wrappers
that are going to help me are
from the IO module in Python.
And so one of the things that
is helpful there is that I
could have buffered reader.
And so if I put
something in here that
just lets me read blocks
at specific offsets,
then this will give me
something that could actually
buffer things up and feed
me one line at a time.
But let me just actually,
I wanted to show
you that I can use
this to read at specific
locations, right?
So I could read a offset.
I think I could read like
500 bytes at offset zero.
Maybe I'll just put that here
and show you what
that looks like.
Right? So this is
definitely this native file
that I got from
Piero is letting me
read bytes at at
different locations.
But the buffered reader is
going to actually
help me pull in
a bunch of bytes
at once and then
break it into these lines.
Right? So I might
create a reader
from that, and I
could loophole it.
I can say for line and reader.
Maybe I could just print
off what that line is.
Alright, so let's try that.
I'll just try me
this out for now.
All right, so I could do that.
And I can see that it's giving
bytes for each of
these lines, right?
So there's different
things I could do.
One is that I could
use some decoder,
I could convert it
to a string with
like UTF eight encoding.
Right? There's different ways
to c rode strings as bytes.
UTF eight is the most common,
so that would be a good chest.
The other way I could do it
is I could use
another thing from
IO called the text IO.
Wrapper. And the
text style wrapper
would also let me
specify and toting,
but I'm going to use the
UTF eight by default.
And that will, as I get
all these bytes from it,
automatically convert
them to strings, right?
So I can do this, and then
I get these nice strings.
And I think actually,
it's giving me new lines,
and I'm printing them off.
So maybe I'll just like n equals
that and know the default is
that it prints a new line e,
and I'm sing to
say I don't print
anything Xtra because
I already have that.
And so then I could
jump in and I
could just start
reading text files.
I think that this would
be more convenient.
Then doing something like
the open up here, right?
When I'm kind of
opening and using
at rest API and
maybe trying to get,
you know, a few
blocks at a time,
because when I'm using
the other web HDFS,
since everything is blocking
it retiring to a data node,
I might have to do a bunch of
these different open calls so
to get different blocks of data.
Pero is try to
take care of that.
And if you use the
extra stuff and Python,
it starts to feel very
much like I'm just
reading a regular
file on my cyst,
someone to get all
that set up going.
Right, people have any
questions about how we access
data in HDFS? A few
different options.
Fantastic.
And the project we'll go
to practice all three,
and that always makes
it more concrete.
Fantastic. So I'm may to head
over and switch
gears a little bit,
we're we move on to a new topic,
which is we have all of
this data in our
distributed file system.
How do we actually analyze it?
Right? How do we
actually make use of it?
And I'm may spend most of
the time talking
about map reduce?
And we aren't trying to do
any projects in map
reduce this semester.
I think it's like
a classic system
that is inspired a
lot of other things,
and people describe
other systems
in the context of map reduce.
So it's something you
have to know what it is
and how you would
in theory, use it.
But then the hands on suf
we're act to do is with Spark.
And set. I'm trying to do
a little bit of
history lesson and learn
how map reduce work?
And then we'll actually
be doing projects?
Multiple projects with
Spark this semester.
So I have a few goals.
Map reduce, the name,
Map and Reduce.
There's mappers and reducers
that you write code for these,
so you need to be able to
describe what the
role of those are.
I want you to also
be able to describe
Spark concepts that we
might use when we're doing
some of this computation.
And those concepts are
related to data linage.
Often when I'm trying
to produce some result,
it's not that I go from my
original data that result.
There's a series of steps
I used to get there,
and data linage
related to Strib.
Like, how do I get
from this output data?
What is my linage back
to my input data.
There's a bunch
of concepts there
that we have to
be familiar with.
We should learn how to deploy
Spark on multiple workers.
And then finally, there's
a couple of ways we can
program with Spark.
One is with something called
RDDs and other data frames.
We can actually use SQL two,
but I want to cover
how how we interact
with it in that way.
Okay, so a little
bit of background.
I want to introduce
this term Data Lake.
It's actually kind of a
relatively newer term,
but it's related
to this concept of
a data warehouse
that we saw earlier.
So let me briefly review
what the data warehouses.
Remember that when
I have a database,
it could either be row
oriented database,
and OLTP database where
I'm handling transactions,
adding rows, looking at
rows, things like that.
And a lot of applications
that people are
interacting with,
things are happening at
this row granularity.
So an organization
might typically have
lots of different
OLTP databases,
and that's not a great setup
for doing analysis, right?
The file laid out
is bad for that.
I want some kind of column
oriented layout for analysis.
I want to pull data
from different places
to do my analysis, right?
So what people
often do is they'll
write these ETL jobs, extract,
transform and load, and
they'll pull data from
all these different
OLTP databases,
and they'll dump it
in OLAP database,
and online analytics
processing database,
and they're going
to call that big
database their data warehouse,
and then some business
analysts will be
doing SQL queries on it, right?
And So looking at this OLAP
database data warehouse,
there's some nice
things about it.
One is that they have
a storage layout that
is codesigned with their
analysis engine, right?
If they have some idea for
how they can do analysis faster,
but it needs a little
extra information,
they might change
their data layout
to make that analysis
possible, right?
This is generally
highly efficient.
But it's a bit limited, right?
What if we want a machine
learning engineer
to train some model
on that data there.
That person is going to have
to write a giant query,
which is like select
star, and they're
just going to dump all the
data in another format.
So the data is already
duplicated and it's
going to be slow.
And so this is not great if
you want to do something
beyond the bare minimum
of of doing SQL
queries or whatever.
So the alternative to
the Data warehouse
is something called a Data Lake.
And a Data Lake is a little
bit of a free for all.
What we'll have is some kind of
giant distributed file system.
Maybe it's the
Hadoop file system.
People also use things
like S three on
Amazon or Google Cloud Storage.
There's different
systems people use.
We talk about HDFS
because that's what we
are just coming out of.
And people will put
files there, right?
Maybe some of these files
are structured like you can have
part files CSV files there.
Maybe some of it's
also unstructured.
Maybe they have different
images or PDFs,
or it could be a
variety of formats.
The idea is that
we have this giant
file system where we're putting
all our data so that it
can be analyzed, right?
And then what we can
do is we might still
want to do SQL queries
on some of these.
And so Spark, for example,
will let us do that.
Spark, I could
write a SQL query,
and it might run
that query on top of
these Park files
and HDFS, right?
But I could also use
other engines, right?
I could use map reduce on there.
Maybe there's some
people using map
reduce and some
people using Spark.
Um, PyTorch is a famous
machine learning framework.
Maybe people are using PyTorch
to train on some of
the images there.
The idea is that even
though we don't have
any system that's closely
coupled with the data layout,
we can have a lot of
different tools that are
taking advantage of this data,
which is now in one big
centralized place, right?
So there's going to
be some people maybe
their job is getting the
data into this place,
other people that are
taking advantage of
this data that's
in our data lay.
All right. So when we look
at Map reduce first, right,
which is one of the
things we might use to
analyze the data in our data.
And so Map reduce was originally
built on top of HDFS,
although you can
imagine integrating it
with other things as well.
Okay, so I want to contrast
this with how we use SQL.
When I am using SQL, Well,
in both cases, right?
I have questions about the data,
and I want to answer them.
In SQL, I would formulate
my question as a query,
send it to a database,
and it would
send me back some results.
A Map reduced job is
significantly harder to write,
but it has advantage that it
can be more scalable, right?
So I have map produced
as a platform,
and I have to give
it a few things.
Instead of writing a query,
I actually write code,
like in Java or Python
or something like that.
And I have to write
code for two functions.
There's a map function
and a reduced function.
I write that code,
and I feed that in.
It's also highly distributed.
So I will say, like, how many
mappers do I want to run?
How many reducers
do I want to run?
I'll feed those
configuration settings in.
And then finally,
rather than just like
sending a query and ding
some results directly back,
data comes from HDFS and
it ends up in HDFS, right?
So I might have a
big table somewhere,
maybe Park files or whatever,
and I'm feeding those
into map reduce.
And then instead of the query
results coming back to me,
the query results
might be too big
to just have coming
back to one machine.
So those query results are
also going to go right back to
HDFS in the end and
then I could have
all the other tool that helps
me use those results
for something.
Alright, cool. So that's
the general structure.
And so I want to
give you a sense
of how we would write
code for these.
I think Java is probably
the most common language people
used to write these things.
I'm going to be just showing
pseudocode and the pseudo
code will kind of
look like Python,
so it feels a little
bit familiar.
But it's just pseudo code.
It's not something that
would actually run.
So how would we write
a map function?
What would we achieve here?
Okay, so a map function is
going to take two inputs.
It's going to take
a key and a value.
And it's going to be
getting these keys and
values from some
sort of input data.
So here I have an input
dot CSV file on HTFS,
and I'm describing a bunch
of different shapes, right?
The different shapes
have different
colors and different sizes.
And I want to write some code,
that's going to help me
answer this question.
And the question is,
what are the colors of
the squares, right?
So I guess there's two squares.
There's a red square
and a green square,
and in SQL, I
would write a query down
here like the bottom.
I say select color from table
where shape equals square.
But I want to accomplish
the same thing now by
writing a little map
function instead.
And so to do this,
I have to think about well,
how is this going to be called?
And so the cool thing
about map reduce is,
I write the map
reduce functions,
but I don't actually call them.
They get automatically
called for me with the data.
And so what will happen is
that Map reduce the
platform is going to
loop over all of these
lines and it's try
to feed them in to
my key in value.
And what we're going to do right
now is actually
take the whole row,
the entire thing and feed
that in as my value, right?
So my value is just
the whole row.
And what is my key?
For this particular case, I
don't actually care
too much what it is,
and different important sources
might do different things.
I may imagine that in this case,
the key is just the
line number, right?
So line number zero.
That's my key. And
then Red circle
three is my value, right?
And it's a very
flexible framework.
You can write different classes
that will take data from
different places and kind
of identify the key
and value differently,
but this would be one setup
you might have, right?
So next one on line one,
I have Red Square five, right?
And so these are all
feeding into my function.
And so then you can start to
imagine how I could write
code here that would
identify all the
colors of the squares.
And so inside of the function,
there's another function
we call called EMT,
and EMIT produces
output data, right?
So there's data coming in
and EMIT has data going out.
And EMIT really has
the same form as the
input data, right?
So we have a key going out.
And a value going out.
And you know, I could
emit whatever I want.
It's an extremely
flexible framework.
But in this case,
what I'm trying to do
is I'm just really
trying to filter down
the original data.
So when I have this
row coming in,
I'm just interested
in the color,
so I could say dot
color is my value out.
And the key in
this example, I don't
really care what it is,
maybe I'll just put the same key
out that came into me. I
could do something different.
It doesn't matter
for this example.
But you can see that
if this function was
automatically called for
me this input data set,
the things I mit would
be red and green.
And those were the colors
of the squares, right?
There's a red square
and a green square.
Okay. So I can
filter things down,
right? Would be one example.
Any questions about MP,
the Map function before
I go to the next slide
about how you might
program something
like this? One.
Oh, how did five be column one.
So when I emit
the key I mean, I can
emit whatever I want.
In this case, I'm
emitting the input key.
And so for me,
the input key was one because
that was the line number.
Right? So the line number
was one. I emitted that.
And then five was the size,
and I never emitted that.
I could have, right?
I mean, I could have made
the size the key if I wanted to,
but I just took the input key,
which was the line number
and use that for the output key.
Yeah, thank you for clarifying.
Yeah, there are questions
people have. Oh, right.
Cool. So how does this
thing actually run?
Like if the data data is huge?
And what they'll do is they
will split it up, right?
I might have a cluster of a
bunch of different machines,
and they will have
these mapper tasks.
And each map or task is
going to get a piece
of the input data.
And each mapper task
is going to have
that map function called
many times, right?
So here I have two map or tasks,
and each of these tasks
is starting to have
the map function
called twice, right?
So I'm cutting up
the data that's coming
from some source,
in this case, is
coming from HDFS.
I'm not really showing the
whole HDFS architecture,
but remember that this
file has probably also
broken up a bunch across a
bunch of different data nodes.
And you can imagine
that you might even,
side to relate these
things, right?
If I know that the block
size is, I don't know,
64 megabytes, maybe I'll have
64 megabytes chunks of the
file going to each mapper.
And so the great thing
about this is that
if I have, you know,
a very large amount of hardware,
then this scales quite well.
Like the data is spread
across a bunch of
different machines.
The computation is spread across
a bunch of different machines.
As long as I have
enough computers,
it doesn't matter
how big the data
is and a fixed amount of time,
I can filter down
this large data
set to a smaller
piece of data, right?
To a smaller subset matching
some condition that
I want to filter to.
So that's already powerful
in and of itself, right?
Now, eventually, we have
to get some output data,
and that's where a
reducer comes in, right?
And so these mappers
are going to have data.
The data coming
out of the mappers
is called intermediate data,
that intermediate data is
try to be sent to a reducer.
And the reducer can
do different things.
But one of the things it might
do is it might just take
the output data from these
different sources and just
concatenate it and
plop it all goes in
one output file
somewhere, right?
So these are going to be
put in all the data here,
and then I could just combine
that into a single output file.
That'd be one thing
a reducer. Could do.
And that's what
it'll do by default.
You get one reducer
that does that.
But you can also write
custom reducer code
that could further process
the data in different
ways, right?
So I have a reduced
function here.
And the things that
it is emitting is
actually the same, right?
It emits keys and values,
right? Why did I say?
I guess I used the word
ro, right? But row value.
It doesn't matter
what I name it.
I'm emitting keys and values.
Again, I could probably emit
as many times I wanted.
The input to this function
is a little bit
different, though, right?
So the map the map function
had a key and a single value.
Here you actually see
it's plural, right?
I have a key and
one or more values that
are coming in, right?
And so I'm writing these two
functions, Map and reduce,
but the map reduced
framework itself
is doing a lot of
work on my behalf.
And so what they're
going to do is when they
get the data coming out of
all of these different mappers,
they're automatically going to
shuffled across the
network for me,
and they're going to make sure
that all of the map output
with the same key is grouped
together in the
same place, right?
And so what that will mean is
that For one unique key
coming out of the Mappers,
I will have one reduced call,
and I will get all the
values with that key
together with a single function
call like this, right?
It turns out to
be very powerful.
It's kind of it's not
doing a lot for you,
but we can based on
that simple property accomplish
a lot of things. Yeah,
a question right here.
Yeah, excellent point.
So in this case,
for the example I
was drawing for,
the key would be the row number,
and so nothing would be grouped
together, right? Exactly, right?
In this case, for that
particular input data,
every time values, we just
have a single thing, right?
But in other cases, we
might do something more
interesting with it.
Yeah, Excellent point, though.
That's why for the first case
where I'm just trying to, like,
filter down to squares,
I probably want
to actually write
a reduced function, right?
I just write a map or a
map function, and I'd say,
give me the default,
reduced function
because I'm not doing
anything interesting.
For more complicated analysis,
then we might write
both of them.
Yeah, yeah, excellent point.
Yeah, there are
questions people have
about the reduced function.
All right. And let's
just see how this
data would flow in.
And I've changed it,
so I have a different map
function than I used to have,
because I'm doing something
a little more complicated.
So first, I'm going
to just walk through
how the data is flowing through
and what the results are.
And then after that,
we're try to talk about, well,
what question was this code
trying to answer about
the data, right?
So I have the same input data,
and the map is doing something
a little bit different.
It's still taking
the input values
and putting the output
values of the same.
I see there's no if
statement in there,
so every input row is start
to be outputted as well.
And what's really interesting
about this one is I'm
changing the key.
The key coming in
was the line number,
but the key coming out of the
map is actually the color.
Right? And so when I run this
map on all these things,
I may have some
intermediate data that
looks like this
over here, right?
Now I have the key is the color,
and then the value
is that whole rope.
So there's a little bit of
redundancy between the key
and the value because the
value also contains it.
That's fine, and
it's common, right?
But I can see that was the key.
I was able to choose key
to be whatever I wanted.
The Map reduce
framework itself is
going to do a lot of work on
that intermediate data for you.
The things that it's going to do
is it's going to
group together all of
the related keys, right?
So I can see that the two reds
are part of the same group and
it'll actually
sort them as well.
So I guess BG R is how things
are alphabetically sorted.
And what they're
going to do now is
they're going to
call on your behalf,
they're going to call
the reduced function
three times are three
unique keys, right?
And they'll just try
to feed this through.
So the first group,
where the blue group
is trying to come in.
And what am I doing over in
this reduce? I have
a count of zero.
I'm looping over all the rows in
the group and just
counting them and then I'm
emitting my key and
my count, right?
So in this case, my
input key was blue,
my output key is blue.
There was one row I looped over,
so my output value is one.
And so as this first group
feeds the reduced function,
I may say blue one.
Okay? The next one
I think is very similar. I'm
going to get a green one.
And then finally, for
this third group, right?
I'll just have one
single reduced call
and it's going to emit red.
But this time it will have
two rows that loop over,
and it'll be a red too.
And I'm just kind of
looking at how I
wrote this code here.
This is the kind of results
I could have produced
with a SQL query.
I'm wondering if anybody
to help me figure
out what is the SQL query that
this code is
basically resembling.
Yeah, right here.
Yeah, select count star
and then group by color.
Absolutely, right? Was
there another time Sorry.
Okay. Great. Yeah. So that's
what this code is
doing here, right?
It can do a group by.
All right. Any questions
about that example?
All right. So how would
this actually run?
We already talked about when
our input data is large,
we might have a lot of mappers.
In this case, the mappers are
outputting the same amount
of data that they
have coming in.
So the intermediate
data is also large,
and the data that the reducers
are taking is also large.
So just like we wanted to split
up and have multiple mappers,
we might want to have
multiple reducers, right?
The number of reducers
doesn't have to be the
same as the number
of groups because
a single reducer can have
multiple calls to the
reduced function, right?
So in this case,
I'm going to end up
with three groups of data,
and maybe one reducer has
two reduced calls and maybe
the other reducer has
one reduced call.
And then each reducer
is trying to produce
its own file in HDFS.
And so maybe that's a
little bit annoying, right?
It's highly scalable
because I run this thing,
and I had my results,
and my results is
in some set of HFS files.
So I could go track
it down and read
all those HFS files and do
something with it, right?
But it's straight
because there's
no central bottleenck
here, right?
Like the mapper scale out.
HTFS scales out very nicely.
The reducers scale out.
R I can work on
very large datasets
and do things like a group
bi and an aggregate.
Oh, right. So I
want to talk a little
bit about how the things
we do in SQL could
correspond here.
Basically, everything
you can do in SQL,
there's a way you
could do it with
more pain with Mp reduced,
but also in a more scalable way.
So something like select, right?
You're choosing which columns
you're interested in.
In the map phase, right?
When you're outputting
a value, you
could choose which
columns there.
Same thing with the
reduced, right?
I a value that the
reducer is is a row,
you could figure out what
columns you want there, right?
So the select that's choosing
specific columns could be there.
We already saw how where
it could be accomplished
with with a map, right?
If I'm doing the wear,
I can just like
emit certain rows.
Group by is really
accomplished with
all three of these
stages, right?
In the map phase, I had to
choose the keys for
what I was grouping by.
And on the reduced phase
was where I actually
had everything in
the same groups.
And I had to do the
aggregate, right?
So the aggregate is paired
with the stroop by.
The shuffle phase happens
in between the
mapping and reducing.
Even though I'm not
writing code for that,
that was a key part of that.
Map reduce itself was shuffling
data to bring groups
together for me.
What about having, right?
So the reduce is the one
doing the aggregate.
And so let's say,
like the reduce is
counting up bros,
the reduce could
have a final filter
like Having does to figure out,
do I want to print out the
summary statistic or not?
So we could do
having and reduce.
What about order by?
So when the shuffle happens,
there's may be different chunks
of data for each reducer,
and each chunk of data might
have multiple groups in it,
and those groups are
going to be sorted.
So one of the ways you
could do an order by is you
could is you could have
a single reducer because
that single reducer is
going to have a bunch
of reduced calls,
and we're guaranteed
that those keys
will be an ascending
order, right?
So you could do an
order by as well.
And then I think
joint is probably
the most complicated one
to think about here.
But there's different
kinds of joins,
and the joint I have in mind
is where I have a foi and key
that is exactly equal to
some primary key in a
different table, right?
So in the examples
I've given so far,
I just have like one kind
of table coming into the mapper.
But there's no reason
I couldn't have
two different tables
coming into a mapper.
And then the map function
will have to figure out,
like, well, which
table is it from.
But the idea then is that
as I have these two tables
coming into the mapper,
it could figure
out, well, what is
the value we're joining in,
that primary or fog and key,
and it could emit
based on that because
to have two tables
and match them up,
I have to figure
out which rows and
one table match which
ones and the other table.
And if I have the
same both of them,
I can bring those rows
together in the same place.
And then what would happen
is that the reducer,
is going to get some rows from
one table and some
rows from other table.
So I'm going to be mixed
together in that same values.
But that reducer can say, well,
these are the rows from
one table that match with
the rows of the other table,
and it could complete the join.
Right? So all of these things
that we can do in SQL,
we can do as map reduce as
well if we're clever, right?
It would be more difficult,
but we could do it.
I also want to point
out that map reduce is
actually more flexible, right?
So For example, when I
do a group by in SQL,
every input row rows
to a single group.
But you can imagine
cases where you have
some kind of analysis where
a single row might d
throw a multiple groups.
So for example, imagine some
Facebook messages, right?
A message has both a
sender and receiver,
and if I'm trying to count
how many messages each person
would have in their mail,
right, then I might
have a single row
that would d throw
to multiple groups.
Very easy to do in
map reduce, right?
You can say, for
this one input row,
I might emit multiple
output rows.
Or let's say even bigger.
Maybe my input data is
something like images
or something like that.
And maybe the key I'm outputting
on is what some classification
model has, right?
Maybe the map is
taking an image,
and then the key output
will be a cat or dog or
it'll kind of identify what
it thinks that image is of.
Right? So map reduce
is going to be more
scalable than a lot of
traditional SQL systems,
is going to be more
flexible as well.
But it's more
difficult to write.
And so means there have
been projects out there,
that will try to build SQL
basically on top of it.
So, for example, Hive QL
builds a little language
that looks like SQL,
and we'll translate
those SQL queries to
to Map reduce jobs
for you, right?
And we see something similar
to that when we learn Spark.
When we're doing Spark, we're
going to write SQL queries,
and that's going
to get translated
to these Spark jobs
that will run.
And Spark will be a little bit
more flexible than
the MapR Produce,
but it'll still kind of have
a lot of these same concepts,
and it will produce
our final results
to accomplish whatever that
query is trying to do.
All right, people have questions
about SQL or how it fits in with
the Map reduce. Oh, right.
Cool. Let me talk about
an optimization here,
which is called data locality.
I've been trying to
talking about HDFS and
map reduce like their
separate systems.
But again, they're designed
by the same people,
and there's optimizations
that you can
do where they will
be located together.
So what will often happen
is you'll have a cluster
of machines, each box,
the red machine, and
maybe I have a data
note on each machine.
And then maybe on some
of these I have mappers
running and other ones that I
might have reducers running.
You could try to choose
which piece of data go to
mapper based on locality, right?
So for my input data,
maybe I could say that
the block coming
from this data node,
we'll go to that that map,
and I could avoid a
network transfer.
Same thing for the
reducers, right?
Maybe the reducers
could try to write out
those data node blocks
on the same machine.
We could avoid some network
transfers there as well.
Right? We have a couple
of things we do, right?
We have data that
lives somewhere,
and we have to have
computation on that data,
and a very general strategy
that people use in a lot
of cases is you want to
try to take your computation
and do that computation
where the data already is.
So we don't have to move
the data over the network.
The bigger the data, the more
important that strategy is.
Alright. So, you know,
Writing one map reduced job,
there's some complexity there.
I guess it's an insane
amount of complexity.
Once you kind of
practice and think about
different examples
with Map and reduced.
You know, you can kind
of get got at it,
but Once you do that,
that's not the full complexity
because one map produced
job generally doesn't do
everything we need to do.
So, for example, I
showed how we could
use map produced to do a
join. Okay, that's one join.
It's very common to
have SQL queries where
somebody has like this table
that they're selecting from,
and the table has a lot of
foreign Ps referring
to other tables.
And so you might want to pull
in some data from one table,
and pull in some other
data from another table,
tell me to get
this final result.
There might be many
joins, right where
I'm keeping on adding
more information.
And so it's very common that
we'll have some input data,
and we'll feed it through
a map produced job,
to get some intermediate data,
feed it through another map
produced job, get other data.
We could have this long pipe
wouldn't be crazy to have
a pipeline that's say,
like 100 map produced
jobs, right?
And it's like, Well,
there would be
like teams that their job is
to maintain this pipeline
of map reduced jobs, right?
So we could totally do that.
And when you look at that,
you have to ask yourself,
is this really efficient, right?
Map reduce is kind of great
for just like one job,
but does it really work well
when we chain a bunch
of them together?
And I have some concerns
about it related to
intermediate data, right?
So there's a bunch of
HTFS files that we're
producing that we don't care
about in the long term.
We're only doing this as a
step towards some other end.
We don't care about
the intermediate data.
We just want to have
the final result.
And so there's a few
things that are bad here.
One would be if we went with
default replication and we
have intermediate
data replicated.
That's just wasteful, right?
Because if I lose that data,
I could reproduce it, right?
So anyway, we could set
replication to one to fix that.
But that'd be one
thing to think about.
Another thing to think about is
whether we can ever
change this together
more efficiently,
we have the output
from one reduce,
and then we're about
to do a map again,
do we have to write it to
some separate HTFS file,
or could I immediately take
that data coming out of
one reducer and just
immediately start
running another maper, right?
And then, finally, when you
do something like this,
you're materializing results for
all the intermediate
data, right?
You're saying like, I have
to have this data here,
because that's the way
we're programming it.
And There might be
different ways to get
the same end result,
and optimization tools
could potentially
come along and find a
better way to do it.
But if I'm doing
this like this, say,
run this map produced job,
run this map produced job.
There's no opportunity for
an optimization tool
to come along and see,
Oh, this is your end
result you want.
Here's a faster way
to do it, right?
So when we're doing this,
either it might not be very
efficient or the
programmer doing
it might have to do some crazy
optimizations to get
good performance.
It's hard to build tooling
that will automatically
optimize that.
So I'll say is that,
intermediate data is one of
the big weaknesses
of map reduce.
And so that's trying
to bring us to Spark.
And so Spark said,
we're going to do a lot
of these same things,
and Spark, they have
MAP. They have reduce.
They actually have a bunch
of other functions as well.
But the most interesting
thing they do is that they
handle intermediate data
very differently, right?
So here I have some
HTFS files for Spark.
There's some operations,
some intermediate data,
more operations, and
then final HTFS files.
The difference is that
for that intermediate
data, HFS files now,
it's something called an RDD,
and an RDD stands for resilient
distributed data set.
And what's really cool
about is look at an RDD,
there's actually not always
bytes of data
associated with it.
An RDD is more actually a
description of the computation
you need to do to get
that data if you wanted
that data, right?
So if you go to be
like, Here's the data.
Oh, here are our directions,
how you could get the data if
you needed to. So it's
going to be lazy.
And so we can have
RDDs based on RDDs.
And S's going to give us
this concept of data
lineage, right?
Where I have this RDD,
and it's based on
that one, which is
based on this other one, right?
It's going to be
lazily evaluator.
I can run this whole thing.
But until I actually want to
look at some bytes of data,
I might not actually
do any work, right?
And then the final thing is
that A RDDs is that
they're immutable, right?
Like, I can define one, and
then I cannot change it.
I could define
another one based on
it that looks a
little bit different.
But once I have it,
it's fixed, right?
So we're going to
spend more time
next time talking
about these RDDs.
And that's going to be
like the key concept that
is build on for the
next, like, week or so.
Alright, have a fantastic day.