Here today. I hope everybody's
having a good Friday so far.
So we're learning about
storage right now,
and a lot of things in
systems are built in layers,
and so we are really
starting with the lowest
layer and working our way up.
So what was the lowest layer?
Well, we learned about
SSDs and hard drives.
Then maybe on top of
that, we learned how that
might be partitioned or maybe
a a raid a combined
together multiple disks.
On top of that, we are
learning about file systems.
Have a file file
system. What do you do?
You store files at
it, and those files
could have different formats.
We'll be talking about
file formats today.
You might be using those file
formats directly
or maybe you have
some kind of database that
stores files in a
particular format.
We're just going to
be working our way
up up and up and up.
So let me go back to
where we were last time.
We had learned that
there were actually
a bunch of different
kinds of file systems,
and in particular, we were to
look closely at the
local file system first.
The local file system
lets us write files,
read or write files,
and then, in turn,
it will read and write
blocks from a block device.
And so we had this
picture from last time.
This is, there's lots of
different ways people
build local files so this
is like one example.
What we learned
about last night was
this idea of an IO IO is
a data structure that
doesn't really have any file
they have associated with it,
but it points to all the blocks
containing data at a file.
We also learned
about directories.
Directories were
these special files.
That basically refer to
a bunch of other files
and give them names.
And so just look at
this picture up here,
we saw that there's this 01
that has block three
associated with it.
And block three, the data,
and there was some file Names
associated with IDO number.
So File Dot text is
associated with IO zero.
If I go to IO zero, that takes
me to blocks two and four,
and then I could find the
data in file dot text.
And because of that, it would
be totally possible to have
the same IDO number in different
directories with
different names.
Right? The IO is a
thing that really
is uniquely associated
with the data.
A file able, I can have
one or Betty, or it
doesn't really matter.
So, based on that, right?
We can have directories that
contain files and
other directories,
those other directores
can contain other things.
That really gives us what
we call file system tree.
It's like a tree. In some sets,
you might actually think
it's more generally
directed Asic like F because we
could have a file that
exists in multiple
directories, right?
So anyway, we have these dags,
I'll just call it a
tree because that's
kind of what people
normally refer to.
And the leaves in
it, I guess would be
either et directories or maybe
maybe just files, right?
And at any given time,
if you're a shell or
a running program,
you have sub current
working directory.
So maybe I have in current
working directory B.
And from there, I can
refer to other things.
In this graph structure.
That's why we call
it a path, right?
Because you can have
a path at a graph
where I'm hopping from
one node to the next,
say, Hey, if I'm at
a file system tree,
I have a path from
one place to another.
So sometimes we
have relative paths
relative to where
we currently are.
And other times we
have absolute paths,
which is basically relative
to the top of the tree.
And so, for example,
If I want to have
a relative path to
e dot text and I want to
get there from my
current directory,
I have to specify the path
as nodes along that draft.
I would say C s
TXT to get there.
I could get that exact same
file with an absolute path.
If I do that, then
I would say slash,
that would start
me up at the top.
And then my path would
be B dot tax, right?
So two different ways to
refer to the same file.
Let's do one more complicated.
Let's say I want to have
a relative path from
B over to d dot CSV.
If I want to do that,
then I actually have
to go up and back do.
The way we say that
we go up is we
say dot, dot, dot means up.
So if I go here, I'm dot dot,
and then A, then
d dot CSV, right?
We should be able to be from
any place and have a
path to any other place.
People have any
questions about that
first before I do
a top hat on it.
All right, F. So the
question will basically be,
what is the absolute
path to CSV?
So I'll come over here and
bring up that top hat.
Maybe I can have
the slides open at
the same time because it'll be a
little bit easier to see there.
I had a little more times
since you actually have
to types up again?
A 20 seconds left.
So most people are
saying slash A slash dS,
which is correct, right?
And we have to start
with a slash, right?
Because it's an absolute path,
so we're starting from the top.
This one right here
would be an example
of a relative path. So
that was not quite right.
Could this work, I guess
we could row down,
and then what would that do?
I guess that would be saying
not quite sure what
that means, right?
I guess if you're at
the top and you go of,
I think that you can
d row up anymore.
I think that would
actually stay the same.
Maybe that would work, but it's
not the shortest
possible answer.
This first answer is
the one I'm really
looking for. Alright, cool.
And so one of the reasons I
want to get you to get
really comfortable with
that is we're going
to be starting to
think about storage in
the context of containers
and thinking about
file paths gets a lot more
complicated in that t text.
So do people have any questions
about file paths before we
move on? Alright, cool.
So let's talk about
multiple partitions,
because we learned last
time that you could
take your disk drives,
and you could have different
partitions on them.
And each partition can
have its own file,
local file system on it.
And so maybe I have
these three here.
This works a little
differently at
different types of machines.
On a windows machine.
The way it'll work is that each
file system on a partition.
I is to show up as its
own file system tree.
It'll give it like
a d letter, right?
I might have a C drive,
I have a tree for that,
a D drive, E drive.
Right if you've used windows,
you've certainly seen
this at some point.
The Udix approach is a
little bit different.
Ux. Well, what is Udix?
Like Lytix is an
example of Udix.
MAC is also an example of Udix.
So this will be very similar,
whether you're on a back
or on a Lytix machine.
And the way the different
file system trees
work is that it appears
as one big tree,
and it kind of reminds me of
this fruit tree here where
they did some drafting, right?
They had one tree, and maybe
maybe it was like
an orange tree and
they grafted on some
limon branches and
some line branches.
They grafted a bunch of
things together and
then they ended
up with one big tree in the end.
And that's actually what they
do on unix systems, right?
So what I imagine
here is that when I
partition these things,
that might be the partition
might be called like SDA one,
SDA two, and SDB,
and I have these
different things,
but I would never see
them dependently.
What we would do is we
would somehow identify one,
which is called our
root file system.
So say the one of the middle
of the root file system.
And then what we would do is
we'd have these mount commands.
Usually there's a bunch of
mount commands that happen
automatically for you with
the system first boots up.
And then you can do
additional mount commands,
or if you create
docker containers,
there's other mount
commands that are going
to be done on your behalf.
And so I could say
I want to mount
the file system on D SDA
one on top of
directory A, right?
So I could take a different file
system by say I
want to mount it on
top of directory and
another file system.
And I would do that. I basically
would look like it's
on top of that.
You see kind of
there was before.
Now all of a sudden, A is
not the original directory,
but it's really the root of
this other file system
we mount it on, right?
So we have individual
file systems,
and then we also have
this unified view
of a bigger file system.
This one's going to be a
little bit more interesting.
I say, I'm write about SDB
one on top of A B, right?
I can really mount it on top
of any directory I wanted to.
That's a little
interesting because
B has some stuff in it, right?
And what happens there is
that that stuff just
gets headed, right?
So take this tree,
and now all of a sudden that's
there and other stuff is headed.
If I mounted later, then
maybe I might see
that stuff again.
But basically, I'm saying, like,
now this directory
is a mount point,
and I'm going to see
a different tree
there instead of
whatever that directory.
Or originally had repurposing
that directory to be
the root of one of these
sub trees. Alright?
And so we'll get this
big unified approach.
Do people have any
questions about
that unified file system tree?
Right. Cool. Now, if
I don't think about tators
at all, I just
have one of these.
But if you're creating
Docer tators,
every time you have a
new docu tator created,
that door tator also
has some unified view
of some number of file systems
that are stitched
together in this way.
And so what I'll really refer to
this whole thing as as a
mount name space, right?
Because I created by
mounting a bunch of things.
And then that he determines
a name space. What
can I see in that?
And so each new containor
I have is going
to have its own mount name space
that might have a different
number of mounts,
or it might be combining them
in different ways, right?
This is kind of a simplified
view of what's happening.
Usually on my Litux machine,
right, maybe on my
virtual machine.
I have a big file system, tree,
lots of different things
mount in different places.
And what I might do
is I might try to get
a specific directory that has
everything I need to
run a contor, right?
So the might have like a
bunch of ubutu files there.
I might have like a tiporary
file system, right?
So different directories on
my Made system are
basically going to look
like they could be the top of
an install for a container.
And what happen is when
I run these containers.
They have about name spaces.
And basically what they're to
see is that kind of
sub directory from
the Maine system is going to be
their whole file system, right?
So we can basically
let these different
containers that are
already feel like
they have their
own file system and
all this stuff,
even though it's just a subset
of what is actually on
the virtual machine.
And if you do a lot
of pokey around,
you can actually
see that, right?
You could see, like, a,
here's the stuff
for the container,
but my virtual machine,
you could find that if you go
pokey around a little bit.
Alright, let's head
over it and do
some demos to make that a
little bit more concrete.
So I want to show some
different file systems as well.
So I'm going to come over
here to my L lynx VM.
And one of the first things I
want to do is I want to run
this Mount command because
the Mount command can be
used to make new mounts,
but if I just run like that,
it lists all the mounts
I currently have.
And, you know, I've been
using lynx for a long time,
and over time, they just
find more reasons to mount
more and more things.
So at this point, I have this
unified file system tree,
which is actually, you know,
close to different
things, right?
Some of them, I
know what they are.
Some of them, I don't.
I'm be talk about some
of the highlights.
The most interesting one was
this SDA was mounted at Slash.
What that means is that
whatever file system
is at SDA Wd is maybe
by root file system,
and everything else is
mounted on top of that.
That's my starting point,
I could graft other file
systems on top of that.
And I see what kind of
file system that is.
It's a EXT four file system.
That's a very popular
local file system,
you'll see a a lot of
different Lits machines.
What else do we have?
We learned about the
POC file system,
which we'll be
looking at shortly.
So I can see that
the Proc file system
is mounted at Slash Proc.
We talked about the TEP
file system, right?
So I see that
there's there's actually a
bunch of tip file system,
but there's one about it at
Rudd. So what does that mean?
That means that if I am
create files underneath d,
it's not on a hard
drive or SSDT,
where it's just a memory.
So that'll actually
be pretty fast.
If I want something to be fast,
I might create files under
slash rud with under
setting that I reboot,
all my files will
be lost, right?
Sometimes that's Okay,
depending on what I'm doing.
Right? So I have all these
different file systems
that we can see. What else?
So the other thing
that we learned
about before is this DF Cad,
which tells me how much space
is used on a different
file system.
So if I say DF, I can see that.
One of the things I might do is
I might say what
directory I'm in.
I might say, for this location,
that part of that
route mount, right?
I don't have anything else
drafted on top of it.
I can see how much
space I have here.
But if I go to a slash
run, for example,
and then I say, Well,
how much space do I have here,
you see it's a completely
different file system.
It's a tip FS instead
of the binwod,
and I can see it's
smaller, right?
It's like 400 gigabytes.
I'm to use 1% of it, right?
Was the other one was like
something like 24 gigabytes,
and I was using 16 gigabytes.
I can do a different
place. I can see
how much space there are these.
And of course, the
tip FS is not to have
much space because I don't have
that much memory
to have a big one.
If I go to slash
PC, and I check.
Well, doesn't really
make sense because
the PC FS is a
pseudo file system.
It doesn't actually
store data anywhere.
The purpose of this
file system is to
give me information
about processes, right?
So if I do LS, there's
a bunch of stuff here.
But if I try to
say something like
Echo High to file a TXT,
It's not going to let me
do it because this is
not a file system where
files are actually stored.
They're all pedo files.
There's no hard
drive behind this.
Whereas if I go back to like
my main directory or
something like that,
of course, I can create files
wherever I please, right?
So let's see how we can actually
use the pseudo file system.
When I look at the things
that are under that POC FS,
I see there's a bunch
of directories with
different names and numbers,
and those numbers
correspond to process IDs.
So, for example, I
may run a sleep.
Come out, I may
sleep for 5 minutes.
And I'm may run that
in the background,
and I'm going to figure
out what process ID it is.
I guess it's process
ID, this right here.
And so if I go to S
Proc and do it LS,
one of these should
be that number,
and rather than look it,
I'll just CD into it.
And so I can look here, and
all this stuff here is giving me
different information
about that process.
So, for example, I
could look at the
command light arguments.
I did a sleep 300 before.
I could look at how
much memory its used.
I can find out a lot of different
information about that.
You see that for a process,
there's quite a bit of
information Li keeps track of.
Most of us, I don't
know what it is,
but you can kind of go
ahead and figure out
what's going on.
So do people have
any questions about
these different file systems so
far about the Proc file system?
Right. Cool. So the
next thing I want to
do is I want to see
how this all plays
out for containers, right?
So I'm going to go to F 24
and this directory where
I have some stuff.
And what I will do is
I will Try to share
some stuff between my host
VM into the Cttor, right?
Because I have options, right?
There's maybe like
a default about
name space that's straight
for the new contator,
but I can choose to have
some extra stuff out there.
I can say that there are
certain directories on
my host virtual machine
that I want a appear
inside of my contator.
It's I make a directory
called Lecture Wood.
And what I do is rod
Ub Tu container,
right, and maybe 24.04.
I want it to be interactive
and I want to have bash.
And then we've seen before how
we can have port mappings.
And very similar to that,
we can have volume mappings.
When I have volume mappings,
I can say something like
Lecture one should show
up inside of maybe
I'll call it like slash
share inside, right?
So this is outside,
and this is inside.
Let me just set that
aside for a moment.
I say something like
that echo high again.
And I put that inside
of e one. All right.
So let me run this command.
And when I do this,
I I go under slash share.
And I made a mistake that people
often make. I want to
talk about it now.
For some reason, I see it empty.
I'm not seeing
that filed at TXT.
And the reason why is
that I put this here,
dockers trying to figure out,
is this like a directory,
or is it the name
of a new volume
that Docker should
create for us?
And so unless it looks very
clearly like a
path of some sort,
I assumes that it's something
new that should be created.
And so I have to make this look
more like a path. So
Docker doesn't do that.
So I should say something
like that, like,
look at this
directory or maybe I
can have an absolute path.
Now I'd bet to run that, and I
can draw under slash share,
and I can see that I have
that file TXT, right?
So if I'm outside
of my container,
it's in the Lecture
one directory.
If I'm inside my container,
it's the share directory, right?
I can see what is there.
I could do other things, right?
I could echo like by
to file two t XT.
Then if I exit this, I would
be able to see that outside.
So I can run that command
inside a container just
like I did outside,
and let me run that word outut.
I guess there's not
quite the same number
of them as before.
But I can go through
here and see some
interesting things.
One of the interesting
things I see is that
the root file system
is not associated
with a partitions SDA one
or something like that.
It's actually this
overlay file system.
And what this is actually
doing is it's taking
some directories d by
Host virtual machine and
kind of stitching
them together and
giving me a file system
inside of here, right?
I have a Pc file
system like before.
I have a tip file
Lots of stuff in here.
Maybe what I might
do is I might wrap for share.
And what I could see
is that there was
an EXT four file system in
a directory there the host
that was mapped to slash
share here, right?
So I have a different view of
all these different
file systems from
inside the container
from outside, right?
You could stitch
together a bunch of
file systems in different
ways to make a unified tree.
That started one way
on my virtual machine.
It started a different way on
my container because the
container shouldn't see
the same things or
as many things as I
see on my virtual
machine in general.
Oh, right, cool.
Any questions about
that volume share that I
did? Yeah, right here.
Yeah, yeah. Why is it EXT four?
Well, when I read this, I said
that this directory
should show up as share.
And this directory of
my virtual machine was
part of an EXT four
file system, right?
That's why it's showing
up as EXT four bedside.
So if I kind of do work inside,
it'll show up show up there.
Does that make sense?
Yeah. Yeah. Thank you
for clarifying that.
Yeah, there are
questions people have.
All right. Cool.
So, the other thing
I want to show you
is just how we
would do our work later, right?
Be we have some upcoming
projects where we have
Jupiter lab running inside
of a notebook and
that's where you're
going to do your work.
And I actually have
something that builds that.
I guess I'm running
it on Port 300.
Let me just build this again.
And R that demo.
T, that'll start
up Jupiter inside.
And then there's some more
things I have to do here.
Well, the detached mode.
One of the things I
have to do is I have to
do the port mapping like before.
And so maybe for the port
mapping, I'll do 127001.
And just to keep things simple,
I'll keep it the same,
300 inside, 300 outside.
And what you'll do
is that we'll try
to set up the SSH
tunnel like before,
so I can be working
at this Jupiter lab.
But I'm also going to
have one directory
where I have all of my work,
because even though you're
working at a container,
you probably want some
things outside of
the container so
you can you know,
push that toe for your project
submission later, right?
And so I have to
do a volume map,
to say for Lecture
one. And inside.
I'd maybe say that's
under like B for
notebooks. I'm going
to run that thing.
And then I have to
set up my SSH tunnel.
And I'm to do that.
It's 300 on my virtual machine.
I'd have to do psdo to
use port 300 for my MAC.
I'm to use 3,000 there.
But I'll set up that SSH
tunnel like we've done before.
And then what I should
be able to do is I
should be able to come
over here and row
a local host 3,000 on
my laptop that I'll
forward to 300 on the Va,
which will further forward to
300 inside the virtual machine.
And what I can see here now is
that I have this
notebook directory here,
same files actually
that we had before.
And this is where I
would do my work, right?
I might call this
like I don't know,
I might call this like project.
Maybe I'll just call it like a
demo or something like that,
and whatever. I'll to save that.
And then, you know,
there's a bunch of
other files here,
and you have to be a
little bit careful.
I know what to
share, what's not,
because if I created my file
somewhere else so that I
killed this container,
I would lose my work,
but whatever I save
inside of this will
be saved outside because
I mapped it, right?
Somebody come over here. And one
of the things I could see
is that under Lecture one,
that file is there, I'm
on my virtual machine,
but I could see a
file that was created
by Jupiter inside the
container, right?
And so even if I
kill that container,
somebody kill it, that
if I come back here,
it should be dead, right?
I still have my file, right?
Anything inside of notebook?
Let me just show you
how I ran it again.
Anything inside of notebook
is still visible
inside of Lecture one.
It would save anything I created
elsewhere inside of
that container is gone.
So I just want you to understand
it a bit so that you don't have
a unfortunate accident where
you lose some work, right?
It double check this, right?
Don't do like a ton of like
a ton of work on the
project at the end,
like realize that
you lost something.
Alright. So what
questions people have
about volume mois
or port mappings?
All right. Cool. So I
am to actually just
have that I'm going to
have it up and
running again because
I'll need it for
some upcoming demos.
Let me just make sure
this is still running.
There we go. Okay, great.
I'll just leave that
there for later.
All right. So that was
file system stuff.
Let's learn now about
the format of files that we
might put inside
of a file system.
Alright, so I have a few
different goals here.
What I'm talking
about a file format,
there's a lot of words or kind
of aspects of what
I could talk about,
I could talk about the
orientation of the file,
how we encode data,
whether or not it's compressed,
how it's compressed.
Does the file give us
a schema that describes
the types of her columns.
So when we learn that,
we learn a new type,
which is Park, and we
want to learn how to
use write code that
works with Park.
You know, for kind
of trivial t things,
I use CSV files.
But if I'm doing
anything kind of,
like serious with bigger data
I like very organized because
I have lots of files,
like Park would be the go to
thing I would use, right?
In that case, maybe
somebody gave BCSVs.
Number one thing I'll do is
I'll just travert it to Parke.
I'll use Parke for everything,
and that will save
a lot of problems.
So I want you to
do that as well.
We're going to talk
about different kinds of
workloads that are
accessing these files.
There's transaction processing
and analytics processing.
We want to be able to
distinguish those and
choose the right tools
for the right job.
And then finally,
a lot of you are going
to go off some day
and have jobs where you're
writing what we
call ETL pipelines,
extract, transform and load.
Different kinds of systems are
good for different things.
And so often we're
moving our data
from one system to another.
For a particular purpose, right?
And so a lot of data
engineering types
are going to be doing
work like that,
we're going to motivate
that today. All right.
So I may take a look here.
There's a couple of
different approaches to
how we can use a
file system, right?
So here's a local file system.
It's story it's stated
some kind of block device,
or maybe it's like a
docker file system,
maybe stored a different
file system, whatever.
There's a bunch of
file systems there.
One approach is that we
could directly write files
ourself and put them in uh put
our data directly to file.
The other thing that you might
do that we're going
to be talking about
more pretty soon is you might
have some kind of database.
We go to put our data
in the database,
that database might write
its data into a file,
and then the file
system might write
that file file data into
a block device, right?
So there's going to be trade
offs between these and we
want to understand, what
should we do one approach,
or what should we do
the other approach?
In both cases, right?
Whether we're using a file
directly or there's a database,
there are decisions
that are made
about the format of that file.
Okay. So the way I've
talked about this,
I've to introduce Park files,
and I'm go to contrast
them with CSV files.
And I've talked about four ways
that they do things differently.
And so the first thing I'm to
talk about is orientation.
CSV files are oriented,
and Park files are
column oriented. Okay.
So what we learned
about block device
is we learned that we
have to transfer data,
the unit of blocks,
which is probably
at least 512 bytes,
maybe bigger, maybe a
couple of kilobytes.
And so we talked last time about
this text based dataset
here that has all these
weather stations,
and I highlighted
different trollers
the different blocks.
Those are 512 bytes of data.
And what we ought to do is
we ought to figure out,
well, how can we
efficiently access it?
Sometimes we want to access
all the data in a row.
all the data in a column.
So if I have this text
file like this right here,
It's good if I just
want to access one row,
because then I would only have
to access one block of data.
If I wanted to
access one column,
that's actually very
unfortunate because
that column is spread across
a bunch of different blocks.
I have to read all
three blocks of data,
even though I don't
care what is in most of
those three blocks. Right?
I'm ignoring all the columns,
but I still have to read
it all from disc, right?
So depending on my
access pattern,
this format might be
good or it might be bad.
I tip some naves to
these access patterns,
and the naves I may give them
are transactions processing
and Adalytics processing.
In this same space,
transactions has
another meeting that
we we'll be learning
about soon, so we
hold off on that.
But for the context of that,
transaction processing
means that I'm really kind
of working with rows, right?
Maybe I'm adding rows or
reading rows or
things like that.
A few rows at a time, doing
lots of operations like that.
Analytics is
analytics processing
is where I may be
on this big table,
and I choose specific columns
that I do some
analysis over them.
Maybe I want to get like
the average in a
column, for example.
What we're doing
analytics, we're often
look at whole columns of data.
So these are different
access patterns
you're going to see.
And so depending on how
we lay out our data,
it might be faster for
either transactions
processing or
analytics processing.
So for example, here,
I have a seple table.
Columns one, two, three,
Columns one and
two have numbers,
and Column three has
some letters in it.
Even though it looks
too dimensional,
when it throws in a file,
it's one dimensional, right?
I just have different
offsets for different bytes.
And sometimes show
how I can write
a row oriented file or
a column Oriented file.
In the row oriented file,
I have rows together.
So 15 A, 15 A goes together.
And the column Oriented file,
I took a whole column 1234,
and I put that consecutive
within that file.
Alright, so let's say I have
a transactional access pattern.
That means I'm accessing
whole rows at a time.
If I have a transactional
access pattern,
it will be fast to use
the row oriented file
because all the data in
the row is going to be
right next to each other
in the same block, right?
But if I have a transactional
access pattern and I have
a column oriented file,
that's actually terrible.
If I want to read the first row,
I have to pull a little bit
of data from different places.
I'm going to have
to touch a lot of
different blocks to be
able to access that one row.
So to pause if people
have any questions,
Is it making sense like
why we care about,
what is the access pattern
what file format we have?
Here. Related to something
like that cache x. Yeah,
it could be you're say, well,
you're making a reference
to C or maybe C plus plus.
And those language, we often
care more about memory layout.
But another language we
might care about
memory layout too,
by Python to, I might
care about memory layout.
And so absolutely, when
we have cache lines,
that's a very similar problem.
We saw that, we would create
these numpy matrices,
and we saw that there
was one way to get
basically a row oriented matrix
or column oriented matrix.
And then depending on if I'm
adding all the
numbers in a column,
it might be faster or slower.
So absolutely, it's
just like that.
It's even more
important now though,
because when I'm talking
about cah lines,
We're talking about
like 64 bytes.
You know, I I read 64 bytes
extra from something that
fast like Rb, who cares?
Here, if I want to access
a small piece of data,
I have to access like 512 bytes
for something that's slow.
That's a big deal, right?
So it is like being cash aware.
Same principles, but now
it's much higher stakes.
Absolutely. Great analogy.
Yeah, O questions people have we
comparisons or points.
Yeah, right here.
Buts. X, that's a
really best point.
I guess you're saying,
like, you know,
I'm giving an example of, like,
small pieces of data,
but you're saying,
well, I mean, who knows?
Maybe I could even like an
image or something in a cell.
I can have a table of images.
And in that case, like
a single cell would
spat across many
different blocks, right?
And in that case,
kind of I have to do
the same axises in either case.
And I agree with that, right?
I think that if you
have single values that
are very large and there
are a bunch of blocks,
then then it starts to
become less important,
which format you have, right?
But we often have a mix, right?
We might have some
very small values like
editors or big
values like images.
I agree though, right,
if it's very large,
that this becomes not very
important. Excellent point.
Yeah, there are other
points or ideas
people have. All right.
Cool. Let's do the opposite,
right? So this right?
I have the two file formats,
the two files aren't changing.
All I'm changing
now is I'm doing
a different type
of access to it.
So now I have an
analytics access pattern.
I'm trying to add up all
the numbers at a column.
In that case, if I'm
doing analytics,
I would like to have a
column oriented file because
all those numbers
are consecutive and,
you know, one block or
maybe a few blocks.
If I'm trying to do analytics
at a row oriented file,
that's actually pretty
terrible, right?
B I basically to
touch all the blocks.
CSVs are oriented?
Park files are column
oriented, right?
So people use CSVs all the
time for analytics, and
that's terrible, right?
It's a terrible
format for analytics.
We want column oriented
data for analytics.
Park files give you that.
That's already a
good reason to use
Park instead of CSV files
if you're analyzing a data
set of any significant size.
Okay. What are some
other differences?
The differences? How
do we encode suf?
Is it just plain text?
Are we using kind of bits
and bytes a little bit
more intelligently in some
kind of binary formats?
So let's have an example
of a number up here here.
I have a pretty large number.
I could store it as a string.
In CSV files, everything is
represented as a string,
or I could store
it as a park type.
But if it's a park type,
I'd have to choose
something like a 64 at 32.
In this case, how long is
a string or how many digits
is it it's ten characters?
It would take ten
bytes to represent
that number at a CSV
file at a park file,
it would be eight
bytes if it was at
64 and four bytes
if it was at 32.
Now, you could make the case
that some numbers might
be more efficient
as strings, right?
So if I had a number
like 12, you know,
the parte types would
be the same size,
the string would
only be two bytes.
But in that case,
we still want to have
a binary format.
There's a binary
format that's better,
and that would be something
like protocol buffers.
Protocol buffers have this
variable length in toting.
It's I can take a number
like 12 and actually
get it down to just one byte.
Right? So what I want
to show here is that
when we have things
that are not text,
text based formats are
actually terrible, right?
Binary formats are much better
for representing numbers.
That'll be much faster
and more compact, right?
Maybe, maybe we use Park
as our binary format.
Maybe we use protocol buffers
But Bideary is generally
more efficient.
It's a little harder
to use, right?
Because if I have a CSV file,
I can just open a text
editor understand it.
If I have a binary file,
it's like, maybe, like,
protocol buffers or it's
Park files, you know,
I have to have some extra
tool to help me read it.
But it's faster.
Alright, let's talk
about compression.
CSV files have no compression.
Part files do have compression.
They different compression
options the default.
One is something called Snappy.
Let me just explain the
idea of compression, right?
A lot of things people
do or say or or
put in files has
repetition to it.
And if you want to
be more concise,
you should avoid
repeating yourself.
Okay. And so if I
have a dataset that's
very repetitive and find a
way to avoid that repetition,
then I can compress it a lot.
I could shrink it down a lot.
So let me give you an
example of a dataset.
So let's have a dataset
where let's say it's
like all the buildings
on campus, right?
And at every building,
there's a street address for it.
Of course, that'll be a
very repetitive dataset
because I mean, for one,
there's going to be
this substring often,
like Street in Madison Wiscos,
that'll appear very often.
Maybe I have 12 Ted
West Add Street,
Madison Wisconsin, 12 oh
two West Johnson Street,
Madison, Wisconsin.
I might have a lot
of repetition there.
So the idea of
compression is that,
as we're going through here,
rather than repeating it,
if we kind of notice like, Oh,
there's some texts
that appeared earlier,
We could have a
pointer back to it.
We could say, it's
that text, refer back.
It's the same thing that
I saw earlier, right?
And so To compress
a file like this,
you have to have algorithms that
could search for repetition,
find it, and how hard they
search for repetition.
If I have, like a gigabyte file,
how far back to
earlier of the file?
Do I look to find repetition?
That's a challenging thing.
Algorithms,
compression algorithms have
different approaches, right?
So Snappy is not
trying to have the best
possible compression.
I try to strike it down
the most possible.
It is trying to process
the data very quickly.
You'll have to decide
in different cases
what typ of
compression you want.
If you're trying to write a
bunch of data frequently,
then you might be
able to do that fast.
If you kind of just
write your data what,
and then you have it as a
backup for a year later,
you probably are
willing to spend
a little more time to
get a smaller file.
Snappy is optimized
for that first case.
There are some disadvantages
of compression.
Compression is if I just
have like one big
file, I write it what?
If I have a file, I'm making
changes to a fit it
often is a problem.
So, for example, if I
wanted to come through here
and I wanted to
edit this address,
I can't just edit the first
address in isolation,
because if I change
it here, that I would
accidentally change
something that's
not supposed to be changed.
When we have compression,
one of the downsides
is is that if I want to
make a small change,
I actually have to end up
rewriting a lot of data, right?
So compression is
t kind great for
big files that you write
what so that they
don't change again.
Do people have any questions
about compression?
Alright. Cool. I want to
combine compression
with the idea
of column versus
row oriented data.
So compression
algorithms like Snappy,
they often work in blocks.
So by default, Snappy looks
at 32 kilobyte blocks.
That means if there
was some repetition
that was, like, you know,
the same string
appeared, let's say,
like 100 kilobytes ago,
I won't realize it.
I'll only look for repetition
of the last 32 kilobytes.
And so I may imagine here
that I have my data.
I could have a row oriented
file or column oriented file,
and then I want to
compress them both.
I wonder which one is dt
to be more compressible.
Which one can we
strike down more?
Does anybody want to make
an argument that one or
the other is better
for compression?
Yeah, right here. Of ent
you'll see similar
values. Excellent.
Cool oriented is probably
better because we have
similar values and
close proximity.
If I look at all the
values in the column,
those values probably
more similar to each
other than values and
separate columns.
Like you can imagine some
kind of weird taste,
but that's generally
what we would expect.
So for here example,
when we have all the data in
that last column of
strays, we have AB AV.
I can find some
repetition there.
But if I have that spread out
in a row oriented format,
then those repeated
values are too far apart,
and we might not actually see it
because we have this
block wise compression.
All right. The last thing
that might distinguish
different file types is whether
or not we have a schema.
Askema tells you explicitly,
these are my columns,
and this is the type
of data in my column.
So aschema a fatsy word
for a simple idea.
What are the types
of my columns?
Okay. And so in
some files, right?
Like CSV files, that's
inferred, right?
In a CSV, everything
is a string.
So you kind of have to
guess what the types are.
And so there's a
couple of ways, right?
What is that when
I read the CSV,
I can actually
manually say, right?
I could write this big
dictionary by head and say,
like, column, what is a
string, column to is a ze?
That's a little bit
annoying, right?
I could do that.
That would make it
faster for sure to read it.
Or I could just say
data type equals no,
then it will automatically
infer. That's kind of slow.
Sometimes that ess rug,
actually, so that's not great.
Park files explicitly
say what the Schema is,
and that makes it very
fast to load, right?
When I kind of first
open a Park file,
it doesn't have to
read all the values
of the Jets, what they are.
It knows immediately
what they are.
So' will be much faster
to read a Park file.
Alright, so hopefully I've
sold you on park files.
Do you have any questions
about different file formats,
or these different
characteristics
that differ between them.
All right, so let's head over
here. Let's do some demos.
Let's get our hands dirty
with some park files.
And fortunately, I still have
this notebook up and
running from before.
And I'll just use that as
a place to do my work.
Okay. And so for
my lecture sips,
I actually have a
data set over here,
which is a Zip CSV file.
I'll just copy both
of these lines.
And I will just download
that as a first step.
Remember, if I put
an exclamation mark
in front of a light,
it does a shell command
instead of a Python command.
I'll zip it.
Maybe I'll just
try it this cause
I if I rerun my notebook,
I don't want it to
redo that each time.
I already have the data,
and then I could say
L LAH start zip.
Actually, maybe I'll
just do this star.
All right. So I downloaded
this compressed file,
which was 21 gigabytes.
I extracted it to a CSV,
and now it's 167 gigabytes.
This is clearly highly
compressible data, right?
Because it struck down so much.
And then I want to find
different ways to use
this data, right?
And I may use Pi
arrow like before.
I may import Pi arrow
as PA. Have you
ever we saw Pyro before
and with CSPs, in
particular, right?
Before what we saw is that
Padns is really slow at
read CSV files because
it doesn't have
this kind of column
formatted analysis.
We saw that read CSV and
Pierro is much faster,
but I I use that as
a baseline, right?
So kind of the fast
case we saw before
Pro with CSV is the baseline,
Obviously we can get even faster
than that by using P K files.
Okay, so what I do is I report
some other stuff as well.
I have to port Pierrot CSV,
and I port Pierrot pK.
Alright, cool. And so
what I'll do first
is they'll say table
equals table equals
Pi arrows read CSV,
then I'll just read
this thing, right?
Alright. So I will do that.
That's going to take a while.
I just want to type it. One of
the ways I could type it is with
these basically magic
adaptations up here.
And so I will say I want
to type that thing.
I'm to type it.
Alright, that took a
couple seconds, right?
It would have taken a lot
longer if I had used pad this.
But still, this is
like a worst case.
We're going to try
to beat this, right?
So what I want to do now is I
want to see what happens if I
be it into a Park file, right?
So what I may do
now is I may say
Pi arrow park right table.
And I want to write it out
to maybe I'll just frill,
like the same thing,
but dot park dot
park K. All right.
And then I want to write out
this table specifically, right?
So literally, it's like, one
of the first things I'll do.
If somebody gives me
a big nasty CSV file.
I'll write a couple
of lines like this,
and I have park files, and I'll
never touch the CSV again.
I'll only use that Park file.
And so what I may do is I
may try to read that it,
I may say Piero dot
p dot red table.
And I pass that sad.
And, I might run out
of memory actually.
I don't think I
have space to have
two tables of memory
at the same time.
And so I'm just going
to say t equals nod.
That will free up
some memory for me.
This will only
reference the table,
and this should have enough
memory to actually rod oops,
and I will run it like that.
And that should be faster.
And indeed it is, right?
Atally normally, I see kind
of a bigger difference there.
But anyway, it's still faster.
So it's 2.7 seconds.
This is 2 seconds.
The other interesting thing
here is by doing the timing.
The wall clock time is like
the time we're used to.
I look a to watch and
see what's happening.
But I see they have
some other statistics
up here as well.
And so one of the things is
total time versus wall
clock time, right.
So wall clock time is how
much time I saw passing by.
Total time is actually CPU time.
And so I see that not
only was it taking this
amount of time to do the CSV,
but it was basically using
two CPU cores during
that whole time, right?
So it was using a
lot of resources.
It will break this down into
user user time means like
the time running
directly in my program.
And system time means that
the operating system is
working on my behalf, right?
But the point here is
that it had to use
two CPUs basically constantly
for this whole time.
This one down here,
I guess it was able
to do it with, like,
you know, Mostly one
CPU utilized for a
shorter time, right?
So it was less time and less
re compute resources
used during that time.
Alright. Cool. So that's
already one benefit there.
I try to show
different as, right?
I want to show I want to
show the coding for
both of these, right?
It's the way I'll do
that, I'll just open them
up directly as a file, right?
I'm open up this one right
here. I'll open that
As F and I may actually
read it as a binary file,
even though it contains texts,
and I may print off f read 100.
I want to see the
first hundred bytes.
This is text. It's something
I could understand and read.
If I do that to the Park file,
Well, now I actually
see that it's binary.
I can just peek inside and see.
I have to use a tool
to access the data.
But other thing I can do
is when I'm reading
the CSV file,
I can really just like
read the whole thing.
That's my only option. When
I'm reading a Parque table,
I can actually read a subset
of the columns, right?
So I can say columns,
equals, and maybe I'll just
read a couple of these.
I'll get this kind of
identifier column,
and maybe I'll get
like the county code,
county code like that.
Let's t this as well.
All right, sob time that.
And I may call this table too
because it only has like
a subset of the stuff.
And we see that
this is way faster,
right? So often, right?
What is even in
that table, right?
If I kind of look at look
at that full table, it's
like a bunch of stuff.
And if I do analysis
at any given time,
I probably don't care
about a majority
of that stuff, right?
So ibn it's a
calibraratd format,
I can very quickly read
just the things I want.
With the CSP, there's no way
to do that because while,
it still has to read
all the data, right?
Alright, so we see the
difference in toting.
We've seen that the
Skiba dance is faster
because we don't have to ad
first Skiba when I
read the Part A.
We've seen that the
calibrated format is helping.
Let's look briefly
at the pressure.
That will be the
last thing I do.
And so I say Ti good.
At IA say Pi arrow p dot.
How did I do it before?
I did like a writ table.
IB write this T. ABA
call this. Snappy par.
I say that the compress
should equal snappy.
All right, let's do that.
I will take a moment,
and then I do another one,
which will be G ZIP.
GSP is willing to go a little
slower in order to get
a smaller file, right?
So the first one took 1.5
seconds, wall clock time.
This one took over double that.
But if I do my L L AH and
look at different Park files,
Then what do I see, right?
The snappy one is 16 megabytes.
The G ZP one is 13 gigabytes.
Am I willing to spend twice as
long to get a slightly
smaller file?
Maybe, it really depends on
how often I have
to do this, right?
And of course, let's
compare this to LAH.
I want to look at
my CSV file, right?
All of these are
way better than 167
megabytes there, right?
So Park is the way to go.
If you're doing any kind
of data analytic stuff,
take your CSVs, get it there,
then forget the CSVs even exist.
I'll leave out that thought.
Feel free to come up and chat
if you have any questions.