Great to see
everybody here today.
I'm really excited to start
a new semester with you all.
How is the volume in the back?
It sounds a little echoy for me.
Is the volume good in
the back? It's bad.
Is it should it be
louder or quieter?
Louder. Okay. And how
is that in the back?
Does thumbs down mean
quieter or it's bad.
It's led. It's muffled.
Hm. Yeah. So people are
saying it's muffled.
Oh, is that better?
How is that? Is it
good in the back?
Okay, I'm seeing a few
people and nod their head.
Yes. So, that's fantastic.
So welcome to Intro to
Big Data Systems, 544.
Really excited to have you
all here this semester.
I've taught a bunch of courses
here at Wisconsin now,
and I think this is a favorite
my favorite thing
that I've taught.
I'm going to do a
few things today.
We're going to do some
introductions of myself, of,
of the course, try to
understand the logistics,
the tools, the resources
available to us.
And then a time permitting,
we're going to jump into
some actual resources
related to computing.
When we're working with systems,
we're trying to figure
out how to manage
resources in an efficient way.
And then finally, at the end,
we might talk briefly about
how we deploy systems.
So, my name is Tyler
Carraza Harder.
You can just call me Tyler.
I use mail pronouns.
I have my e mail up
there on the slide,
so feel free to drop me an e
mail if you want
to get in touch.
I've spent most of
my career teaching,
but I have spent some
time in industry.
I was at Microsoft for a
while working in SQL Server.
I've done various
collaborations and internships.
Most recently, I've
been working with
a company Bow plan on some
data engineering tooling.
I'm also really big
into Open source.
The Open Source project I'm most
involved in is
called Open Lambda.
Kind of similar to
Amazon's AWS Lambda.
Maybe some of you have run
across it or maybe not.
But basically, it's a way to run
small Python functions in
an isolated environment in
response to vari SE bents.
So sometimes students help
out with those projects.
So if your interest
in open source
or or servlus computing,
you know, drop me a note,
and we can always chat
about it further.
So I want to get
a quick sense of
who is in the room right now.
Do we have any freshmen or
sophomores in the room?
So like, maybe like two,
how many juniors are here?
And seniors. So pretty
heavy on seniors.
We have many grad students.
So a few and not as many
as in the first thing.
So we kind of have
a good spread.
I think this is really good for
people at a variety of levels.
I do want to point
out for the graduate
students that there's
another course,
which is just big data systems,
not enter the big data systems,
and they're more
focused on research
around big data systems.
How can you build new big data
systems, things like that?
Whereas we're really
focused on kind of
hands on experience
with these systems.
There's a couple of
pathways into this course.
You could take 320 and or 400.
How many of you have
taken both of those?
Okay, just a few, how many
are coming from the 320 side,
and then the 400 side.
So pretty split. Last time
I taught it was mostly
from the 400 sides.
It's good to see kind
of people coming
through various paths.
What about any of these other
courses that are related?
The operating system course,
database course or
networking course.
Is anybody taken any of
those handful of you.
All I will say there
is there's a lot of
overlap between the first third
of this course and there,
so don't get complacent, right?
It's trying to get harder
if you've taken those,
but the first part of the
semester might be a little
easier if you have some
of that other experience.
So I want to just survey
people so I have
actual date on this.
So please do fill out this form.
And and then so I just
know who you are and
what your background is.
And that'd be a huge help to me.
And it's worth, you
know, some small amount
of extra credit if you do it.
Here's a picture of
the various courses
that are related to this one.
U We have a couple
majors related.
One is data science, and
the data science majors
actually take a bunch
of ventral courses,
but most relevant to us
is the Python tracks.
That's 22320, and then
you could take this
course right here.
And having previously
taught 320,
I really built this course
with the 320 student in mind.
I thought about, what is
their level of
python experience?
All of that. This
is designed for
students coming out of 320.
There's also a path over here.
All the computer science
students take 200300400,
and that's in Java, and
that's also a path
do this course,
but you know, you've
had three CS courses.
I'm not going to
teach you Python.
I'm expecting you'll just try
to figure it out as you go.
Some ways you could
do that is you
could read this
stink Python book,
which is pretty
introductory to Python.
This fluent Python book is
a more advanced python
book, which is excellent.
I've learned quite a
bit from it myself.
I think, regardless
of your python level,
you probably learn something
if you pick it up.
Other courses related
to this is that
CS students take the
systems Track 252, 354,
that's definitely relevant
to what we're doing,
but it's not a prerequisite
because again,
this course is really
designed to be accessible to
data science majors who are not
taking some of those
other CS courses.
Some universities with a
big data science course
might have prerequisites like
operating systems or
databases or not working.
That kind of makes sense from
the perspective of the content,
but then it makes
the course not accessible
to that many people,
and there's a lot of
things here that you can
learn quickly and
directly apply.
And so I'm going to spend
about a third of the semester I
try just the bare minimum of
those different areas
so we can get into
big data systems without
having to go take a
whole another course.
I'm just trying to try switching
the mic quick because
I don't know,
if it still just kind of
sounds bad to me up here.
Let me see if the
other mic is better.
Is that any better? Can
people hear me well?
Okay, I see some happy faces.
So, I visit all my
classrooms before I teach,
and I don't remember it sounding
that horrible last time.
So hopefully, it was just
the mic, and we're good now.
But now I hear it crinkling
ale bit again. All right.
Fingers crossed. Great. So
those are the other courses.
Let me talk briefly
about what our systems,
since we're learning
about big data systems.
As a programmer, the's different
kinds of code you might write.
In one case, maybe
you're given some question
that you have to answer,
and you go off and
write some code to
analyze some dataset
and get that answer,
maybe it runs once,
or maybe if the answer
keeps changing,
there's new data,
maybe it runs on
some schedule. That's
analysis code.
Maybe you make some
plots from doing that.
Other kinds of code people like
to write as application code.
Right now I'm using
an application
called keynote for
showing you these slides,
and it will kind of run as long
as I'm using it, and
I'll close it out.
And I might use it many times.
Any kind of website is backed
by some application, right?
It's running there and
serving up web pages to you.
And so some people prefer
that kind of programming.
You know, you all are probably
in the stage of trying to
figure out what kind of
programming you like to do.
And I'd say a third
major category
of programming is
systems programming.
When I'm building
a website, right?
I'm serving up web
pages to people.
The content of those web
pages exist somewhere,
and the way it exists
is as bits on,
say, a hard driver, and SSD.
And if I'm programming
a website,
I don't want to have
to worry about bits or
ones and zeros.
What a pain, right?
And the reason I
don't have to is
because as my
application is running,
it's using a file system.
That file system shows me files,
and that file system is kind
of in charge of worrying
about these ones and zeros that
are start on a hard
drive somewhere.
So when we're talking
about systems,
we're talking about software
that's kind of playing
a supporting role.
It's managing hardware and
making that hardware easier
to use for people
writing analysis
code or applications code.
So this is going to
be super important
to you regardless
what you go into.
Some of you might go
build new systems,
but even if not, you're
always going to be
interacting with systems.
And if you know how
those systems work,
you can get better
performance out of them.
And you can also anticipate
weird things that can happen
different failure
scenarios where you
might lose data or
things like that
because you know what
these systems are
guarantee you and under
what circumstances they
break down, right?
So we want to learn
how systems work.
There are lots of systems,
an operating system,
which kind of the composed
of many subsystems
running on my laptop right now.
Those are not big data systems.
So what are big data systems?
Maybe it's a little
bit hard to define.
But in my mind,
what I imagine is that often
we're working with
some data set,
either for an
application or analysis,
and that data might keep
growing and growing.
And what do we do as
that keep strawing?
One thing you can do is you can
try to write more
efficient code, right?
Maybe you go take 577 and
learn about algorithms and
complexity and write algorithms
with a better complexity class,
or maybe you just learn
in general about how
to streamline things
and avoid waste.
What we're really interested
in is the other case where
maybe you kind of played that
out as far as it will go.
And we're to the
point of we need
more resources or
better resources.
So I think our main focus of
those course is when we
have datasets that it's
not very practical
to just kind of
analyze it or work with
it on one computer.
Maybe we need a
cluster of computers
working together to
work with that data,
or maybe you need some kind
of specialized hardware.
Like a lot of people
are using GPUs now,
originally built for graphics,
but very useful for a
lot of analysis and
machine learning and other
things in that space,
right, maybe you need
some specialized hardware
for dealing with your problem.
So what are you going
to learn this semester?
A few things.
If you're lucky, maybe someday
you'll be working somewhere
where somebody else
deploys these big data systems
for you and you just use them.
But I think a lot
of us are going to
go on and have to deploy
these things ourselves.
We have to have to
figure out how to get
it running on
computer somewhere.
That's often very challenging.
It comes with troubleshooting
skills that we
need to learn to get these
things up up and running.
When the ones are
up and running,
we want to figure out how to get
data on them so we can
actually start using them.
I want you to be able
to efficiently analyze
large datasets on these various
systems and train machine
learning models from them.
When we're doing all
this, we're using
various computing resources.
I want to be able
to measure that
and optimize it and improve it.
And then finally,
the last couple of
weeks of the semester,
we're going to look at various
Cloud services, right?
More and more of this work
is moving to the Cloud.
And that's just going
to be a critical skill
for all of you in your careers,
or at least the vast
majority of you.
That's the what the
semester looks like.
Those are the goals.
Hopefully that
aligns with your interests.
Today, we have just a
few narrower goals.
I want you to just remember
the logistics and
policies of the course.
I want you to be
able to describe
four major categories
of hardware resources.
I want you to be able
to compare and contrast
a scale up approach versus
a scale out approach.
And then finally, where I spend
a little bit time going a little
deeper on what actually
happens when we run our code?
How do we get code
in a language like
Python or Java to run on a CPU?
Okay. So first, let's
talk about some
of the tools and
websites we have.
There's three main websites
that we'll be using.
I'm just trying to pop
over the first one.
This is the most important one
because it links to
everything else.
This is a public facing website.
I like to have
public facing stuff
because and it's
easier for you to
access it later on or for
people to sit in or do whatever.
This will be the
main place to go.
It has links to everything else
you need like the syllabus.
On each day, we can
see what is there.
So you can see that today,
your reading the syllabus.
Please go read that. I have
the slides from today.
There's some flash cards
I'm going to come back to.
Later, I plan to post
a lecture recording
on here as well.
You know, I think, by the way,
I'm recording right
now, in case,
I it matters to anybody.
I encourage you to
still ask questions,
even though it's recorded, but
everybody can make
their own decision.
In general, I just record,
and then I post it.
Sometimes there's
technical difficulties,
and then while
there's no recording,
I'm not trying to redo a
lecture for the sake of that,
but I see no problem in just
posting a recording if I
have it available to me.
I generally plan to do that.
So all that stuff there, right?
You should take a look at
the core schedule, you
should read the syllabus.
There's a tab for
getting help, right?
There's lots of
different options,
Async, or synchronous,
however you like.
P help when you need it.
There's various
resources over here,
like an office hour schedule.
And then all the
other tools that
you need to care about
for this course.
That's the main site that
you need to remember.
What else do we have?
We have a Canvas.
You know, Some people love
Canvas and they use
it for everything.
I don't love Canvas, but there's
a few things that does nicely,
so I will do all the
announcements there,
so you'll never
get another e mail
from me. You're going
to find it here.
Make sure you turn on
your announcements
or your e mail reminder,
so you don't mess a Canvas
announcement, please.
I use it for weekly quizzes.
So there's going
to be a quiz due
next Wednesday on the
content of this week.
I use it for grading summaries.
So, there's a few
things that what we'll
use on Canvas. What
else do we have?
We have this repository
here, which is on Git Hub.
And how many of you have
used Git Hub before?
Fantastic. A lot of you.
I often have some stuff here.
The kinds of things I do here is
I post project description.
So here's P one.
You know, I'm kind of coming
from this background of,
like, everything's open source.
You don't have to
have everything
polished before it's done.
So you can see, what I'm
thinking about for the project,
but it's not ready yet.
So don't do it because
it might change
until that notice goes away,
and I tell you, hey,
go ahead and start.
But yeah, that stuff is there,
kind of general project
policies, some testing stuff.
I like to do a lot of
examples during lecture,
and so I might be
posting those examples
to the Git repository
when I've done as well.
This might actually
change because I'm
looking at moving towards
Gitlab this semester.
Kind of strangely,
GitHub has trouble
scaling when you start to
have hundreds of students,
and it does some
weird things with
respect to how they
manage rosters.
So, you know, Git
Lab looks like they
actually do it better even
though Git Lab is less known.
Has anybody use Git Lab before?
A few of you. So by the
end, all of you will.
So I guess that's
another thing we get to
learn this semester.
Looks like even though
they're not as famous,
they kind of do things
a little bit better.
So we're going to be
transitioning, you know, soon.
Oh, Zoom office hours are
also on on that on Canvas.
You can find that
there. Some other tools
that we have is top hat.
How many of you
have used top hat
before? Fantastic, right?
So I'm not going to
make top hat required.
It's going to be
for extra credit,
some small amount of
extra credit that will
saturate at 4% of your grade.
So you can totally get an
A and never do a top hat,
but I think it's
a small incentive to
come here to lecture.
I don't care if you do it in
this lecture or my
morning lecture,
but you're not allowed
to do it from home.
Sometimes I just have problems
with actually
dozens of students.
They'll just like watch it and
they click some random thing to
make it look like they're doing
something when they're
not doing anything.
So anyway, it's allowed
as long as you're
in person at one
of the locations,
but I don't care which one.
And again, it's
just extra credit,
so don't stress about it, to
keep people a little
bit more engaged.
Were you use Pizza. How many
of you have used Pizza before?
Fantastic. Piazza rules
vary from course to course,
and responsive how
responsive people
are, stuff like that.
Our goal is to respond to
every post within 24 hours,
regardless of whether
it's on the weekend.
I think maybe, like,
Thanksgiving break
might be a little bit different.
We won't check as often.
A lot of courses say
no code on piazza.
Course if somebody
took the whole project
and dumped it on
Piazza and said,
you know, what's
wrong with it, then
other people are
going to copy that.
So that's not allowed.
But, you know,
as long as it's five
lines of code or less,
I think it's sometimes
be helpful to
ask a question in the
context of actual code.
So go for that if
that helps you.
Piazza, I think is for
questions of general interest.
There's like a private
post on Piazza,
but we're not going to really
use that this semester.
If you have an
individual question
related to just you or
you and your team member,
we're going to do
e mail for that.
So what I might be doing
soon is I'm may be assigning
each of you a
primary TA contact.
And so if you have an
individual question,
that's the person
you're going to e mail.
Their expectation is
that they should get
back to you within
two business days.
If they don't,
please don't send me
a separate e mail on
that same thread,
just CC me, and then I
will kind of nudge them or
maybe check in with them.
Maybe they have
something going on that
they can't keep up
with the e mail.
I need to pull another TA.
So just loot me in on that,
give them the they're two days,
and then, you know,
I'll just ndge them.
When that happens. I mean,
they're students too.
They're busy, and
nobody's in trouble,
but I just need to
know if they're not
responding to e mail
within that time frame.
So Git Lab, we talk briefly
about that already.
Make sure that any code
that you're putting on
Jet Hab or it Lab stays
in a private repo.
Otherwise people
will cheat off of
you that has caused
problems for people
even like semesters
after they're graduated.
And then finally,
this is something I
started doing myself in the
last a couple of years.
I started using Anki flashcards.
Anybody use chi flashcards
before I've heard of
it. Just a few of you.
I really think that, It's
such a fantastic tool,
and it kind of doesn't
look very nice,
but it's such a good
way to learn things.
So the idea of Aki is
that it's flash cards,
but it has spaced
repetition, right?
And so what that means
is that when I see
a flash card, I will
either say, Hey,
I got it right, and
it was like easier or
harder or something like that,
or I say, I got it wrong.
And if I see I get it wrong,
I'm going to have to
see it again soon.
If I got it right,
they'll kind of
space it out exponentially.
And it's really efficient
because if there's
some card that it's
just like easy
for me and I keep saying easy.
I do it like four or five times,
and all of a sudden
they don't ask
me again for another two years.
Maybe in ten years, I might
actually forget. So
that's kind of useful.
But given that
exponential back off,
I don't spend a lot of time
on things that I don't know.
And then I just to
keep seeing things
that the scheduling of it
just seems like it
really works nice,
at least for my mind,
I think probably for
a lot of people.
So I think that we should all do
some ky flash cards to
just memorize terms.
You know, there's this
emphasis on kind of,
like general concepts and
kind of, like,
critical thinking.
And I agree with that, but
sometimes I think that we focus
too much on that to the neglect
of just memorizing stuff.
If we're talking about general
concepts and we don't have
a shared vocabulary
because maybe I
said some term and
then it was forgotten.
Well, then you can't do
the conceptual
thinking here either.
So you just have
to put in in time,
memorize some stuff, and
then you can build on that.
And so you should make
your own chi flash cards,
but I also for almost
every lecture,
I have some that I may
be posting as well.
So here you can download these.
There's like 30 flashcards from
today Some of them might
be terms you already know,
and you're just going
to quickly, you know,
space them out and
not worry about it.
And other ones, then
you're just going to make
sure that you have
all the vocabulare that
we're talking today,
and you're going to
have it down solid.
I can't recommend it that much.
I've just been amazed like once
I started doing
this and making a,
a ten minute day habit,
how much I've been able
to retain. All right.
Any questions about course
logistics? Yeah, right here.
I said that we'd
be able to go to
your alternative
lectures in the morning.
Yeah. We? Oh, yeah.
When is my morning lecture.
So it is at 9:55 in the morning,
and it's probably one of the
highest points on campus.
It's in room 272 of Bascom Hall.
So walk up Bascom Hill,
and then you can do
the morning one.
So people not only want to wake
up early, but I
guess climb a Hill.
So kudos to you.
Yeah, Any other logistics
or policy questions people
have? Yeah, right over here.
Oh, Yeah, so I will
provide feedback on
Jitb. Sorry about that.
I'll look through my slides
and make sure I update that.
We're switching just this
semester from JT Hub toGit Lab.
That'll probably be interesting,
actually, interesting in quotes.
But yeah, and I have to update
some stuff that
might say GitHub.
But the future is Git Lab
for this course. Thank you.
Yeah. Other questions
or comments.
And feel free at anytime.
I know it's a bigger
class and sometimes
people might feel shy
about raising your hand.
But I think that whenever you
raise your hand, ask a question,
that's useful to
everybody here, and it's
useful to everybody
watching the recording.
So I encourage that. Please ask
questions as you have them.
Alright, so let's get into
some technical stuff.
Let's talk about resources.
And I think that resources can
actually kind of appeal to
people from a wide
variety of perspectives.
One is that you
think about it in,
like, computing resources,
I either have to buy it, I
have to own some hardware or
maybe I rent it if
I'm in the Cloud,
and that trusts money, right.
So if you figure out how to
use resources better that can
directly translate to
higher profits, right?
So if you're very
money oriented,
then you should think
about resources.
You might also care a lot about
resources just from the
perspective of waste
and trying to be environmentally
conscious conscious.
You know, Data centers
are huge energy hogs,
right? You might be
worried about that.
We do a lot of mining to
create this hardware.
And so if you're coming
from that perspective too,
if you can find more efficient
ways to use resources,
that's hugely valuable, right?
I just think it's a general
Good idea to think
about, how can we be
good stewards of the
resources that we have?
And so there's lots of
different ways you
can define resources.
I'm going to draw a computer
with four resources in it.
Compute, memory,
storage, and network.
This is going to be kind
of our guiding compass
for the first third
of the semester.
We're going to do a
deep dive on each
of these resources
and what we need to
learn before we get into
the big interesting
distributed system.
For computer resources,
the main one
that has been around for
a long time is a CPU,
the central processing unit,
and a central processing
unit can execute code.
And that's the first thing
that we have to think about.
We also have GPUs,
which are graphical
processing units,
and graphical processing units,
maybe were originally
used for video games or
other kinds of visual stuff,
and a lot of that
is kind of a lot
of calculations with
floating point numbers.
And it turns out a lot of
those calculations are useful
for machine learning and
things as well, right?
So there's maybe more
programming that
people do with GPUs
in the future.
When we're running programs, it
has to keep its data somewhere,
that place is in RAM.
And so, kind of any
active data that
we're using as we run our
program is maybe in RAM.
GPU is actually, I wasn't
really sure what box to put it.
I think it's mostly compute,
but it also will have a bunch
of RAM built right into
it because it's kind of like
a CPU and RAM combined.
In terms of storage,
we need a place to keep
our data longer term,
and there's two devices you
need to know about there.
One is a hard disk
drive on the left,
and then the solid state
disk on the right hand side.
Then finally, if we're
trying to get a bunch of
computers working together,
they have to be able
to talk to each other,
and to talk to each other,
they need a network.
And the way we do that is
that each computer might have
some number of NICs
in it that sends for
network interface card or
network interface controller.
And this one right is
for a wired, right?
I could imagine attaching
an either net table to
that and plugging it into the
switch or router over here.
I do that with a
bunch of computers,
and then they can
communicate with each
other and work on
a bigger problem.
We'll be talking a
lot more about that.
Here's a picture
of a real server,
a little bit dated, but a
real server, nonetheless.
On the left hand side, I have
this power supply, right.
All these components are
drawing a lot of power.
Here I have two sockets
on the motherboard.
This kind of big square.
The greenish bluish
square is a motherboard.
Here I have two sockets,
and they plugged
in two CPUs there.
Those are kind of
draw a lot of power,
and they get hot, so
they have bands on them.
These green sticks are ram.
Over here, I have Nick,
that's actually built right
into the motherboard.
And then up here, I
have two hard drives.
This is an example of,
kind of an older server
that they had at
Google, actually.
Okay, so what are we going to
do when we're dealing with
bigger resources or bigger data
and we need to use
these resources?
Right? We could run into
a couple of problems.
One is that, what
if it takes like
a year to do my analysis?
That's not really
reasonable, right?
I might need to throw
more resources at
it to get things done in a
reasonable amount of time.
The other thing is that
maybe my dataset simply does
not fit in RAM or heaven forbid,
maybe doesn't even fit on desk.
And then I would have
a problem, right?
So things might not be
able to run at all.
So if we can't make things more
efficient or we've already
made it as efficient as we can,
we have to somehow
use more resources,
and there's two ways.
One is we could buy
better hardware.
We could buy a server with
more compute, more memory.
That's called scaling up.
And that's actually becoming
more and more possible because
hardware is getting kind of
amazing the capabilities of it.
So a single machine can do
more and more over time.
But eventually, right, it might
make sense to
actually scale out.
And then said by more and
more powerful machines,
you just have lots and lots of
machines that are
working together.
Google really played
out this strategy.
You know, before
Google, a lot of
companies are like, Oh,
we have bigger data,
let's buy, like the
best fanciest hardware
with all these
reliability features.
And Google is like, Well,
no, let's just buy
commodity hardware.
Comodity hardware
is stuff that like
anybody could just
buy off the shelf.
Let's buy lots and lots of it,
and it's starting to fail
all the time because
it's kind of like this cheap
stuff that everybody uses,
but we can build software on
top of it to deal with it.
So they kind of really
push that forward.
I think a lot of
the systems where I
see this semester
are kind of like
built around that strategy.
Now, I mean, in recent years,
it is changing some companies
like Google and Facebook or
Meta are kind of
building more and more
custom hardware, right?
But this is kind of the
history of big data systems.
All right, let's do a
deep dive on each of
these four different
resources now
compute memory
storage and network.
I'm to look at these.
The CPU is actually a
little bit ambiguous.
If I'm trying to be unambiguous,
I would probably
say a processor.
So this actually has
two processors here.
Each of those processors
might have many
different cores in it,
and each core acts
basically logically
like its own own CPU.
So sometimes people use CPU
to refer to one of these cores,
especially if you're
like a kernel hacker,
you probably use CPU
to refer to a core.
Some people will use CPU to
refer to the whole thing.
So I'll try to use either
the word processor
or core because CPU is
a little bit ambiguous.
But anyway, these cores that we
have can run instructions,
and that's how how our
programs get executed.
So how do these cores execute
some machine code that was
basically written for them?
All right.
So I'm going to drop a
picture of this up here.
So here I have a
CPU, and this CPU,
I guess I should just call it
processor has two cores on it,
and I want to run four
different processes.
What is a process? A process
is just a running program.
I write a program. I run it.
The running thing is a process.
Here I actually see
that processes one and
four are both program P.
I guess I started
program P twice.
But I have these four
different processes.
They each have some data in RAM
In RAM for them. They each
have some code, right?
So that's a machine code
that can be executed.
And one of the most important
things for our process is
knowing what instruction
is currently executed.
And so each of them have
this red instruction
pointer indicating
what part of the code is
currently executing at
that moment in time.
So to execute code,
that pointer is going to
have to move and we're
going to have to run
different instructions.
And so cores at any
given time can be
associated with one of
these different
instruction pointers,
and they can move along, right?
The cores will advance
those instruction pointers
and execute the
instructions as we go.
The operating system has
a scheduler and then
the scheduler can decide
at certain points
to switch which
process is running.
So even if I have a bunch of
processes and not that many
cores, to me as a human,
this switching is
happening so fast,
it really feels like
everything is kind
of running at the same time.
It's kind of a basic
picture there.
You know, modern cores of
modern CPUs have
some hyperthreading,
they might actually have
two arrows like this,
but it would still be
kind of the same
general concept, right?
At anytime the operating
system is going to have
knowledge of which
process are running here,
it's process one and three, and
then which ones
are ready to run,
but they're not currently
running. That's two and four.
Alright, so we could do
that. The more cores I have,
the more things I
can run in parallel.
Alright, so what exactly
are they running?
So let's zoom in on
this blurred out code.
They're running
machine instructions,
which are encoded
as zeros and ones.
Very, very few people
would be writing zeros
and ones like that
for machine code.
Some people might be using
something called assembly.
So here's an example of some
assembly instructions over here.
Assembly instructions
very closely
correspond to
machine code, right?
So here I have
like Ad L up here.
That might correspond to
some combination
of zeros and ones.
I represent that's an instruction
we need to do, right?
More people will
write assembly code,
but still not that many, right?
More people, what
they're doing is they're
writing higher level code,
that's not really
for the machine,
it's really for a
human to understand.
They're going be doing that
in a language like Python or
Java or something
like that. Right?
So how do we bridge
that gap between
the high level code
that humans like to
write and then the
low level code
that's actually running
on a machine, right?
This is an important
question for us because even
though most of our examples are
going to be in Python
this semester,
we're going to be using systems
built in other languages.
So for example, we're
going to be looking
at Spark very closely,
and Spark has written a
language called Scala
and Scala runs on the
Java virtual machine.
Now, I'm sure all of you have
seen stack traces before, right?
You remember stack
traces where like, Oh,
it crashed on this line
inside of this function.
And it was there
because this other
function called it
from this line.
You get a bunch of line numbers
helping you figure out
where you crashed.
You all are going to be
getting very exciting
stack traces a semester
where you're looking at,
there's like some Python code,
there's some Scala code,
there's some Java code.
And I don't expect you
to know Scala or Java,
but you still have to
be troubleshoot that.
And so I just want to
have some sense of how
things run and brace ourselves.
It's going to be really
nasty exceptions that
we're going to have to deal
with and troubleshoot.
So it's better You'll be less
shocked if we're talking
about it now, right?
So how do these
things actually run?
Okay, there's a few ways.
One way is that the programmer
could write some
high level code,
and then a tool called a
compiler could travert
that high level code
into machine code.
You would do that once, and then
that machine code
could run many times.
You could also run on
different machines
that have the same machine code.
Different processors
might be expecting
different instructions.
So it couldn't run
on every machine,
but it couldn't run on a
certain sum set of machines,
and then the CPU would just
be executing that, right?
So that's one option.
A compiler is one kind of
translator that does this.
The other approach that
people have, which is slower,
but it's a little
easier to run things in
different places is
with an interpreter.
So in this case, the
interpreter is a program,
and that program is
represented as machine code,
so the core can run
that interpreter code. What
does an interpreter do?
It has a big loop in it,
and that loop is looping
over lines of code here.
You can magine
looping over lines
of python code or
something like that.
And as it loops
over each line of
code, it will execute that.
It might do a bunch of steps
to actually make
that thing happen.
So that's one step. I guess when
people learn about
compilers and interpreters,
this is like the
first introductory,
like, this is what happens.
The real world is a little
bit more complicated,
and so I'm going
to t to dive like
maybe one level
deeper and see what's
really happening with a
language like Python or Java.
They both actually
use a third approach.
Which is almost a
little bit of a hybrid.
The idea here is that there's
a compiler in place still,
and it produces something
called Byte Code,
and Bite Td is not
really something a human
would like to look at,
but it's also not really
something that can
directly run on any
specific hardware.
When I actually want to run it,
I need a piece of software
called a virtual machine,
a program virtual machine,
and I might have one for
Python or av
different languages.
That virtual machine is
written in machine code.
And so the core knows how to
execute the virtual machine,
and the virtual
machine, a lot like
an interpreter is looping
over that byte code up here.
But because the byte code
has already been
processed a little bit,
the virtual machine
can be a little
faster than the
interpreter was, right?
So we have to have that kind
of byte code in between.
And so Python
actually does this.
Python,
It gets compiled. And sometimes
depending on the Python version,
it might show up as these PY
C files that have
byte Trode in them,
and then the Python virtual
machine will execute that.
Let me actually just show
you what some Python vial
some Python bite
trod looks like.
So my head over here. And I'm
going to make this a
little bit bigger.
And I am going to
import this module.
Called disassembly.
And disassembly has a
function called disassembly.
And inside of there, I
can put some Python code.
And so I'll just say like z
equals x times two plus y.
And I do that. That's
going to show me
what is the byte code for
that one line of code?
So one line of code
might actually
be a lot of different
byte code instructions.
This stuff down here
is not interesting.
I guess after I do
that assignment.
If I kind of took
the whole thing,
it would give me back none.
There's nothing really
interesting there.
The interesting stuff
is all this up here.
So let's just walk through
what this is doing.
It's loading a name, which is X.
Then it's loading a
constant which is two.
Then it's multiplying
those two things together.
So I'll get x times
two. Then I'm
loading in another name,
which is y, and then I'm
adding those together.
So then I'll have
this whole result,
and then I'm storing
it back in Z.
Right? So you have
this Python byte code
that's a result of executing
that line of code.
Now I'm curious. I'm curious,
what are some possible
types that X Y and Z might
be. Yeah, right here.
Maybe they're integers.
Yep. Yeah, other thoughts.
What else might they be?
Here. There might be floats.
Yep. Anything else
they might be?
What's that? Strings.
Excellent. I didn't see
who said that, but yeah,
that's like somebody coming from
a true python
background will will
realize they can also
be strings, right?
By multi by a string by two.
It just like repeats it twice,
and then this
contatinates two strings.
Right? So when I look
at this byte code,
it doesn't necessarily
specify what the types are,
and that means that the
Python virtual machine
when it's running this is
going to have to
do a lot of war.
Because by time things
run an actual CPU,
we need to know
what the types are.
Right? Even though
this is byte code,
it's still kind of
high level byte code,
and the Python virtual
machine is going
to have to do some
serious work there.
I'm showing Java now,
and you can see Java is actually
identical picture in terms
of these boxes flowing,
but the byte code
is very different.
Right? Java makes
you specify types.
And so when you
compile to byte code,
those byte codes
will specify types.
And then when we
actually run it with
Java down here on the
Java virtual machine,
that will be faster,
right because it doesn't have to
figure out the types anymore.
There's some details
here that are
just kind of like
about the tooling.
In Java Roma, you'll run
Java C as a compiler,
then you'll separate run Java,
whereas Python just does it
all automatically for you.
There's other languages like
go where they could
do either, right?
You just kind of say, just
like run and then they'll
compile and run it,
or maybe you explicitly
do it as two steps.
That's not the interesting part.
The more interesting
part is see how
they both have an
intermediate language,
which is byte Tad,
and they kind of
have different levels of
closeness to machine toad.
Let's make the
picture. First, I'll
just pause there before
I make it mess here.
Any questions about that so far?
Oh, right. So, some
other details here,
there's a project called Jython,
which I don't know.
It's almost like a toy.
I don't think it's like
really actively developed,
but kind of interesting
proof of concept,
they'll take Python code and
convert it to JVM Bitterod.
I have to imagine
that wouldn't be
very efficient because
like that Tod would
probably still have to handle
different types, right?
So I'm assuming it
would be kind of
bloated and efficient bite Trod
it couldn't be done nonetheless.
What is more efficient
is that scala,
rather than building a new
Scala virtual machine,
they decided to piggy back
on the Java virtual machine.
So when you compile
some scalar code.
You get these class files with
Java byte code that
can actually run.
And so Java and Scalla
play nicely together,
and some of the
systems we're looking
at are built as a
combination of those.
Alright. So let's talk
about some alternatives
to using CPUs.
GPUs are the main one we're
going to talk about
in this course.
A CPU core or
a U processor might have
a handful, of course,
maybe eight, 16,
something like that,
and they're relatively fast,
and they're relatively
independent.
They can each different things,
and they're fairly
general purpose.
A GPU, in contrast,
what they're going to have
is lots and lots of cores,
but they're very
optimized for one thing.
They're optimized for doing
floating point
number calculations,
and they have to work and lock
step with each other, right?
So That's very useful,
for example, if I have
a big matrix of data.
Like in machine
learning. We're often
multiplying two
matrices together.
And on all the different rows,
I have to do the same operation.
I'm like doing a
row multiplication,
and so I'm doing the same work,
but on different pieces of data,
same instruction, multiple data.
And so that actually
works sraight.
If I have a bunch of threads
or I have a bunch of
cores that are kind of
working in lockstep
with each other,
that's useful for
some applications,
and that's how they but
that's how they built GPUs.
L et's just compare these.
So sometimes when
you're buying hardware,
this actually might save
you some money someday,
right, by making you
a better shopper.
One of the things people look
at and maybe brag about,
maybe not reasonably is
the clock speed, right?
So this one here has a 3.2
gigahertz clock speed.
So giga is billion
Hertzs per second.
That means that that CPU
has a clock in it that's
ticking 3.2 billion
times per second.
The GPU over here on
the right that I'm
comparing to that CPU
is like less than 11.5.
That's not the end
of the story because
they have different
numbers of res, right?
That CPU only has eight cores,
whereas this slower VDA one
has like 3,500 cores, right?
You might think you could
multiply those together.
It's still not
quite a final story
because just because that
clock is ticking super fast,
doesn't mean you're completing
instructions super fast.
Sometimes an operation
might take like
two clock cycles or
eight clock cycles or
you don't really know.
It gets so complicated
that the only way to
know which one is faster
is to actually run
something on it.
Okay. So I could write a program
explicitly for
measuring performance,
and that's called a benchmark.
I could also take an
existing application
and run it and see
how fast it is,
and I'm basically
turning an existing
application into a benchmark.
Benchmarks are
programs we run to
see how fast some hardware is.
So if somebody wants to
compare these two things,
what they might do
is they might write
a program that does a bunch
of floating point
operations, right?
Like you know,
adding some floats,
dividing some floats, whatever,
lots of some mix of
floating things.
And then it could measure how
many floating point operations
can we do per second?
So that would be called flops.
And so when I compare
this up here,
I have 409 i iga
flops for the CPU
and 11,300 giga flops
for the GPU, right?
So prefixes here that
you should know.
So K is 1,000 M is
1 million G is 1 billion,
T is 1 trillion.
Right? So when I have T
flops, that's Tera flops,
that would be
measuring billions of
floating operation floating
point operations per second.
See here is that GPU and
this is a little bit dated,
but this one is
about 30% cheaper,
but it's 28 times faster
for this specific workload.
So you have to understand your
workload and then find out
what is the cheapest way
to run your workload.
If it was some kind
of other thing,
maybe I'm dealing
with like strings
or integers or
something like that,
or maybe the data
is not as uniform,
then the CPU might win, right?
So different hardware
are going to
win on different benchmarks.
But here we can clearly see that
if we're working with big data,
GPUs are very critical to that.
Any questions about CPU so
far? Yeah, question right here.
It's not too complicated
if you sp a little bit
on how be optimized.
Yeah, how could a GPU be
optimized for floating
point operations?
Like I'm not like a
hardware design person,
so I won't be able to
have a great answer.
But you can imagine, right
when they're building
any of these chips, right?
They have some transistors
that they're using,
and you could imagine having
like a bunch of transistors
for different things,
maybe some for operating
on strings or some for
operating on integers, right?
Or you could imagine
using all your transistors
to do floating point
operations, right?
So I can kind of figure out
how I'm allocating transistors.
I like they're making
everything lockstep, too.
They can optimize that
in terms of as I'm like,
fetching the next instruction
to execute, right,
that logic can be
shared across a lot of
different cores
instead of each of
them having their own, right?
So they can just
figure out how they
actually build it and
what like components,
what units are going inside
of that chip, right?
And they can spend
more transistors.
They're kind of
spend that budget
on the thing that they
want to optimize for.
That makes sense? Yeah,
Yeah, great question.
Yeah, there are
questions people have.
All right. Fantastic.
Alright, let's
talk about memory.
So here's a bunch of sticks of
RAM in the bottom right.
That's our memory.
And RAM stands for
random access memory.
And random means that as
I'm accessing my data,
maybe I'm reading in my data,
or I'm writing my data,
I can jump around a different,
have samples from
different places,
and I can do that efficiently.
In contrast, this
is a tape cassette,
this is not random.
It's very sequential.
If I want to listen
to the little bit
at the beginning, and a
little bit at the end.
I can't do that efficiently.
I have to wait a long
time to kind of go
through the whole tape to
fast forward to the end.
I actually hear that
these are kind of
making a comeback for kind
of nostalgia reasons.
I don't know if that's
true, but that's what
I grew up listening to, right?
So definitely a device that's
random random kind of
has a bad connotation,
but here it actually
means that it's faster.
I can jump around and access
different parts of it.
So RAM holds bits.
A bit is a zero or one.
Those are two possible
values you have.
If you have two bits,
well, you can have
more combinations.
I can have zero,
zero, zero, one, 10,
11 The pattern is that
if you have n bits,
you can have two to the power
n different possible
values. Okay?
And so what you're going to do
is you're going to think about,
well, how many bits do I have?
How may different possible
values can I have?
And what do those values mean?
That's a question
of representation.
Different representations
have different trade offs.
When you learned
about this semester,
some representations are
very memory efficient.
I can have a lot of
data and few bytes.
Some are optimized for helping
the CPU execute as
efficiently as possible.
I just want to like
Open up that concept.
Here I have three bits, so
there's eight combinations.
I could use those to
represent letters.
represent positive numbers.
I could use those to represent
a mix of negative and
positive numbers.
I could have
derivative of these.
If I have numbers, I can use
that to represent colors.
You have to think
carefully about what
is a good data representation
that's going to be
efficient for what
you're trying to do.
All right. So a byte
is just eight bits,
and so 28 is 256,
so a byte can hold 256
different possible values.
And RAM is going to have
all these bytes of data.
And what we'll say is that
RAM is byte addressable.
So every different byte has
an address associated with it,
and there are
instructions you can use
to get the byte at
that specific address.
And what that means is
that if you wanted to say
just one bit instead
of one byte,
it's actually a little
bit more we, right?
Because you'd run
one instruction
to kind of get that
little piece of memory,
and you'd run another
instruction to
actually pull out the bit
bit you're interested in.
Some languages, like CPS pus,
for example, will actually
if you have a Boolean,
you might think you
could represent
a Boolean with a
bit, and you can,
but they actually will use
a full bite to represent
a single bit just because
RAM is bite addressable.
That's kind of wasteful,
right? We're using
one eighth of the
memory available,
but it's faster for
the CPU because
we can access it with
fewer instructions.
We have those same suffixes
over here, Kilmga Giga Tera.
You know, you can
think of those as
like multiples of 1,000.
Sometimes people will
do nice round numbers,
not in terms of base
ten, but base two.
So two to the power
of ten is 1024.
So if somebody says 1 kilobyte,
sometimes they might
mean 1024 bytes,
that's two of ten, or they
maybe mean 1,000 bytes,
but fortunately, the numbers
work out pretty close.
So unless it's something that
is very kind of particular,
then maybe it doesn't
matter too much.
Some characteristics of RAM
is that it's small, right?
So maybe like some of the
VMs we might be using
this semester might have like
4 gigabytes of RAM,
that's not that large.
It's volatile, meaning that if
you reboot your
computer, it's Guan.
It's not for long term storage.
And then the redeeming quality
of it is quite fast, actually.
It's quite fast compared to say,
like a hard driver and SSD.
So some use cases for it is
any kind of active program
data you're using,
if I have like a Python list or
a data frame faster
than a BN RAM.
Sometimes people will use it.
To have the same data
on both storage,
long term storage, and in RAM.
If we have all this data
on long term storage,
some of that data
is probably hot.
Hot data is data that
we access frequently.
And if we access it frequently,
we don't want it to be
sitting somewhere slow.
So usually what you'll
do is you'll take
all your data and then some
subset of it that is hot,
will be in in RAM.
Systems do this
automatically for us.
And then when I see some systems
like Spark where
we have to choose,
like, this is the data
that I want in RAM.
This is the data I don't
want in RAM, right?
So we have to start thinking
about the trade offs
of these different
storage mediums.
Alright, let's talk
about storage.
Here are two devices
you have to know.
They're both called
block devices.
One is a hard disk drive.
I have that on the left.
That's abbreviated HDD.
And again, like those
ki flash cards,
you're just trying to
memorize all that stuff.
You're going to
know what HDD is.
You know SSD because you're
going to do the flash cards.
On the right hand side, I
have a solid state disk.
On the left, I
have moving parts,
and moving parts
introduce delays.
So the hard disk
is kind of slower.
It's spending this
big magnetic platter.
The good thing is, you
can pack a lot of bits on
that magnetic platter based
on whether it's
magnetized or not,
so it has a high capacity.
The SSD is based on charges,
and they haven't figured
out how to make that
as dense. So it'll be faster.
There's no moving
parts involved,
but it won't have
as much capacity.
Both of these are what
we call block devices.
And the idea of having
a block device is very
related to that idea of memory
being bite addressable, right?
So when we were
talking about memory,
we said like each byte
has its own address,
and if I wanted a
bit within that,
I have to kind of grab
the whole bite and
then pull a piece out.
It's like that here,
but instead of bytes,
we have blocks.
So you can think
of these as being
block address, and
blocks are big.
Blocks are something
like maybe 512 bytes.
And so if you want to get
just a single byte of data
from one of these devices,
you'll actually have to
read in a whole block,
that 512 and pull out
just the data you want.
Whether you read one byte or
512 bytes, same
performance, right?
So we generally to have to
think about how we can have
data representations that let
us access these efficiently.
If you're frequently accessing
a small subset of a block,
you're going to have
terrible performance.
So both of these, I'll kind
of lump them together,
and later we'll talk about
them in more detail,
but they're both large, right?
I think, you know,
it's affordable to get
a device sets more
than 1 terabyte.
They're non volatile,
so the data
lives beyond a reboot,
and they're slow.
At least they're much
slower than RAM.
So you could use them for
very large data sets,
and you can also
use them for data
that needs to be
persisted long term.
I've been talking about
different resources, right?
Like, you know,
memory or storage.
But we can think of more
fine grained resources
for some of these.
So one resource I might think
about is capacity, right?
I can say, what is the capacity
of that hard drive, right?
And I can measure that in bytes.
How much data can I store there?
I might also think about
throughput as a capacity.
How quickly can I transfer
bytes from that hard
drive into my memory,
so I can actually analyze it.
So maybe I have a 500
gigabyte block device,
but maybe I can only transfer
200 megabytes/second, right?
Another statistic we might use
to evaluate these
things is latency.
I I just want one byte of data,
how long do I have to wait?
Latency is about how long
we wait for something?
Maybe that might take something
like ten milliseconds.
So SSDs are much faster,
but in terms of capacity,
hard drives are much better.
That gap is closing, but
here's a trend that
goes through 2020.
And so we can see at 20:20 that
SSDs cost six times more
than hard drives per byte.
So disks are not dead yet.
Google uses a bunch of disks.
You can imagine like
on YouTube, right?
There's a bunch of videos
that take up a lot of bytes,
but nobody watches them, right?
Like, some things
people watch a lot,
and you want that on SSDs,
some of that other stuff you
just want on a slow hard disk.
You know, this last week, I
looked on Amazon and
their overall pick,
very, like on scientific.
But just looked at
the two devices.
And here, there was a three
times difference, right?
Like the recommended SSD cost
three times more per byte.
Maybe that eventually, I
don't know the future, right?
Maybe hard drives have
a long term future.
It might also be that, you
know, ten years from now,
we're just all using SSDs for
everything because it
might be strictly better.
Oh, right. How are we doing?
I think we have 1 minute left,
and so I don't have time
start another resource.
But I'll hang out here
and you can all come up
and chat if you want or if
you have any questions,
and I'll see you on Friday.
So I have a great evening.