Coming today. We've been
learning about Map reduce.
And just at the very
end of last time,
we started transitioning to
Spark Spark solve some of
the issues that MapReduce
has specifically around
intermediate data.
I'm going to start today by
doing just a little bit of
review with Map reduce by
doing a top hat question,
so you can starting your
phone out if you like.
But basically,
you can see there's not
much out here today,
and that's because there's
just a lot that really kind
of spans two lectures, right?
So Aki flash charts cover both.
And I may spend some time on
the slides from last time.
Alright, cool. So I may
bring up this top hat first.
So a question about Map reduce.
And then we'll talk about that,
and we'll try to jump
back into the content.
About 3 seconds left.
Alright, so people have a
variety of different answers.
The most popular answer is X,
which is actually correct.
So one of the important things
to remember here is that you are
providing a map function
and a reduced function,
each of which might
be called many times.
That's not necessarily related
to how many R tasks are.
A Sigle MAP task could
have a lot of calls.
A SL reduced task could have
a lot of reduced calls.
And so I really
interested, well,
how many times is
reduce actually called,
And that makes us remember
that it's not just Map reduce,
but in between the bap
and the reducing phase,
there's a shuffle phase.
And shuffle, what it's really
similar to in SQL is a group by.
When we shuffle the data,
we're bringing a bunch of
related data together.
And so what happens
is these bappers
are emitting a bunch
of keys and values,
and then the shuffle
phase will bring
together all the related
keys in the same place.
And then all the related keys or
the identical keys
are going to be
passed in to a
single reduced call.
People have any
questions about that?
All right. Cool. So
we're gonna do one more.
So my head over here.
Just a moment. I saw
a bunch of people
like run out the door as soon
as they were done
with the top hat,
so um, that makes me feel
like doing one more today.
Oh, right. So it's time
a similar question,
but now I'm asking
how many output files
are going to be written to HDFS.
About 30 seconds left.
Alright, so the
most common answer
is R, which is correct.
If the data coming out of
the Mappers is quite large,
we might need to have
many different reducers
involved in processing.
Right? That's fine.
We can choose many
reducers we want.
We can have a very
distributed lots of reducers.
And ultimately, those reducers
have to produce output.
And you can imagine that if
they were all working
together on the same
Output file, we
then they'd have to
coordinate and that would
become a bottleeneck.
So each reducer gets to write
its own HDFS file as output.
If you really wanted to have
just one file of output,
you'd be forced to
have one reducer,
it wouldn't be very scalable.
This doesn't mean that for
kind of large map reduc jobs,
you're going to have
a bunch of files,
and anything that's using
those, we'll have to
somehow consider all of
those output files. Any
questions about that one?
Oh, right. Cool. So
I'm to exit that out,
and we're ahead over here.
And so we've been learning
about map reduce.
And oftentimes you're
not just running
one map reduced job, you're
running a chain of them.
You have some kind
of data pipeline,
and the first one will
persist a data on HDFS files,
and the output from
one Mp reduced job
will then be the input
to the next one, right?
That's actual bytes of data.
We actually have actual bytes
of data for intermediate data.
What I'm saying is that I'm
materializing that data.
And we talked last time
about some of the reasons
that's not super efficient.
HDFS is just trying
to slow in general.
And so that leads us to a
different design with Spark,
which is more clever
about intermediate data.
Instead of actually materializing
those bytes somewhere,
there's an RDD, a resilient
distributed data set,
and that's really just
like a recipe for how we
could compute that data
on demand, if need be.
Right? The key observation here
is that we don't care what
the intermediate data is.
We care about some
other end result.
And so we shouldn't be spending
extra work generating
data that we might not
end up using or that
maybe in the end,
we might have some
optimization tool that finds
a better way to get
to the end result.
So that's what RDDs do.
Let me give you a
very concrete example
of some RDDs in action.
And so I have a little snippet
of python code here that's
really driving spark.
And I'm operating on
this table of data.
It's really kind of
just a simple table
of data where I have
a list of tuples.
I'm imagining each
tuple is a row.
And to get some results,
there's various transformations
I might want to
do on that input data.
And these transformations
can often be done by
writing functions of some
sort that do something.
And so up here, I have two
just regular Python functions
that are operating on this data.
My goal is to get
two times the number for
all the A rows, right?
And so I ended up writing
two functions to get
these two parts.
The first one is multiply two,
and it's going to take in a row,
the row is going to be
one of these tuples.
And then it's going
to return a tuple,
which is a different row, right?
The first value
in the output row
is going to be the same as
the first value
in the input row.
And then the second value
and output put row will be
two times that second
value in input row.
Okay. Great. So I have
some functions like that.
Other function that
might be used to
process the data
returns a Boolean.
That's really
useful if I want to
filter the data in some way.
So this function
only A is returning
true for A rows and
false for other rows.
So one way I can accomplish
my goal is with these
four steps down here.
I have four different
spark operations.
The first one is parallelized.
I takes some Python data
and basically turns
it into arrow data.
The next one is Map.
So Map will call the
multiply two function
on each of my four rows.
I'll get double back, which is
a four row resilient
distributed data set.
Double dot filter
means I'm going
to reduce those rows
so that I only have
the ones where it's A,
that will give me double A,
that will be a resilient
distribute dataset
with two rows.
And then finally, I say collect.
And what collect
does is it takes
that arrow result and it brings
it back to Python for me,
which will look
like this list of
tuples over on the
right hand side here.
And so I have these
four operations,
and operations and Spark are
broadly in two categories.
And it's really
important to remember
these two categories because it
has huge implications
for performance.
One kind of operation
is a transformation.
A transformation takes an
RDD and returns an RDD.
And remember that an RDD is
just a recipe to produce
the data on demand.
So if I write a little piece
of code that does
a transformation,
no work actually
happens immediately.
And the first few of these
are transformations, right?
They all are giving
me back RDDs.
And so there's no real
work being done there.
When I want the real
world to happen at
the very end, I say, collect.
Collect is not a
transformation. It's an action.
Actions are when
I say, I actually
care about my final result.
So this distinction between
transformation and action
is how we distinguish
between intermediate data and
final results that we
actually actually
care about, right?
And when I actually
do the collect,
that's when all the
multiplication and
the filtering all
that will happen.
It won't happen
where the line of
code happens. Yeah, right here.
You're saying right here
when I do table that map.
So what this is doing is
it's returning an RDD.
And so double if I looked at
the type of would be an RDD.
And internally, what
it will be saying is,
these are the steps
that would be
necessary to get this data,
but it doesn't actually do any
work at the moment I run this.
It just says it just
remembers, Well,
here's how we could get that
result if we wanted to.
That makes sense?
Yeah, there's another
question right here.
How is this faster than actually
Yeah, that's an
excellent question.
Why is it fast why is it
faster to do it
instead of eagerly?
Yeah, I'll come back to that.
There's a couple of ways
that's going to be faster.
Yeah.
Yeah, Yeah.
You're asking I guess that
was be my very next question,
which you kind of
just answered, right?
So when we're looking
at this, right?
Are there alternate
paths? And you said,
what would be the
faster way to do it?
Hm. Like, could it reorder them?
Yeah. And so, first off,
before I talk about
what it does,
let's just talk about what it
could do hypothetically, right?
There's another way to
get the same end result.
And presumably this
other way is faster.
I mean, honestly, it
feels a little wasteful
if I have a whole
bunch of numbers,
and I multiply them all by two,
and then I throw away
a lot of the roads.
Why did I do
all that multiplication when
I didn't care what it was?
I should have filtered before
I multiply We could
totally do that,
we could do filter and then map,
and we would have ended
up with the same result.
And so by distinguishing
between these,
these transformations
versus actions,
it gives an opportunity for
an optimizer to come
along and find,
Okay, here's a faster way
to get the same result.
Now, in this very
particular case
is an optimizer
going to do that?
And the answer is no.
And the reason that the
optimizer does not do it is
the optimizer would have
to understand Python code.
And it's very hard to
write a tool that reads
some Python code and understands
when it's okay to
switch the order of it.
So here, It wouldn't
be optimized.
In other cases, it will be.
And the reason we'll be in
other cases is that instead of
writing all these lines
of codes ourselves,
what we'll typically
be doing is we'll
be writing something
in Spark equil and
the Spark sequel is going to get
translated to these
transformations and actions.
And in those cases, each of
these transformations
is very well defined.
There's not an opportunity
for me to slip in
some type of function that has
something a little bit strange.
And so in those cases,
an optimizer tran trim
along and see, Okay,
there's a different way to
get to the same result.
So here it we'll not,
even though there's
an opportunity to.
In other cases, an
optimizer will absolutely
maybe do something
in a different order
or maybe skip some step.
Maybe even add some steps that
help us filter sooner
rather than later.
Absolutely. So when we
distinguish between
intermediate data and final data
via transformations
versus actions,
that absolutely
creates an opportunity
for optimizers to step in.
And hopefully that
answers the question.
Yeah, Yeah, another
question right here.
No. Yeah. So to clear that,
it doesn't know that
it's not dependent.
The way I would
say it is that if
you have two steps and you
understand what the steps are,
you as a human can see,
sometimes it's okay to switch,
and sometimes it's not, right?
And here, to actually
understand that,
any kind of tool would have to
understand the
Python rode, right?
So when our transformations are
based on kind of arbitrary
Python functions,
an optimizer isn't going
to know to do with that.
But a lot of the transformations
that Spark is doing,
it's not just some
arbitrary Python function.
It's like a very
well defined step,
and then it can be smart
enough to see that k,
it's safe to do
this, and so' get
the same result.
That makes sense.
Yeah. There are other
questions people have
about these transformations
and actions.
Oh, right. So that's
one opportunity where we have
an opportunity to be
faster by being lazy.
And Ao has to do
with the granularity
at which we do this, right?
So I have all these
stages in the pipeline,
and I have a bunch of
rows at the beginning.
And you can imagine different
ways I could do it.
I could take one row
of data and sve it
in the pipeline and then
see what pops out
the other side.
Maybe a row pops
out, maybe nothing
pops out because
maybe I got filtered,
but I could just start
sending rows through
one at a time.
I could also take
my whole dataset if I wanted
and try to chunk it along,
like, you know, the whole data
set could drow step by step.
Um, both of those have
some disadvantages, right?
I think that the
disadvantage of having
the whole data set is that
maybe it's quite large.
I don't want to have
the whole dataset
in memory at the same time.
On the flip of it, if I
send one brow at a time,
then there's this overhead
of kind of like spending
up a task to process it for
a stage in the pipeline,
so that won't be very efficient.
And so what Spark actually
does is something in between,
one brow and the whole dataset.
And what it does in
between is a partition.
And we have some control
over the partition size.
So you can see down here when
I did SC dot parallelize,
I pass in my list of
tuples, which is data,
and I could say I
want one partition,
or maybe I want two partitions.
By the way, SC stands
for Spark context.
I'm may be showing
that again later to
the common name for a
Spark context variable.
And so I could do that. I
could choose what granularity
I want to pass pass
my data through.
Okay. Why does that matter?
These partitions?
So A RDD I look at,
I can see how many partitions
are there for this RDD,
Work gets done and spark at
the granularity of
something called a task.
And a task brings
two things together.
A task runs on
exactly one CPU core
and operates on
exactly one partition.
And so if I have twice
as many partitions,
I'm going to have twice
as many tasks, right?
And so when you're choosing
the partition count,
you're going to be
directly choosing
the task count as a result,
and that has some big
performance implications.
So if I have larger
partitions, well,
that means I have fewer tasks
and less overhead for
starting those tasks.
It's kind of slow, it's like
starting up a java process.
What are some disadvantages
of having larger partitions?
Um Maybe maybe I
have ten machines,
and they each have 20 cores.
That means I have 20
cores in my cluster.
I could be running 200
tasks at the same time.
If I don't have at
least 200 partitions,
I can't use my whole
cluster, right?
So I might need to have
smaller partitions so that I
could use the whole cluster.
It's a little harder to
balance work evenly, right?
If I have lots of partitions,
maybe some of them
are heavier than
others. I can kind
of balance them.
If I have big chunks of work,
it's hard to make sure that
all the workers are getting
the same amount of work.
And then finally, this is
probably the most important one.
How much memory am I using
at any given point in time?
Whenever we're operating
on a partition,
that entire partition is memory.
Some people say that Spark is
an in memory analytics platform,
and that's true,
but that doesn't
mean that all data is in
memory at the same time.
What it means is that when we're
operating on these
partitions of data,
all partition of data will
be in memory while
we're operating on it.
Alright, so you're
going to have to
figure out how to tune
this a little bit.
And and By default, right?
If I don't say, Spark
will try to choose.
It might look at how many
CPs I have in my cluster,
how much memory, how
big the data is,
it'll try to choose.
It doesn't always choose right.
And so that's why you might have
to come in and set it, right?
It would be kind of a finicky
thing to choose correctly.
So I want you to
be able to observe
different problems and
then correct it, right?
If if you're doing
some spark job and
you're running out of memory,
try smaller partitions.
Smaller partitions means
more partitions, right?
If you have a large cluster
and you're not really
utilizing all the
cores in your cluster,
I'll maybe try more
partitions, right?
It's kind of a piniky thing
that you have to get right.
Alright. Any questions about
tasks or this idea of partition
size? Yeah, right here.
Get to Yeah.
So if you choose way
too many partitions,
then each partition is going
to correspond to a task,
which is starting like
some kind of Java process.
And so, like if I
had one partition
for every row would
be kind of extreme,
then I would have to start up
a whole Java process
to analyze one row,
which is the start up cost is
going to be much greater than
the actual analysis cost.
So that's why we
don't want to go too
extreme in that
direction. Makes sense?
Yeah, a great question.
Other questions
people have. All right.
So sometimes, as
we're doing this,
we might have to be intentional
about changing the
partition count.
I think a very common scenario
is that we might start
with a very large
dataset, four rows.
A, that's not that large,
but let's pretend it is.
And we might filter it down.
Maybe the filter,
if it's restrictive
might output 10% of
the original rows.
And so the number of partitions
that's good for
the original data
or the original RDD might not
be good for something
downstream.
Okay. By default, what Spark is
going to do is at each step,
it's trying to keep
the same number
of partitions. Why is that?
Well, Spark is trying to
avoid sending data over
the network, right?
And if I have kind of
like a long chain,
long, simple chain of
partitions, right?
We just like one flows to one,
then I can put all of
those on the same machine.
I can schedule all the tasks
for that chain in one place,
and I don't have to be sending
data over the network, right?
If I'm somehow changing the
partition count, right?
Maybe I have my data spread
across partitions that are
on many different machines,
maybe it's like 100
different machines,
each with one partition.
If I want to shrink that down
into ten big partitions, well,
I'm going to have to set a
lot of data over the network.
Maybe it's worth
and maybe it's not.
So if you have a resilient
distributed data set,
you can just say, get some
partitions to see what it is.
And then you could do
a different resilient
distributed data
set by saying RDD
dot repartition,
and you say some count.
This is a transformation.
Sometime I do
anything right away.
But then if I do some
calculations on RDD,
it's going to involve
that coalescing data from
all these places into
relatively fewer places, right?
In this case here when I'm
filtering down might
be a classic case.
There's a couple of
ways I could do it.
I could let it alone, right?
And after the filter, I could
cheat the same number
of partitions.
Or in this case, I could
observe, hey, after the filter,
I don't have so
many, maybe I want
to repartition it. That's
an investment, right?
Because there's a cost of
shuffle of the data
into one place.
But then after that,
everything will be
faster because I won't have
to start as many tasks,
and starting tasks as slow.
Do we have any questions
about repartitioning?
Oh, right. There are
other scenarios.
So repartition is one case
where I send data
over the network.
Another case might be
for certain kinds
of transformation.
So we already said, Okay,
everything is an operation.
Operations are either
actions that give us data
or transformations
that just define
a new RDD in terms of other RDs.
Transformations have
two sub categories.
They can either be
narrow or wide.
And basically, I've been
showing you a bunch of
narrow transformations so far.
A narrow transformation means
that I have one
partition coming in,
and then one corresponding
partition coming out.
There's a question right
here? Nope. All right.
And so I can see on the left
hand side when I'm filtering,
one N one out, that's
a narrow partition.
Some things just I can do that.
So, for example, if I wanted
to take some input
rows and then order,
like, I want to sort
by some column,
that's going to be
a wide partition.
Why? Well, my original
data was ABAB.
I wanted to sort
it, so it's A ABB.
And so the first two
are going to go to
one partition and the BB,
are going to go to another.
Each of these is pulling
from two different sources.
Um, if you're lucky,
right, this might not
involve network io.
I mean, it's possible,
right that both of
the input partitions happen
to be on the same computer,
in which case, I can
do the two output ones
without doing network iO.
But in general, right,
partitions are going to
be on different machines,
and this will involve sending
some data over the network.
Right? I want you
to start to look at
these different
things and see things
that might be slow, right?
If you have a large
number of partitions.
Maybe you have to worry
about how many tasks are
starting if you're having
wide transformations?
Maybe you have to
worry about there
being some network IO, right?
These are different
things that might
arise as you're
working in this space.
If I have an action that
collects all my data together,
maybe everything was fine
before the action right,
maybe I might have a lot of data
spread across
different machines.
Once I do that action,
maybe it brings
all the data together
in one place.
Any questions about
these different kinds
of transformations?
All right. Let's talk about
another thing that's going to
be critical to performance,
which is caching.
And so I'm going to imagine
a concrete example here.
Let's say I have weather data
from weather stations
all across the world,
but I specifically want to do
a study of weather in Wisconsin.
And so there's different
things I might do.
I think that maybe
in my first test,
I might filter down
to Wisconsin data,
I might do some other
transformations,
and then in the end,
I might pull out an average
temperature for Wisconsin.
Maybe I want to get the
rainfall in Madison.
Maybe that involves
filtering down to Wisconsin,
maybe filtering down to Madison
further and then
getting rainfall.
Each of these RDZDs,
you can see it's
just a chain, right?
But these different
chains I have might
have a common source of data,
which is maybe some
file somewhere with
weather data from all
across the world.
And so if I just do
this naively and I
run each of these
three jobs, Well,
what's unfortunate is that
each time I do a
new computation,
it's try to refilter all
of the data in the world.
And, of course, that's
slow to loop over
all the data in the world just
to extract the Wisconsin data.
I wouldn't necessarily
want to do that
more often than necessary.
So there are certain cases,
even though even though
an RDD is kind of a recipe
for how to get some data,
sometimes I actually
want to save the result
of what I achieved by
following that recipe.
And so that's
caching. And before
with all these caching
policies we were on like LRU,
for example, what those things
were trying to do is they
were trying to predict,
what data you're going to need
soon and keep it in the cache.
And they were really,
like least recently used,
Recent is talking
about the past, right?
So in LRU cash is like trying to
predict where you're going to do
the future by
looking at the past.
Sometimes that works.
Sometimes it doesn't.
What Sparka is doing is
not anything so clever.
They're asking you as
a programmer to say,
like, Oh, well, you're
computing this thing,
and you have to
explicitly identify,
I might need it
again soon, right?
So, how might we
do this up here?
Maybe this all weather thing
is reading from some file.
I filter down to Wisconsin.
And then I can say
Wisconsin weather.
Then At that point,
no work has actually
happened yet, because,
again, these are all
lazy transformations.
When I compute the
average temperature,
then in addition to processing
all this computing, like,
filtering down to
the Wisconsin data,
it will also save that
Wisconsin data in memory.
It'll save it for me later.
Then when I come along and I
do Madison rainfall later,
it doesn't have to go
back to the beginning
where we have the
whole world of data.
It can look at the Wisconsin
data that's in memory.
Same thing when I'm
looking at the correlation
between different weather
stations and Madison.
When I'm all done, I can say,
Wisconsin weather
or not persist,
and then it can free up that
memory for other things.
Alright. That's another thing
you have to get rid of.
You have to figure
out, we, you're
working with all of these RDDs,
which ones do you want
to cache and which not,
and when are you actually
done with it, right?
So, you know, I think a lot
of people could
draw and be like,
a naive spark user.
What I'm hoping you will all do
is understand a little
bit about how things work
internally and then be a
more sophisticated user
that can get the best
performance out of this system.
That's what my goal is for you.
So Any question about caching?
All right. Cool. So we
talked about Map reduce.
Spark came along with
this idea of RDDs,
which is in just a
lot of ways better,
right than Map reduce, so they
started kind of replacing
it with based on that idea.
And so that's like the core
thing they're doing it.
But they built all this stuff
on top of it and around it.
So I want to talk a
little bit about that.
One is that not everybody
is going to want to be
programming RDDs, right?
Maybe not everybody
has that background.
There's plenty of
people who know SQL,
but they could not,
write a Python program.
That's fine. And so what
they did is they built
something called Spark
Sequel on top of RDDs.
A lot of these things like
group by or filtering, right?
There's corresponds something
you could do in RDD,
but it also corresponds
to something
you might see in SQL, right?
So that builds on top of that.
And SQL actually has
various formal standards,
and so they aren't just
building some SQL language.
They built like a
legit formal version.
They supported a legit formal
version of SQL, right?
They have a standard And for
Spark SQL, in particular,
a lot of these optimizations are
possible because you look at
things that are
happening in SQL, right?
Like you're doing group
buys or joins a lot of
standard things that happen
in a variety of situations.
And so it's possible
for an optimizer
to understand this handful
of things that people
do all the time
and understand when it's
possible to reorder,
or find different ways
to get the same result.
So Spark SQL can optimize
that Some people like
doing analysis with SQL.
Other people like data frames.
Is there anybody
here who, really
likes programming with
Pandas, for example?
Like, I guess, like five of you.
I thought it was more
popular, but anyway,
I think Pandas is a
nice way to program.
I like Pandas, right? And
so people like data frames,
and so they wanted to
support that as well.
And rather than build that
directly on top of RDDs,
they built that on
top of Spark SQL.
All these things that you
might be interacting with
the data frame ultimately gets
translated to some
kind of SQL query,
ultimately gets translated to
something that's
happening with RDDs,
and, of course, optimized.
Now, If I'm doing a
data frame in Pandas,
it's really easy to change
data frames in Pandas.
I can add columns, change
values, whatever I want.
And that's because Pandas
data frames are mutable.
Data frames in Spark
are based on RDDs,
which are immutable.
Once I have an RDD,
I can't change it.
And so one of the
implications is that
a Spark data frame
is going to be
basically kreate it
and it's read only.
I can't change it any further.
It's immutable, right?
Alright. The powerful thing
though is that if I
have a spark data
frame and I'm using it,
it's not in memory on the
computer I'm using it.
I just I'm doing operations on
it to leverage the resources
of my whole cluster,
maybe thousands of machines.
And even if those
machines cumulative,
don't have enough memory for
it, that can be okay, right?
I can have a data
frame that there's not
even entirely in memory
across all these
different machines.
And so I can do a
lot of things for
bigger data sets that Pandas
would just fall over
for very quickly.
Let me just show you some ting
examples to compare them.
I think Pandas is easier
to use because, well,
it's also not trying to
help us with big data.
So here I'm creating
a pandasata frame
up here and I have a picture
of what it looks like.
If I want to add a
column to it, right?
It originally has x column,
I can just say pandas Sta frame
y equals the x column
squared, right?
So I have 123, 149.
Very easy to mutate
it and add stuff.
If I want to go from a Pandadta
frame to a spark
data frame, I can,
I can just say spart
dot create data frame,
passing a pandasta
frame Spark DF.
If I want to convert
it back later,
I could say Spark
DF two, to Pandas?
You have to be a little
bit careful there,
right because it
might be huge, right?
That's a commonplace where
you'll run out of memory,
and then, you know,
things will crash on
your machine, right?
But if somehow you did a
bunch of stuff on big data,
and then you got some
smaller aggregate,
you could bring it back if you
wanted to. Right,
so I can do that.
How would I do
something like above
where I wanted to
add a y column?
So I cannot change Spark DF,
but I can make a new data frame
that looks like it
with some changes.
So I could say something like
Spark df dot with column.
I'm adding a new column y,
and I can say that y
should be computed
as column x squared,
and that will return
Spark DF two, right?
I'll have one data
frame with just x,
and I'll have another
data frame with x and y.
Any questions or
concerns about that?
Here. Why is what?
Five. Why can Spark
not append it?
Yeah, Spark, it's immutable,
right Because the Spark
data frame is on top of
Spark SQL which is on
top of Spark RDDs,
and RDDs are immutable.
I can create a new
RDD from an old RDD,
but I cannot change
an RDD, right?
If I wanted to, I mean, I
could use the Python variable.
I could say Spark
DF equals Spark DF,
but I cannot change
that data frame object.
Sons? It's very similar
to strings, right?
In the language in some
languages strings are mutable,
but in Python, strings
are immutable.
So if I wanted to a pend
something to a string, well,
I don't change that
string, I just
make like a new string object,
which is the old
one plus a new one.
Python, right if I'm kind of
concatining one large string
with another one is
a little bit waste.
There's multiple
copies of the data.
But this would actually, even
though it feels like
a string to be waste,
well it's actually
very efficient,
because what is Spark
DF and Spark DF two?
They're both recipes for
computing the data
and all the cells,
if I ever need to
look at them, right?
So Unless I ever look at them,
there's actually
no work even being
Done here, right? You know,
maybe Spark DF is a
recipe that has, like,
steps 123, and Spark DF
two is a recipe
that has steps one,
two, three and four, right?
It's not expensive to
create new data frame.
So it kind of feels
weird that I'm creating
new data frames that are like
old ones with a little bit more.
But internally, it's fine,
and it's fast. Yeah, right here.
A small size.
Yeah, the RDD is small, right?
It's just a list of directions.
There's no data associated
with it, right?
The only time there's
ever a lot of data
or a lot of costs is when
I have an action, right?
And then all of a sudden,
there's data that's
going to flow through the
RDD until it hits my action.
And at that point,
there might be
a lot of data and
memory temporarily.
But until I actually
materialize it somewhere,
then there's no
significant cost.
Lists of instructions
at point to a data set?
Are they a list of instructions
Yeah, yeah, they usually are.
So usually it's like maybe
PK files and HFS or
something like that.
So that might be my
first RDD, right?
We would be referring to
that data in that file,
and I could have other
ones that transform
the data in that
file in some way.
Absolutely. Yeah. Thank you
for asking and clarifying that.
Yeah, both great questions.
Yeah other questions
people have.
Yeah, question right here.
Exactly. So that's a
great point, right?
So this Spark DF two,
when I say with column, that's
not calculated
until later, right?
If I said spark df
two dot collect,
that would try to bring
it into memory on
my node, that would trigger it.
Or if I said two Pandas,
that would trigger
it or if I said,
give me the average
value in a column.
That would trigger it.
At this point, nothing
has been triggered.
No meaningful amount of work
has been done anywhere.
Yeah, thank you for
clarifying that.
Yeah, other questions or
clarifications people have.
Right. Cool. Let's talk
a little bit about how
we're going to deploy it.
And so they have lots of
different deployment modes
that interact with
different systems
like Yarn or C Kubernetes.
We're just going to look
at two this semester,
and the first is called
a standalone mode.
Is not any other
kind of framework.
In this case, we have
to take different parts
of the Spark cluster and
just run them ourselves.
The most interesting thing,
I think is a Spark executor.
A Spark executor is a process
that runs Spark tasks for us.
Here I might have a few of them.
If I have some Spark
job that's running,
a decision has to be made about
which tasks run on
which executors,
and so I may have some
kind of cluster manager,
maybe a separate process
that's in charge of that.
Now, I as a programmer
I'm probably writing
some code like in
a Jupiter notebook or
something like that,
and I'm interacting with it via
something called
the PySpark module,
which is also in Python.
But it turns out that
all the spark stuff is
running on the JVM.
Spark was not written in
Java actually, it was
written in Scala,
but Scala can compile
to JVM Bite Trode that's
what they do, right?
So they've built this as
JVM Bite Trode they have a
couple of components here,
a Spark driver and
a spark session.
And those are the things
that are going to be
communicating with
these other nodes
in the cluster, right?
So I may be writing Python
rode, but internally,
there's going to be this scala
running on top of the JVM.
That doesn't mean that a
lot of the air messages
we see are going to be
pretty awful, right?
Because there might be an
exception, and I'll see, like,
well, you know, I had
this Python line of
code that was running,
and then there's
some scala lines of
code and some java lines of
code that might be a little
bit overwhelming, right?
It will have quite long errors.
And I don't expect anybody
to know Scala or Java.
I don't know Scala myself.
But we'll so have
to kind of dig into
these nasty error messages
and try to pull out
pieces of information to
troubleshoot what actually
went wrong. All right.
So that's one thing
that you could do.
Another thing you could
do is called local mode.
And in that case,
we basically just
have a Spark executor built in
to the same JVM that's
running this process over
here inside of Python, right?
In that case, everything's
just running locally.
So I couldn't take advantage
of a large cluster or
anything like that
because everything's
running one on one machine,
which is fine, I guess.
It's often used for testing or
development because
yeah, it's not scalable.
There are cases
where I think it is
useful for real things as well.
If I want to do all my
computation on a single machine,
but I don't have
enough memory to
keep all my data and
memory at the same time.
This would be a nice
way to do it because
the computation will happen
on one partition at a time.
And so I could still doing this.
I could work on some
datasets that are bigger
than what say like
Pandas could deal with.
Alright, Cel. So
I'm head over here.
And if you go to my lecture
snippets for today,
I have a link here to
some starter stuff.
I have a docker file there
and also a Docker compose.
And let's just take a
look at that briefly.
So let me make this
a little bit larger.
Great. And so I have
a Docker file first. I'll
take a look at that.
Kind of pretty typical, right.
We've already seen how
we install HDFS before.
And installing Spark
is actually very
similar. What are we doing?
We're downloading a
G zipped tar file.
We're decompressing it, and
then it's installed, right?
That's installed just a
lot like it does for HDFS.
You know, We have that Pi
spark wrapper around it.
Uh, we have the JVM as before.
There's some kind of
Java environment variable
stuff we have to do.
Anyway, nothing too crazy here.
And so you could build this.
And if I look at
my Docker Compose,
that image that I built from the
Docker file is
called Spark Demo.
And even though I have lots of
different services in here,
what I thought might be
convenient would just be to have
the same image for all the
different types of service.
I just have to build one thing.
Do a Doctor compose
up and I'm good.
Now,
they have different purposes,
these different containers,
and so the way I deal
with that is I would put
in different commands
for each of them.
Like, for example, this one
is starting Jupiter
inside of it,
and I'm may have the
notebook directory
shared so I can
save my files out,
and I'm may have some
port mapping so that I
can access Jupiter
on port 5,000.
Here I'm starting a name node.
This might actually
help you with the
current project, by the way.
It's often natural that when
you're starting a container,
you want to do multiple steps.
For example, maybe you want
to format a name node, right?
And then actually
start a name node.
You can only put one docker
command in for start up.
And so the trick
here is I say, H a,
my one docker command
is to run a shell,
and I'm just trying to
pass at this sting.
Well, guess what this string
has two commands in it.
Kind of just a dirty trick.
I mean, the other
thing you could do,
which might be a
little bit cleaner,
and you actually did
on Project one is
that your one start
up command could
be a shell strap
like a dot SH file
and you can put whatever
you want in there.
So, you know, figure
out what you want to do
with P four. I either
would be fine.
Either the old way or
this kind of dirty hack.
I may have one data node
talking to the name node.
And then down here, I have
my executors and these workers,
and I may have two of them.
I'm going to tell
them that they each
have one CPU, right?
That means in this cluster,
I can run two tasks
at a time at most.
And then up here, I
have a boss, right?
So a lot of systems have
this architectural.
You have one centralized
boss and a lot of workers.
Sometimes different
vocabulary is used for that.
So for example, in HTFS,
the boss is called a name node.
The workers are
called data nodes.
Another name that
you might sometimes
see is they might call
it like a master.
I think the systems community
is getting away from
that because it has
this kind of nasty association
with slavery, right?
But anyway, if you see strips
like that you should
know what it is, right?
That's starting the boss node
in my cluster, and that's
what this is doing here.
So I can do a Docker compose
up, which I've already done,
and that will bring up all of
these many containers
that are part of
this little project that
I'm doing right now.
And if I head over
here to Jupiter,
then I should be able to start
interacting with
this Spark cluster.
So may come to the snippets,
and there's a bit of code
here I can use to connect to it.
I think it warrants a
little bit of explanation.
I'm just going to pause
here for a moment.
First, I'm going to import
from Pi Spark I'm to
import this Spark session thing.
And inside of Spark session,
they have this thing
called a builder.
And a builder is a
special kind of class
that has a very
particular purpose.
Job is to create new objects.
And I think the way most of
you have probably
seen many times
actually is that you create
new objects by invoking
a constructor.
And maybe the instructor has
lots and lots of arguments.
And then based on
those arguments,
it will actually initialize it.
That's one style for
creating objects.
Not everybody likes that style,
because if the language does
not have default arguments,
then it's kind of
annoying having this long
list of arguments, right?
So that has led to
this other style
of builders for
creating objects.
And so the way it works is
that I have this
builder object here,
and I can say something
like app name,
CS 544, and that's going to
return a builder object.
Again, it's actually
returning itself.
And I can have
other things here,
like I could specify the
boss node like that.
And that will again
just return itself.
And the idea is that I can call
any combination of
functions like this,
and each function configures
something that's going to
used for creation later,
and it also returns itself.
I have a long chain of
configuration is a little bit
more readable than
having just like one
constructor with
lots of arguments.
So anyway, that's what's
happening up here.
It's creating all this
stuff, it's configuring it.
And at the very end,
I say G or create.
And so when I run
that, that's going to
spin up some JVM stuff.
I I start running
my spark driver.
It's kind of slow honestly,
but once it's up and running,
at least it's scalable.
So I'm going to do that.
And this G or create,
I should be a little
bit careful about that.
If I were to run this line
of code again, it
will say, Oh, great,
you already have an app named
CS 544. It won't re run that.
So it's faster the second time.
It's also annoying because
if I change these settings,
and it's already there, it won't
pick up my new settings, right?
So When I'm doing
a Git or create, if I
want to change that,
then I'm going to have to make
sure I actually shut down
my notebook and restart,
so I pick up the new one.
All right, fantastic. So I
have the Spark session now.
And with the Spark session
is usually how we're
going to interact with it
via SQL or data frames.
But internally, they
have a Spark context,
which is getting back to the
roots of when Spark started.
The Spark context
is how we interact.
Directly with RDDs, right?
And normally, people are
not interacting
with RDDs directly.
They're either using data
frames or SQL, right?
Because that's easier, and it
makes more sense in
like 95% of the cases.
I like to start here
though because I think
it's really important
pedagogically to
understand what's
happening internally so
we can optimize later.
We're going to do some
stuff with RDDs and
the spart context is
how we would do that.
Alright, so I have
the Spark context,
and I can give it
some data, right?
So maybe I have a
range of numbers
0-1000000. I could have that.
Maybe I get a list
of those, right?
So I could have some numbs here.
Let me just take a peek at
like the first ten of them,
so I start counting
up from zero.
That's all fine and well.
And so then if I wanted to,
I could turn these into an RDD.
I could say a spark
context that parallels,
and I could pass in
however many numbs I want,
and that would give
me on RDD. Great.
So I'm going to have that
RDD and I can look at it
and it's type suggests
that it's an RDD.
Things are going well so far.
And then I can do different
operations on it.
I could define some
kind of function here,
and then based on that,
I could say RDD dot map,
and I could put that function.
In a lot of cases where I have
functions that really have
a single purpose like this.
And so there's a shortcut
in Python call the Lambda.
Lambda is just kind of an
anonymous, simple function.
And instead of doing
that, I can say Lambda,
and I have to say
arguments here and then I
say a return value down here.
And that's what
I'll do right here.
So what I may say is I
want to get n verses.
And for every X in nums,
I want to get the n verse of it,
and that would just
be one over x.
And I'm just wondering,
does anybody have
any thoughts like,
what will probably happen
when I run this line of code?
Yeah, go ahead. Zero vision.
Okay, I always catch
somebody. Yeah, I
was hoping that
somebody will say that.
And surprisingly,
I should have a zero vision
arr, but I don't, right?
And now, this is a good
point to stop and think,
Okay, Spark is doing
some things that
are a little bit different
what we're used to.
Why did I not get an
error? Yeah, right here.
It's not actually running it.
All it did is that it
created a recipe for
how to get the verses,
and it doesn't realize
that the recipe is bad
until I would actually go
along and try to do it, right?
So I could even have other
transformations on here.
Nothing bad will happen
until I actually
try to look at the data, right?
So let's try to try
a pause to make sure
people understand it.
People understand why there's
no error. Yeah, right here.
I'm curious what the
previous lights.
What does. Yeah, so this
returns on RDD for me.
It's basically trying to
take this python data
and make it available as
spark data that I
could operate on.
That makes sense? Yeah. Mm hmm.
Yeah, other questions
people have?
All right. So, right?
This was just a
transformation, right?
So just a transformation
doesn't do anything
yet. It's lazy, right?
And so if I try to do an action,
right, let me think about
some actions I could do.
I could try to
collect everything.
I would try to bring
back 1 million numbers
that would try to
bring everything.
Often, to just make it faster,
I might try to take
the first ten, right?
So this would be an action.
And because it's an action,
I'm going to get an
error down here, right?
So this is an action,
and it triggers.
The prior transformations,
including the divide
by zero, right?
I'm going to do that. And
this will run for a while.
And it's probably failing
and retrying some
stuff honestly,
right now, often it'll retry
automatically for you.
So initial job has not
accepted any resources.
That's not Dred. So I
wonder if I Somehow,
I'm wondering if the other one
needs to be shut down first.
I shut down the other one?
Would that help me? Let me
just shut down all and see
if I can get a clean start.
Sometime do you see that forever
reason if there's no workers
or something like that,
then it might say, Hey,
this job hasn't
even started yet.
So not what I was
wanting to show,
but also something
interesting to see.
Let's see if we have any
more luck this time.
And that's not good.
So what this means is
that the Oh, I think
that might be better.
Okay, great. I think it's
actually running now.
Maybe from the morning lecture,
still using some resources
and I couldn't get
resources now.
Okay. And it crashed, right?
And you can see that
for division by zero,
this is probably the
worst division by
zero message that anybody's
ever seen, right?
Way down at the bottom, I
can see my code, right?
Here's the division by zero.
And you know, this is a
notebook, so it's even worse,
right like it's doesn't
tell me what cell it is,
but I guess when it
was running that cell,
they put it in some
file like this.
It was like line
one of some cell.
If I draw up further,
I can see, there's some
java stuff going on, right?
Because we're in the JVM.
I go up further, there's
some scala stuff.
And so the takeaway is that
some very simple benign errors
give you these very nasty
output messages, right?
So don't get
intimidated. Slow down,
dig through, find out what
you need to know from it.
I don't know Scala either,
but I can still dig through
and try to figure out
what happened, right? Cool.
That's an action. Can't do that.
Another action that I could
have is like inverses mean.
It actually has to do the
inverses before it can
try to the means,
so that's going to fail
as well. Same thing.
And so I think one of the
things that everybody should be
familiar with is that there's
different operations
I should do,
and you should
start making notes,
which ones are which ones are
actions and which ones
are transformations.
So how could I actually
do this correctly?
Well, I think that I
have the inverses.
Well, actually, let me
go back to the RDD.
What I could do is I could
actually filter it first,
and I could have another
Lambda function,
and for each number, I could
return a Boolean, right?
And so maybe I
could do is I could
say if X is greater than zero,
so that would help me out.
And then after that, I
could say, do this map,
where I say, Land
of X is one over x.
That would give me some
inverses over here.
And then if I wanted to, I
could actually have
real actions, right?
I say verse dot mean.
Mostly the number will be pretty
small. I mean, I
have like 1 million.
As X gets pretty big.
These numbers will be
small. And then there we go.
I can see that I got this number
back here, which
seems plausible.
All right. What else might I do?
I might do things like,
say verse dot, take ten.
That would be another
action, and then
I could get like the first
ten numbers out of it.
Yeah, question
right. What's that?
Oh, yeah, that's
a good question.
So if we do the flip of it,
my expectation is that
it should do the
vide by zero, right?
But let's find out.
Oh, but then I actually
have to do an action.
Right? Oh, do the inverse
twice or Oh, I see.
You're wondering if it's like
going to somehow optimize it.
So you're saying, So
you're saying like,
RDD and then I inverse
it and inverse it twice,
and then I guess take the
mean or something like that.
I think it will do it
because I think it
will still divides by zero
before it grows back, right?
So it looks like it does fail.
It does it say divided by
zero. You saw it
somewhere? Okay.
I'll trust that it
said it somewhere.
Thank you for saving me.
Okay, yeah, it's still
doing that in order.
It's the same as if
I actually ran it.
It's just that the thing
that's different from
what we're used to is
when it actually happens.
And when it actually happens
is when the action is there.
Alright, Col. Thanks, everybody.
I'll be around to
people want a chat.
Otherwise, you know, there's
lots more examples I go
to dig into next week.
So I have a fantastic weekend.