They were going to do
a couple of things.
First, we're a wrap up
from Wednesday's lecture.
So we looked at three
of the big resources.
We looked at tribute,
Babary storage.
We didn't have a
chance to talk at all
about networking, so we'll
do a little bit of that.
I have a recording up
from Wednesday as well.
So if you missed for
su reason or you just
got into the course,
that would be a good
thing to review.
There are more Anki
flashcards coming.
How many people have
already installed Anki
and spent at least some
time studying on it.
So just a couple of you.
I think that's really a
good way to get ahead.
What I've seen is that some
people will try to, like,
save them up, and then they try
to cram for the
mid term with it.
I think that actually you
end up spending more time
overall more time of
your life if you try
to do it all at once,
like a little bit here and there
can really help you
remember things.
I think now is the easiest
time in the semester
to make a habit of doing
that. You're not as busy.
And if you start a few weeks in,
well, you have 30 here,
30 here, and all of a
sudden starts feeling
a little bit daunting
to get started.
So I'd strongly encourage
you to just get started now.
That'll give you kind of
an edge in the course.
If you do end up starting later,
there's ways to configure it,
so we'll show you
at, like, most,
say, like 20 new
flash cards a day.
So do something like that.
So whatever it takes to make it,
something that's
not intimidating
and something you actually
want to spend time on.
Alright, cool. So I have a
worksheet for today as well.
You know, I used to
print these, but then,
like, a lot of
people have tablets,
and you know, there's
always some people who are
sick or or don't make
it for whatever reason.
So anyway, I'll leave
these to you all to print.
I'll just send a reminder
when there's one to print.
This one is kind
of a simple one.
It's just a bunch of
terms to remember.
And what I'd like
you to do is as
I'm showing you a bunch
of Linux commands today,
I want you to just write
down in your own words,
what each of these does.
And then you can
check back across
this list later to
see if you miss any.
And we'll actually spend
a couple of lectures
to get through this.
Alright, I'm going to
head back over here,
and we will look at the slides
where we were last time.
And we're going to talk a
little bit about networking.
And networking is really key to
this idea of scaling out
instead of scaling up.
Right? If I have a bunch
of different computers
that are working together
to solve a problem,
they have to
communicate and that
communication happens
over a network.
Let's see how that might look
in a typical data center.
So when you're buying a server,
it'll often look a bit
different than say, like,
a laptop or maybe a deskop
computer you might buy.
They're just trying
to make it compact
in a nice boxy shape like this.
So here's an example of a
common server you might see.
And you can stack all
of these on top of
each other in something
called a RAC, right?
So I have a rack
up servers there.
On the bottom, I have
some power supply,
and also Um, there's
some network switches,
so all of these can
communicate with each other?
They're attached
to each other via
those either net tables.
If I have a lot of
computer resources,
I could have a whole data
center of these, right?
Racks upon racks on racks.
Now, if I have two
machines in the same rack,
they're directly connected
that same switch,
and they can communicate
pretty fast.
And so sometimes people
will try to colocate
two applications
that are working
together in the same place.
Can anybody think of a reason
why you might not
want to do that,
even though it's faster?
Yeah, right here.
Excellent, right? If the
switch goes down and I have
maybe two copies of my data
or something in the same Iraq,
then I would lose it altogether.
So Iraq is what we might
call a fault domain, right?
It's kind of a case
where, like, one problem
could take down multiple
instances, right?
Looking a little
bit more broadly.
I mean, there could be a tornado
or an earthquake or
something like that,
but we could lose the
whole data center,
there could be a
local power outage.
And so that's also
a fault domain.
You could start imagining having
different data centers and
maybe even different countries.
And so we're going
to be talking about
that in the middle
part of the semester.
We're going to be worried a lot
about how we can
be fault tolerant.
When something
like that happens,
how can we make sure
that we don't lose
data or we don't
lose availability?
So for example,
were going to learn
about the Hadu file system,
and in the Hadu file system,
you can configure it,
and you can tell it about
your network topology.
Network topology refers to
kind of the structure of which
computers are connected to each
other directly or less directly.
And so you can see with
the Hadu file system,
you kind of specify that,
and it might take some steps
to make sure you don't have
all the copies of your data
in the same rack or
something like that.
Some of the metrics that we
have with networking are
actually pretty similar to
what we saw for a disc.
So latency Latency is
just a general measure of
how long something takes.
And so there might be different
latency measures people have.
Maybe people just
have a question of
how long it takes to get
from point A to point B.
People might talk about
round trip latency,
how long it takes to send
a message to the server and
actually get a response back.
But ultimately, it's some
measure of elapsed time.
We can also measure performance
in terms of a rate.
So people might talk
about bandwidth.
Bandwidth would be kind of
a theoretical maximum bytes
per second that we might be able
to send over our hardware.
Throughput is also a rate.
Maybe more often used.
It's the same idea,
it's more often
used to refer to what
the application is
actually doing instead of
perhaps the hardware
capabilities.
And with disks,
that's usually measured
in bytes per second,
for whatever reason, when
we're talking about
net networks,
it's more common to talk
about bits per second.
And so people might
say things like this.
They might say BPS.
And the fact that the B is
lower case means it's
bits per second,
and that would be in contrast
with MB over S, right?
So 10 megabits per
second is in bits.
10 megabytes/second would
be 88 times faster.
Often, if things
are lower latency,
I might also have higher
bandwidth, but that's
not always true.
You can imagine a scenario
where this computer in
the middle is talking
with two other computers.
And on the one hand side,
I have a computer that's kind
of geographically nearby,
but maybe my switch doesn't
have much bandwidth, right?
So maybe I can, you know,
send a packet to an
response very quickly,
but I can't send a lot of
data at the same time.
In contrast, maybe this computer
is somewhere else on the
other side of the Internet,
and it might take
a long time for
messages to go back and forth,
but maybe I have a higher
capacity on my connection.
So I just wanted to do
a quick top at to make
sure people are still
good on these units.
I'm going to pop over
here and start that.
And so a computer can
download eight B MB pS.
What is that in BPS?
A 20 seconds left.
Alright, fantastic.
Most people are
saying 64 megabits per second.
Right? There's eight
bits per byte.
So if I'm going from a byte
based unit to bit based unit,
I'd have to multiply by eight.
All right. Cool. So
that's networking.
Let's talk a little
bit about deployment.
Deployment means
actually figuring out
how to go and run
your code somewhere.
That's often quite challenging,
especially if you have
kind of a large cluster,
and you have to get your
software running out
all the different
workers in the cluster.
This semester, we're at
least for the first
half of the semester,
we'll deploy on Google's Cloud,
which is called GCP
Google Cloud Platform.
And basically what all
these cloud providers
are doing is they're
buying large,
powerful physical machines
that are in a data center,
kind of like in that
picture I showed you,
and then they're running
virtual machines on top of it.
And so a virtual machine,
it really kind of feels
like a physical machine.
You can interact with it
in a lot of the same ways.
But it's only using a fraction
of the resources of
that physical machine.
So they might actually pack
on a lot of virtual machines,
and they will rent that to you,
of course, with some
kind of mark up.
I put rented in quotes
because you're going to get
some free Google credits that
you'll use for that
this semester.
Your VMs are going to be
running Ubuntu Linux 2404.
So that's their most recent
long term support
support version.
So I've shared some
details about that.
This link here shows you
how to get those resources.
We need to make sure we
don't run out of credits,
otherwise you have to start
paying out of out of pocket.
And if you follow all the
directions carefully,
you will not find yourself
in that situation.
And so what we're
going to be using is
E two small instances
with 25 gigabyte disks.
And basically what I've done is
I've entered the
daily cost here,
and I show the cumulative
how much you should be
spending of your free
credits by a given date.
So for example, on October 15,
check in and make sure you've
not spent more than $20 Um,
this is what is going to happen.
Unless you somehow
misconfigured.
If you have multiple VMs
at the same time or
something like that,
you might burn
through that faster.
I guess you could
end up spending
a little bit of money depending
on whether that matters to you.
But one way to catch up
would be just be turning off
the virtual machine
when you're not
using it, say, like overnight.
I somehow you make
a mistake and you
need to catch up on the budget,
so you can save yourself
a bit of money there.
We'll see what happens
after October 15.
I think the department's getting
some new servers that will
probably use for a
portion of the course.
So I'll kind of
fill this in based
on when those servers
are ready for us to use.
But we might get
some more resources
than we've had in
previous semesters,
which would be pretty
exciting. So check up on that.
And there's a few
responsibilities that
you're going to have
with regard to your VM,
the semester, you have to
go create it yourself,
and if somehow gets
messed up you're going
to have to recreate it.
You have to figure out what
region you want it in.
I choose Iowa because
it's close to us,
right, so it's going
to be lower latency.
You have to figure out how
to connect it with SSH.
I'll show an example
of that, but you're
going to have to
kind of get that
set up on your computer.
You're going to have to install
some software on your
virtual machines.
As we talk about
like, we just give
you like a strip that
does all that for you,
but I think it's actually
valuable to learn how to
set things up yourself so
that after the semester,
if you have some project
idea, you can go
Do stuff, even if you don't
have the supportive
office hours.
So we're trying to making
you do some extra work,
but I do think it has
pedagogical value.
You might have to
reboot after updates.
Make sure you back up your work.
You know, occasionally,
people's VMs get
messed up and they
might lose work there.
You know, you could
do that by pushing to
a private repository
on ditab or GitHub,
or I'm going to teach
a tool SCP today that
you could use to download
stuff off of your laptop.
And then you have to
resolve any issues
directly with Google
if they show up.
By far, the most common issue
is that they think
people are cryptomining,
and I'll believe
my students that
always tell me they
weren't cryptomining.
Basically,
Google is worried that they
give you free credits,
and then you basically
turn those credits into
money by min mining
crypto, right?
That's against their policies,
and they try to detect,
based on your CPU
usage or whatever,
if you're doing
something like that,
and then they'll
sometimes flag you
and they'll, block
your account for Wb.
H is like, Oh, you're
a crypto mining,
and you just submit
a form saying,
I'm very sorry I
wasn't doing that,
and they're like,
Okay, ok, fine.
You can have another chance.
Anyway, I tried to interject
myself in that process,
and I mean, they're a business,
and they're like, Oh,
you're not the customer.
We will not talk to you.
They're not really set
up to think about while
there's an instructor
and students.
So anyway, You know,
you'll have to
interact directly with
Google if that happens
because they don't
want me as an instructor
in the middle, but it's
always been sorted out.
If you just kind of
follow up with them.
Do it quickly, right
because there might be
some delay to them
getting back to you.
We're also going to be in
addition to virtual machines,
we're to be using containers,
this semester and particular
docker containers.
We'll talk more about what
containers are, but for now,
we can think of it
as a lightweight
alternative to virtual machines.
And so on your one and
only virtual machine,
you'll have this semester.
You can have a bunch of
different docker containers.
And by doing that,
they're going to have
kind of like a virtual
container network.
And so it'll feel like you have
a small little cluster of
systems that are interoperating
with each other.
And you're going to be alone the
same skills you would
directly apply.
Someday when you actually
have a real cluster of
machines available
to you and you're
deploying these systems on them.
So everybody will have
these many clusters
running on top of their
own virtual machines.
A quick conclusion, right?
Systems, manage resources,
whether you're writing
analysis code or
building applications.
You're going to
be using systems.
Maybe you're even making
new systems yourselves.
So this is stuff
we have to learn.
And these systems manage
resources, right?
Like compute memory
storage network.
We want to figure out how to
use systems in a way that we
use those efficient
resources efficiently.
We're learning about big
data systems a semester,
and that means we're
going to be specifically
looking at cases where we need
either specialized
hardware or more
typically just a
cluster of machines.
So I'm going to head over.
We're actually going to
jump in and start doing
some examples on the
virtual machine,
and I've sent direction
so people can
start setting that up
if you would like.
M. Yeah um, so how can we
deploy things on Linux?
I have a few things I
want you to learn today.
I want you to navigate
your way around a
Linux file system,
operate in a Linux shell.
I want you to learn how to
automate repetitive tasks.
You can imagine if
you have to deploy
the same thing on 100 machines.
Wow, that's very important.
Where I learn how we can chain
multiple Linux programs together
to accomplish more
complicated things.
And finally, how can we capture
the output of a
process in a file?
In this kind of environment
that's hugely important,
maybe most of you
are used to kind of,
like running programs and
directly seeing the output.
If there's a bunch of
things running at once,
it kind of makes more sense to
put that output to
different files.
And so we're kind of
redirecting output to files and
then checking up on what
those files contain.
Okay, so to do all
this, you have to get
extremely comfortable with
a program called the shell.
You all have used shells before.
But let's just think a
little bit more deeply
about what a shell is
and what it's doing.
If I was write pseudocode for
a shell, it might look
something like this.
It's just a big loop that prints
a prompt and the prompt means,
tell me something to do.
It takes some input
from the keyboard,
and that input is the
name of some command,
and then it will
run that command.
And it's really a
super helpful program
because it's just
constantly asking,
what can I do for you,
and then it does it,
right, so you can kind
of type those things in.
So there's no graphical
user interface.
We're just doing everything
based on typing.
One of the reasons this is
really powerful is that if
you figure out how to do
it manually via typing,
then you can put
all those commands
in a text file with
some extension,
maybe SH or whatever,
it doesn't matter.
And you can feed
all those commands
from that text file
into the shell,
and it will automatically
do all those steps for you.
How many of you have ever
automated something where
you kind of have to, like,
click buttons or actually, like,
manipulate a real browser
or anything like that.
So a few of you, was that,
like, a fun thing to do?
So if some people are
nodding their heads,
yes, I hate doing that, right?
It's kind of finicky,
and I kind of get it working,
and then, you know,
buttons change position,
and it doesn't work anymore.
So this will be much more robust
and faster than trying to
automate something with a
graphical user interface.
So a shell can let
you run programs,
and a shell is itself a program.
And so maybe you can infer
from that that you can
actually use a shell
to run other shells.
And I'm actually doing that
here. I have a bash shell.
I'm typing some stuff in it.
That's fine and well, and then
putting what directory in.
And then I run ZSH.
That's the Z shell, and
I'll start running that,
and I could start running
commands and that
The most common situation
where you're going to be running
a shell inside of a
shell is with SSH,
which is the secure shell.
And SSH is a special
shell because
it lets me type my
commands on one computer,
but then they execute on
a different computer,
say that virtual machine
that I'm running in
the Cloud, right?
So here I type SSH.
And then down here, I run
some more commands and
those commands are
running in the Cloud.
So that's extremely powerful.
And you're going to be doing
you're going to be living in
SSH this whole course this
semester. Alright, cool.
So I'm I jump over, I'm
going to do some examples.
Just trying to help everybody
get on the same page.
I know some people who have
used virtual machines before,
maybe even on Google Cloud.
So my apologies if some
of this is repetitive,
but I just want to
make sure we're
all coming at it with
the same background.
So right here, I am signed
into the Google Cloud Console.
And what I want to go to is
their Compute engine because
under Compute Engine,
they have a virtual machine.
Instances, and I have a few.
If you have a few that's
probably actually
a problem you're going to
burn through your credit,
but I was just try
messing around.
I only have one really
running right now.
And you can see this
one's up and running.
And I can see that it has
an external IP address.
I'm going to click on
this to copy that.
We may be talking
more about networking
and IP addresses
pretty soon, actually.
But what I can do now is
I can use a secure shell,
and I can say my user name at,
and then I can paste
that IP address
and try to get access to it.
So, okay, great.
What is my user name?
So I'm mana come
over here and I'm
going to go down to metadata.
And under metadata, I have
these things called SSH keys.
And I actually see
I have two of them.
You'll just have one,
and you're going to have
to create it yourself.
And I'm going to
use this one TRH.
I'm going to put that SSH,
my user name, and then that
IP address. You to run that.
And now I'm inside of
my virtual machine,
and I can run commands here.
So how did this SSH
stuff get set up?
Well, I created what is
called an SSH key pair.
The way I did that
is I came over here,
and I ran this program
called SSH key gen,
and it kind of walked me through
this step a few steps you
can kind of go through.
I'm not trying to
do it right now
because I already did it before.
I actually hit Control C.
Control C doesn't copy things,
that actually kills
what I was doing.
Anyway, that will generate
a key payer for me,
and it's showing
me right here that
this is where one
of my keys will be.
So let me just take
a look at this.
And This one that it
generated is what we
call a private key.
And a private key is really
an alternative to
like a password.
That's what how I show
that I am, who I say I am.
So I'm not going
to show you that
right now because that
would be terrible.
All of you could do all
kinds of horrible things.
What I will show you is what is
associated with
that private key,
and that's the public key.
So here's a public
key right here.
So these two things
come in a pair,
and I think the private
key, it works like
an actual key based on
your intuition, right?
I kind of open
things up for you.
I think the public key,
maybe it's more intuitively
like a lock, right?
We can put the public if you
install a lock on something,
you have the key for it,
and you can open it.
So things you might
do is you might put
your public key on Git Hub,
and then it'll
give you access to
if you have the
corresponding private key.
I might put my public
key on the Google Cloud,
and then I can get access to
those VMs because I have
the associated
private key, right?
It's try to I'm comfortable
showing you my public he
is there's not much
you can do it.
You can just give me access
to stuff, and if you do, why?
Thank you very much. So what
I could do is I could copy this.
And I've already done this.
I'm not going to do it again.
But under this
metadata SSH stuff,
what I had done before
is I pasted it in,
and that's how I was able
to get that set off.
And you can actually see
that I had done it twice.
I actually have two
different users
each with a different SSH keys.
You might end up
in that situation
if you like switch laptops,
mid semester, I guess I' just
having fun with SSH keys.
I be kind a little bit weird,
great, but whatever
is fun for you.
Cool. So I was able to do that.
Because I have that is
why I'm able to do
this SSH, right?
So when I do this SSH,
let me just do it again.
When I'm doing that,
it's automatically
finding my private key.
If I had more than one private
key I'm like a more course,
I might have to change it a bit
to tell it which one I'm using.
But because I have
that private key,
I don't need to password
or anything else.
That private key says,
I am who I say I
am, and I'm able to
get get access to
this virtual machine.
Right? So if I type up here
it's on my virtual machine,
I I hit Control D, Control D
means I'm done typing,
and I drop out of it.
Now I'm back to typing
things on my laptop.
You know, I could do
like SSH, TRH each time.
That would be
annoying. I can use
up and down arrow keys, right?
To get to these
different commands.
That's one thing I can do Let
me just do Control
C to kill that.
The other thing that's
going to be a big
time saver is Control R.
If I do Control R, I can
do a reverse search,
and I start typing SSH,
and I jump back to that
previous command, right?
So it's really important.
If you get dread at
all these commands,
you memorize them,
you're going to have be able to
complete this course
with spending less time,
and it'll be more enjoyable.
So get dread at these commands.
It's really important.
Alright. Fantastic. So now
I am on my virtual machine.
Maybe I just pause
there because maybe
some of that is
new to some folks.
People have any
questions about my BM
or my SSH keys or any of that.
Yeah, right here.
Cloud.
Are we supposed to be at
this at this point or Yeah,
I think that I didn't add
anybody to anything, right?
I think that if I come back
here or where it was it.
So I updated all the
links to on Project one,
if you just start
doing Project one,
it will tell you how to get
access to the stuff, right?
So you'll have to go to
this Canvas page and that will
tell you how to get
like the free credits,
and you have to create
an account with that.
So I don't know if you've had
a chance to look at that.
So drove through that and
if you get stuck on that,
you know just show somebody
in person like during
office hours or after lecture
and we'll make sure
everybody gets on.
Yeah, Thank you.
Yeah, other questions
people have. All right.
Cool. So I'm on my
virtual machine,
and I can start running stuff.
One of the first
things I do is PWD.
That shows me the
working directory.
So one of the things
you're ready notice is
that I'm not trying to
use the word folder,
I'm going to use
the word directory.
They mean the same thing, but
directory is the
more technical term,
and all the acronyms have D
in them for directory, right?
So if you remember
directory, you remember the.
So print working directory,
that means that this is
the location I'm
currently in right now.
It's one of the first
commands I run when I jump on
a on a new environment.
The other thing I
often run is I run LS.
LS is short for list,
but it shows me what
files are there.
You already notice
that Linux commands
are notoriously turf.
That means they're going
to be harder to learn,
but once you learn them
you're going to be a
lot faster, right?
I don't know how many
hundreds of thousands
of times I've typed LS,
but probably adds up that I've
been typing two characters
instead of four.
So spend time, get rid of these,
and then it's going to save
you time in the long run.
Let's talk about files.
Let's create some files on here.
One way I can create a file
is with the Touch
command, right?
So if I touch example dot TXT,
and then do LS, I see
all of a sudden I
have an empty file there
called example dot TXT.
I probably want to edit
it and write something
inside of it.
So I need some kind of editor.
Now, in an intra level
course, I would tell you, Oh,
use exactly this editor,
whatever it is I
want you to use.
We're in an upper level course.
I think now is a point
where you can kind of,
like, explore different editors,
figure out what you
like, find one tool,
get really good at it, right?
And so I'm just trying to
quick show you a few options,
and you can talk
with your friends,
see what they're using,
do a little research.
One of the simplest
command line editors.
I'm kind of interesting in
command line editors
because I'm inside
of SSH right now is Nano.
And so I could do NO this,
and I could say, hello, world.
Why is Nano so simple?
Well, all the
commands you need to
know are right down here
on the bottom, right?
So that little arrow
means control.
And so if I say control X,
I know that's going to it
for me, right? I can do control.
Oh, H. I can do control X.
See how simple it is to use.
So Control X, do I want to
say buffer is just
my memory file?
Yes, I want to save it.
That sounds good to me.
And then I can see
it's there, right?
Another editor you might use.
That's a bit more complicated,
but we'll save you
some time is VM.
And so I'm going
to do VM on this,
and I can open it up, and I
can see it's the same thing.
Do you have any Vn
users in the room?
Yeah, maybe maybe
ten or 15% of you.
So I think that's kind of one
of the more popular
command line ones.
I'm not a VM user, but kind of,
like, what is interesting about
is it kind of switches
between, like,
a typing mode and
a command mode,
and I can hit escape to
kind of toggle those.
And so when I'm here
in the command mode,
I can say colon, and
then I could say Q.
And then I could quit out
of that if I wanted to.
The one I'm going to be
doing my examples in
because I'm most familiar
with it is EMAC.
Any EMAC users in the
room? A few of you.
Cool. So I'm going to use E MAC,
and then I can edit this and
change it however I like.
Alright, C, I can do
any of those, right?
So those are all options.
Another thing that's
becoming very
popular is visual studio code,
any visual studio
code users here.
That's graphical,
but it would still
it has like an SFH plug in.
So you kind of have
that graphical
experience on your laptop,
but you can edit files remotely.
And so you can look
into that if you want.
Actually, Under resources, I
have these lecture snippets,
where sometimes I
just like paste
random stuff that I might
give people access to.
So you can see some
links here for
visual studio code
and the SSH bug in.
So feel free to do that
if you like, as well.
I think the important
thing is choose
one thing and get really
good at it, right?
So you can operate quickly
in this environment.
Some of these things
were already installed.
This virtual machine
came with an AON VM.
It didn't have emaCs on it when
I did it before, so
I had to install it.
So I go back and I'm
going to search for APT.
And look for my command I
use to install that, right?
So I have the pseudo
app to install,
and then EMAC with
no user interface is what
I had to install for that.
Let me just get rid of some of
these things to show kind
of a simpler version of it.
So APT is what we use to
install software on Ubuntu.
And when I run it like that, it
doesn't give me access to it.
So I can have access to root or
what we'd call administrator
privileges if I want to,
but I have to say that this
is something I want
to use it for.
I can kind of help me not use
my powers to do something
I'm not very confident in.
So if I come back to
this, the way I can use
those powers is I
can say switch users
And do this one command.
So I can say pseudo, and
then it would do it and
it won't complain about
about the permission stuff.
So you can be using
pseudo freal.
You all have pseudo axis.
Sometimes when you
do something this,
it'll put up a prop,
that says, Oh, this is
like so many megabytes.
Are you sure you want to
install it? Do you have space?
And if you're automating things,
which you all will be doing,
you don't want to be
propped at anything,
is it just like you
want to hit like
go and everything should happen.
And so that's why I might
say d y here, right?
So Apt can have a
dash that means, say,
like, yes to
everything, just get
it installed, get
it done, right?
Alright. Cool. So
That's all good.
Let's get like a real file
with some actual stuff in it.
So if I come back to
these lecture snippets
that you can again
find from the website,
or you could use this tiny URL.
I have a little dataset here
that I'm just going to grab
and use as an example.
Somebody come over here.
I'm going to download
it using W GT,
so we'll get something
from the web.
And again, like, your notes now
should have a bunch of
commands in them, right?
You should have W
G, SSH, LS, PWD.
All these different things
we've been learning, right?
So I'm going to do that, I'm
going to download that file.
If I do LS, I can see now
I have that right here.
If I wanted to, I can move it.
I could say move, and then
I could say that and I
could say like some
directory I wanted to go to.
I could also give it a new name.
So Move is also for renaming.
So this is the old name. This is
the new name. I'm
going to do that.
LS. I can see that this is gone,
and I have stations instead.
CP is for copy, right?
So I could copy stations,
and maybe I call
that backup dot TXT.
Those are commands
you're going to be using
all the time to just
move stuff around.
Sometimes I might want to copy
something not on
the same machine,
but I might want to copy
it to a different machine.
Maybe I want to copy
my homework off of
my virtual machine onto my
laptop for backup purposes.
I'm exit out of the
shell right now.
And maybe, what is a
shortcut to get out
of here? Right here.
Control D, excellent.
I'm out of here now.
And this is going to be
a combination of SSH,
which we've seen and CP,
and the final thing
is just called SCP.
I'm actually trying
to go back to
that SH command. I'll do SCP.
And what I can do is I
can say colon after that,
I can say my VM file.
Space, and then
I'll say, where I
want it to go on
my laptop, right?
What file do I want there.
And so on over here on
my virtual machine,
it was called stations dot TXT.
And I have to say what
directory it's in,
and I was just trying like
in my home directory.
That's where I land by default.
And Tilda is basically a
shortcut from my home directory.
So I can copy that, and I
can tell whatever I
want over here, right?
So I can maybe call this
my Stations dot TXT,
that will download it from my
virtual machine onto my laptop,
and then I can open
up my stations,
dot TXT if I wanted
and use it there.
All right. So let me pop back
into my virtual machine.
So I could download it and I
could view my data that way.
Another thing I can do is I
can actually view it on here.
A lot of these
commands are named.
Again, you just have to memorize
a bunch of stuff here at the
beginning of the semester.
So CAT is a way to see
what's inside of a file.
So I can say CAT stations at
TXT and try to dump
what all is there.
That kind of took a
while and if we're
actually dealing with
like a serious data set,
it will take even longer.
So some other commands people
typically use are head and tail.
T's just the beginning
or just the end, right?
So I could say head of stations.
By the way, when I'm typing
this, like, don't
type the whole thing.
L type a couple of
letters and hit tab.
That's going to save
you a lot of time.
I could do head of stations,
or I could do tail of
stations if I wanted to,
and I could get either like
the last ten or the first ten.
Right? So you should
be kind of like
noting down like what
these commands are.
And I also want you
to be able to go and
learn more details about
how these commands work.
Now these commands might be
on different versions of Linux,
they might be on Mac,
maybe it's on Windows.
I don't know. And so one of
the challenges is
when you Google it,
sometimes you'll see directions
for it that don't
apply to your system.
And so it's actually really
useful to be to look up
directions directly on the
system you're working on.
And so one of the ways I
could do that is I could
say tail dash Hell, right?
This is an example of
a flag that a lot of
commands have that can
give me some more
directions, right?
And I can tell me
more how to use this.
And so maybe instead
of getting ten lines,
maybe I only wanted
like three lines.
And so can anybody just kind
of read through this and see
any flags I can use to just
output the last three lines?
Yeah, right here. Dash
in. That was fast.
Excellent, right?
I can do dashN,
and I can say three
lines, right?
So I can say tail the
stations and dash in three,
and I would get three
lines or I can do
five lines or however many
I want to have, right?
So get d red at kind
of looking up
documentation like that.
It's going to be
faster than Googling,
and it's going to
be more accurate
because it's actually
on your system.
Another one that I
want you to know.
So N F is maybe super
useful a semester.
This is called Tail
with following.
So, like I said, right,
you might be running a
bunch of different programs
and it doesn't
make sense to have
all the output coming
to the screen.
You may be redirecting that
output to the various files,
but you might want to watch for
a particular process
like what the output is.
And so you could look at
Tail of a log file.
But maybe that log file
is constantly growing.
If I do a dash F on
it, it'll follow it.
And you can see, like,
it's still running
right now, right?
So if there's more stations
that are appended to this file,
it'll just keep showing
those as they keep coming,
right? So it they'll
run forever.
And it's nobody's writing
to the file right now,
so it's not very interesting,
but I can follow that file
if If I want to kill it,
I have to do Control
C. Control C
kills whatever it is
I'm trying to do.
Oh, right. Cool.
So that was files. Any
file questions so far?
Fantastic. So files live
inside of directories.
And so let's learn a little
bit about directories.
Maybe I'll make a directory.
So MK for M and
DIR for directory,
and I'm going to make
one called Data.
So I do that, and if I do
LS, I can see all of these here.
Maybe I kind of have a hint that
it's a directory
based on the color,
but it's not really telling
me all I need to know. Right?
Like it's not necessarily
obviously, it's a directory.
I need to get more
information out of LS.
Let's learn a little
bit more about LS.
I could do LS help,
like we did before.
Another thing I could do
is I could say, Man, LS.
Man stands for manual,
and your Linux distribution
comes with a manual.
Isn't that fantastic?
So I could look up in the
manual and see what LS does,
and I can kind of
stroll through here.
And it actually has quite a lot.
You could spend a lot of kind
of time reading through this
and getting proficient.
But I can see that L will give
me a long listing format.
So let's see what happens
when I go back to LS,
I do L. Now I see instead of
putting these horizontally,
it puts them vertically,
and there's a whole bunch of
other information
that trues with it.
One of the things
that trues with
it are these permission strings,
and those kind of permissions
tell you what you can
do with a resource.
And we're going
to be looking and
learning what all
of these things do.
But the very first
character tells you
whether it's a directory
or a file, right?
So data is a directory,
so I have a D here.
These other ones where it's
a dash are not a directory,
so that is kind of implying
they're a file in that case.
I can kind of go through and
read what's going on there.
Other flags are useful are H.
So this column right here is
telling me how many
bytes there are.
And that's a little
bit hard to read.
It's kind of a large number.
If I say H, that means do like
a human readable
format, and I say, Oh,
this one is 11 megabytes,
or this one's 4 kilobytes.
I can see it like that.
These are flags, and it
depends on the tool,
but a lot of flags, the
order doesn't matter, right?
So LH, HL, doesn't matter.
I can get the same output.
Another flag for this,
that is very important is A.
A means, show me
everything, right?
I do A and there's
a bunch more stuff.
The stuff that I got
now that was missing,
where all these files here.
They all start with a period.
Files and directories
that start with a period,
and Linux are what
we call hidden.
They aren't shown by default.
If I want to see everything,
including the hidden stuff,
I'm going to run that
to see what is there.
What happens if I go inside of
the stata directory and I
run that command again.
I actually see that
even though I didn't
put anything inside of
the stata directory,
there are two things
that are already here,
and I almost don't even
really think of these as
real things that are existing,
even though they are, because
I almost think of them
as like aliases, right?
So the dot is like an alias
for the directory I'm
currently in, right?
So if I do LS dot,
that's the same as just LS.
And dot dot means one directory,
right? So let me just see.
This is the directory
I'm in now,
cd dot dot, This is the directory
I'm in now, cd dot dot.
This is the directory
I'm in now.
You actually see
that that dot dot
was a relative path, right?
If I say cd dot dot,
where it ends up really
depends on where I started.
It was relative to
where I started.
We can use relative paths or
absolute paths in
general, right?
So I could do CD back to TRH.
Actually, let me
just see this here.
I could say CD back to TRH,
which is my users directory,
or I could say CD home TRH.
So this one was a relative,
I was relative to where I was.
This one is an absolute.
It tells me from the top
directory all the way down,
where exactly am I going?
You might see that under
this home directory,
there's actually things
for a few different users.
And I kind of actually did that.
The common thing
is that a student
will come to me panicked
and they'll be like,
Oh, I lost all my homework.
And the most common reason
is they switch laptops
or something like
that or somehow
they end up with
a different user,
and the new user doesn't
have any files, right?
So that happens. Well, talk
to me if you want,
but don't panic.
L check here first.
There's probably under
a different home
users directory.
Yeah, question right here.
Oh, that's an
excellent question.
What's the difference between
this one and this one?
So I'm an EMAC user,
and EMAC will automatically
create backups for me,
and backups, it just
puts a tilt at then.
So it's like an E MAC thing, and
other programs might do
all kinds of backups.
And I should actually delete
those because I was
going to create those.
Again, thank you for
pointing that out.
That was from the
morning lecture.
Yeah. Anyway, it's
just a backup,
and you'll see that if
you're an Emax user.
Yeah, Drew great question.
Other questions people have.
Again, anybody should feel
free to just pop up
a hand at any time.
I want to make sure
that everybody's
following along and getting
their questions answered.
All right. Fantastic. So
let me come back here.
And what I want to do
now is I want to try
creating a file here
because we're going a learn
about some permission stuff,
and when I try to
create test at TXT,
which I actually just deleted,
it says, permission denied.
I have permission to create
stuff in my home directory.
I don't have permission
to create stuff here.
So I could do, like,
a pseudo if I wanted to,
and that would work.
Or what I could do is I
could try to switch to
the root user in general.
If I just say SU, that's to
switch to a different user.
And so it's asking me, by
default, it goes to the root.
It's asking me what is the
password for the root?
I actually never set that, so
there's no password
that's going to work.
I'm going to do control
C. And so there's
this weird pattern
you'll sometimes see
it's pudo pseudo Su.
So pseudo means do
one thing as root,
and that one thing I'm going
to do is switch to the root.
If I'm switching to
the root as root,
I don't need to pass
word. So I do that.
Now you actually see I'm
running as the root user,
and now I can do whatever
I want as a root user.
So I may say, Touch test at TXT.
Then I have that file here.
And then maybe
I'll just edit it.
I'll say test at TXT,
and I'll say hello
from root file.
A fantastic.
And if I want to, I can
see what's inside of
it. All that works.
If I do control D, I'm
may pop out of the root
and back to my regular user.
I'm going to try this again.
Can I see what's
inside of this file?
And kind of surprisingly I can.
I can see the root users
data in some cases, right?
So why is that? We have
to dig in and actually
understand how Linux
file permissions work.
And so I'm do is
I'm may do an LSL.
I'm going to look at
this test dot TXT.
And I'm to look at these
ten things over here.
There's always ten
characters at the beginning.
We talked about the first one.
That's whether it's a
directory or a file.
And then there's nine here.
And the nine comes
in groups of three.
It's RW X, RW X,
RW X, that stands for read
the file, write the file.
Execute the file. Execute means
it's like running
like a program.
Some files are programs,
So files are not programs.
Okay? And so why do I have
to have it three times?
Because it depends on who I am.
The first three are for
the owner of the file.
Whoever owns this file
can read it and write it,
but they cannot execute it.
They do not have
permissions to execute it.
Who owns the file? That's
this first column here.
The root user owns
the file and they can
read it or write it.
Okay. The next one is
for the group, right?
So the group for this file,
anybody in that group can
just read the file. That's
a little bit confusing.
That's the second element
that there's a root group,
which I'm in, and then
there's a root user,
which I am not, right?
And so that person can read it.
And then finally, this
last one stands for
other users who are not in
like any relevant group,
and they can just read the file.
And that means I'm another user,
and so I can read
that file just fine.
Okay? So what if I
want to change this?
What I could do is I
could use a CH mod.
And CH Mod works like this.
I say, who is it?
And then what do I want
to change about them?
So, and then I finally have
to say what the file is.
I'll say test TXT.
So who, I'm going to
say that's for others.
And what am I interested in?
I'm interested in being
able to read the file.
So I'm going to do that.
And that's not permitted.
I'm going to do a pseudo on it.
I'm going to do LS again.
And that changed nothing, right?
I mean, I said, let
other people read it.
They already could. It doesn't
hurt to do it more
than one time.
If I want to take it
away, then that means
instead of doing plus,
I'll do a minus.
So I'll say other users can
no longer read this file.
I'll do that. I see
that's been taken away.
And so now as a normal user,
If I try to look at it, I can
have permission denied, right?
If I go back to this and
I give it back to myself,
then then I can
peek on it again,
and I can see what's
in side of it.
Right? So you have to
change that. Most often,
you'll be change
because you might
be writing some little program,
and you want to
make it executable,
so I can run it like
a program. Right?
Even if I'm the root user,
I will get permission denied.
You kind of think the
root Why did it do that?
I'm There we go.
I'll get a permission
tonight if I try to run it,
eventhough I'm the
rode user, well,
if I don't haven't given myself
executable permissions,
I can't run it.
I can give myself
those permissions,
but that doesn't mean
I can do it unless
I choose to give myself
those permissions.
Oh, right. Any questions
about Linux permissions?
Yeah, over here. Yeah. How
would I change the group?
That's a good question.
Is it like change group?
I don't know. It's
not something I do
often. I'd have to look at it.
I wonder if this would change
the group for that file.
Change the group of that staff.
I wonder if I could change
try change the group of test.
Like I have a docker group
on here. I wonder
if that would work.
Maybe I have to just switch.
Alright. So there we can do it.
So it's just CH GRP.
Yep. Yeah. Thanks for asking
and I learned myself, too.
Yeah, other questions people
have. The little
shortcut I did there.
I typed CH. I hit
like Tab tab tab,
and then it showed me the
commands that start with that.
I thought, Oh, say,
change Mod, change group.
All these things are related,
and you can just learn
by poking around in
that way and seeing what
is available to you.
Alright. Cool. So what
I want to do now is see
how we can actually write a
program and deploy it, right?
So I want to be, run it.
I need to make sure all
the permissions are right.
I wanted to work regardless
of what directory I'm in.
And so I'm going to
pop out of here.
I'm going to go back
to my home directory.
And what I want to do
is I want to be able to
run as a Python three program.
Right? I'm may look
at Python three.
I can run stuff in there.
I can say control
D when I'm done.
I want to make a simple
little Python three program.
And what I'm trying to
do is it is tra to count
how many stations there are
in my stations file over here.
Oh, I'm going to move all
my TXT stuff to that data.
All right? So let me
just say look at data,
and then stations at TXT.
I want to write a
little program that's
sin count how many
things are there.
I'm going to show you how we can
then deploy this program.
All right.
So I'm going to make a new
program called count dot pi.
And what I'll do is I'll
say the count equals zero,
and then I want to loop
over all the lines in
that file. So I will open it.
I'll say with open
data stations dot txt.
I'll open that as F,
and then I can just loop over
it for line and F. I can
just say count plus equals
one, and then what?
Then I can just print
off what that count is.
Just have a simple
little Python program.
And let me just exit out of
here and see what it does.
So if I want to, I can say
Python three count Pi,
and it runs, and it counts
how many lines are in that
station's file, right?
So what I want to do is
I want to be able to run
this count Pi program like
anywhere on my system,
and I don't want to
have to say Python
three in front of it. All right.
So let's try that. So first,
I'm going to try to say
count dot Pi like that,
and it's saying that
it's not found.
Where I come back to
that. Help it find
M say very explicitly,
it's in this directory.
So now I know you can find it,
and I can say count dot Pi.
Now it's saying
permission denied.
I don't have permission
to run that.
Why do I not have permission
to run it? Let me check.
M say LL, and I can see,
a, nobody has permissions on it.
Nobody can execute
that file, right?
So let me make it executable.
So I'm going to say CH Mod,
and then I'm going to say
something and then
I'm may say count Pi.
Any thoughts on what I might
put here to make it executable.
Maybe for my user or for
anybody, you can decide.
Yeah, go ahead. Let's try
plus x. I'm going I do that.
There we go. Now other
users can execute this.
Let's try executing it.
And what do we get?
I guess before we got something
about permission denied
when we tried to do it,
it's always good to
pay close attention
to those errors because
if you try stuff,
sometimes you're
making progress,
but you're getting
a different error.
Different error is often
progress. I may run this.
And well, that's
kind of interesting.
I wonder if it's like
looking at the owner for it.
Let me try The CH mod again.
I'm going to say
A for everybody.
I can do it. And then let me
take a look at that again.
I actually thought that
was during to work.
I was a little
surprised that doesn't.
Maybe it's just like only
looks at for me particularly
instead of checking for others
first. And I can do that.
And now I actually get
a different error.
It's not permission denied,
but it's like, Well,
I can run this thing,
but I don't even know
what to expect in
there. What's going on?
Now? Well, Linux doesn't
know what kind of file
this is. Is it Python?
Is it PHP? Is it
Java? What is it?
And so it's assuming that
it's a shell stripped, okay?
That's my problem. And so
I need to tell it this
is a Python program
specifically, right?
Not just some other
kind of random program.
I have to run this
program with Python
like this with the Python three.
And what I have to
do is I figure out
where is Python three.
So this which command is super
useful in your deploying suf
because it shows you where
it's installed on your system.
And so Python three on
my system is at this
location right here.
I'm going to grab that. And I'm
going to come back
to count of Pi,
and I'm going to
put something at
the top called a Shabang line.
And the Shabang
line it starts like
a comment explanation
mark, and then I say,
this is the program
that should be
used to run the
following program.
Right? I'm going to
do this. All right.
And now I ought to be
able to say count dot Pi,
and it works just fine, right?
I can run it like that without
saying Python in front of it.
It's executable, and it
antains information internally
about how to run it.
Now, if I really
wanted to deploy this,
I'd probably want to be able
to run this anywhere, right?
So if I go to like a
different directory,
like I should be able do
count Pi anywhere, right?
And so I have to figure
out how to install it.
And how do I install it?
Well, If I run
something like LS,
that works fine, and LS is
a program in this location.
So there's certain locations on
my computer where it
will look for programs.
And if it's not one of
those, then I have to do
the dot slash and tell
it exactly where it is.
And what I want to do is I
want to move my program to one
of these special
directories where it looks.
And that's defined
by something called
a path variable.
So I do echo path.
And this is actually a whole
bunch of different paths,
and they're separated by colons.
This is a place that look, this
is a place that'll look,
so on and so forth.
Maybe what I'll do is I'll
move Pi, into one of these.
Maybe I'll choose
this one right here.
And let's try that.
And I don't have
permission to put it there
because I'm really kind of
installing it for everybody.
I'll do a pseudo for it.
And now I can just say Tount
top Pi, and it will run it.
If it's not here anymore.
So if I say which on it,
if I say which on Count top Pi,
and I can see there it
is. These little tools.
I kind of like
looking at the path,
running the which command.
Change the permissions on
stuff, adding a haban line.
All those things are going
to help you install stuff
somewhere and make it
generally available.
You know, if I come up
here, I can do it, too.
It'll crash because I
don't have my local file,
which is maybe not a big deal.
I could fix that other ways,
but I could have it there.
On Linux, file extensions
are just for the human.
They just are kind of a way of
telling you what
is probably there,
but it doesn't actually
have any meaning to it.
So if I want to, I can move
this user local
Ben count dot Pi.
And I could call this
like something like Count
demo, if I wanted to.
Oh. And like I said, I
have to have pseudo on it.
And now I just have this
count demo program.
And the way it figures out its
Python is by that a bang line.
Linux doesn't care the
extension, only I care.
So I was able to take my program
and basically deploy it.
It's a generally
runable thing that
anybody can use now
on this system.
Fantastic. So we'll
come back next
time and do more examples.
Have a great day, and
I'll be around for
a while if anybody
has any questions,
so feel free to
come up and chat.