Kind of loud. How is
the volume in the back?
Alright, great. So today
is just a student
driven review session.
So you can ask questions
about anything that
you want to that
will help you prepare
for the final exam.
You know, I print
off some old exams.
Like you could ask questions
off of there, right?
If you've looked at it,
and there's a question you
don't really understand
the answer to.
Of course, all the answers
for that are posted, right?
Or you could just
be asking things
more generally about
different topics.
One message I just said,
I finished drafting the exam,
and so I want to
give you an idea of
the breakdown of
different topics.
Like I said, there's more
weight on the new stuff,
and it's kind of what that looks
like is that about
six questions on
Ta Sparks Strea about
seven questions
on Big y and the Cloud.
And that's the new stuff.
You know, we covered five
major systems this semester?
So I want to have at least
sub coverage. Excuse me.
Kind of echo for me.
I want to have
at least sub coverage of
each of these, right?
So we have three questions,
HDFS, Park, and Cassandra.
You know, there's a bunch
of miscellaneous things
we've learned throughout
the semester.
You should still
be, for example,
traced through for like a cash,
like how many hits or misses
there are, stuff like that.
This is approximate
because I'm still adding
and be moving questions
accounts might change.
There's some questions
that don't really
fit neatly into one category,
but just to give
you a general idea.
Do people have any questions?
Yeah, right here.
Yeah, 29 on the fall 2023.
All right.
Which big query model uses
leftover CPU and
memory resources.
And the answer is
on demand, right?
And so really what we're
working with here is that
we pay for a few
different things,
different cases, right?
There's CPUs. There's RAM.
There's a colossus IO.
And then there's
Closus storage, right?
And so the first
model that they do
is they will just let you
reserve these, right?
And that reservation is called
capacity building, right?
So we have capacity.
You reserve some CPU and RAM,
kind of at a more
expensive rate than
a VM because they have a
platform on top of it.
And when they do
that, of course,
there's some leftover
capacity, right?
Maybe they don't sell all of it,
or maybe people aren't
using it continuously.
And I'm sorry, I should
also indicate that this
is up here as well.
And so what they do is they have
a second billing model that
you just have here, right?
And on demand, I mean, the name
is almost a little bit
misleading, right?
If you demand it, it kind
of implies you get it,
it's really kind of a
best effort, right?
Whatever is left over, you get
the CPU and memory for free.
And then you'll be paid
be paying for Closs IO.
And so we did on
demand billing for
PA and all the
examples of semester.
And because of that,
the Closs SIO can be
measured in bytes,
and that's why each query
we could look at and say,
well, this is how many
bytes are processed.
This is how much it will cost.
So they can have two
complimentary billing models.
Yeah, does that make sense?
Yeah, there are
questions people have.
There right here.
Question 27? Absolutely, right?
Let's take a look at
question 27. All right.
So you want to do a streaming
group by with Spark,
using a Kafka topic as a source.
Great. Okay, the
column you want to
group by in Spark
is different than
the column used to
set the key for the messages
and the Kata topic.
Does Spark support such a query?
The answer is, yes.
It does support such a query.
Anybody kind of walk me
through the details of
how Spark would
execute such a query?
There, right here. Basically
try to look at the keys.
Mm Yeah, I guess,
like the first one.
So there is kind of
some topic there,
that has presumably some key
and that means that
there's already
a natural grouping to the
messages and the topics.
However, that grouping is
not the one we want, right?
I guess we did these
examples, for example,
where we had animal
sightings and I was like,
Well, animal sited on a beach,
and it's a particular animal,
you might want to do a group
by and count per beach
or you might want to do
it by animal, right?
If you're kind of doing
a group by query,
which is like the same key
that TOFCA has
already grouped on,
that's a very easy
thing computationally
to do because you don't have
to move any data around.
So does anybody
want to elaborate?
If we're trying to group
on a different key, right?
Any thoughts on how
Spark is going to be
execute that query?
There are here. You just
shove the data around.
S. Excellent.
Yeah, we're going to have
to shuffle the data around
to bring together
related data, right?
So the data was already
not shuffled into
the groups we want.
So we'll have to shuffle
it into different groups.
And the technique we
would use for that would
be the hash partitioning, right?
So, of course, like
Spark has hash
partitioning baked into it
because it's supposed to be
any kind of SQL stuff
in general, right?
And even if you just
have regular data,
it's not streaming
or anything, you
have to shuffle things around.
And so it's very natural
that here we would just
shuffle using a hash partition
again, and then it can do that.
It would be an advantage of
having Spark streaming be
your consumer instead of
building a consumer yourself.
If you were writing your
own, just kind of, like,
raw python road to
consume these streams,
it would be difficult
to do this operation.
You have to implement
your own shuffle,
which would be challenging?
Yeah, great question.
Yeah, all the
questions people have.
Yeah, right here.
So the first part
you said is correct.
So Spark requires a shuffle.
It does, in this case,
because the data is not
already grouped the
way we want it,
so I can shuffle to group
and how we want it.
What was the second
piece you asked?
Well, I guess you said is
Kafka more consistent?
Maybe, like when I'm thinking
about consistent, I mean,
there's like all these
different technical meanings,
and you can define
it in terms of,
like, you know,
what does it mean for
somebody to be in sync?
And I'm just like
a little bit, when
you're using the
word consistent,
I'm like maybe going
off the rails.
I guess, do you mean,
like consistent in
a technical sense,
or do you mean something else?
In a technical is
Kafka consistent?
I don't know if I would
say it's more consistent.
I mean, I guess,
what we're ultimately trying
to do is we're trying to produce
correct results from the
Spark stream, right?
Like, we want to do a query,
and produce correct results.
And the ways we might get
correct results would be if
there are some messages that
are like double counted or
missed and it needs
to be correct
even if some machines die.
So, you know, in this case,
Spark can take
advantage of KAFKA,
right if somebody
dies, it can go
back and replay it, right?
So, so I don't want to say
KAFKA is like more
consistent because well,
Spark is taking advantage
of its features.
And then Spark has
additional features
that even if it goes back and
replays it to
produce some output
for some kinds of output,
I can recognize, Oh, I have
these duplicate outputs,
and I can suppress it, right?
So we can produce
correct output with
Spark on top of ACA,
if we're writing to say Park.
So I don't know if that quite
answers the question, but Yeah.
Yeah, they're working together,
so I don't want to say,
one is more consistent,
right? Alright, C.
Yeah are questions people have.
Yeah, here.
C two.
There's currently three in one.
Is it like a message two
res one liter Mm hm.
Yeah. Okay. Excellent. Yeah, so
the question that was
being raised was from
Top Pad and maybe I'll just
write something similar
since I don't have that
handy at the moment.
But what we are
imagining, right,
is that we have
different brokers,
right that have different copies
of the same partition, right?
So maybe up here, I
have the leader, right?
And then down here,
I have the follower.
And then I have another
follower down here.
Right. Now, we want the system
to keep working even if
some followers are maybe
either dead or they're
going to to solar.
So we want to have some
tolerance for that.
And but we want to
identify which ones are in a
mostly healthy state, right?
And so the leader will decide
which ones are n sync.
And it can define
that different way.
The more important
thing is that, it's
very clear who is in sync,
and then we're going to take
action based on who
is in sync, right?
So there's a little
bit wiggle room there.
And so let's say
that this one down here
is considered n sync.
By the leader.
And that's based on
this follower is
doing a pretty good
job of keeping up
with the messages that
are up here, right?
And it doesn't have
to be perfect,
but the leader
says, Okay, you're
good enough you're
in sync, right?
And so what I'm going to do
here is I'm going to say,
let's say we have
some messages here.
We have A B C and D. And
then the follower down here.
Let's say this one has a B
C. And then the one down
here has Let's just say AB.
Right. And so we
want to say which
of these messages are
committed, right?
Because the producer
sent us the message.
And maybe that producer
is part of some
application actually,
show something to
the user, right?
If it's like a whatsap message,
maybe I wrote it,
and then it will
pop up and say, Okay, it's safe.
There's a check mark by
or something like that.
Or maybe if it doesn't
that Mark has committed,
I might like hold on to
the message and
retry later, right?
So we ought to know, when can
we tell us like the sender,
the producer, that a given
message is safe, right?
And when it's safe,
what we're thinking
about is, you know,
replicas could die, and in
particular, the
leader could die.
The leader dying is the
worst worst case, right?
So I want to say, Hey,
for a given message,
if it dies, is that
message safe, right?
And, um, Whoever is
the leader has the authority
on what message is at
each position, right?
So, you know, if we
somehow elected this
follower down here,
we would have lost
C and D, right?
And so if this follower down
here is a candidate
for being the leader,
then and this one's
dragging behind this.
It's going to be really hard
to commit anything, right?
And so the rule, right?
The rule is that
sync replicas are
candidates for leadership.
Right? And kind of what
this means, right?
Since the leader based on
some metrics decides who's sync,
then the leader is
really saying, Well,
these are the other
nodes that could
take over for me if I crash,
and that information is stored
in a separate system, right?
So even though the leader
decides that if the leader dies,
we can kind of look
at those notes,
and we can figure out, k, this
is the one that is eligible.
And so the problem here, right,
is that if this sync follower
becomes a leader and it
doesn't have message D,
then D would have
been lost, right?
So what this means is that
D is not committed, right?
This is not committed because
because one of the candidates
for leadership doesn't
have it, right?
And so when I think sync,
I think candidate for
leadership, right?
It's kind of a
funny word for it,
but that's what I'm really
thinking to reason about it.
Right? But this one
is committed, right?
Alright. And so that's
the fundamental thing
about how the system works.
Now, there's this other detail
about the men Sync
replicas, right?
And when I hear that yc,
just based on the name, I think,
I and most people think, Oh,
that's about kind of, you know,
having some kind of minimum
replication factor,
and it does that too.
But The concern here,
right is that if the
leaders going ahead and
all the followers are kind
of starting to fall behind,
right, then eventually
there will be
no candidates for
leadership, right?
If all the followers
get too far behind.
And at some point, if the leader
keeps taking all these messages,
we're going to have a
worse and worse problem.
So what the leader should
eventually do is send
basically what's called a
back off message that says,
Don't send me more
messages for a while.
Lots of systems have
that webservers,
for example, have like a 429.
We see four oh four,
not available.
Web servers have
429, which says,
Hey, back off, don't retry
again for for a while.
The producers are
expected to respect that.
And so the Mint sinc
means that hey,
like, we don't have
as many followers that are
keep input as we want.
Stop sending me
messages for a while,
so they can catch up, right?
So that detail is not so
much about correctness.
It's more about, you know,
we don't want the system
to get too far behind.
You can imagine throwing away
that tail about me Ncinc.
And then it would just
kind of, like, you
know, run away, right?
We would never
elect a bad leader,
but eventually, there might be
no candidates for leadership.
That makes sense.
The Mint inc is about
making sure we have
enough candidates for
future leadership.
Follow. Yeah. Like
message she sort of
committed and she was
left followed Mm hm.
Okay, great. So you're saying
that this leader dies,
and now this follower becomes
the new leader, right?
And then you're
saying the original
leader comes back, right?
Yeah. And first of all,
have you said what happens to D,
and the simple answer
is, it's gone, right?
This one that's
now the leader is
the authority on what
is in the log, right?
So D is lost forever, right?
Okay. Now, I mean,
there's a whole bunch of
other details that
we kind of glossed
over because, you know,
I guess if this were like a you
can imagine a similar class
be like distribute systems,
and we focus more
on those details.
We're trying to focus more
on the big data aspect,
but it is interesting.
L, what would happen if
that other one comes back,
and then they both
think they're the leader
what could happen there?
There's techniques people
have for that, for example,
you can have something
called a lease
where you can say, like, Oh,
like, you are the leader for
the next 10 seconds, guaranteed.
And if you kind of, like,
are offline for a while
and you come back,
you'll know if your
lease expired,
and so you have to go
out to system and say,
can I renew this lease, right?
So it might be the
lease time where we
cannot fully make the
new follow the leader,
but there are techniques
to make sure they aren't
both trying to be the leader
at the same time, if
that makes sense.
Yeah. So anyway, so the new
leader is the authority.
It doesn't matter that the old
leader had extra messages.
Those are lost forever, which is
fine because we never
said they were committed.
Right. It's okay to lose
something that's not committed.
Yeah, lots of great questions.
Yeah, the are
questions people have.
Yeah, right back here.
Planet. Yeah. So the
general question is,
like, can we like, you know,
how does the planet
algorithm work?
So the planet algorithm is
for decision trees, right?
Maybe I should just
bring up some slides
and we can kind of
go over it very
quickly if that
would be helpful.
Let me
Was it this one?
Yeah, yeah, here it was.
So, generally, what
are we trying to do?
Like, we want to build a
decision tree like this,
and every node in the tree
asked a question about
the data, like, you know,
is x greater than five,
if it's a numeric thing or maybe
is y equal to a, if
it's categorical.
And so as we're building this
tree at any given point,
I hope nobody can see it, they?
Yeah, feel free to
just, you know,
shout out if I'm ever
not showing stuff.
At A given point, we have
a partially complete tree.
What we want to do is, we
finalize the top parts,
and we keep growing it down
until we have relatively
few rows at each each node.
There might be other
stopping conditions, right?
And so one of the key
characteristics of
this is it's hybrid, right?
Sometimes a given node
doesn't have very many rows.
And we have few enough
rows that they could all
fit into memory on
one machine, right?
And the classic decision
tree training algorithm,
it just works in memory
on one machine, right?
And so when that happens, when I
have a few rows in one place,
I want to bring
together all the rows
for the same node, right?
And so just looking at
this picture over here,
The way we'll do that is we will
hash partition our data, right?
Whenever you hash
partition your data,
you bring together related data.
The interesting
question is, well,
what is the key that
we're hashing over?
And that is what node
you're in, right?
So I can look at a given row,
and given the decision tree,
I can say, Oh, this is a node.
F. Oh, that row is
a node A, right?
I can do that. And then
when I has partition it,
I can say, Well,
what is the hash
of F? I get some number.
If I want like four partitions,
and I'll mod that
number by four,
and I can bring together
all the related data.
Once I bring together
all the related data,
then I can run
the classic decision
tree algorithm, right?
So that was one piece.
The other piece of
the hybrid one is when
we have Big nodes.
And when we have big
nodes, First off,
we don't want to
shuffle all that
data over the network because
it's expensive to move all
these kind of all these rows.
There's a lot of them
by definition, right?
Even if we do move
them over the network,
the reason I'd want to
do that would be to
bring together all the ones
that are in the same node,
but there's no machine that has
enough memory for it, right?
And so what we have to
somehow do is we have to
look at all these big
nodes, and we have to say,
is there a way to have a
good split point that I can
calculate without actually
shuffling it around?
And so way we do that is we
compute some statistics based
on each of them, right?
So rather than actually
sending the rows,
we send some summary
statistics, right?
And, In general, like,
what we're trying to do
is we're trying to choose
a split point that
reduces impurity.
And impurity could
be something like
variance or there's other
metrics like entropy.
What we want to do is, if
it's like categorical,
where I'm predicting yes or no,
I want to have one branch of
the tree where I
have all the yes,
another branch of the tree
where I have all the nose.
And so what we will do
is we will consider every
possible split point.
Right? A split point is
combination of a
variable like X one,
x2x3 plus some threshold.
The thresholds are not 012,
but I've just assigned indexes
to those thresholds, right?
So for every possible
split point,
I can compute some
stats about that.
And I get partial stats
across all of these different
partitions of the data,
I can sum all of
those up together,
and then I can say,
Well, given those stats about
any possible split point,
which one is best, right?
So I can say, I want to have
a new split point without
actually having to
shuffle the data around.
So that kind of the big
overview you're looking for?
Yeah. People have any
follow up questions
on that or other questions.
Right here.
Class
right now.
Yeah. Yeah. So the question
is about threads and locks.
Okay. So context I shot context.
We're done talking
about plan right
now we're talking
about reads and locks.
The rule with Locks
is that I can't have
two different threads holding
the same lock at the
same time, right?
And that's all you
get. Sometimes people
think that locks are
doing more than that,
but you should just,
like, remember that.
I can't have two threads
holding the same lock
at the same time.
That's all we get.
So for example,
if one thread is holding a lock,
but maybe like the
other thread is buggy,
and it doesn't hold a lock,
it could inter leave.
It could run at
the same same time
because only one of them is
holding the lock, right?
The code is only going
to work if they are
both if they both try
to acquire a lock.
You know, I could have
different locks, right?
So in that case,
I'd really want to
make sure I can
context switch away
from the current
thread because maybe
the other threads
are doing things
that are touching
different variables.
Maybe they don't
need a lock because
they're doing
something unrelated to
shared data structures or
maybe they're touching
different stuff, right?
So holding a lock
does not prevent you
from context switching or
running something else
from at the same time.
It just prevents you from
having two pieces of
code from holding that lock
at the same time. That's
the only thing we get.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, great question.
Yeah, a lot of people
get thrown off on that.
Threat and lock stuff is
definitely very tricky.
Yeah, are questions people have.
Yeah, right here.
Oh, okay. Great question.
So the question is about
dictionary and toting.
And we learned about
dictionary and toting
kind of at the end.
A little bit of the history
here was that there were
a few there were a few
formats. All right.
And so the format,
you kind of like draw
a little picture over
here that happened
at Dugal, right?
And so, you know, first,
they had a Column Mo at Dugal,
and they used that with
the Dremel engine.
Does you remeber why
Dremel is important?
Like what is Dremel used
inside of Big query Excellent.
So Dremel is the SQL
engine that they ended up,
you know, kind of packaging
up Iseling is big query.
And so this at Google
inspired the public format,
which is Park, right?
And inspired Park, which
we've been using a bunch.
And then eventually, right,
it evolved at Google into
something called the
Capacitor format.
So capacitor format.
And, you know, a couple
of the features.
I'm sure they did
a bunch of stuff,
but a couple of the
features I know about
are dictionary and Tading
and run length Tading.
Those are the two
totings that they do.
And these are
independent, right?
You could have one or the
other or both or neither.
And so let me just try to
talk about what they do.
Dictionary tooting is
really useful if I have,
some large strings or
maybe if I have bites,
maybe like the bytes are
for images or
something like that.
And so not only do I have,
kind of these long values,
but they are repeated, right?
So maybe I have this
long string that shows
up many different
different times, right?
And so that's a little
bit wasteful, right?
To kind of have these big
strings that are repeated.
The data is bigger, you know,
I might not fit into a
CPU cash as well, right?
And so the idea
of dictionary and
toting is that for
each unique value,
put it as a value
in a dictionary,
and then assigned it like a
numeric lookup value, right?
So, maybe maybe like the string,
Madison, Wisconsin, appears a
lot of times in my dataset.
I'll say that, you know,
Tad five is Madison, Wisconsin,
and five is short, and so I can
have five in a bunch
of places, right?
So that would be an example
of dictionary toting, right?
Run length and toting
happens is may be useful,
especially when my
data is sorted,
right if I am
looking at my data,
and it's like, you
know, five, five, five,
five, seven, seven,
seven, 77, seven,
rather than repeating
all those values,
I could say something like
there's like four, five,
so there are six, seven,
something like that, right?
And so you can imagine,
Is five an actual value,
or is five an entry in
a dictionary either
would be fine, right?
So you can use these features in
combination or you can use
them each individually.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, question.
Yeah. Other questions
people have.
Yeah, right here.
Semester Yeah.
Exam two for this
semester, question 11,
and that's version one
of the exam or science.
I'm curious like to
speak of the details.
Oh, per cluster
per file.
Okay, great. This
one right here.
So what granularity can the user
specify the block size in HDFS?
And the answer is per file.
And there's not a
fundamental reason.
It's just like we the
people who built HDFS,
that's that's what
they did, right?
You could have imagined
that they could have
just said, Hey,
you create this
cluster, you choose
a replication for everything.
I mean, it's kind of
nice that they make it p
file because You know,
there are good reasons
why I might want to have
files with different
replication factors,
and it's nice that I can
just put them all on
the same HS cluster instead of
having to create
different HDFS clusters.
So for example, if I just
have some data that's
time sitting there long term,
three is a common choice, right?
Maybe I want to
have three copies
of all that for all
those files there.
Now, I might have some special
case where I want more or less.
L, what if I am based on
that original data set?
What if I have a
derivative data set,
for example, by derivative,
I mean that it's just like, Hey,
I do some computation
on this original thing
to produce the second data set.
Maybe maybe like
the secondary data
set that's derivative is like
the first dataset where I'm
applying some kind of filter.
For that data,
maybe it's a little
wasteful to have three
time replication factor
because if I lose the data,
I can just recompute it,
right from the source, right?
So maybe there I decide h,
like, two or one
is enough, right?
So it's kind of nice when I have
that derivative
dataset that doesn't
need as high a
replication factor,
I can just have it
in the same cluster
or maybe like this data
is super valuable, right?
I'm very paranoid
about it, maybe
I have a higher
replication factor,
or maybe the data
is really popular.
Like People are reading
it so much that I
don't want to just have
three data nodes overloaded.
I want to have like a ten
times replication factor,
so there's more nodes that
can help service
reads to it, right?
So it's nice that they
let me do it a profile,
and, you know, just kind
of what they chose.
Now, what about a key space?
So a key space is not
a concept in HDFS.
That's a concept in Cassandra.
And a keyspace is a
collection of tables.
And in Cassandra, they specify
the replication factor at
the granularity of
the keyspace, right?
And there as well, right?
That's just kind of, like
an arbitrary decision
they made. You could imagine.
I mean, it would be
an improvement to
Cassandra if you
could start studying
the replication factor per
table per key space, but, like,
the people building these
systems just decide you know,
how much complexity
they want to build and
how much flexibility comes
with that complexity.
Right?
Yeah, thanks for asking
other questions people
have.
Yeah, go ahead.
A two. Yeah.
Okay, let's talk about
this a little bit
broadly and I can hear
your thoughts. I'll
come back to that.
So first off, you said that hey,
these two kind of have the
data in the same format,
but you said this one has
two copies of the data,
and this one has one
copy of the data, right?
This one has copies in
different machines.
That's just kind of a
naming standard, right.
There's three different
modes that I asked to
do remember the semester and
each of them come
in pairs, right?
It's like the two or
not, there's six total.
Okay. Maybe before we talk
about the load balance aspect,
Can they remind me
what the other two L,
instead of memory only,
what were the other two
that we learned the semester?
Yeah, one with SCR,
that's short for
sterilization, right?
And the difference there is
that when it's memory only,
it has, like, all these
JVM types because,
um, because Spark is built
on Scala and Scala
compiles to the JVM code.
And, you know, these job
JVM types are
notoriously bloated,
like strings are bloated.
You know, integers maybe have
this big overhead if
it's like the object
instead of the primitive.
And so what they
want to do is they
want to serialize it to a
very compact byte format,
that doesn't have
all this waste.
But then all the scala
code compute over.
So with the serialized version,
maybe it might be like four
or five times smaller,
but then I have to do extra
compute to switch it back.
X. That was one of
the other ones.
What was the other
one that we have?
So we have memory memory only
serialized and disc
only excellent, right?
And so, in that case, if
I'm really tight on memory,
right, I might write
it to local disk,
that's still going to be
faster to access than say,
like going through
HDFS again, right?
Or maybe doing a bunch of
computation to get that.
All right. So those are
the three different ones.
And for each of those, it
can be just a single copy,
or it can be two copies, right?
And then what is load?
I guess it just load is like,
work that these
machines are doing.
And I guess when you were
asked me a question,
you were kind of
frame it as like,
Well, you could
argue that there's
more load if there's
more copies, right?
But I guess I'm not quite
asking about total load.
I'm asking about balance, right?
So I'm asking how evenly is
work shared across these
different dif machines, right?
If everybody's doing
a similar amount
of work, it's more balanced.
If there's like one node
that's doing all the work
and all the other ones are idle,
then it's imbalanced, right?
And so what I
was really interested in
here, I mean, I guess,
like the When I'm
thinking about load,
I think about like something's
actually executing.
Not just that it's like
sitting there in
the cache, right?
I mean, we can talk
about like, you know,
memory usage or storage band.
So I'm thinking about load like,
what's actually executing there?
And when Spark tries to
execute on this data,
Israel say, I have to
do some execution,
and it's on this
partition of data,
Israel look at all these
workers and say, well,
that partition is on
this specific machine.
It's not on other machines.
And so then Spark will say,
I can run it on this machine,
and there's no network I owe.
Or I run a different machine,
I have to send that data
over the network, right?
So Spark is always going
to choose to run
it on the machine,
where it doesn't have to
do network io, right?
And so if there's only
one copy of the data,
then whenever I do
computation on that data,
it always goes to the
same machine every time.
Even if that machine is
overloaded, if it's overloaded,
the other ones are IDO, so
it keep sending it there,
so it doesn't have
to do network io.
If it has two different machines
where it has that data,
then Spark can look at it.
I can try to figure out
which machine is less busy,
and it can run run it there.
So it'll help Spark
balance the load a little
bit better if we have
multiple copies,
because we have more choices
about where we run things,
and we will run things
so as to better
balance the load. Yeah.
Excellent question.
Yeah, other questions
people have.
Yeah, right here. Spark
Streaming modes Oh, yeah.
Excellent. Okay.
Spark Streaming,
we have these three modes.
There's a pen update
and complete.
And with a pen,
that means that as
I have new inputs,
I produce more outputs,
but I never change
anything that I
previously said, right?
So if I produce some
output with the Pen mood,
that means it's final, I
can never change it, right?
Because the Pen means that
I keep writing to the end,
but leave the original
stuff intact, right?
And so in a pen mood,
there's some things
computations I
can do and some that I cannot.
So, for example, if I
have some data coming
in and I'm just like
filtering it in some way,
then any output I have
will never change, right?
So a pen mode makes sense if
I'm just filtering or doing
something like
that because while
I have new rows coming in,
I have some new rows coming out,
that doesn't change what I've
already outputed, right?
Now, there's some
things that just
don't work with the pen mode,
for example, if I'm
doing like a group by
with a count, right?
Because let's say I'm
counting animals and I
say there are five sharks,
and I output that.
That means I can never change
that if I'm doing
a pen mode, right?
So then if I see another shark,
I can't say six sharks
that contradict what
I said earlier.
Pen mode means that once
you output something,
that's final, right?
Because that's a pen mode.
That's maybe the simplest one.
The complete mode recognizes
the fact that like
an output I had,
when I say there five sharks,
recognize that I
can change, right?
So previously output rows.
It's not that I just keep
adding rows, but I
change things, right?
That's complete.
So complete means
that anytime I'm
producing output again,
I'm going to produce my
incomplete results set, right?
Even maybe if I
just saw a shark,
I'm going I say, Okay,
there's six sharks,
I also say there's three
dolphins before I output
the whole thing
every time, right?
And so that gets around
the problem with a pen.
And in some cases it's
kind of reasonable, right?
If the results set is small,
it's fine to stump out the
whole thing every time, right?
Now, sometimes it might
be inefficient, right?
Like, I like let's say
there's like a let's
say it wasn't animals,
I was like, I don't know,
bacteria or whatever.
And let's say there's like
100,000 different kinds.
And then I'm outputting
all that again,
just because I saw
like a new sample.
That would be kind
of wasteful, right?
And so the update
mode means that Hey,
I can put a current count
out or whatever sat,
and then later I can change what
my previous stat was, right?
I can modify it.
Now, there's some systems
that I can do that for
it and some I cannot.
Like if I'm writing Parke files,
Parke files are compressed,
and we talked earlier
in the semester about,
if you have some
compressed data,
I can't row in and just
make a small change, right?
Be compression is
based on kind of
redundancy and kind of
not repeating patterns.
And if maybe I kind
of broke that, right?
So Park files, I can't just
throw updated in the middle.
So the update mode,
is not trying to work
with Park files.
But if Spark Streaming was, say,
updating some stuff in a MQL
database or something like that,
it is smart enough it can do
a query that will update
the results there.
That makes sense or Any of those
you want to clarify
in more detail?
Fina. Yeah, update would
often be used for
aggregates, right?
I think that that Complete and
update are ones
that I would well,
first off, I said there was like
a problem with a Pen, right?
And then complete and update
both solve that problem.
Update is what I would usually
prefer because it's just
inherently more efficient,
except not every place
I can write my data
supports it, right?
Some places I can write
my data support update,
and some do not.
Right? So both
update and complete,
solve the problem
with a Pen, Depending
on where I'm writing to update
may or may not be an option.
I would probably prefer
it if it is an option.
That makes sense? Yeah,
thanks for asking.
Yeah, other questions
people have.
Yeah, right over here.
Question.
Walking Oh, yeah.
Does anybody have any particular
numbers for walking the ring,
or at least we could always
make up an example, too, right?
I'll just try to flip
through here and see.
Is there anything with
walking the ring?
I guess here we have a ring.
Can you Can you what is that?
Oh, B I'm on the Here's the dom.
Yeah. Okay, here we have a ring.
And then I have the
token map, right?
So We eventually saw
that we want to have a
single physical node,
owning multiple
parts of the ring
because then when
new nodes join,
we can pass off, you know,
the work at a finer
granularity, right?
It's not that we have
to transfer as much.
So here what I see is that
node one only has one V node.
So it only owns one
range of the ring,
and then node two and node
three have multiple v nodes.
So the first thing
I might do is I m
annotate this, right?
This is node one.
And then node two is
here, and also here.
Great. And then node three
is four and negative two.
Yeah. Okay.
Alright, great. And then
we're assuming two
times replication.
So which nodes are
responsible for
Row token negative five,
assuming the
following token map.
So I'm gonna start at
negative five here,
and then I start walking, right?
And I'm going to walk until I
get two different
physical nodes, right?
I'm going to walk all
the way up until here.
And so in this case,
I'm going to have
node two and three.
Right? So I'm trying
to think what
we want to remember, right?
So first, I draw
a picture of where the V
nodes are on the token ring.
And then Once you have your row,
right, figure out where that
is on the token, right?
Maybe I'll just tell you
what the token is or maybe
you'll have to look
it up if I have
some kind of table,
figure out where that is.
And then, um When I
started that token ring,
we have an exact match,
we include it, right?
So it's inclusive, and then
I keep walking to
the right until I
get whatever replication
factor I want it, right?
If it's two, then
I have to get two
of them or however many.
And then that's like
the main algorithm.
And the only two tricky
things on that are
that I might walk off the
end on the right hand side,
and I just wrap around to
the left hand side again.
That's why we call it
the wrapping range.
That's why we call it a ring
instead of a number line, right?
That was one of
the tricky things.
And then the other tricky
thing is that given
these are V nodes, right?
I'm trying to find V
nodes for my data,
but I don't want to
have two V nodes on
the same machine because
if that machine dies,
then I lost both those replicas.
There's not a lot of
benefits of having
two copies of my data
on the same machine.
So as we're walking the ring,
sometimes we will
skip some V nodes,
right? I'm trying
to find two, right?
And if I don't like
the second one I find,
I'll keep going and I'll
consider it maybe like
the third one, right?
And so the simple case,
like all they do is they skip
multiple V nodes on
the same machine.
You could plug in more
complicated policies
where they might say, Hey,
I'm worried about like a
whole zone in the cloud.
Failing, right?
Because those things
share not working in power.
And so you can have
more complicated
policies where I say,
Oh, I have this V node.
The next V node is
in the same zone.
Som skip it, right?
So skipping policies that
you can plug in help you
avoid having multiple copies of
your data in the same
fault domains, right?
A domain is some collection
of machines or
places where things
could fail together because
they share something.
And then, you know,
the fault is just anything
that can go wrong, right?
Like machine dying or power
going out to a data center or
a tornado, anything, right?
Does that answer the question
about walking the ring?
Yes.
What's that?
Two age Exactly.
If I hit in two twice,
I would skip the
second one and keep
going until I find
something else.
Yeah, exactly. Yeah.
And then I guess,
Like after we identify
these replicas,
remind me like,
what happens next?
Like if I'm reading
or writing data,
what was the other big piece
of Cassandra that
we learned about?
Oh, yes, that was
what I had in mind,
but that's another big
piece of the costs, right?
So, all the nodes
need to know what the other
nodes are in the ring.
And so they do that
with the cos up, right,
because since they all have
that token map right that
tells us which nodes are wear,
we need to keep it in
sync on all of them,
but there could be some
machines down, right?
If the machine is down,
I add a new machine.
I don't want to have to
wait until all the machines
are up to add the new machine.
It's like gossip each
other. So quickly,
all have the same view
of the token map.
That was another
component, right?
And then we're kind of going
back to this though.
So we walk the ring.
And then let's say
they find like
the two or three or however
many nodes are involved.
What would we do if we want
to write data to those?
How will we determine if
that's successful or not?
So I guess here, we identified
nodes two and three.
I'm trying to write some data.
I'm trying to write
some row there.
How will I decide if my right
to those was successful or not?
Yeah, we have to have Xs, right?
So if I get an ac, that
means it was successful,
or maybe I don't
get an C, right?
And if the system is not
available at the moment,
I might not get an C. And so
there are ways we can t
to tune the availability.
Does you remember
what are some of
the variables involved
in that process?
So what I'm thinking of is like
the read and write
quorums, right?
So that's not talking
about it here,
but another component
of the system.
We know that the
replication factor here,
the replication factor
was two, right?
And then there might be
someil details that are
not part of this problem.
What is the how many
do I have to write to
to consider a success and how
many do I have to read to?
If this W is two,
and the replication
factor is two,
that means I can't
write unless all of
the nodes are currently working.
So let's imagine this
was one, for example.
In that case, I'm
going to try to
write two node two
and node three.
But as long as it works
on at least one of them,
I'm going to say, Hey,
it worked your right
was successful.
So that's something
you could tune, right?
And then what would
I set R two here?
If I want to make
sure that anybody
reading will see that right.
Excellent, right? And
so the formula that
we can remember is
that we usually want.
And this is usually because
maybe you have some game
or something where you
want availability
over consistently,
C. Usually want R plus W
greater than R F, right?
Greater than R F.
So for example,
let's say I have these
two nodes, right?
I guess it was in this case,
it's like node two
and node three.
If I'm writing and I just
write to one of them,
I say, Okay, well,
that was good, right?
Write equals one. And
then when I read,
if I only read from one, I
might read the
wrong data, right?
So if I do this, then I
could have read equals two.
Right? So that was those
were of the main pieces,
like, you need to know
how to walk the ring.
And then when we walk
the ring to identify
some number of nodes that
are part of the operation.
And then you need to understand,
well, how to read
and write quorums,
determine whether or not it
was successful or determine
where the data gets
read or read in.
Right? There's a couple
of big pieces there.
You can td break down
and have these skills
independently.
Yeah, there are
questions people have.
Yeah, right here.
You said question
was 16 on this one.
Was this this right here?
Oh, the final review.
Oh, that was, like,
a PDF, right?
Okay, yeah, sure. I
can pull that up.
Yeah, the first semester
I ever talked this.
I didn't have any old
old exams, right?
So I created this
final review document,
which is S 23 final
review. Okay, great.
And you said et
Question 16, right?
All right. Great. So
then you can all see it.
Okay, so replication
factor is five for Kafka.
So we have RF for
kafka and Cassandra.
And the minimum number of
sync replicas is three.
And there are currently four
sync replicas with one lagging.
Okay, great. A message is
read in to three replicas.
So the leader and two
of the followers,
and is it committed?
And the answer is no.
It's not committed 'cause
our data is not safe.
Can somebody tell me what
is something bad that could
happen where I could lose
this data? Right here.
The ser breaks down
the head 46 replica
that doesn't have that.
Excellent. So I'll
just repeat that.
So if the leader breaks down,
and then the fourth
encyc replica
that doesn't have the
message that is elected,
it's lost, right? So the
data is not committed.
We can't say it's committed yet.
So at this point in time, at
this moment in time
it's not committed,
now, as time goes forward,
there's two things that
could happen, right?
One is that and I
guess the good case
is that the fourth nyc replica
will get a copy of that data,
and then it's safe, right?
And then we'll say
it's committed.
That might take some time.
The other thing is that
this encyc replica
is maybe in the process of
becoming like, not in sync.
Maybe it's starting
to lag behind.
So if we wait a while,
the producer is not going to
have to wait forever
for the act.
Because eventually, the
leader is going to say,
Well, this one was in sync,
but I'm going to
write out it's not
in sync anymore. Lagging behind.
At that point we can
say, Okay, well,
I eliminated it as a candidate
for future leadership,
and now our data is on all the
candidates for leadership.
Let's call it Clo Dred.
Yeah, great question.
Yeah, all the
questions people have.
Yeah, right here.
Yeah. Yeah, in this case,
let's say that this
one that was in
sync keeps lagging behind.
So then the leader will say,
Okay, it's not in sync anymore.
And then at this
point, we see, well,
there are three the men
sync replicas is three.
And so we're say Okay,
good enough, right?
Now there's only three,
and they all have it.
We're gonna call it
Dread. Like, what if
men in sync replicas was four?
If it was four and we
lost that follower,
then we would actually go back
to the producer and say, Hey,
we're having trouble keeping
up. I don't have enough.
Followers keeping
up, but we would
just like reject it, right?
So it's not that like
waiting infinitely
for an act to say,
Hey, like, I can't you're
sending me too many rights.
My followers can't keep up with
all the rights you're sending
me. That makes sense?
All right, Awesome questions,
everybody else people
are trying to pack up.
So just feel Pred up
and chat if you have
have more questions and
dad luck on Friday.