Spark. I have some more
performance things
from last time that I
want to sill cover.
That's probably
actually most of today.
Maybe we'll have
a little time to
actually start today's topic,
which is machine learning.
Some other things that should
be on your radar is that
we have a mid term
again in two weeks.
You could start thinking
about maybe starting
to prep a little bit,
maybe review some stuff, maybe
start making a note sheet,
and I'll send more reminders
as that gets closer.
Some other things is that I
sent some canvas in those,
but I just want to draw
people's attention to.
What is about at GPT and
large language models?
Different courses have
different policies.
I actually allow the
use of these tools,
but it's very important
that you actually cite it.
And the way you can cite it
is that I need to see the
specific chats you had.
So lots of screen shots as
you're using these tools.
There's a director
you dump them all in.
That's really to protect
yourself because
u We run plagiarism
detection tools.
I used to be that I'd run these
things and be like, well,
somebody shared code with
somebody else, and
that's why it's similar.
Moreover, we're seeing now is
that you have different
people who are both using,
Chat GPT or whatever,
it produces similar code,
and they get a match.
And if you were both citing it,
I see, they have similar code
because they both
use the same tool.
I'm like, Okay, there's
a legitimate reason
why it's similar.
Even though it flags you when I
manually review it,
you'll be fine.
If I'm like, Oh,
they're very similar
and they didn't cite anything.
Well, that's not
going to end well.
Send up with the You know, well,
I'll meet and hear
your side of it,
but that'll end up in a report
to the university. So
anyway, just do that.
It takes a little extra time,
but, you know, that will
help protect yourself.
I'd encourage you to
use these things.
I also highlighted down here
that the university
provides coal pilot,
which is going to be better than
the free version of C chat EPT.
So if you are using that,
consider checking out
that version of it.
Any questions about
those policies,
while we're all here?
Oh, right. Cool.
Other thing that's
happening is that
the university is
while the department
is buying a couple of
big servers that we're going
to start having our VMs on.
The idea was that actually will
have more memory than we've
had in past semesters
Everybody's
going to have a VM with
8 gigabytes of RAM.
One of the machines is having
some weird hardware issues,
so I still want to
get some practice and
experience trying to run
the class on these
machines going forward.
So right now what
they've done is
they've created a
virtual machine for
literally everybody on
one of those servers.
I only has 4 gigabytes
of RAM per VM.
I think it's of tricky
to get that set up.
You know, you can't just
SSH shot from anywhere.
You have to be on
the campus network.
That might mean that if
you're working from home,
you're connecting
to the VPN, right?
So I have some details there.
Anyway, like, you could do P
five on Google Cloud
again if you want.
But I want to incentivize
people kind of jumping
through these hoops to
figure it out and
just kind of get
experience in the environment.
So if you do do it
on the new machine
and you provide a
screenshot showing that,
there'll be a little
bit of extra credit.
For that. So I'd encourage
you to go ahead and try that.
Try to see if you end up working
there sooner rather than later,
especially like the VPN stuff.
I even like my TAs trying it and
the TAs are having trouble
getting their VPN working.
So you start early
and if you don't get the
extra cred, that's fine.
Are you just do
it the way you've
been doing other projects?
Cruel, all that logistical
stuff behind us.
I want to talk about some
performance things now.
And let me just remind everybody
where we were last time.
We were learning
about group buys,
and there's the logical level
where we're bringing all
the same keys together,
and there could be millions
of different keys,
millions of different groups.
At the partition level,
we don't want to have
millions of different partitions,
though at that level,
what we need to be sure is that
all the related rows
go the same partition,
but it would be
totally fine to have
say all the Cs and Ds together.
The same partition.
I just can't take
one letter and split
it across, right?
That was a basic idea.
And we learned the
AP's called hash
partitioning tal y very briefly.
That's in contrast to
regular partitioning,
where things are try to be
split up any which way.
We talked about different
optimizations on that.
What is it? If I'm
multiply just trying
to sum up all the
numbers in a column,
maybe I can do partial
sums on the input data
before I have to
shuffle all this data
around over the network.
We also talked about how when
you are shuffling, right?
Well, I do the
hash partitioning,
how many partitions is
all the data land in?
There's not one
obvious right answer.
The default is 200,
which is often too many.
But Smart has this newer feature
called partition co less,
where they'll actually combine a
bunch of small partitions,
and the bigger ones to get
in nice size partitions.
We've talked before
about why you don't want
your partitions to be
too big or too small,
that tries to get them
to be a decent size.
And then finally,
we talked about
how if the data was
already pre partitioned,
and the word for
that is bucketed,
then things would
be great because we
could maybe do a
group by and get
some aggregates without
having to shuffle
the data over the
network. Great.
That's what we ended last time.
Just try to a very brief,
get that back in everybody's
mind after the weekend.
I want to do some examples
to understand that in
a bit more detail.
I'm over here in the
same notebook that
I've done a bunch
of things in. And
I'm going to show an example
of how we do hash partitioning.
Hash partitioning is
based on a hash function.
First I do is I'm
just trying to call
the hash function that's
built into Python.
I'll just make a note here.
This is hash partitioning.
I can get hashes of
different values.
If I put the same value
and I get the same number,
I I put in a slightly
different value,
then I might get a
completely different number.
A good hash function. It
takes any kind of value,
maybe it's bytes, maybe it's
string, gives us a number.
Same input, same output.
But other than that, if I have
slightly different output,
I can get a dramatically a
different number, right?
And so we can build on
that to have a strategy to
group similar things together
in a roughly even way.
And so what I may do is I
may imagine that I
have some partitions.
And in this case,
I want to have four
partitions, right?
I'm just to have four
empty partitions here.
And the idea is that I have
a bunch of different rows,
each with a letter,
and I want to put
the rows with the same letter
into the same partition.
And what I'm really imagining
is that each of these lists
of rows is a piece of work.
It's a partition of the data.
I want to show how could I do
a partitioning on
a bunch of values.
And so first, let
me get some data.
Right? So I'll say my data.
Is going to be the string.
So I'm going to
say ABC, AAA, BB,
DEF G, H, maybe some more Hs.
I'm show I have a
bunch of data there,
and I'm going to try to create
some rows by enumerating it.
I'm going to enumerate that,
and maybe you get a list.
All right, so I'm get
these values like so.
I have all these rows
and I want to group
them by the letter over here.
This will be my data.
Each of these rows,
I want to put in one of
these partitions down here.
I need to make sure
that the same letter
goes to the same partition.
Maybe I'll just look at
the first five of these.
Fantastic. My strategy
is that I can
hash over let's say I have the
first row and that letter.
Let me just print off
what this was again.
So I'm may print off this,
and I may print off
the hash of it.
And what I'd really
like is instead of h just
a big number like that,
I'd like to have zero,
one, two or three.
If I have 012 or three,
I can assign it to one
of these partitions.
And I'm going to do is I'm
going to actually just
take this modulo four. Right?
If I do that, then
this number will be zero,
one, two or three, right?
And so I I hit
hashing with modulo,
then I can put it in one of
these different buckets, right?
And so I'm going to do
that right down here.
I'm going to loop
over all these rows.
I'm going to say
for row and data.
And then I'm just trying
to pull out the values.
I'm going to say
index and letter.
Is going to be pulling those
things out of the row.
What I'm say is, what
partition index do I want?
It's going to be a
hash of the letter.
And I'm going to mod it by well,
how many partitions do
I have, I'm to do that.
And then what I can
do is I can say,
my partition is
going to be one of
these partitions at that
partition index, right?
And then I can append to it.
I can append that row of data.
And so I come out
here and I'm going to
take a look at these
partitions again.
Maybe what I should do is I
should just loop over them.
I could say for a
partition in partitions.
Maybe I'll print
off that partition,
maybe I'll just print
a little header here.
Partition to make it very clear.
I can see it's totally fine for
a partition to have some
different letters in it.
But if I did it right, then
any specific letter
should not be split.
All the Hs, for example,
are in last partition.
There's no Hs anywhere else.
All the As are in
this partition.
I can group things
together in that fashion.
All right. So just
pause there and
see if people have
any questions.
This is the foundation for
this shuffling that's
happening up here.
If both machines have
the same hash function,
they can both be hashing
these rows and they
can figure out,
well, which of these partitions
over here should be going.
Here there's three,
they'll each has, three,
and we can pull all the
related data together in p.
Now, out of curiosity,
I know, based on
the pre records,
not everybody has seen this,
but how many of you have
seen hash tables somewhere?
This should remind you
of hash tables, right?
When you have hash tables, you
have keys and values
that you're putting
in the hash table,
and you have some kind of array
of buckets, very
similar to this here.
And you're taking
each key in value
and you're putting into
one of these buckets.
And when you have hash tables,
you do not want
collisions, right?
You don't want different keys
going in the same bucket, right?
Is that kind of ringing
a bell for people?
And that's because when you
want to look up
something quickly,
you don't have to
loop over a bunch of
different keys and values in
the same bucket
to find something
Here, collisions are fine
and then they're necessary.
I have many more rows than
I have partitions here.
So I just want to say, Hey,
it's similar to that, but
also a little b different.
There, we want to
avoid collisions.
Here, we actually
want collisions.
We want a good sized
partition with lots
of data because we
can process it,
and we're not doing
a calculation
where that would be slow.
Any question about the
strategy in general or
about the comparison
to hash tables?
Cool. This strategy is
what we do for group by.
We're going to do
similar things for join.
With the doin, we're
often have to bring
related data together
in the same place.
First, what I want to
do is I want to show if
I have all this related
data in the same place,
what are some different
strategies for joining?
Then we go back to
the slides and I can
show how I can use
these as building
blocks to build distributed hash
or distributed join algorithms.
First, I'm going
to do some local
and by that I mean, one machine.
One machine join algorithms.
In for this, I have some
example data over here.
I'm going to go to the resources
and under lecture snippets,
where is lecture snippets.
There it is. I am
going to copy some
data down here. Great.
All right, let's just take
a look at this and try to
figure out what
we're trying to do.
I have a bunch of
different fruits,
and each fruit has a color,
and the fruits are
either apples, bananas,
or carrots, rather than
having that all in one place,
these codes up here,
it's almost like
a four and refer down to here.
This first fruit is a
yellow, which is banana.
This is a yellow banana.
This one is a green
a green apple.
Okay. And that's my goal.
I want to do a droit.
I want to loop over
all these things,
and I want to print
off my yellow banana,
green apple, so on and so forth.
And I'm show two different
strategies for doing that.
Okay. In this case,
each of the fruits up here
has exactly one corresponding
kind down below.
I'm going to write code that
works for that scenario.
If I had duplicates, if
there are two As down here,
there are cases where you
might have a joint like that,
it's a little less common, and
my code would be a little
bit more complicated.
But I'm not trying to
handle that case here.
I assume that each of
these has one match below.
Each one down here could
have any number of
matches up above.
But how can I join it together
for this particular data?
The way I'm going to do this is,
I am going to take
these kinds and I'm going to
convert it to a dictionary.
I'm going to convert
that to a dictionary.
And this is great because
if I loop over that,
I can match each of these up.
I am going to loop
over the fruits.
I'm going to say for
fruit and fruits.
Really there's the two parts.
There's the kind ID,
and then there's the color.
Maybe first, actually,
I'm just going to
print those things.
I'm going to say kind
ID and the color.
Maybe I'll just actually
switch these because
it'll just be more natural
and when I do that.
I'm printing all
those things off.
I'm going to put this
dictionary back up here.
I'm going to put it
in a kind table.
I have kind look up here.
What I come down here so I'm
just putting off the kind
directly like B. I can do
a look up on the table.
I can say kind look
up, like that.
I can say yellow banana, green
apple, so on and so forth.
What this is doing right now is,
it's called Approach one
is called a hash rain,
right? That makes sense.
You take whatever
table is smaller,
you make a hash table out of it,
you can loop over and match up.
And when I talk about
distributed drains soon,
that will be one of the
strategies we have there.
Okay? All right.
What else can we do?
Approach two approach two
is going to be called
a sort merge join.
Maybe I'll just make these
similar. A sort merge join.
What is going to require
actually is that both of
our input datasets are sorted.
Maybe it'll do is I'll
say fruit St sort,
and then I'll take a
look at the fruits.
Then I will say, what
else do I want to have?
I want to have the kind sort.
And then I'll take a
look at the kinds.
They're both when you start,
you start on the first
value in the tuple.
Both of these are ordered now.
What I want to do
is I want to write
this weird double loop
where I'm walking over
both of these together.
I want to match up all the As
here with all the As down here,
I want to match up
all the Bs with
all the Bs on and so
forth. I can do that.
Once it's all sorted, I can just
make one pass over
each of these.
First one I do is I'm just
write a pretty slow
loop actually,
I'm going to say for fruit
and fruits and for ks,
Maybe I'll just put
off every combination
of them fruit and kind.
I can do that. I can see in
some cases, this
is a match, right?
I want to output something.
This is not a match, so I
would not want to
output something.
Maybe what I can say is
I can say if the fruit
of position zero equals
the kind of position zero,
that would be a match and
then I'm just going to
only put it off in that case.
I I'm only going to
print off in that case.
I is what I'm looking for.
And then you know what I think I
can do is from the fruit,
I can grab the color,
right from here, I can
grab the type of fruit.
I can say green apple, red
apple, so on and so forth.
Now, this is very slow,
because I'm comparing
every combination to
every combination.
I'm not really taking
advantage of the fact
that that both of these
are sorted, right?
And so what I want
to do is I'm just
trying to make one forward
pass through all the fruits.
What I want to make sure is that
when I'm looping over the ks,
I shouldn't always go back
to the beginning, right?
And so I have to kind of write
a stranger loop here, right?
I have to say something like
fruit index equals zero.
And then what could I say?
I could say while
fruit index is less than
the length of I'm
sorry, what am I doing?
I wanted to loop over the
kins. Let me go back.
So I could say, what is the
I'm going to switch this.
I should check my
notes more instead of
just draining ad hoc.
I'm going to do this.
I'm going to have each
kind pair up with a fruit.
What we do is I may
change the student.
I'm going to say fruit
index equals zero,
and I'm going to say y,
fruit index is less than
the length of the fruits.
Then down here, I'm going to say
fruit index plus equals one.
I think at that
point, the code shod
the code is doing
something horrible.
I think what I messed up
on is I just had my old
variable from before.
So I can say the
fruit, in this case,
is the fruits of
fruit index, right?
Okay, great. So I have
the same quota as before.
This is equivalent to
my four loop so far,
I haven't made anything faster,
I just refactored, I've run
the loop a little
bit differently.
And that's why I set me up for
my next step because
since I have
this wild loop and I'm manually
increasing this index,
I can rewrite it in a
more efficient way.
And I think one of the
things that I don't want
to do is that as I'm
passing over the fruit,
I don't want to always go
back to the first fruit index
because the earlier fruits have
already been paired
up with something.
I'm to bring this
up here, right?
I'm to have that at
the very beginning.
And then I have another
case here, right?
It's possible that
the fruit that I'm
on has already gone past the
current kind I'm on, right?
Maybe I'm currently on banana,
and I saw a s value.
That means I need to go
past the banana to carrot.
What I'm going to do is in
this case, I'm going to say,
if fruit of zero,
if I've gone past it,
then what I want to
actually do is break.
Somehow if I'm on see orange
and I'm still in banana,
then I don't want to pass
the fruit index forward,
because I want to remember
this one for when
they're the carrot.
I'm just trying to break
out of this inter loop,
and then I'll go onto
the carrot and then
I can match it up.
I can do that where is
that I'm having an issue.
I always title
these line numbers
to in troubles a little
bit more quickly.
I just started writing
the same thing twice.
Silly me. All right.
Let's do that.
Now I can do the same thing.
Then what's great
is that I make one
pass over all the kinds
with this funky loop.
Given that, I go to
the sloop many times,
but each time it starts
where ended last time,
I'm only making one pass
over each of these,
and I can merge these two
different data sources together.
That's called a
sort merge joint.
I started it and I'm merging
these two sorted
resources together.
Any questions about
that approach?
All right. The theme here is
going to be in both cases,
I can do run this code that
I showed on one machine.
I mean, I literally just did
with regular Python rode.
If I have some strategy
in Spark to bring
the same kind IDs together
on the same machine,
if I have a shuffle
strategy like that,
then I'd be able to
do those drawings.
Okay. So I had those things.
I want to show some
spark things as well
before I go back to the
slides and the concepts.
And so what I'm going to
show now is, for group by,
how we can both see what
kind of group by it's
doing and also see some
ways we can optimize it.
I may have an
example query here.
I may have Spark dot SQL,
and any kind of group by
query would work here.
But may select call type from
the Fire Department
data like we've done
before and do
account star Count,
and select that from Calls
and then down here I
may group by type.
A general query. We've seen
a bunch of times before.
Maybe I'll just limit it.
I can see a few of these
All right, so that's T to Run.
And I see a few of these counts.
Great. That's all fine and well.
And And so what I can do
is I'm curious about what kind
of operation was
being done here,
I can actually say explain.
And when I explain,
it's telling me all these
different steps that actually
got done. Re road we started.
We talked about RDDs, and
there's all the things you do
with RDs like mapping and
filtering and whatever,
even though we're
writing Sparks SQL,
those things are
still happening.
And if I say explain the query,
it tells me what
those things are.
And so this explain, I think,
has a pretty dense
red representation.
And so what I
generally prefer is to
say give me a formatted
version of it,
right? So formatted version.
What that will show me is what
the transformations
are at each step,
and there's these numbers.
I can see one down here
that corresponds to
more info down here.
I can see the general shape
of what the query plan is,
and I can also
read more details.
The very first thing
is going to be doing
is scanning some Park data,
is showing me what
that Park data is.
That's my San Francisco
Park file and HDFS.
And then what I see here is
that I have to have
some kind of exchange
when I exchange,
I have to bring
related data together.
So that's three
down here. I take
a look at the
exchange down here.
I see that they're ding
hash partitioning,
like we talked about
and like I just showed.
I can see that they're hash
partitioning on the
call type column.
That makes a lot
of sense. You hash
partition or whatever
you want to group by.
You can also see, like
I mentioned before,
by default, when they do
the hash partitioning,
they take module of 200,
which gets you 200 partitions
that used to be a big problem,
but now they will co lass.
Though it says 200 there,
it's going to be
less than the end.
Why will it be
less than the end?
Well, up here, I see if there's
an adaptive spark plan and
some that's like the top
level of these query plans,
then it will make some of
these optimizations
as we're going.
We're shuffling around the data.
Then we can also see that both
before and after we
shuffle around the data.
We're doing some
hash aggregation.
So let's take a
look at this one.
After we shuffle the data,
then we're doing a count.
So we're just kind of
counting unique values.
What are we doing before
we shuffle the data?
Well, we're actually
doing a partial account.
If I have like a
bunch of A rows,
maybe I can collapse into
a single row and see
how many that we.
I mean, there might be a
rows on a different machine,
I can't get a final count,
but I can least do a
partial account and then
s less data over the network.
This is the kind of
thing I want you to be
able to do on the project,
right to go in and kind of,
You know, this project
is a little bit unique.
Because there's a
couple of cases
where you have to explain
a little bit about
what's happening
instead of just
answering the question.
I'll be grad you on some
comments that you have,
and I'll be very clear
where those comments
have to be. All right.
Any questions about this
explained or what we're seeing
here for the query plan?
A right. Cool. I also
want to show the
bucketing optimization.
We have to shuffle the data
because These call types
could be spread across
different machines.
If call types happen to
be all in the same place,
then I wouldn't really
have to worry about that.
I'm going to come down
here. I'm to show
how we can get that
data bucketed.
I'm say Spark dot table, calls.
What I could do like
before is I could say
dot dot save as table.
This will save it
as a Hive table,
which is remember some
Park K files in the H CFS.
I'm going to call this table.
Just check in my notes
here, what will I call it?
I will call it calls by type.
All right, so I can do that.
I don't want this to
be a super long demo.
I'm going to say I'm
just ting a sample
that's not super interesting,
but I'll just make
this all run faster.
I want to say do
10% of the rows.
The other thing I can do now is
after I have this write thing,
then I see I have
this data frame writer and I
can put different options on it.
One of the options is I can
say bucket by then in here,
I can say, Well,
how many buckets do I want?
Also what do I
want to bucket on?
This bucketing by,
it's the same thing
as that hash partitioning,
but it's going to do that
before writes out the file.
All right. Let's take a
moment and let's do that.
Again, I could
totally what is it?
Call type has an underscore
in it, doesn't it?
So let's give that
another attempt.
I think there was six
partitions over here,
so it's doing sampling
of those six partitions
then they're going to have
to write out some data.
Any questions while we're
doing that bucketing?
To are in progress
out of the six.
One is done, two are
done, two in progress.
Six, right here.
Is bucket pi equal
to a group pi?
Not quite. I think they're often
used in conjunction, right? So
Group by is like a SQL query.
We're actually trying
to get some analysis.
When we do a group
by, we have to bring
together related data,
which is expensive.
Bring de related data,
usually requires some
network transfers.
What Bucket bi is
doing is saying, well,
let's put the related
data together
when we initially
write the file.
Then when we do
queries on that file,
we won't have to do it later.
Really what I'm doing is
I'm just trying to
write the data in
different form so my
group bi will be faster.
Does that make sense?
Yeah, great question.
Let's come up here and
try the same query again.
But instead of doing
it on the calls table,
I'm going to do it on this
new table that I created.
All right. I'm going
to run this up here.
So now what I
actually see is very
interesting is
that I didn't have
to do an exchange
between my partial account
and my total account.
The data was already bucketed
as it was supposed to
be bucketed, right?
So that's going to be faster.
If I did this query
on a different field,
right like if I did it by area,
I'm trying to think
what other I ought
maybe I forgot to save
it with that field.
What are some other
fields we have here?
Sparked out table, calls.
What if I do it by I don't know,
let's say a call date.
I want to know how many events
there are on each call date.
Then why am I having stri.
No table, I change it up here?
I want to S. I had calls
by type. Great. Do that.
I see in that case, I
would still have to do
the exchange because
this call by type data.
It's bucketed by type.
But if I'm doing a group by
that's on a different field,
it's still going to be slow.
Then the takeaway
here is that how
do I didn't want to do Silly
I'm to go forwards redo.
Yeah, it's not for
whatever reason.
My apologies, I'll just
type it again. Spark SQL.
Then I'll say, select call type,
and then count of star
from calls by type,
and then group by type.
I think that's actually good.
And I wanted to explain it.
My apologies again for
deleting my example.
We can only be fast avoid
the exchange for one thing.
You could have different copies
of their data if you
know there's a couple of
different queries you have
and you're willing to spend
extra space to make
different things fast,
or if you want one
copy of your data,
you can make one thing fast.
Cool. Any questions about
that bucketing by technique?
And that would help also
with the join of course,
because the doin,
we also have to
bring the related data together.
Okay, so coming back here.
We've talked about these
different optimizations
for group by.
We've shown how if we
pull all the related data
together on the same
machine for a drain, right?
So the related data from
two different tables,
we can join it locally.
Let's talk about how we can do
joining across data that's
distributed, right?
And so there's two strategies,
which correspond to the
two local strategy I have.
The first one is
called a broadcast in.
And I have the same data example
here that I had in my notebook.
So In this case, I
have two tables.
One has a fruit ID and a cost,
and that's partitioned, right?
The bold boundary is a
partition of the first table.
I see there's some three rows
of data on each of my two
machines in that case.
Then also my table of look
ups is partitioned as well.
I have a thener border on
that, that's a smaller table,
so I have A and B up here
and the C down here.
And when I want to join these,
I have to bring the related
data together in some way.
And so the first strategy,
remember that what I did is
that for this look up table,
I just created a
dictionary from it.
And so the first strategy is
that we will actually have
an identical dictionary on
every machine in
the cluster here,
it's two, but if I
had 100 machines,
we'd have 100
dictionaries like that.
Right? I'm really shuffling
everywhere everywhere on
the small table and building
building this dictionary.
It's a small table, it's fine,
right if it's like a
couple kilobytes who
cares of every single machine.
Once I do that, the
rest is going to be
relatively fast
because it doesn't
matter how many fruits I have.
I can each machine independently
loop over its fruits and
join it against that look.
There's good things and
bad things about this.
The bad thing is
that the small table
gets sent over the
network everywhere.
It's in memory everywhere.
The good thing is
that the big table
Never has to go
over the network.
If there's an extreme
difference in size,
if I have a very large table
and a very tiny table,
this is a good strategy.
Caveat being that even if
there's a big difference,
if the small table
doesn't fit in memory,
this simply is not an option.
Sometimes this is great,
sometimes it's really fast.
Other times I can't do it,
other times it's slow.
All right. So before I showed
a sort Merge join, SMJ.
The distributed version is
called Shuffle sort Merge Join.
I forever reason, they also have
the S is covering both
shuffle and sort.
So we also call that SM j.
I start with the data
in the same place.
This one more closely resembles
what happens with group.
We will both of the tables,
and we will bring together
all the pieces that are
As from both the tables.
Well maybe I might B and C. L's
say at function module
two is one that I bring both
those pieces down here.
Once I bring both
those pieces there,
that I can just do the
regular sort merge join
that I did in the
notebook earlier,
and I can match all of
that up just as before.
Any questions about either of
those approaches? All right.
What are the trade offs?
Again, with Sort Merge Join,
it's expensive in some sense,
because every table goes
over the network once,
even if one of the
tables is huge.
The BH, advantages that only,
the small table goes
over the network,
but it goes over the network.
Many times, the more workers
involved in the cluster,
the more times it does well.
Sorbo default because it
just always works
even if it's slow.
But sometimes, if you
have very big skew
between the tables,
one is very large,
one is very small,
and the small and
fits in memory.
There's not too many
workers involved.
Sometimes BHA has
fantastic performance.
All right. So one of
the things you can do,
right is if I have
some query up here.
I mean, this could
be Spark SQL or it
could be the data frame API.
When I do that, I can
say that explain,
just like I did with a group I,
and here I get some more
complicated output here.
And I can see in this case,
it's automatically doing a
broadcast has doin, right?
Another reason I say the
shuffle sort merge join.
That's one of the
things I want to do.
If you have some kind
of drain, I want to b
just run explain and tell
me what kind of
drain is it doing?
That's one of the things that
we should walk away with.
The other thing is that
you can do a head up here.
I could say holidays
dot h. I could say there
merge or broadcast.
If I could do that, I can
force it to do bother type.
For some reason, Spark makes
a wrong decision
about what is best,
I can make it do
something different.
All right. Cool. Any questions
about joints? All right.
We're going to move on
and I start a new topic,
which is machine learning
and specifically machine
learning in Spark.
And so in Spark,
they have a library
called ML Lb,
and that's where we learning.
So I have a few goals for you.
I want you to be able
to understand what
these different common
machine learning tests
are, how to do them in Spark.
What is like a train test split?
How can I pre process my data?
How can I take create a
pipeline where I do a bunch of
transformations to the data
before I actually train
or predict with it?
How can I evaluate how well
my models work? Lots
of things there.
I think this is not a
machine learning course,
but it's just like,
Well, how do we do
machine learning with big data?
And so I'll have a bit of
a brief background
of machine learning,
and we'll just look at one
algorithm in closer detail,
which is a decision tree.
So I want you to understand how
decision trees make predictions.
And then third, there's
this research paper called
Planet that Google published,
and we're going to
learn how planet works
because planet is what has
been implemented in Spark.
Spark uses something similar
to the planet algorithm
to train decision trees,
and we'll try tag that
in detail and see how
if we have these giant datasets,
we have to train a model.
How can we do that
without having to
send too much data
over the network?
How can we keep the
data in place and
still train one big decision
tree and then the end?
All right. So I may do
I should re label this.
I used to have some
machine learning
stuff earlier in the
semester that I pulled out.
So this is not review.
You're seeing this
for the first time.
So it's okay if you don't know
much about machine
learning at this point.
So there's different categories
of machine learning.
What is called
reinforcement learning.
That's where you have
some kind of agent
that's like making decisions
and it's getting rewards or
the opposite of rewards,
and it's kind of
adapting over time.
Another strategy, category of
machine learning is on
supervised learning,
where you might be looking
for general categories.
We're not trying to look at
either of those this semester.
We're going to look at
supervised machine learning.
We're trying to train
models that can
predict on known values, right?
And what is a model?
A model is actually
just a function that
takes some information
about the world,
and then the return value of
the function is a prediction.
Right? And so you
as a human just
like who write some
function, say,
Hey, this is my model,
you could evaluate it,
you could do a lot
of things with it.
The idea of machine
learning is that rather
than having a human just
write down a model,
we want the computer to
automatically figure
out what this function
should look like.
What that often
involves is there's
some math inside
of this function,
and different numbers might be
almost like hard
coded into that math.
And so creating a
good model often
means finding good values
for those numbers.
So I have that
And then we return
some prediction here.
I might re each turn either
a number or a category.
Like a number would be like
one, two, three, category,
it might be like yes,
no, or apple banana.
And so there's names for these.
The first one is a
regression model.
The second one is a
classification model.
I have an example down here
where I have a weather forecast.
The weather forecast is
taking in some values.
The temperature today, the
temperature yesterday.
Maybe I can predict what
the temperature is.
Tomorrow, is it a
regression model because
I'm returning a number.
This is kind of a broad idea of
what machine learning is and
specifically supervises
machine learning.
All right. So let's walk
through an example.
How can we actually
figure out how to make
a good function or model
based on some data?
A common situation that
you're going to find
yourself in is that you
have a bunch of data.
Let's imagine that
it's a table of data,
and there are some unknown
values in some of the rows.
Down here, there's a few values.
I don't know. And what I want
to do is I want to try to
figure out when I do know
both the x and the y values,
Can I figure out what
the relationship is?
Can I find some pattern, and
then use that to infer what
the y values probably are
where they're missing, right?
So there are special names for
these columns I have here.
The column that I'm trying to
predict where I have
some missing values,
where you call that
a label, right?
So in this case, y is my label.
There might be
other column names
for a label, but y is common.
So I want to predict
this label column y.
And the things I'm using to make
the prediction are
called features, right?
And so this case, my features
are X one and X two, right?
I want to figure
Can I predict what
those unknowns are
from my other data.
Lots of different methodologies
or strategies people
have for doing this and it
should show one methodology.
What is that? We're going to use
different subsets of our known
values in different ways, right?
So one of the things somebody
might do is they might
randomly split our known cases
into two or three parts, right?
And we're going to have
one part that we
train our data on,
where we actually
look for patterns,
and other parts that
we might use to try to
identify the best model or
say how good our model is.
And so we'll
randomly split that.
That randomly split here in
the picture, I just
have chunked it.
But normally it would
be randomly split.
All right, what would you do?
You would feed
your training data
into different algorithms.
And what those algorithms are
returning is a model
or a function that can
make predictions, right?
I can feed this into
different algorithms,
and I could get different
models out of that.
Okay. It's very common,
you have some data.
You're going to try a bunch of
different machine
learning algorithms,
and then the end, you have
to recommend one, right?
In the end, you want to just
start using one of them,
and she'll say, I recommend
model A or model B.
How do we choose one?
Well, we have to give it
a test to see which one
is the best, right?
So what we'll do is we'll take
this validation data where
we actually know
the true answer.
And we feed these values
as arguments into
both these models,
and we'll get some
return values.
We're doing that, even though we
already know what the
real Y values are,
because what we want to see is,
can these models get values that
are close to the real y values?
And just kind like
eyeballing it here,
I can see that Model A is making
more realistic predictions
than Model B, right?
So this point in the project,
I might come along
and I might say
that Model A is the winner.
There's deferent ways to
categorize or not categorize,
but to quantify how good
your predictions are.
We be look at that a
little bit more detail.
Anyway, so this point
might say Model A,
U, in addition to
recommending Model A,
people might be interested in
knowing how good is model A.
It would be a little
tempting to just say, well,
what was the score
that Model A got,
when I use of the
validation dataset.
But that's not quite right
because imagine like I was
trying to test students.
Maybe first I want to say pick
a student that knows
the material past,
and I want to say,
how well do they do?
Let's say hypothetically that
the group of students all
just randomly pick answers.
If I do the methodology
I've had so far,
there's going to be
some students that get
higher scores than
others just by chance.
It's a little bit biased. If I
pick the one that's
a winner and I say,
this is how well it does.
Well, maybe what that score is
reflecting is the fact
that it's the best
one out of a large
number of them.
And so what we'll do is after
we finally pick a winner, right?
This is the best one, we'll
give it another test,
and this will be its
final score like.
Well, how well does
this model that we're
recommending do on
the data, right?
So at this point,
we have a model
that can return predictions.
We have some sense
of how good it is,
and then I might actually
use it to make some predictions,
where I really, truly don't
know what the result is.
Yeah, for sure. What's that?
Could it do better
on the validation
data than the test data?
Yeah. Yeah, absolutely, right.
So try to come back here.
Imagine that I have,
100 different models.
I actually is pretty
common because when
we're trading these
models there's
different parameters
you can tune, right?
So even let's say both A
and B are decision trees,
they might be decision
tree models with
different parameters.
So it might be totally common
that it might have
hundreds of these.
Let's say hypothetically that
all the models are equally.
But when I feed the
validation to them,
some will kind of do better,
and some will do a
bit worse by chance.
And so if I have
a lot of bottles,
odds are that whatever
the winner, however
well the winner did,
the validation score is probably
not how well it will
do on a second test.
That makes sense.
Yeah. There are
other questions.
Yeah, right here.
Yeah. I use both of them.
I use them for
different purposes.
I'm using the validation
to select this is
the model I want,
and then I use the test to
communicate how
good that model is.
That make sense. Do what
I need to run the test
model B? I could, right?
But if I then switched to
model B based on the test,
then I kind of defeated
the purpose of having
a separate test from
validation data set.
There's different methodologies
people use for machinery.
I'm just like
showing one, right?
Like a simpler methodology,
like the one we'll use
on the project is like,
you know, there's strain
data and there's test data.
That's no separate
validation, right?
So there's other
things people do
where they'll split
up the data multiple
times and different
times they'll have
different validation and test.
Lots of different methodologies.
I'm just actually showing
you one example methodology.
That makes sense? Yeah, good
question. Other
questions people have.
Right. Cool. So we
have that thing,
we can deploy it and then
use it for real things.
And so There's
different frameworks out
there that people have used.
For example, people coming from
320 have probably
seen Psych learn.
PyTorch is extremely popular.
They teach Pi torch now in 540.
I just want to compare and
contrast these a little bit.
I know some of you
are seeing machine
learning for the first
time ever. That's fine.
But for those of you who
have points of comparison,
I think I do want to spend
a little time doing that.
So I have some
example code for all
three of these and how
we might train a model.
And for both psych
learn and PyTorch,
the models are what
we call mutable.
I have this model object
to make predictions,
and I can make modifications
to it to make it better.
So for example, in Psych learn,
I have a model
object. I say dot f.
When I say dot fit, I'm giving
an example features and labels,
and it's trying to
figure out what
those internal parameters
should be to make good
predictions, right? I fit it.
I'm making changes to
that model object.
In PyTorch, which is often
used for deep learning where
I have some model as well.
And typically, the models
we're using with PyTorch have
lots of internal parameters,
and we keep showing it
more and more data.
Progressively refines
those parameters, making
it a little bit better.
But in both cases, right, we're
making changes to the objects.
Spark, as you see
more about Spark,
so if you kind of
get a sense of like
the style of the people
who built Spark,
how they like to program, they
don't like things
that are immutable.
And so in Spark, all
models are immutable.
And what that means
is that I will have
an unfit model, whatever type.
And if I call FI on it
and pass in some data,
what it will actually do is it
can't change the unfit model.
So when I call FI on
Ofit model it returns
a different object,
which is my FIT model,
and then my FIT model I can
actually use to make
predictions, right?
So models and Spark
are immutable.
Predicting has also done
a little bit differently.
In Psych learn, a model is
an object that you
can predict on.
You give it some x values.
It returns back y values to you.
In Pytorch, they made that
a little bit more elegant.
The model object itself can
also act like a function.
I can say model, gibits
x values, and' return Y.
It's both an object
and a function
at the same time. Is kind cool.
Then in Spark, You know,
Spark people are always
thinking about like
everything is like a
transformer and an RDD.
That's the mindset to be in.
For them, what they'll
do is they will
transform a data
frame that doesn't
have any predictions into
it into another
data frame that has
all the original stuff plus
a column of prediction.
Transforming in Spark is
something that we will actually
do to make predictions.
Let me just show you what that
looks like in both cases.
For psych learn and Pytorch,
we have this big x,
which contains all
these features,
and then we will
predict in some way,
we'll get back a
column of y values.
I Spark, it's very different.
What I'm doing is I'm be
feeding in this data frame.
And what's strange is that it
will only look at one
column for the features.
I have this x features over
here, and based on that,
I'll return the same
data frame with
a new column with the
labels on it, right?
Given that Spark reason,
they said, Okay,
we're always just going
to base things on
one column of features,
what that column
of features will
usually be is vectors that
contain all the different values
that we're interested in.
I other values are
two and three,
they'll combine that into
a tuple that says
23 or a vector.
And they'll use
that as a features.
Some terminology is also
a bit different here.
They use the words transformer
and estimator in different ways.
In sich learn, a transformer
is something that will pre
process the data in
some way before you
either do training
or prediction.
In Spark a transformer is
any object that has
a transform method.
Somebody that's making predictions
is also a transformer.
What about estimator?
In Psych learn
an estimator is something
that has a method,
and when you call FI on it,
it will modify the objects
that you can later predict.
A estimator can make predictions
and after it learns
some parameters.
In Spark, an estimator is
an object that has a fit,
but an estimator will never
actually make
predictions itself.
An estimator will return
a new object that can
do transformations
that add predictions.
All right. Any question on
the terminology so far?
There's lots of differences.
I want to make
sure I'm not going
too fast over this.
Any questions?
All right. The last thing we
talk about today is pipelines.
It's very common
to do a bunch of
transformations to the data and
then train or a bunch of
transformations
and then predict.
All these tools have that.
Here I have an example of
a pipeline that has multiple
transformers and it
does an estimator.
If I'm doing Spark, what will
happen is that we'll feed
the data through here
and we will make a bunch
of transformations of data,
and when it gets this
estimator object,
we call FI on it, that
will return a
transformer over here.
If I say pipeline not fit,
the first thing it
does is it gets
a transformer that can
make predictions with
the same put data.
If I'm using that to
make predictions,
that has to have
the same pre processing
that we had before.
These other transformers
are just going to
get copied over
and exactly the same as
they were originally.
Once I have that, then I
can feed new data into
the pipeline model.
I'm going to do a bunch
of transformations and
the end will out pop
some predictions.
I use that transform
to do predictions.
A little bit different
than maybe what you might
expect with other
pipeline tools.
I end there and we'll
maybe just start
next time with tophat.
Have a fantastic day.