I'll be back today, and we're
learning more about HDFS.
And I may have a
few more concepts.
I'm going to go over
the slides, but mostly,
I want to give you some heads on
practice actually using HDFS.
P four is going to be released
some day before midnight,
and that's going to
be all about HDS.
So I think the things I'm
do today are very very
naturally set you up
for what you're doing
in the project.
There's going to be a
lot of similar examples.
So hopefully this will set
you up for success
on that project.
I'm head back here to the
slides where we were.
And what we were
learning about last time
is that we have these Hadoop
file system clusters,
and they have a
bunch of computers
running these programs
called data nodes, right?
I have a bunch of data nodes,
each on a different server.
Maybe there's a bunch of
hard drives on each of them.
And the data nodes are
responsible for storing
blocks of data,
physical blocks of data.
When we have files up here
like F one and F two,
we might break them
into partitions,
and then we might have
multiple replicas
of each of those,
and then we'll save those as
blocks on each of these systems.
The data nodes are
running on top
of just a regular
local file system.
So even though HDFS is
a file system that's
across machines,
it's built on top of just a
regular local file system.
And so when it stores
one of these blocks,
it just creates a file somewhere
to store the data
inside of those blocks.
This design makes
it more reliable.
If one of these machines dies,
sure, we lose some
physical data,
but fortunately, we have
this logical data up here
that's replicated elsewhere.
So, this is the way that HFS and
also the Gool file system
were originally built,
and so we'll have
these multiple copies
of data. That's
called replication.
That's the main strategy
we're learning this semester.
I just wanted you to be
aware of it even though
I'm not try to ask you about
it or do anything with it.
But the latest version of
HFS have something else
called erase Code.
And that's a different
kind of redundancy that
doesn't just play and have
multiple copies of it.
I td to details
about how it works.
But if you take the
operating systems class,
for example, you'll learn about
erasure and tote
with rate of arrays.
And it's basically that
idea applied to data note.
So if that's helpful to you,
great, otherwise, don't
worry too much about it.
I just want you to know if
they have a different strategy.
This other strategy
tends to make our data
reliable without quite
as much overhead.
We don't have to have all
these full copies of data.
Which is good, but it tends
to be less o efficient.
And so what the D pile system
will do is it will use
this general strategy that
I've been describing so
far for any kind of
new or hot data.
And if there's some data
that's sitting around
for a long time and
not being modified,
they might put it under this
erasure coding instead.
Great. So those are all those
data node nodes out here.
Let's look at some
other computers
that might be involved.
Up here, I may have a
system called a name node.
And what the name node is
responsible for doing is
keeping track of all the
logical blocks of data, right?
So all our files are broken into
these blocks, these
logical blocks.
And the name node knows,
for any given logical block,
what data nodes has it, right?
So I can see up here that
for block one of file one,
the name node knows
that data nodes one,
two, and three it.
And indeed, it does for let's
say file two, block two.
It says, data nodes
two and three have
that, which is also true.
We also have client programs
that actually want
to read the data.
Sometimes the client
program might actually
be already on the same
machine as a data node.
Here, I may imagine it is a
separate machines by laptop.
And if the client
wants to read data,
then it's I have to talk
to the name node because
the name node knows
where that data left.
So I'll send down a message
to the name node saying,
I want to read file, too.
And then the Dabb will
respond and say, Okay,
well, here is where you can
grow and a fide that data.
And then the cli industry to
directly talk to
the data Dodes and
do the network transfers.
The really important thing
here was that the data,
which is probably large,
did not flow through
the DAB node.
The Da Bode was only
responsible for
beta data about where
the data lived.
The big data transfers
are with the data nodes,
and that's supported
because we have
lots and lots of data nodes,
and so we can spread
out all that work,
but we only have one name node
at our whole cluster, right?
So it'd be very easy for a
nab node to become
a bottle deck.
It will become a bottle deck
if we have to transfer
all the data.
Through that name node. All
right, so we might do that.
We might also say that
I want to write a file.
So I write file three.
And when we do that,
we'll specify how many
replicas, we want to write.
Let's say we want to
write three of them.
And in this case, the name node
could really choose anything.
That data doesn't
already exist somewhere,
so we'll try to choose
a good place for it.
Maybe it might take
into consideration
how heavily loaded
each data node is,
I might trying to spread out
the data somewhat evenly.
In this case, it'll say the
locations, I'll record.
Okay, we're going to write it
to nodes one, two, and three.
And then the client program is
going to write that data in
each of those places, right?
Now, one thing that's
a little unfortunate
is the lie program is
sending the same data
over the network to
a lot of places.
That could be a
bottleneck, right?
We're kind of sending a lot
of data from a single node,
especially if my client is not
in the same data center, right?
Maybe I'm in the same rack,
or I'm just like somewhere else.
I might have limited bad width.
I'm wondering? Does
anybody have any ideas for
a faster way to get
that same data on each of
these three data nodes?
Yeah, right over here. XL.
That's a great idea. That's
exactly what they do.
So we could send XY Z to
one of the data nodes,
and that could send
it to the rest,
and that's called a
right pipeline, right?
So they're go to use
pipeline rights when
we're writing HFS data,
and that's going to
be that we don't have
as much bad width consumed
for any given computer,
especially important, if that
first has limited bad width.
Alright, so I just want to
think about how
all this happens.
The different questions I
like to ask to make sure
people understand
HDFS is I might say,
Oh, I'm writing this much
data, this kind of file,
or I'm reading this much data
from some other type of file,
and I might ask
things like, Well,
how much data is transferred
over the network or
how much data is
going to have to be
read from disc or how much
is going to be rented?
And so I want to have a
couple of examples here.
So I have a client and it's
writing 4 megabytes of data,
and it's ready into a file
that's two times replicated.
And so it's sad is data nodes
is I have to get ready.
I'm wondering how
much total data
across all these nodes
is ready to be read
into hard drives.
Maybe everybody can hold up sub
number of figures to indicate
how many gigabytes
of data will be
a into hard drives
and by cluster.
Yeah, so I'm looking for
everybody to answer, right?
So you can say, I mean,
you could say like
2 megabytes or 4 megabytes
or some of that.
I'm not looking for a voluntary.
I want everybody to hold
up sub number of figures.
How many megabytes of data
will be a into hard drives?
I'm seeing some eights,
which is correct, right?
Be even though we have
three data nodes,
right we're only writing
into two of them.
We have two times
replication, and so
that four megabyte data will
be read in two different
places, 8 megabytes total.
Okay, so now, let's
say that we're going
to read some data.
We're going to read
2 megabytes of data,
and this data lives in
a file that has three
times replication.
How many megabytes
data have to be
read from hard drives
by these data nodes?
I'm seeing a mix of six and two,
the answer is two, right?
So even though it's
strictly replicated,
that data is a save
a in each place.
So we're reading it, we just
need to have one copy
of the data, right?
So I'll choose. One of
the takeaways here
is that when we have
replication rites
just inherently
become more expensive
than reads.
And there's other things higher
the stack that make
that true as well.
So I just want you to see
that as we start
adding these layers,
rites are more
expensive than what
might expect. Yeah,
go ahead, right here.
They are. They're from
last time, right?
They should be,
right? Yeah, because
we're just catching up from
these concepts from last time.
Yeah, yeah, please
check on that.
Yeah. Other questions.
Yeah, right here. What's that?
Yes, the name node, we do
have to worry about it
becoming a single point
of a failure, right?
And so in the original
like GFS and HTFS,
what they did is they would add
what they call a secondary node,
and they'd have these two
pairs of nodes together,
and they'd try to be ready
so they can fail over
that second node if
need need be, right?
I won't get into a lot
of the details about
that because it's
not a great design.
Its even kind of having two?
Two is not great, right?
And so in Google, right,
they actually don't use the
Google file system anymore,
they replace it with
something called Closs,
the Closss file system.
And so the Closss file
system gets rid of that.
So they don't just
have like one or
two nodes for this meta data.
They really have it
spread out, right?
And HDFS still kind
of has that design,
it's like a name node, and then
they call it a secondary node.
I won't look too much at it
because we're going to see
other systems later
like Cassandra,
that solve similar problems, but
they will have it
highly distributed.
So I think that yeah,
this is kind of a bad design.
You could imagine some kind of
hacks on it, but, you know,
other systems like class
file system or cassaa
that we see have a way of
making the meta data
highly distributed,
like the actual data
as Excellent point.
Yeah. Other questions or
concerns people have. Oh, right.
Cool. So I just want you know,
when you're using these systems,
you already have make
some choices, right?
Like, you can decide what
is the replication I'm
using to write my files?
What blocks side I have?
I just want to think through
what are the tradeoffs for
these that you could
make informed decisions.
And so I'm just to get
four different volunteers
for each of these.
So I'm wondering if
somebody could say,
raise your hand if you think
you know what might be
benefit of having a high
replication factor.
Yeah, right here.
One shuts down.
Excellent. I think that's
the main reason, right?
So if we lose some of our data,
we have a higher
replication factor,
then our data is safe.
The higher the
replication factor,
the more nodes that could die
and it would still be okay.
Are there any other reasons
we might want to have
a high replication factor
beyond reliability?
Yeah, right here. Excellent, I
might do it for
performance, right?
Like, I I have some piece
of data that is
extremely hot, right?
Like everybody's trying
to read this data,
and I only have a
replication factor
of three and then 1 million
people are trying to read it.
They'll have to send the request
to these same data nodes, right?
Maybe if I don't even
care about reliability,
but I just have the data
that everybody's
trying to access,
maybe I want to have 20
copies of it, right?
Yeah, To are the reasons why
I have higher replication.
Can anybody tell me
the flip of that?
What might be the
benefit of having
a low replication factor?
Yeah, right back here.
Lower cost, right?
I'm using less capacity,
so maybe I don't have to buy
as much hardware. Excellent.
All right. What about
the block size?
What would be a benefit of
having a larger block size?
Yeah, go ahead. Less overhead,
I gus you're saying maybe
there's when you're
transferring the blocks,
you know, maybe there's some
met data with that, right?
So you kind of have one big
transfer with a little bit of
metata that might make sense.
I send another hand up.
I think that's true.
There's something
I'm more worried about though,
too. The same idea.
So the main bottleneck
in the system,
right, that potential botle
neck is the name node,
right because we only
have one name node.
So thinking about the name node,
why might we want to
have a large block size?
Yeah.
Excellent. Yeah, so
we have a smaller
mapping, right?
So it's all the data appears,
and sometimes the data
structure hold a block map.
Maybe it's kind of like
a dictionary where
you look up a key,
which is the block name,
and then the value
would be that.
And so if we have bigger
blocks per file, right?
Then that means there will be
fewer blocks in each file,
which means we can really cut
the size of this data
structure in half.
You know, the name
node is already
kind of bottleneck and is
kind of hard to keep up.
So they will try
to keep that data
structure in memory, right?
You could easily magine
ny out of memory, right?
So larger block size can help.
Now, sometimes people
might try to sell
a larger block size
for that reason, and
it might not help.
Because maybe they have a
bunch of small files a HDFS.
If you have a bunch
of small files,
that it might be the case that
most files have just
a single block.
I think that's actually
more common than
people anticipated when
they built the system.
But assuming that we have this
ideal case that
it was built for,
which where we have
these giant files,
larger blocks will
be less kind of load
on the name node
for both storing
this information and
transferring it.
Alright, great. What
would be a benefit of
having a smaller block size?
Yeah, go ahead. We could
read process and transfer,
I guess it's smaller
chunks, right?
If it's smaller chunks,
we have to have to
do more chunks,
so why would that be good?
Why might we want to have
a smaller block size?
Yeah, right here.
Oh, if hardware breaks down,
we lose less information.
Maybe. I mean, that gets a
little bit complicated, right,
if we kind of think
about I guess,
we're trying to have
replication to deal with
this problem of
hardware breaking down.
And so then the question is,
if you keep the
replication fixed,
and you have kind of
more small blocks
or a few big blocks, what
makes it more reliable?
In a lot of cases, if you lose
a small piece of
data in the middle,
the data might be
garbage, right?
Because if you had some
kind of compression
or things like
that on top of it,
then kind of losing a piece
in the middle makes the
whole thing corrupt.
So I think actually, It
depends on the
nature of the data.
But actually, if you have
kind of more small blocks,
there's more opportunities
to actually lose
a piece of data and often
that means you lose
the whole thing.
So maybe I think you're onto
something there, right?
I think maybe it depends
on the file format.
I think there's maybe another
simpler answer why we
might want to have a small
block size there right here.
You might be reading a lot
of data you don't need.
Oh, that's an interesting point.
So I guess you're
saying, like, Hey,
if you have this
giant block of data,
but you're only using smart
part of it, is that wasteful?
And they've actually
optimized for
that because let's say,
the block size is
like 64 megabytes.
Then whatever is at the block,
they're going to save it in
a file a local file system.
And so if they're only
using 1 megabyte of
that 64 gigabytes,
they will actually just
create a 1 megabyte.
File. Interesting point,
but they handle it.
So what I'm looking for is
actually this question
of load balance.
We want to share work
over the data nodes.
We don't have one
data node that's
overloaded and others
that are not, right?
If we just have
these giant blocks,
and we're kind of putting a
lot of data on a single node.
If we have a lot
of smaller blocks,
we can spread the load more
evenly over many
different nodes.
Anyway, there's a
lot of factors here,
and I think that it
would be good if
you if you're using HTFS,
identify performance
problems or other issues
and then figure out how to
tune these things accordingly.
Alright. So, we have a
fault tolerance system.
We have a strategy
of replication so we
can handle data nodes dying,
but we actually have to
have some way of knowing if
a data node does die, right?
I mean, if it's dead.
It's not going to
announce that, hey,
I'm no longer helping.
It's just Guan, right?
Its communicating. And so
the name node is going to
be the one that recognizes that.
And the strategy they use is
something a lot of systems use,
which is called a heartbeat.
So each of these systems will
regularly send messages,
maybe like every 3 seconds or
something like that
to the name node,
basically saying I'm still here.
They might say other information
like this is the
data I have, right?
To make sure that that
agrees with what
the name node has,
but they have these
regular heartbeats.
And then if it doesn't see
a heartbeat for a while,
what should we do with
that data node, right?
One thing is that
we won't do is we
probably won't try to
write any new data on it.
Eventually, if I assume that
data node is really lost,
then I want to figure out where
other copies are of
the data that it
had and add extra replicas
of that somewhere else.
Right? If I can have
three replicas,
and one of them dies,
then for a while, I
have two replicas.
I eventually want to get
back to three, right?
And so what the name node will
actually do is we'll
keep track of these,
and I'll see how
long has it been?
Since I had a heartbeat.
And then try to
based on how long
it expended it can
do different things.
At some point, it's
going to be state and
it's not t to be
writing new data there.
Eventually, it will
be considered dead,
and then it will
say, Okay, we have
to recover this data elsewhere.
You don't want to be too
aggressive about that
because maybe the Data
node had some updates,
maybe, like, the machine
is just rebooting, right?
Maybe it's trying to
come back. But also,
if you wait too long,
then maybe you're going to
in this stable position.
I have a three times
replicated file
that is only two times
replicated for a while.
So it's star matter for
you for the project
because one of the things
you're going to do on
the project is you'll
have your little cluster,
and you're going to manually
kill one of the data nodes,
and you see like, Okay,
after it's detected as dead,
I can still access the data
that was on it, right?
So actually two of those
things very low for
the project because we want
to see it happen fast,
but, you know, normally,
it might take like hours or
something before we
say, like, Okay,
this dta note is no
longer part of it, right?
All right, so there
are some key ideas
I show up with HTFS.
I just want to recap these
because you might be
working with other systems.
These are going to
show up in general.
When we're building
complex systems,
we generally want to compose
them in layers, right?
So what are some of
the layers here?
I guess on the very bottom,
we have block devices.
On top of that, we have
local file systems.
Right on top of that,
we have these data nodes,
and kind of on top of that,
we have this view of the data
across all all the
data nodes, right?
I helps us decompose
the complexity into
these manageable pieces
instead of building
one giant complex thing.
We're trying to scale
too many nodes.
And the key strategy there is
we had to partition
our data, right?
We partition into these
blocks. To handle faults.
So like a machine dying,
we had to replicate our data.
You have to have some way if
you want to handle faults,
you also have to identify
when it happened.
The strategy here is heartbeats.
That's a common strategy.
And then finally,
to optimize writing,
it's good to try to
split up that work if you
can by pipelining, right?
So a lot of general idea is
that even if you
aren't using HDFS,
you might see these and
other other systems.
Alright, cool.
Any conceptual questions about
HDFS before we move
into hands on.
Yeah, right here. Yeah.
Is there an overhead to
send you the heartbeats?
Yeah, I mean, some, right?
You can kind of tune
how often it is.
I mean, I think, if you have
it like every 3 seconds or so
and you have a few hundred,
it's probably not a big deal.
So there's some other things
they do there that
are useful as well.
So, there's some overhead,
but you kind of have to, right?
You spend some
resources to detect
failures or Like
another useful thing
they do there is where
they send the heartbeat,
they send something
called a block
report as well and that says,
these are all the blocks I have,
and that could help us
handle all kinds of faults.
So, for example, if one of
these machines has
like ten hard drives,
the data Node is managing
these ten hard drives,
and what hard drive dies,
we're still sending
that heartbeat,
but then we might
also say, like,
Oh, I used to have
all these blocks.
I just what I don't
have them anymore.
And so you could be
in a situation where
the name node and the data node
disagree about what
data they have.
And the data note is right.
The data note says, I
don't have this data,
well, then the data
note doesn't have it.
And so there's kind
of yeah there's some
overhead, but, like,
lots of things problems get
solved by just having
regular communication.
Yep. Yeah, great question.
Yeah all questions.
Yeah right here.
Data Yeah,
would you say is it
automatically re generated?
I mean, you saying is there like
another machine that gets
added or you mean like the data?
Are you talking about would
you say regenerate talk
about like the data
or the data node?
I guess Yeah. What
A. Yeah.
So if a data node fails,
then after some amount of time,
the name node will
realize it's dead.
And the name node will
then realize that, Oh,
this file is supposed to be
have three times replication,
I only has two
times replication.
And so it'll ask one of
the data nodes that
still has the data,
send it to this other one.
So it'll find a new
home for the data.
Eventually, right, a human
might come along and
realize, like, Oh, like,
this machine is dead forever,
and they might actually install
some new hardware or set
up a new virtual machine
or something like that.
That would probably
involve human invention
to kind of add machines.
And failures isn't the only
reason you do that. Right?
As the data grows,
you might want
to just add more
machines over time.
To deal with it,
right? So, you know,
you're usually adding
some machines over time.
So machines might be
leaving because they die,
and then the name
note is making sure
that we in the long term,
maintain our goals
with regard to
replication factors.
That makes sense?
Yeah, great question.
Yeah, all the
questions people have.
All the interesting
stuff is around, like,
what happens when
something breaks,
when something goes wrong.
That's a lot of distributed
systems because those things
happen more often. Alright.
Cool. So head over
here to my terminal.
And actually, I have some
stuff in the repo here,
which is checked out.
And so there is a link here.
So you could fan that as
well if you wanted to.
When I'm over here,
I have a couple
HDFS and notebook Docker files
to set up my environment.
I'll just look at
the first one, which
is HDFS docker file.
You're going to
start your project
from something very similar.
You can see that I'm
downloading Hadoop.
It's just this pressed tar file.
I'm extracting it, so
that's really like the whole
install for Hadoop, right?
You just download it and
you extract it somewhere.
Hadoop is written in Java.
And so there's some Java
stuff I have to do, like,
I have to install install
the Java virtual machine.
I have to set up
some environment
variable stuff with
regards to that.
So I won't get into
too much detail.
It's not super interesting.
Anyway, that's how I get Hadoop
installed on the system.
And so the first command
up here builds that,
and so I'm going to
build HDFS like that.
I tagged it as P four HDFS.
And I'm going to look at
the other docker file now,
which is for a notebook.
And I actually start
my notebook from the
image I created.
This is the first time that
you're kind of seeing that
you use a Docker file
to build an image,
and then you use
another docker file
to build a second image
based on your first one.
So I want to call it out
that's a little bit unique.
And you're going to be
doing that on the project.
Why do I do that?
Because when we
have the notebook,
we want to have an HHS client
there so we can
actually read our data.
I'm intelling all the stuff like
Jupiter lab and whatever.
To do some class path stuff,
tr some JBM thing
to tell it like,
Okay, here's where
you find these jars.
A lot of Java stuff is
bundled up in jars.
Here's how you find
these jars related to
the Hadu client so that
everything just works.
Anyway, it's starting up
Jupiter lab and where
we're going to have that
in our environment.
Alright, cool.
I'm going to take a look at
the doctor Compose file.
And this is a little bit simpler
than what you're going
to have for the project.
I I want to do something like
similar to the project,
so you get the ideas,
but I don't want to do
exactly the same thing,
so you have to
think a little bit
about how things are
working as well.
In my environment, I'm
going to have two services,
each with one replication.
So I'm going to have a
notebook and then HDFS.
And so I don't have
any replication here I'm try
to one container with HDFS.
And so for me, and
my environment,
inside of that
container may start
both the name node
and the data node
together in the same container.
You're going to do something
a little more interesting.
You're going to
have the name node
and one container and
you're going to have,
maybe like two or
three data nodes
and separate containers that
are going to be talking to it.
And then you'll also
have this notebook.
Alright, I have some
memory limits here
and I have 2 gigabytes
for each of them.
And if you go back here,
you actually notice that I'm on
a machine with more
resources now.
And indeed, if you
come to P four,
which is not
released yet, right?
It says draft at the top.
But if I come down to
the general directions,
I added some details here
under the budget plan.
You should spend $11 of your
free credit on this project.
You need a little
bit more memory
than we have previously.
So we've been previously
using two small instances.
Now we're going to do e
two medium. I apologize.
It's going to be a little
annoying because you have to
create a new virtual
machine and tell
your old one and then reinstall
the stuff we did in Project
one L Docker and all that.
Don't worry, you're just
going to fast at it.
You know, we have
some other projects,
so we're some new hardware
that we're going to use
for the next few projects.
We're going to have
some more resources
and we get on the VMs,
and we've been
experimenting with that.
But there's just like
some weird stuff like,
you know, hardware failures
happening over the weekend.
So I thought we would
do P four on that,
but probably P five, I
think is more realistic.
Anyway, keep you updated.
This should still keep us within
our free credits
because you have $50.
So anyway, go
create that new VM,
D P four on just a bigger VM,
and then, hopefully we're
ready to go to the
new hardware soon.
Great. So I can do a
Docker compose up now,
and I'm just trying to do
that in the background,
and that will start
my two containers.
If I say Docker, PS, I
can see them running.
What I want to do is I just
want to jump inside the
HDFS one so I can
show you around.
So I'm going to
say Docker Exact,
and that would,
and I want to get
a bash session
there. Alright, Col.
So here I am. I'm inside
of this container,
and we can see like
this is where we
extracted all of
that Hadoop stuff.
There's actually
a Hadoop command.
If I say which, I can see where
it is that was under here.
I added this to my path
so that I could just
run the HDFS command
anywhere, right?
So there's a few ways
I want to be able to
interact with HS.
I want to be able
to interact with it
like from the command line,
like topping around files,
viewing files, that
sort of thing.
And I also want to
be able to write
Python code that
interacts with HDFS.
So I start with the
first part from
the command line perspective.
And so if I just run HDFS,
I actually see just like Docker,
it's a collection of a lot
of a lot of different tools.
And we just learn the
tip of the iceberg here.
There's a few things
that I want you to know.
Under these demon commands,
we can start up different
kinds of nodes, right?
We can start either like a
data node or a name node.
So you'd be aa data do commands
to start those things up.
You are going to be using DFS.
DFS stands for a
distributed file system.
And so there's a bunch of
DFS commands you could do to
view a file or upload a
file or stuff like that.
Up a little bit more, there's
this DFS admin thing.
You are going to
be using that to
get reports and see like, Oh,
a data note is dead, or this
files under replicated,
that type of thing.
Alright. So the first
thing I want to do is I
want to do the dam Node command,
and I can get some help with
it. Right? So I could do that.
Astra, tell me all these
different options I could use.
And if I don't do any of these,
then stray trying to do is
ist to try to start
a new name node,
and that should fail.
And the reason why is that
I haven't actually
formatted it yet.
And so if I went back
to the help earlier,
when I see I have
to do format first.
We talked about formatting
for local file
systems formatting,
is something you do before you
start creating and
using a file system.
You have to create some
initial data structures
usually somewhere on desk.
And so I have to do
the format first.
And that's creating
some stuff there,
and I could row look at
that if I wanted to, right?
Maybe some files for
different metadata that
the Dabot keeps track of.
It's starting off just epti.
I won't worry about it too much.
But after that, if I wanted to,
I could start the Dabote.
It's all formed doo.
I can spit it up.
It will be running.
That's not good.
I think the thing I have
to tell it as well,
is it's going to be a
server and I have to tell
it what server is it?
And so I will have the
name and then the port.
And the port just
traditionally is 9,000.
And the name should be the
same as my host's name, right?
I'm to say what is my
host's name. It's made.
That's basically came
from my Docker container.
And so I'm gonna call
it made here, right?
Alright, C. So do that,
I can what's stow
it out here, right?
I think I actually have to
say Dave note over here.
I think I got my order.
Raw, great. Astraa spit it up.
Atraa start listening.
You may remember what RPC
stands for? Yeah, go ahead.
Remote procedure call, right?
So a lot of suff
we've learned, right?
This is just how systems
communicate with each other.
And so that's helpful
that we had all those
building blocks.
Okay, so what I want to do is I
want to run this
in the background.
So I'd to do that. But it's
running in the pack ground,
I probably want to collect
the log somewhere.
So I'd put both standard out
and standard error to some file.
I'll call it just name text.
It be up and running.
That's straight.
If I want to, I could follow
that file and see what
it's doing, right?
So I will exit that. Okay, cool.
So I have the name node up
and running. That's
all fighted, well.
If I wanted to, I could run
the socket statistics tool,
and I could see that it's
listed at port 9,000,
like I chose for it to do.
And then I also see it's
on this other port,
which is 987 oh.
It's t for this web HDFS thing,
so it's it's HDFS over HTDP.
And so we're be
using that when we
want to access it from
some of the Python code.
It would be using this
one if we were using like
some Java stuff
that's using like
the standard libraries for Hadu.
Anyway, you're be using both
of those on your project.
And so I have that all been
running well. I could
do other things now.
Like if I do HDFS DFS Ad BID,
there's a bunch of
different tools
related to that that
I could use, right?
So I could I don't know,
trigger block report,
surg data Dot info.
Lot of different
things I could do.
What I want to do is I
want to get a report.
And when I do it, you
can imagine I'm in
this environment where there's
many different doop clusters.
And so I have to
specify which one.
So this is just something
where I do quite often,
where I'd be saying, which
cluster are we talking to?
It kind of seems a little silly,
B like right now,
we only have one,
but a big company,
right we might have many of
them for different purposes.
So I can say which one
I want to talk to,
and I can did a report from it.
And right now, I can see, well,
it doesn't really have any It
does't have any data at it.
It doesn't have any data nodes.
And so what I should
do to give it
some capacity is add a
data node to the picture.
Alright, cool. So
I'm to go back here.
And I'm ready to do
HDFS data node now.
L A Help.
And I can do a lot
of the same things.
I have to say, what file
system is it t to be part of?
And I could dive in some
other options as well.
Actually, it can be
very similar to how I
started the name node.
I'll just modify this.
I'm going to say data node now,
and I am going to
specify the same thing.
And when I do this, the
new data node is going
to reach out to that
name node and say,
I would like to
join this cluster.
I have so much capacity,
start setting blocks, right?
And I'll put this to a
different log, right?
So I'm to put this
to a data node.
I wonder if we could
see the Dam node,
see it show up. Alright, great.
So I can see now
that that data node
is showing up and I Story
send reports to right?
The data Node, Stay send
reports to the am node, right?
So the am node now knows that
this data node is there.
So what they I want
you to see is that
when you start working
with distributed systems,
there's a lot of this
like deployment work
you have to do before
you start using.
A, you have to start
up different types
of servers in different places,
and you have to make sure
they're all talking
to each other.
And that's just a skill, I
want you to learn in this class.
And it's not always fun,
but we just have to
make sure we have
all these pieces up
and working together.
Alright, cool. So I have
that up and running.
And if I go back and
do a report again,
I should be able to see
that now I have one data
node that's alive, right?
So when you're doing that,
you're going to kind of check.
You're to make sure
everything's working.
Like, before you go out and
start running a bunch of code,
you should make sure we I
have a cluster running.
I have, you know, some
number of data nodes there.
Eventually, you're a do part of
the project where
you intentionally
kill a data node to learn
about fault tolerance.
So then you'll see, like, Oh,
there's these live data nodes,
and there's this Dad data node.
Alright. Cool. So here
we're up and running.
I think that's all
working pretty well.
Does anybody have any
questions so far? Alright.
Cool. So I exit out of here.
And so right now,
I have inside of this one.
I have a date a data node.
Sometimes I just like to start
a container that I
exact to do stuff.
And so that's why I put sleep in
fendi for the start up combat.
I just, you know, a container,
it's up and Rudy and
really not doing anything.
I jumped into it, I madually
started some stuff.
The project, right you're
automatically start
these things as so as
soon as it boots up.
Alright, this other
one down here is
running by Jupiter Notebook,
and I see it's using 5,000
both inside and outside.
And so what I should do
is I should actually
just create port
tunnel or I'm sorry,
a SSH tunnel that does 5,000
on my laptop to 5,000 my VM.
When I was teaching
all this stuff,
I tried to use
different port numbers
to make sure people understand.
But when I'm actually
doing it in practice,
I usually use the
same port number on
my laptop on the V of
the doctor Contaor.
So I don't have
to think about as
hard once I understand
the details.
Okay, cool. Soby come
over here and I can
come to Jupiter lab.
And so this Jupiter notebook
is in a container that's
on the same network
that my HTFS stuff is.
And so if I did that correctly,
I should be able to create
a notebook and start
writing code that interacts
with that Hadoop cluster.
I'd do this under my
notebook directory.
And maybe I'll just tell
this like Lecture one.
Lecture one. Cool.
And let me just clean this
up a little bit. All right.
Great. And so, over here,
one of the reasons I'm
doing this here right now,
I'm s to be doing
some shell commands,
but I thought it'd be nice to
do the shell commands from
Jupiter just so you have a
resource to look back on.
And so just remember that
I can run shell
commands like this.
So, for example, I could do
that same report that I did
over here, not long ago.
Let me just copy
this. All right?
And this is so good at
work, even though I'm be in
a different container now
because they're on
that same network.
And so this main, right?
I be the NoPok container,
but this is referring over to
HDFS and the container
called Maine.
And so I could do
that, and I could
see the block report right here.
That's also how you're
do your project
because I want you to practice
some shell commands
in the project,
and then you're going to do
the shell commands in Jupiter,
so I can actually see
what you did, right?
Cool. That is all fine and well.
And so most of the
commands I'm going to
be using are going to
be under DFS, right?
So DFS has all these
different commands I can
use to interact with
a Hadoop file system.
And they kind of have a
standard form, right?
They have some kind
of command like this.
And then they say there's
generally some kind of path
involved with it, right?
So 9,000 and something, right?
And the idea is that these
commands might be things like
M directory or
copy or CAT or LS,
kind of a strange format,
but once you understand
that format,
a lot of the things that
you already learned about
the shell are going to be
directly applicable here.
So, for example, I'm going to do
a make der strange, right?
That there's like a
dash in front of it,
but we'll just use whatever
whatever they did.
So I could make a
directory called Data on
top of my HDFS
cluster. All right.
Cool. Maybe I want to put
some kind of file
inside of there.
And I have some files over here,
for example, under the Doop.
For my example data
is Ibight grab
like this license, right?
Cool. I'm straight grab
that license data,
and see if I can upload that.
And so I'm going to get
a command over here,
and I'm going to say,
I want to do a copy,
and I can copy something from on
my system, which is Hadoop.
And then the license.
Maybe I'll grab that license.
I can copy this from
my regular local file system
into the Hadoop
file system, right?
Some run that, and then
that should be there.
And then once it
is, then I should
be able to see what's
inside of this.
So I could do
something like a LS.
Oops. And I can see, well,
what I have inside
of that directory
and I should see
that license file.
Cool. And there it is, right?
If I wanted to, I could
cat it out, right?
So I could say, let's do
a CT of license dot TXT,
right, all the same
suf you normally do,
but now we're doing
it Hadoop style.
All right. Or or not?
What did I do there?
Oh, it's inside of the
data directory, right?
Great. And I can see what's
inside of that license file.
I just want to pause there.
I kind of have done
a bunch of stuff.
I want to make sure people
are following along.
Any questions about
either the deployment or
the interactions with HDFS so
far? Yeah, right over here.
Is. Oh, yeah, that's
a good question.
What does ecation of Barth?
That doesn't have anything
to do with Cotaor.
That's just like a
Jupiter lab thing.
So when I'm a Jupiter lab,
normally, when I run a cell,
it has like python code in it.
When I put an exclavation,
that means like a python code.
It should be like a shell like
a bash command or
something like that.
So you could just rely
bash commands with Python.
The only reason I'm
doing that here is
just that I could at the end,
I could just like hand
you this notebook,
and you'll see all the
examples from Lecture.
It's a little bit strange
that I'm doing it here,
but it just makes it easier
for you to have a
resource later.
That makes sense?
Yeah, other questions
people have. All right.
Cool. What else do
I want to do here?
So some other commands
that we've seen so far
are D U for disk utilization,
that I could run
this on directory.
And I'm going to get the human
readable version like this.
So I can see disc
utilization there.
And this will tell me
the size of the file.
And it will also tell me,
this is the logical size,
I will also tell me the
physical size, right?
So this file is supposed to
have triple replication.
It doesn't right now because I
only have one data
node, but ideally,
it would have triple
replication, and if so,
that's how much space it should
actually consume under
its ideal state.
So I can go through and
I can see both of those.
Let me so I can
see it right now,
this file is probably under
replicated because I
only have one data node.
There's no way for me
to have all of those.
I may have another command
out here, which is FSCK.
So I may say FSC K,
And I want to see
what's going on
with this file right here.
So FSC stands for
file system checker.
There's actually other
tools like that.
I don't know if anybody's
ever seen this on
your laptop but
sometimes maybe in
the older days.
They still have
this, but it doesn't
show up as an obvious way.
But oftentimes if you just
like turn off the power on
your machine at a bad
time and reboot, right?
I could have been a corruption.
And so Often, there'll be a
file system checker that rod,
so they might say FSCK,
maybe you might have
seen that somewhere.
Anyway, they have
that here as well.
And it's giving us some
information about this.
The file system is not
quite in the stame we want.
We have this data block,
but it should have
three replicas,
and there was only
one file, right?
The is the default replication,
right that we have, right?
So we're missing two replicas,
because, of course, I don't
have enough in my cluster.
What I will do now
is I'm going to
upload or copy that file again.
And in this case, I want to
get a different
replication factor.
And so what I will do is
maybe I will go back to
the copy command I had a
long time ago, actually.
I'm going to grab this one.
All right. And I'll
paste this out here.
And this time what I
do is I make a copy.
Before I was topping from
the local file
system on to HDFS.
Now I write a copy from HDFS
to another place on HDFS.
And so I recall this.
That was my original one.
I recall my new file,
just like version two TXT.
And it's a Java program.
Java. You could pass
different arguments to
it with D. And so
I DFS replication
equals one, right?
So I have a single
replicated copy of
this file. And you're
going to do that.
When you upload the
stuff for your project,
you're to specify what
the replication is.
So you're going to do
something like this.
It's just a little
bit strange, right?
But if I come and run
this file system
checker on V two Dow,
it should be a little
bit happier, right?
Because I only asked
for one replica,
and one replica is
what I to get, right?
So it HDFS will not be as
worried about it, right?
So if I come down
here and I look
at the missing replicas,
there are no missing
replicas, right?
In this case, I'm all good.
All right? Cool. Let me
check here. Any
questions about that?
It. All right.
So we have a little
bit of time to start
writing Python code or
at least working towards
that so we could,
you know, read data using like,
Python instead of using all
just these shell commands.
Okay? So I'm going
to come down here.
I'm going to say, for this part,
we're going to be using
the web, HDFS API.
And that's a rest API.
And for the lecture sips
I have some
documentation for it.
And so I'm going to open
up this right here.
And these are all these
different commands that I can
use to check out
my files at HDFS.
And so one of the things
I want to do is I might
want to open a file,
so open a na file.
I'm going to look at
that. For the rest API,
I could imagine using
a curl command.
I I did the curl
command work at first,
and then I figure
out how to write
the Python code afterwards.
And so I'm going to copy
all of this right here.
And it's useful to read rest
documentation like this,
so you can interact
with different systems.
This is not just an HDFS thing,
but I'm to try to get
it all on one slide.
And I can see there's some
parts to fill it, right?
When they put angle packets,
that usually beads you
have to replace something.
So my HDS host is
made, The port number.
We're using something a little
different now I've
been using Port D
thousand for everything
because that's
where they communicate
over the RPCs.
With the Java tooling.
Since we're going
over the web Dow,
they actually have list
at a different port,
which was Light 87.
If I went back to the
socket statistics SS,
from what I was thetor before,
I could have also
seen that there.
That's how I figured out
what port was
supposed to be there.
Oh, I changed the wrong place.
I. My apologies, right?
So I will change this to 87.
And then I have a sub
path to a file, right?
So I could say data V two, TXT.
And then brackets, usually
me that sup is optional.
Okay? So there's lots of
optional things here.
I delete some of the
optional things like
buffer size and redirected
have this as a combat
I co come back to
it later if I want.
I get rid of some of
these optional things.
One of the things that I
would like to have those,
I'd like to say, within
this large file,
what offset am I reading from?
So maybe I'll start offset zero.
And then how many characters do
I want to read?
And I don't know.
Let's just say, like 200, right?
So I'd read to do that. And I
guess that's a shell command,
since I'm using curl.
I'd be ready to do that. Oh, I
forgot to delete these brackets.
I'm actually doing it. So
I want to have brackets in
the final version.
Great, I may do that.
And the I means I
may see some extra header
information drawing.
I actually see that there
were two HTTP requests.
There's this one, which
is a three oh seven,
and this one, which is a 200.
This one was set
to the Name node.
And so I said as the Nabod,
please send me this data.
And, of course, the Nabod
should never send
anybody data, right?
Because it's overload.
And by design,
all data should be transferred
for the data node.
And so the way that
this works is that
the abode will pick a data
node that should have the job.
And the way it does that is it
redirects the requests, right?
So it's try to redirect it,
and it's choosing
this over here.
And basically what this is
indicating is what data Dad
should be doing the job,
right so that it will redirect,
and it will automatically
go to that second one,
and it will get
200 bytes of data.
And then finally,
I get 200 bytes of
data from that
actual file there.
All right. And so I
could have different
variants of this.
This would be that it would
not follow it, right?
So I would just
get that redirect.
I could do that, for
example, if I could say,
like, ask the dat bob,
like, where is this data?
It would just tell me
without actually reading it.
I think I do actually
want to do it.
I can also get rid of
this, and I could just get
the data with
nothing more, right?
So I'll just keep it as
this full version for now.
If I want to, I could read
from other offsets, right?
I could read from,
let's say offset
one, but the same length.
Oh, I'll just give rid of this,
so it's a little bit simpler.
In that case, you can see
that I'm reading a little bit
farther because I guess I
skipped a newlide at
the beginning, right?
Maybe it's a little bit
hard to see, right?
Alright, cool. Any questions
about that curl request so far?
One of the things that Chat
GPT I think is really nice
at is that you can convert from,
you can figure out
in one style, like,
maybe a Curl spat,
how do I do it and
you can ask it to
translate to Python road.
You're welcome to do that
right on the project,
to make sure that when you do,
you're street hotting the
chat and then including
it in the citations for
your project submission.
That's the case I might use it.
I think I kind have figured
it out in some form that
I'm more comfortable with,
and I will translate
it to something else.
Alright, cool. So I have that.
I want to, let me see.
I'm a little bit
ahead of myself.
I want to see how we could do
the equivalent of this
in Python Code, right?
So I will just do it myself,
even though I might
normally use chat
GPT for that sort of
translation work.
I use the request module,
I say requests dot,
and I could use that
same URL dot here.
And that will give me
a response object.
Right? Ibo to do that, I'm
to take a look at that.
And I can see that that's
giving me some data at the end.
One of the things I'll
do is I'll say raise
for status so that if there's
something besides a 200,
that I would have an exception
to some garbage data.
And at that point,
I could say, well,
what is the content is
showing me a bytes?
Well, what is the content
that I have there.
Right? I could also,
if I wanted to,
I could say the text,
it'll automatically
convert it to texts
for me, which I might put out.
So I could do that. And that's
all very helpful, right?
I think what else
might I want to do?
You could see that earlier.
I did use this option at
the Ed called no redirect.
That'll just be like
the last thing I do.
I do a redirect right now.
So I copy all of this and I may
say add no redirect equals true.
And then what I should
get down here, content.
I'm going to get some JSI back.
And what I could do is
I could just say JSI.
It'll automatically
decode it for me,
and then I can figure out from
that JSI what is location.
And so in the project, you're
go get some practice,
I figure out,
Okay, where actually is
this specific piece
of data stored?
Alright, thanks.
I'll uphold all this
so that will help you on P four,
which will be released
before I go to bed tonight.
So have a great day.