Okay. We're continuing
to talk about cashing.
Last time we learned
a few things.
We learned about these
different cashing policies.
We learned about how we
could take a given workload
and picture of the
cache and kind of trace
through it and figure
out which ones
are hits and which
ones are misses.
There's a few more
examples I want to
wrap up on the worksheet
today with that.
And then the other I want
to practice today is,
how can we actually
go and write Tad,
say in Python to implement
one of these caches.
And that's what you're
doing on this P two,
that's also released today.
So, of course, that will be very
helpful for you as you
do that. Alright, ill.
I may head over here to the
document camera to where
we were last time.
And I had left you with this
problem at the very end.
I'm just trying to work
through it quickly,
and so that if there was
any confusion on the top at
last time, we'll
see how to do it.
Then we'll talk about
some of these statistics.
And then on this back
hand side of the sheet,
there's some limitations of
LRU that I want to show you.
Let me just make
sure. Okay, great.
So let's just work through
this one to refresh our memory.
So the first one is W,
and that, of course, is a mess
because there's nothing
in a cache yet.
So I'll write W up here.
Then I have another
W, and so that would
be a hit. All right.
This is a FIFO. So
when I have a hit,
I don't have to reorganize
this data structure.
I can leave in the
existing organization.
I have x, x is a miss.
I will write x up here.
I have y. Y is a mess,
so I'll put y up here as
well after it misses.
Still size three
SenoiVctions, yet.
Now I have y. Okay,
so y is a hit.
And y is already
considered most recent.
And even if it weren't,
while we're doing FFO,
so it wouldn't matter?
I wouldn't change
the state up here.
Now we have Z, Z is a mess.
And so this point
to add z up here,
we're going over
the size of three,
and so we have to
bump something out
and we bump out from
this side, right?
All right. Now we
have y. Y is a hit.
I'm going to say check here.
I don't change it
because I'm doing FIFO,
and then finally X is a hit.
Right? So, in this case,
there were There are four
hits and four misses,
so the hit rate is 0.5.
Given these statistics,
I might also ask you to
compute what the average
latency is, right?
So these were the
hits, and then misses.
I guess I should say mis rate
equals one -0.5 equals 0.5.
The hit rate, I can
basically do a weighted
average down here.
There's 0.5 hits,
and the latency for
those is 0.1 milliseconds.
I'm just bringing
these down here,
and then that will be plus
0.5 times 20 milliseconds,
which will be 10.05.
Milliseconds, right?
So I might ask you to
compute an average latency,
given some cash and some details
about how long a
miss and a hit take.
An Any questions about that one?
All right. Cool. So we're
going come over to this side.
And this is kind of an
interesting work load.
Let's take a look at here.
It goes three, four,
five, six, seven.
You can imagine that being
some pass over a data set.
And then we go three,
four, five, six, seven.
Again, we're reading the
same data multiple times,
maybe by many passes like that.
There's all kinds of cases where
you might end up
having to do that.
One is in machine learning
in machine learning,
you don't just loop
over your data once
and then end up with a
machine learning model.
A lot of machine learning algims
involve repeatedly passing
over the data, right?
This is a common pattern
we might end up with.
And in this case,
we're trying to
have an LRU to make
this access pattern faster.
So I'm going to go throw
through this a
little bit quickly.
Clearly, the first five
are all the first
time they're seen,
so these have to all
be misses. All right.
And at that point, after
I've done all of these,
I will have let me put
these in the cache.
I'll start walking
a little bit more
slowly, four, five, six.
I just filled the cache with
these that are all misses first.
And when I got to
seven, that was a mess.
And so when I add seven up here,
I actually have
to do an eviction
because it's of
size four, right?
So I'm going to remove
that over there.
Okay. The next one is three,
which is a mess.
And that's actually
very unfortunate
because I literally
just removed three.
Right before I ended
up needing it.
So anyway, well, I'll
just follow the policy.
Add three. I have to bump
out four to do that.
Alright, now I have
four. That's a shame.
Right? I literally
just got rid of four.
So I bring four back in,
and now five is gone. You
see the pattern here?
Right? I just got rid of five.
And so now I get a
mess on five when
five comes back. All right.
Six is a mess, even though
I just got rid of six.
Alright. Seven is a mess.
I just started of seven.
That's unfortunate, right?
And we end up with a
giant zero, right?
So we spent all this
memory on this cash.
We did a bunch of logic in
figuring out what's in the
cache and out of the cash.
And it actually behaved
horribly, right?
And would FIFO behave
any better here?
No, FFO would actually
do the same thing.
So both Five and LRU,
they're trying to have some
like logic behind them,
or they're trying to be
smart in some sense,
you can try to justify that,
but they're actually doing
the worst possible, right?
And so this pattern
shows up sometimes.
I want you to recognize
it when it happens.
And then kind of a dumb policy
like random eviction would
actually do quite well here.
I I did random
eviction, you know,
I would have probably
gotten four out of
five of those last ones, right?
So recognize those cases
where maybe you have to have
a different policy for it.
Any questions about
that pattern?
Let's just see the
same thing down here.
This is the same pattern, but
now I have a size of five.
In this case, I'll kind of
go through quickly again, right?
Of course, the first five
are all going to be misses,
and I'll end up with a
cache like this, three,
four, five, six, seven.
And then at this point,
everything is great, right?
Be my whole dataset fits
in my cache, right?
So three is a hit.
I'll move three to the end,
not that it's going
to matter for this.
Four is a hit. Great, I'll
move four to the end.
Five is a hit. Fantastic.
I'll move five to the end.
Six is a hit. I'll
move six to the end,
and seven is a hit,
and I'll move seven to the end.
Right? And then in this case,
my hit rate is 0.5, right?
So when we have
this type of pattern where
I keep scanning the data,
and I have a cache it tends
to be all or nothing,
either all my data hits in
the cache, and it's
worked straight,
or it's just a little
bit too small,
and then I basically
get zero hits.
Alright, cool. So that was
the worksheet stuff
that I wanted to do.
I'm my head over here now,
and we will actually do some
real programming examples.
And so here I have a
Jupiter notebook running.
This is inside of a container.
I already did the Doc
report forwarding stuff,
the SSH tunnel.
You can review on the old slides
if you want to how
to set all that up.
And I have some starter code
over here that I'm ma to
use for this example.
So I'm going to
head to resources
and the lecture snippets.
And right now we're
on Lecture nine.
So I'm man copy this stuff
and just try to talk you
through the problem as
we look at the code.
So I'm going to get
this over here.
I'm just going to split this up.
L, so let me get a little
bit more room on the screen.
Okay, that's fine. So I'm
importing a few Python modules.
I'm going to have
to do some random
number generation
for this example.
Request, lets me
do HGDP requests.
And then Pandas, most of you
probably have seen Pandas,
but if you're coming from
the Java side,
then probably not.
That gives us data frames that
are basically tables of data.
Okay. And what we're starting
with is this URL
right here and I
can see that we're
doing an HTDP request
to get the data
off of this page.
Let me show you what
is on this page.
It's a bunch of IDs
corresponding to weather
stations, right?
And so what I may
imagine is that
I'm building some
kind of application
that occasionally has to fetch
data from different
weather stations.
And sometimes the application
will actually go back and
fetch the same data from
the same weather station,
hence thing might
be useful, right?
I have to download all this
data off of some website.
And so if I actually
come down here,
I can see that there are
all these CS G CSV GZ file,
so GZ is a compression
technique.
And so these are basically
compressed tables.
And so what I can do is
each of these is basically
referring to some weather
station data that
I might download.
So straight paste this here.
I could do that and then would
try to download it for me.
Okay. So I have
the code down here that
actually reads one
of these things in,
so PD, that's Pandas,
is able to read CSV files
directly from the Internet.
So that's cool. There's a
bunch of columns in there.
I'm going to get a
subset of those.
We're talking about worry
too much what is there.
CSV files only contain strings.
But maybe weather
data might have
some floats or things like
that if I'm trying to say,
how much snow was there,
that would be a float.
And so Pandas is doing something
called schema and
foram will revisit.
Basically, it's trying to scan
all the strings in a column
and try to see like,
a, All those strings look
suspiciously like float.
Let's make a float column.
That can take a lot of memory.
And so if I don't say that, Hey,
I have lots of
memory, then I'm just
trying to get some errors
and warnings about it.
So I just do that to
kind of suppress that.
So this is reading
that in down there.
Maybe I'll just grab one of
these stations and show you what
a data frame looks like
if you haven't seen
it before, right?
So here, I should actually
run this thing, right?
So here I would get
this data frame, and
I can see it here.
It basically is like a table
that I can program with.
Okay, so that was the
first piece, right?
I'm getting that list, and then
somehow what I want
to do instead of hard
cutting this in is I want to
have some kind of workload
I'm working with.
I don't want to, you know,
contrive some
complicated application.
So this is a little bit
synthetic what I'm doing.
What I'm going to do
is I'm going to take
all the text off
of that web page,
and I'm may have split it.
So I basically get a list
of all these stations.
Let me just take a look at
the stations down here.
I'm going to get a Python list
of all these different stations.
And then you can see on
this line and I'm taking
a sample to get ten of
those stations, right?
So I have ten stations here,
just randomly selected.
And then what I'm
going to do is I'm
going to randomly
generate a work.
Normally, this would
be kind of just based
on what the application
is actually doing,
but I'm just simulating that.
And so I'm randomly
selecting stations,
100 stations from
this list of ten,
so there'll be some sampling
with replacement there.
And maybe you can see
that here, for example,
if I actually look
at the workload,
And maybe if I kind of
print something like this,
I can see it a
little bit better.
If I see the series of requests,
there's going to be a
bunch of repeats here.
So, for example, like,
this station is going to
show up multiple times,
right because from these
ten stations, right?
I'm sampling 100.
I'm not doing it uniform random.
I'm kind of passing
in some weights.
So there's two stations
that are a little more
popular than others.
One has a 30% probability of
getting chosen or one 20%,
and then the rest
all kind of have
a smaller equal probability
of getting chosen.
So anyway, so I kind of generate
this workload, and our droll is,
we're going to loop over all
of these, and each of them,
we need to get one of these
data frames and memory.
And the slow way
to do that is to
download it again
from the Internet.
But if there are some that
are appearing frequently,
we want to have a
cache that would
help us remember those.
Okay? So that's the setup
we're working with here.
A other details, I should
just fall out quick.
Sometimes when you send a
request to a server, right?
I'm asking for this.
It might send me
back a valid response
that's like a four oh four,
like page missing or something.
And I could pull the text
off like the error message.
This means that if I get
kind of a weird
status like that,
I actually want to
have an exception.
Now, I don't want to
keep going with my code.
Alright, you know, I know
most of you know Python,
but some people are coming from
a java background
and this is new.
I'm not trying to spend a
lot of time teaching Python.
But if there's
questions about stuff
that's going to prevent you
from understanding the example,
you know, feel free to ask.
Does anybody have any
questions so far? Right.
Fantastic. So I
have this workload,
and the way I'm
going to work with
this is that instead of
directly reading the CSV,
I'm going to write a
function called G station,
and it's star to
take a station name,
and it's starting to return
some data frame, right?
I'll come back to
that. And the reason
I often do this is a
function is that then
if everybody like in
this code base is
using that function,
then I can just add some caching
functionality to
that function later,
and nobody has to
change their code.
Their code will just start
running a little bit faster,
but they don't have
to make any changes.
So I think the first version I'm
going to do is not going
to have any caching.
I'm just going to come here, and
I am going to grab
that data frame,
and I'm just going to
return it down here.
And I'm just going to make
sure my function is working.
I'm going to say data frame.
Let's say if I do
like a get station
with that station, does it work.
Only if I define
my function first,
and then it works straight.
You know, we're going to
be doing a bunch of well,
actually, let me do this
now. Let's extend this.
I'm going to say four
station and my workload.
Remember my workload up here,
that's this thing up here.
For each station in the
workload, put this in here too.
I'm going to try to get
the station, right?
So I'm gonna get some
data frame for it.
And then I don't know, maybe
phono I'll just print off
the station and how many rows
there are. It could be whatever.
I could do that. Now, one
of the things that you're
going to find is when you're
working with big data sets is
your code might take
a long time to run,
and that's not good for kind
of interactively
debugging things.
And so one thing I'll
recommend you do,
right instead of just
running your code like that.
Find a small subset
of your big data
set and program and
develop on that first.
And then after that's working,
and then go back to the full
data set. Alright, so great.
I'll just start with five,
and after that's working,
I'll eventually go
to the whole thing.
Alright, so I have a function.
The returns a data frame.
There's no caching involved yet.
And so now I want to
introduce some kind
of caching in here.
And when you're doing caching,
there's basically two pieces
of code you have to write.
You have to say, what
happens when there's a hit,
and what happens if
there's a mess, right?
So if there's a hit,
I'll do something down here.
Otherwise, it's a mess, right?
And then I'll do something
down here, right?
Maybe I'll just kind of
print miss down here,
and then I'll print hit up here.
All right. And then I'll figure
out what to put in there.
All right, so what I'm going to
do to figure out if
there's a hit is I have to
have some kind of data
structure that keeps track of
all the data that I'm
currently caching.
And a good data
structure for that is
often Python dictionary, right?
Because it can
have values in it.
To can be the
things I'm caching.
And when you have a cache,
you usually have
to have some way
of labeling specific
entries, right?
So if I have a name
for them or whatever,
I can look them up.
And if you're writing
a dictionary like
this for caching or otherwise,
I think a really useful
python comment that's
just brief is to say what
the keys and values are.
So for me, the key will
be a station name,
and the value will be weather
data frame for it, right?
I may have that.
And then when I'm
down here and I have a
station name like this.
Actually, I should
pulled that in.
When I have a station name
coming in, it's one
of these strings.
What I can do is I can
check if it's one
of the keys, right?
So I station is in
cash dot keys, then
that would be a hit.
And Python, I can do this a
little bit more concisely.
If I just check if something
is in a dictionary,
what it's checking is, is
that key in a dictionary?
Right? So I'll check, is
it like a hit or a miss?
And and so far so good.
And so this code right
here that I wrote before,
I figure out which of these
two areas I should put it.
So should I put this code
under the hit part
or the mis part?
Yeah, right here. Miss
part. Excellent, right?
So the miss is when we have
to do the long slow thing.
And that's what
this is right here.
This is where we actually
have to go out to
the Internet and
download something,
and that slow, and
we don't want to do it
any more than we have to.
Alright. When we do
have to go out and
find some data
to the Internet like this
and do this slow thing,
we want to remember it.
So now would be a good time to
store that data in our cash.
I'll take the question
just a minute.
So this point, I
can say, cache of
the station is going to equal
this data frame I found.
Yeah, cash right here.
Yeah, that's an excellent
question, right?
So this can kind
of you're saying,
this can remember
things, but, like,
how would I ever evix something?
I'll just keep writing the code
until it ends up looking like
a real cash implementation
that has an eviction with it.
So yeah, I'll get
there. Thank you.
Yeah, other questions
people have so far. Cool.
So far so good. I'm going
to put that in there.
And then up here, what
I could do is I could
return whatever that
entry is, right?
That's one of the
things I could do.
You know, Every program
rule has exceptions.
I'm going to kind of say
something that I would
consider good
guidance in general,
but it has exceptions.
It's usually nice if you just
return from one
place in the code.
One reason for that is
later, for example,
I'm going to try to time how
long it takes to get
a station, right?
I'm going to put a
big time around that.
If I'm returning in the middle,
then it's a little bit
hard to do that timing.
Instead of just
returning that directly,
I'm going to put that
in a data frame,
and I'll have return
at one point, right?
So either way I
get a data frame,
and then I return it
down here here at let's
just run that and I see
that I have some misses.
And then at the very
end, I have a hit.
And is that right? So I
guess, like, right now,
I don't have any limit on how
many cash entries I can have.
And so these four
are all unique.
And then this one was a repeat
from what I saw earlier.
So that makes sense that
that would be a hit.
Okay. Now, you know,
when you're doing the
project, you're kind of
building a cash in general,
you're going to
have bugs, right?
Everybody has bugs, and
Maybe you're running
like the auto greater,
and you're like, Oh, I
have this number of hits.
The auto grader says
that number of hits.
It's kind of hard to know
where to start from that.
I think the way you
debug these things
is you look at you print a bunch
of stuff out and you
kind of look I the
cash doing what I expect to do?
Think carefully about
what you expect,
and then print some stuff off
and make sure it's doing, right?
So I just print like one example
of what I was expecting to do.
I may have more prints
of that nature.
I'm just trying to clean this
up a little bit down here.
And you know what
the other handma
make it a little less confusing.
I'm maya print the station name.
And then after that,
we'll see if that was a hit
or a mess, right?
So I can do that.
And so I can see that
this station was
the first one that
was a hit. All right.
Fantastic. And you know,
if you have lots of memory,
Code like this is actually
useful in lots of places, right?
Maybe all the data
frames fit in memory,
and I could just stop here.
I see code like
this all the time.
It'd be a reasonable
thing to do.
We're going to pretend that
we're tight on memory.
And so we want to limit
how many entries can
be in here, right?
So I'm going to say cash size
is let's start with like three.
We can say we can have at most
three cash entries in here.
And then what we'll do
is when we have a mess,
we're bringing something
in to that cache.
And then we have to then
we have to figure out,
do we have to evict
something, right?
Do we have to evect, right?
So maybe maybe after
I added this in,
maybe there's like
four entries in there,
but I'm only supposed
to have three.
Right? So what I can
say is if the length of
cash is greater
than the cash size,
then indeed I do
have to ev, right?
I have to say a victim
equals something.
Who knows what that is. And then
what I can do is
I can say cash p
That. In this case, the
victim will be a key in
the picture and I'll
remove it, right?
So we have to have some kind
of eviction logic here.
And when we do that, we often
have to have some kind of
extra bookkeeping
going on, right?
So let's try to figure out how
to have some extra
bookkeeping here.
What I might do is when
we were doing the
worksheets, right?
We had that area where we had
a bunch of entries in it,
and we would kind
of keep track of
what different entries
were in there.
So I might do something
analogous to that on the code,
and I'm may represent
that with a list.
And Som call my list eviction,
maybe I'll just
call evict order,
and that will be a list.
I'll kind of keep track when
somebody gets pumped out, which
side will they come from?
Maybe I'll make a
note here, right?
So evict from left.
Try to keep right hand side.
Entries in memory, right?
Is my goal here. All right.
And so I'm going to have to
do some bookkeeping with this.
Here, I guess I am adding.
I'm adding that station into
this primary data structure.
And so what I should also
do at that point is
I should figure out
for this new entry,
where should I put it?
So I'm going to put in
eviction order I have to
somehow insert this station?
Do I want to insert it at
the beginning of this list
or the end of this list?
Somebody can just shout
it out. End of the list?
Excellent. I want to
do it at the end.
I'm literally just adding
this data frame now,
and so I want to
try to keep it in
memory if I can, right?
And so I don't have to have
a whole data frame
here, I can just say,
what is the station
that I'm interested in.
I'm going to pen that there.
And then now when
I choose a victim,
does anybody want
to suggest how I
could use my new data
structure to choose victim?
Yeah, right here. Yeah, let's
grab the one at
index zero, right?
So I'm going to say
evict order dot pop
at index zero, right?
So when I pop a dictionary,
I'm popping by key.
When I pop a list, I'm
popping by an index, right?
So I think that should
hopefully be working.
And, you know, I have
five things down here,
and so there probably should be
some eviction at
some point, right?
I'm going to print am
I getting an eviction?
Maybe what I'll
even do is I will
print what I'm evicting.
That would be kind of cool.
So I will print
what I am evicting.
Down here, and then down here,
sure enough, I I'm getting
an eviction happening here.
And again, right, to try
to make sure that these
things are worked
that you want to print
extra suf and make sure it
does what you think
it's supposed to do.
One of the things I often
like to print is what
that data structure is
that's determining the
eviction order, right?
So I'm going to do that.
And now I can see there's
that data structure
that's indicating that.
And so for the
first three, right?
As I'm accessing these,
I'm adding it to the
end of that data
structure until I
get to this point.
Alright, so I'm at
this point right here.
I just access those
three in order.
And now I have something that is
not in this list up here, right?
And so I have a mess,
which means I have
to evict something.
I might check, Am I evicting
the right thing? I am.
I'm supposed to evict what
is at the first entry.
And so what I expect now is
that I'm evict that one.
These two will be at the front.
And then this one that
I'm accessing now should
get added to the end.
Let's just check if that's true.
These two should
move to the front.
Fantastic. And then
this new one should
get added down here.
At the end, right?
So that's kind of
what you should do.
You should print
these things out.
Look at you know,
look at the first time
you have an eviction.
That's often where
bugs are because
that's kind of more
complicated rode.
Look where you have an eviction
and try to figure out,
is it doing doing
the right thing?
Okay. And then after
that, I have a hit.
And my hit is to this
entry right here.
And then my cash data
structure looks the same.
So I have a question
for you all.
Well, first off,
I'll see if anybody
here has any questions
for me first.
Yeah, right over here. Where
did I find the workload?
Yeah, I just to find
the workload up here.
So first off, I just
said, we're only going
to do like ten random
stations for this.
And then I did a sample
with resampling.
I got 100 from that list of ten.
So when I did the sampling,
I got a lot of repeats.
And I also just put in
some weights here to
say that instead of all
stations being equal,
there's a couple that I guess,
like hot stations that
show up more often,
right? Yeah, thank you.
Yeah. Other questions
people have.
Oh, excellent. Which cash mp?
That's what I was
trying to ask you all.
So I will ask you all,
what cash are we
implementing? Yeah, go ahead.
We are doing FIFO. And what did
you see that made you
feel like it's a FIFO?
Well, we always.
But we're not reordering.
Excellent. We are not reordering
when we have a hit, right?
If this was LRU,
then when I hadn't hit here,
it would have moved
this one to the end
because it will say, Oh,
we just used that one.
Let's try to keep
that one around.
That one's kind of
import it, right?
So we'll come back
to this in a bed,
and we're going to try to
see, can we make it an LRU.
So excellent question,
an excellent answer.
What other questions
do people have?
Right.
So before I try to
make it into an LRU,
well, first off, you know, we
should make a comment on that.
Like, the policy should
be clear, right?
So this is a FIFO cash
or it uses a FIFO cash.
Maybe I'll say that. All right.
Now, when you're doing
this cashing work, I mean,
part of it is h you're trying
to make it correct, right?
It's supposed to what
you wanted to do.
But you also care about
performance. It should be fast.
And so as you're doing
this, you should be
taking different
performance measurements.
I mean, the most basic
performance measurement
is like time,
how long are things taking.
But you might also
want to explain
the time things are taking
in terms of like, well,
how many hits were
there, how many misses
were there and stuff like that.
And so let's add some
statistics to track.
These are some perf stats
that we're going to track.
And one of the things I
like to do is I like to
keep track of the
latencies of each thing.
And I often like to
put my units in there.
So in milliseconds,
milliseconds,
to grab each station.
I may have one called that.
And then what else
might I want to have?
I want to keep track of
which ones are hits.
And I might say one is a hit.
Zero is a mess, right?
I want to keep track of
these kinds of things.
If I want to measure how
long something took,
I mean, I will
do it very similar the
way I do it in real life.
I look at a clock,
I do something,
and I look at a clock at again,
I subtract and I know how long
something took.
So let's do that.
I am going to import
the time module.
Import time. And so
the way I would do
that in general is
I'd say something
like time to time.
That tells me how many
seconds have passed
since a January 1 of 1970.
That's kind of
like I don't know,
on the early days of computing.
They just considered 1970
to be the start of time.
And so if I keep watching this,
you can see it's ticking up.
And so kind of a natural way
I would do this is I would
say start equals
that, do something.
And then I would say n
equals time that time.
And then I could subtract
the n minus the start.
I mean, this is an
exponential notation.
That was super fast.
Let's do something slow.
I'm going to sleep
for 3 seconds.
And then I will
see that you know,
it's about 3 seconds with
some extra overhead for
drawing those functions.
Fantastic. So I want
to do that down here.
And that was kind of why I
was saying earlier, right?
Even though we could, from
the logical perspective
return here,
kind of having one
return point at
the end makes it
easier for me to
instrument my code and measure
how things are working, right?
So up here, I may have
a start time equals
time, that time.
And then down here I will have
an end time equals time time.
Then I can say
atencs S dot to pen,
and then I'll say end
time minus start time.
And then since we just shot out,
what soul I multiply this by?
100 excellent because
this was in seconds,
and then over here, I'm
tracking the milliseconds.
So that's one of the
things I'm ready to do.
The other thing I'm
trying to do is I'm just
try to keep track of whether
I have hits or misses.
Maybe it's a little bit easier.
So I'm going to say hits to pend
one because we got hit there,
and then I'm going to
hits dot to pend zero.
I often like to do
it this way because
there's a few interesting
things I can do.
I can just like summit,
for example, to get the
total number of hits.
I could take the average, and
then I would have the hit ratio.
So that will kind
of make it easy to
keep track of our statistic.
Let me just make sure it doesn't
crash or anything when I run it.
And now I think it's
appropriate time
to go ahead and actually
run the whole thing, right?
And so this will take a moment.
So any questions
while that's running?
All right, and it's done.
So we're gonna come
down here now.
And I guess I'm kind of
printing off too many things.
Let me just clean all of this up
because that's not really
our focus anymore.
So I'm going to clean a
lot of this stuff up.
Otherwise, it's just too much.
You know, maybe what
I'll do is I'll
actually say n equal space,
and then I'll just see
a bunch of these on
the on the same line, right?
So then I can see
it's doing something.
All right. Fantastic.
So that done.
And so now what I have is
all of these latencies.
Maybe it was latencies
MS, I think.
And so I can try to figure out,
kind of typical performance.
So for example, I could say,
like the average latencies,
that might be a metric that
I'd be interested in, right?
So maybe that'd be like average
latency and milliseconds.
I would be kind of a
reasonable thing to print out.
I might be interested in
something like tail latency
can remind me what is
tail latency? Right.
Excellent. So if I took like
the 99th percentile latencies,
then that would be an
example of a tail latency,
and so it'd be like one
of the worst latencies.
And so NumPi, which I'm
going to import as NP,
actually has will help
us quickly compute a
percentile like that.
I guess, instead of
quantile or quantiles,
let me just check my notes here.
Instead of percentiles,
which go 0-100.
They have quantiles, which is
exactly the same idea,
but it goes 0-1.
And so I can say something
like give me an array of data.
I'm going to say my latencies
MS. And then I can say
what quantile I'm at.
So I'm going to say
something like 0.99,
or maybe I could do 0.999 if
I really want to in
explore the tail.
I'm I call that my P 99
latency equals that.
And then I could see
what that is, right?
So I could say P
99 tail latency.
And then I can say
whatever that is, right?
Great. And of course,
my tail latency is much worse
than my average latency.
Is unless your whole
dataset pits in the cache,
it's really hard to
beat tail latency
because there's always going
to be some cash misses,
and those are going
to be slow, right?
But certainly we can make the
better case a lot better.
We can also do things like
figure out the hits,
so I have these hits.
I could say, print total hits.
As the sum of these hits.
I could do that. And
then I might also be
interested in the
average of that,
and that would be
my hit rate, right?
So my hit rate it
rate would be 0.48.
And that makes sense
because 0100 hundred
requests, right?
So I can drove through
and do these statistics.
And then you'll often be
trying to figure out, like,
should I have a
different cash size
or should I have a
different cash policy?
So you do a lot of experiments.
You'll run the same thing
with different settings,
and you'll be you
should be able,
talk about these statistics
and make an argument
for the cashing decisions
that you might want to make.
For example, one of the
things that you might
do is You might
rerun this experiment with
a whole bunch of
different cash sizes,
maybe like 0-100 or whatever,
and then you might
create a plot.
On the x axis, you
might put something
like the cash size,
and on the y axis, you might put
something like the hit ratio.
And what will that look like?
Well, it'll be a line
that's kind of like going up
as you have a bigger cash,
you'll have a better,
better hit rate.
But eventually, it does the best
you can do, and it'll
just level off.
And so you could make
a plot like that,
and you could tell
people that a ca
of such and such
a size is useful,
and beyond that, there's
diminishing returns,
you should be able to
make arguments like that
and kind of reason through
that sort of thing.
So no, we actually just try and
see if we have a
bigger cash size,
what would happen?
Hopefully, it's faster.
It looks like it's
running slow right now,
so maybe this will undermine
my point I'm making.
So let's just remember this.
So the average was 37.
And now, okay, great,
we have a bigger cash,
and it's a little faster.
And instead of 48 hits,
we have 64 hits, right?
So a bigger cash size does
have some benefit here, right?
I had a cash size of ten,
then I'd be getting what?
Hit rates of 100%.
Alright. Do people have
any questions about
these statistics?
Here. Oh, that's an
excellent point, right?
So I guess in the best case I
would did a hit rate of 90%
because the first ten always
have to be misses.
Excellent point.
Y. Yeah, are points or
questions people have.
Let's go ahead, and
I'm going to go back
to three for a moment.
And then what I'm going to do
is What I may do is I may see,
can we with that same cash size,
can we get better performance
if we switch to LRU?
So I'm doing FIFO,
can we do LRU, right?
And so remember, right, I
always have these two pieces.
I have the hit code,
and I have the miss code.
And so my question
for you all is,
when I start doing LRU,
what should I change?
Can somebody just shout
it out for me? Hit.
Excellent. I have to change
the hit code, right?
Be because I have this
evict order up here, right?
If I use some entry in
the middle of that,
I should kind of move it, right?
If I used it, then I want
to keep it around, right?
I want the least recently
used things on the
left hand side.
That's why it's called LR U,
least recently used on the left.
And then the important
stuff that I just
touched should be on
the right hand side.
Alright, let's try that.
And so what we'll do
here is I can say,
I can say evict order
evict order dot
Remove, and I will
remove that station,
and then I will add
it back at the end.
Evict order dot a pen
station at the end, right?
So I may say move station
to the end, right?
So it stays in memory
longer, right?
And so let's run this.
Alright. Let's just
look at these numbers.
Da they're about
to change? I think
that LRU will do
better in this case.
So let's hope that the
average latency goes down.
I guess a little bit, right?
And then let's take a look
at the total hit rate.
Okay. In the morning lecture
was worked out better.
I mean, there's some
randomness here, right?
But maybe I was wrong.
Maybe they perform
similarly here, right?
So cash size and cash policy are
things that are going
to influence this.
Usually more than this
example right here. Cool.
So I just want to pause on this.
Do people have any questions
about how we turn
this into LR U cash?
Now, notice that to do
either of these policies,
I had to do a little bit
of extra bookkeeping here.
And one of these things
I'm doing with the
bookkeeping is not great.
Anybody who kind of
knows the details about
how Python lists
work internally,
what are you a little bit
worried about here? There here.
Oh. Yeah, remove I
might have to look
through the whole list.
So that's not great.
Maybe even worse.
When I find it, a Python list
is a lot like a Java, ray list.
I kind of all these things
are packed consecutively.
And so when I pull out, say,
like an entry at Index five,
then I have to shift
over all the other items
at index like six,
seven, eight, so on.
And so this is an
order and operation.
For a cash list size, it
doesn't really matter.
Like the cashing
overhead, doesn't matter.
If we had something
a lot bigger,
then that might
actually matter to me,
and I might try to pick a
different data structure.
Does anybody know a
data structure that
might be good for kind
of what I'm doing,
like the removing and
adding it at both ends?
Yeah, go ahead. A length list,
like a double length
list will be.
Yeah, you want to add on
that. Hh Maybe ash map.
So hash maps are
ordered. In fact,
I even think maybe cache is
in recent Python
versions, right?
The leng list, I think that
might be a good
solution, right here.
A DQ, right? Able length list is
often how people will
implement a D Q.
So DQ can let us add and
remove from both sides.
A link list would be
one example of a DQ.
Some people call it a
double edged Q or a deck.
But we want to do
something like that.
Yeah, question right here.
That's an excellent
question. Can we
still remove from the middle?
And if you just
did a generic DQ,
like the one that
comes with Python,
the answer is no, right?
And so this is not great for us.
If I was doing FIFO,
then everything would
have been good, right?
A DQ would work great.
What I often find myself doing
when I end up writing LRU code,
and I've had to do this in
a few different scenarios,
is I often end up implementing
a doublen list for my DQ,
and then I kind of optimize
it for this scenario.
And the way you can
optimize it is that You
have to have some
way of jumping into
the middle of the length list,
the nth list, and find
a node in the middle.
And if you have a
supplementary dictionary,
you can do that, right?
We don't want to have
just a dictionary
from stations to data frames.
I need to have
another dictionary that
would kind of take me
to a double length list
node in this thing, right?
I can try quickly find
something in the middle.
And then once you do that,
you could remove it, right?
So you might end up having
some extra data structures here,
but, you know, that's more
of an algorithm thing.
We won't get too deep into
that in this course, right?
And it's not a horrible amount
of code to do
something like that.
Alright. Fantastic.
So, what questions do people
have about our cashing
implementation?
Alright, so you all
will go and do that,
and hopefully that's fun
to do on the project, too.
And hopefully, hopefully
this helps you.
You know, I may have
saved this for you all,
and the way I may do this is
I may do a file download,
and then I can save my
notebook somewhere.
And you should
remember that too,
because if you're working
on a Jupiter notebook
inside a container and
you kill your container,
well, your files are gone.
Well, eventually, we see
you in kind of another way,
like when we learn more
about docker storage,
how to do that.
But for now, if you're
doing work inside
of a Docker container
and uper notebook,
make sure you save
it out regularly,
so you don't lose it.
Alright, fantastic.
I'm going to jump
ahead a little bit to
Wednesday's lecture
because we have
a little bit of
time, fortunately.
And kind of what
we've been doing so
far is we first started with,
like, let's just see,
like the purpose of
a cash and some cash policies.
And then today we kind of
go our hands sturdy, like,
how would we actually
build a cash?
This next lecture is things
that you might actually be
thinking about cashing a lot,
and we'll definitely have
hands on applications.
I'm going to look
at some existing
tools that kind of interact with
cashing and see how we can get
better performance out of them,
given some of the things
that we've learned.
And most of those
will be around Piero,
which is a tool introduced,
and then also around this
other thing called umpi.
And so one of my learning
objectives for you is that
you should grow and write
cash friendly code.
Cash friendly coded that is
ting to run faster because
of the cache is trying to maybe
have more hits and fewer misses.
And there are things
that you can decide that
will influence that when
you're building
your application.
Secondly, we're going to
learn about how we can
use these things called
memory mappings with Piero,
and that will be kind
of a natural way
for us to have a table
where we're using memory to
cache portions of our table,
which really lives
on disk somewhere.
We don't necessarily
have to think about it.
It's going to hapen
automatically
for us if we set
things up right.
Another way caching
shows up is with
this thing called swapping.
Sometimes if there's
too much data,
the operating system will put
some of that data to disk,
and then only the hottest
data will stay in RAM,
so that's effectively a cache.
And then finally when I
see how we can configure
some docker limits
on memory used.
That one's actually
important for kind of
troubleshooting stuff
because what will happen to
all of us probably is
that at some point,
we'll have some
dockerized application
that's using too much memory.
And then it's really annoying
because the whole
virtual machine
becomes non responsive,
and you have to go reset it.
You can go on the
console and do like
a reset and it'll be fine.
But still, it's annoying to have
a VM that freezes up on you.
We can avoid that by setting
limits on our docker
containers so that
that docker container
dies instead of
the whole virtual machine
becoming non responsive.
Alright, let's
review a little bit.
So when we're writing
cashwaR code,
one of the caches we
should be aware of
is the CPU caches.
And so I'm going to
take a look at the CP,
remember that the CPU
has these caches.
L one, L two and L three.
And, you can imagine
different policies that
might have for eviction.
Another question that we
have is that when I
touch a piece of data,
I want to bring that
into the cache,
but should I just bring
that piece of data,
or should I kind of bring
a bigger chunk of data?
For example, if I'm
looping over an array,
and those entries in the
array are in the CPUs cache,
do I want to bring one
teger in at a time,
or when I access one eger,
should I bring in a few, right?
So this question of granularity.
The way we talk about
that with CPUs,
as we call it cash
lines cash lines
are the granularity at which
we pull things into the cache.
And, you know, people have
tried bigger cash lines
and smaller cash lines,
and bigger, smaller n
necessarily better.
It really depends on
your workload, right?
If I'm kind of sequentially
accessing a bunch of stuff,
then I would want a
bigger cash line.
If I'm randomly jumping around,
a bigger cash line
is actually bad.
I don't want a
smaller cash line.
Anyway, for a long
time, most CPUs,
modern CPUs have had 64,
so I'll kind of just like
assume that in most cases.
Like some of the, you
know, in the past,
we've had bigger ones and
kind of more recently,
Apple's experimenting with some
bigger cash line sizes as well.
But we have these
cash line sizes.
T to be very clear. What
is the problem here?
If these cash lines
are too small,
then right after we have a mess,
we're going to have
another mess when
we touch adjacent data.
They're too big, then
we're wasting resources
pulling data into the cash
that we will never use.
Alright, so let's see
how this might play out.
This example confuses
people a lot.
I'm going to go through
kind of slowly.
I'm using a language,
maybe like CPS plus
or something that
lets me specify the
size of my integers,
and I'm going to create
an array of integers that
are consecutive in memory,
and I'm going to use 64.
So let me think about that.
In 64 bits, there
are eight bytes.
So I have eight byte integers,
and there are 64 bytes
in a cache line.
So that means I have
eight integers can fit
in one cache line.
Okay. Now, I have 16
integers in my array.
So that means they're spread
across two cash lines.
Okay? Now, just because I
have an array or a
list or whatever,
and memory doesn't mean that I
have to access all
of the data in it.
So, for example, I
could write a program
that loops through
the first four
numbers and prints them.
And so to illustrate that,
I made some of these red, right?
So I have an array of 16 things,
but I'm only looping over the
first four and printing
out what those are.
Okay? And so then we can look
at this, and we can say,
when I do this, when I
access these four numbers,
how many misses, will
there be in the cash?
How many cash lines
do I have to pull
in would be another way of
phrasing that same question.
Yeah, go ahead. There
would just be one, right?
So even though I'm axing
these four numbers,
there will only be
one cash line mess because
I read the first one.
That's a mess I bring it in.
And then the next three
are hits because even
though I'm axing those
numbers for the first time,
they're part of a cash line
that I've used recently.
Alright, so we saw
the first one,
we'll have one cash line mess.
Maybe everybody
together can hold
up some number of fingers.
How many cash line
misses will there be?
And the second example,
a few people say two,
which is correct.
When I access the integer at
index zero, there's
a cash line miss.
I'll bring all of
this in a little bit
unfortunately because I don't
actually use those values.
And then I access another
integer at Index eight.
That's in a different cash line,
so then I have another mess.
Okay? And then what about
this third example?
How many cash line misses
that I have there?
I already hold up some
number of fingers.
Kind of a MX. It's two.
So when I access
that first number,
it will be a cash line mess,
and I access the next seven
and those will all be
heads because I already pulled
in that whole cash line.
Then I go to the
one at dex eight.
That will be another
mess, and I'll
bring in a whole
other cash line,
and all the rest of these
will be heads, right?
So the one on the
far left, right,
we have one cash line mess,
and the one in the
middle we have two,
and one right we have two.
And I think the way people
kind of naturally intuitively,
think about their code, as
they might look at this,
and they might say,
how many different
numbers am I accessing.
And kind of it
feels like that is
what's going to determine how
long your program takes to run.
What I want to start
thinking about
is not how many numbers
are I touching,
but how many cash lines are
my touching, because honestly,
these two on the right probably
have kind of similar
performance,
and the one on the left
is going to be faster,
even though it's accessing
more numbers than the
one in the middle.
Let me just show you, like,
a really cool experiment
on this blog that does this.
It's a one line program.
And it's writing a loop in
kind of a language like,
you know, maybe, like, Java or
C Sharp or something like that.
We have an I that we're
using for our four loop.
And we're looping up until
the length of the array,
this array has four
byte integers in it.
And as we step forward,
we step forward by
different amounts.
So we specify a k value.
If K was one, then I
would be accessing
every integer and I'd be
multiplying it by three.
I K was two,
then I would do the
integer at position
zero at position two
at position four.
Basically, the bigger K,
the less multiplication
I have to do.
And so what they
did is they tried
different k values
on the x axis,
and then they measured
how long it took.
And it's really
kind of striking.
When I go from K equals
one to k equals two,
The multiplications
I do is cut in half,
but it's not any faster because
I'm touching the same
number of cash lines.
When I go from K
s two to K four,
I'm cutting the
multiplications in half again.
No any faster. Be the same
amount of cash lines.
The only time it
really gets faster
is when K gets bigger than 16,
then I start skipping
every other cash line.
So the multiplications
here are irrelevant.
The only thing that matters
to performance here
is how many cash
lines am I touching.
Alright, so I'll leap off on
that thought and
we'll come back next
time and have some more
concrete examples like this.
So a fantastic day.